Hey everyone, and welcome back to Simply Learn's YouTube channel.
Artificial intelligence is helping organizations build systems that can analyze data, recognize patterns, make predictions, and automate complex decisions.
And machine learning forms an important part of AI by enabling systems to learn from data, while deep learning uses neural networks to solve more complex problems
such as image recognition and other intelligent applications. Having said that, let's have a look at the agenda for this course.
We will be starting off with artificial intelligence, machine learning, deep learning, and data science fundamentals;
then AI Engineer, Machine Learning Engineer Career Roadmaps and Applications, Probability, Statistics, Mathematics, and Linear Algebra for machine learning;
data science fundamentals, data types, and exploratory data analysis with Python;
supervised and unsupervised along with reinforcement learning, linear regression, multiple linear regression, and machine learning model fundamentals;
decision trees, k-nearest neighbors, support vector machines and confusion matrix, clustering, k-means clustering, and principal component analysis;
convolutional neural networks, CNN layers, image recognition and CNN use cases;
AI and machine learning projects, career preparation and interview questions.
Hope I made myself clear with the agenda.
With that being said, if these are the types of videos that you would like to watch, then hit that subscribe button along with the bell icon to get notified whenever we upload a new video.
Also, just so you know, if you want to upskill yourself, master artificial intelligence and machine learning skills, and land your dream job or grow in your career,
then you must explore Simply Learn's range of AI and machine learning programs.
Simply Learn offers a variety of master certifications and postgraduate programs, including programs offered in collaboration with leading universities and industry partners.
Now, through these courses, you can gain knowledge and work-ready expertise in skills such as Python, machine learning, deep learning, natural language processing,
generative AI, neural networks, TensorFlow, and many more.
And that's not all. You also get opportunities to work on practical projects and real-world use cases guided by industry experts with experience in leading technology and AI companies.
Now, these skills can help you transition into roles such as AI engineer, machine learning engineer, AI developer, or data scientist, or help you move into a more advanced or higher paying profile.
If you're passionate about building your career in AI and machine learning, make sure to check out the link in the pinned comment and description box to find a program that
fits your experience and areas of interest. So let's get started with our AI, machine learning and deep learning full course 2026 with a small quiz.
So in a convolutional neural network, which layer is mainly responsible for detecting features such as edges and patterns in an image?
Is it a convolutional layer, B output layer, C database layer, or is it D regression layer? Please let us know your answers in the comments below.
Once upon a time in the quiet town of Newbite, there lived a curious teenager named Aria.
She wasn't like most kids in her school, while others were busy with sports or music.
Aria was fascinated by machines, especially the idea of making machines think like humans.
Her curiosity began one evening when she asked her grandfather, who used to be a computer engineer, can machines ever think?
Her grandfather smiled and said, That's what artificial intelligence is all about.
Arya's eyes lit up.
Artificial intelligence?
What's that?
So he began to tell her a story.
Not a fairy tale, but a real story about the science and ideas behind machines that learn, decide, and sometimes even surprise their creators.
Artificial intelligence, or AI is the science of making machines that can do things that normally require human intelligence.
This includes tasks like recognizing faces, understanding speech, making decisions, and even playing games.
But AI isn't magic.
It's built through programming, mathematics, and data.
Aria imagined a robot that could talk like a human and help with homework.
Her grandfather nodded.
That's one kind of AI, but there are many types.
He explained that AI isn't just about robots.
In fact, most AI systems are just computer programs running inside machines we already use, like phones, laptops, or even refrigerators.
Her grandfather told her that AI comes in two main types narrow AI and general AI.
Narrow AI is the kind we see today. It's designed to do one specific task.
For example, the AI in a smartphone that unlocks the screen by recognizing your face is only good at that one job.
It can't cook or write a story.
General AI, on the other hand, would be as smart as a human,
able to learn anything and do many tasks.
But this type of AI doesn't exist yet.
It's more of a dream for now.
Aria asked, How do these machines learn?
That's where machine learning comes in, her grandfather replied.
Machine learning is a type of AI that learns from data instead of being told what to do step by step.
Imagine teaching a dog to sit.
You show it how, give it treats, and repeat.
Over time, the dog learns.
Machine learning works the same way, you feed it data and it finds patterns.
For example, if you want a computer to recognize pictures of cats, you show it thousands of cat pictures.
It starts to see what cats usually look like.
Furry, whiskers, pointy ears.
Over time, it learns to tell a cat apart from a dog or a chair.
The program that does this learning is called a model.
A model is like a brain built by the computer using the data it was given.
The more data it gets, the better it learns.
But how does the computer know what a cat is?
Aria asked.
Her grandfather said, that's thanks to something called a neural network.
It's a method used in machine learning that's inspired by how our brains work.
A neural network is made up of layers of tiny parts called neurons.
These are not real brain cells, but math functions.
Each neuron takes in numbers, does some math, and passes the result to the next layer of neurons.
Imagine passing a note through a group of friends and each one adds or changes a word before giving it to the next.
By the end, the note may have transformed in a useful way.
That's what a neural network does to data.
It turns it into something meaningful, like recognizing a cat in a picture.
The more layers a network has, the more complex patterns it can understand.
When a network has many layers, it's called deep learning.
To get a neural network to work, it needs to be trained.
Training is the process where the model is shown lots of examples so it can learn.
Training involves giving the model data and letting it guess something like whether a picture has a cat.
At first it guessed badly, but then it compares its guess to the correct answer.
If it's wrong, it adjusts itself using a method called backpropagation.
Backpropagation is like checking your math homework.
If the answer is wrong, you go back, find where you messed up, and fix it.
In AI, this helps the model improve step by step.
This cycle of guessing, checking, and adjusting is repeated many times.
The model slowly gets better at the task.
Can AI make mistakes?
Arya asked.
Oh yes, her grandfather said.
AI is smart in some ways, but not perfect.
AI only learns from the data we give it.
If the data is bad, the AI will be bad.
This is called bias.
For example, if a face recognition system is trained mostly on photos of light skinned people, it might not work well on darker skinned people.
Also, AI doesn't really understand the world.
It only sees patterns in numbers.
It doesn't know what a cat feels like or why we love them.
That's why AI can sometimes be fooled by simple tricks, like weird images that a human would never mistake for a cat.
AI is everywhere, her grandfather explained.
It helps recommend videos on YouTube, powers voice assistants like Siri or Alexa, drives some cars, and even helps doctors find diseases and scans.
But not all AI is harmless.
It can be used for spying, spreading fake news, or making decisions that affect people's lives like who gets a loan or a job.
That's why it's important for people to understand how AI works, so they can ask good questions and build it responsibly.
Aria asked, Will AI take over the world?
Her grandfather laughed.
Not like in the movies, but it will change the world.
The future of AI depends on how people choose to use it.
It can help solve big problems like climate change or disease, but it also needs rules and careful thinking.
Just like fire or electricity, AI is a tool, a powerful one.
If used wisely, it can do great good.
Aria sat back, her mind buzzing.
She had started the day wondering if machines could think.
Now she knows that while they don't think like humans, they can do amazing things through learning, data, and clever programming.
She smiled and said, Maybe I'll build an AI someday.
Her grandfather smiled too.
Just remember, it's not about making a machine smart, it's about making it useful and fair for everyone.
And from that day on, Aria started her journey not just to understand AI, but
to shape it with care, creativity, and curiosity. We know humans learn from their past experiences, and machines follow instructions given by humans.
But what if humans can train the machines to learn from their past data and do what humans can do and much faster? Well, that's called machine learning. But it's a lot more than just learning.
It's also about understanding and reasoning. So today we will learn about the basics of machine learning. So that's Paul. He loves listening to new songs.
He either likes them or dislikes them. Paul decides this on the basis of the songs tempo, genre, intensity, and the gender of voice. For simplicity, let's just use tempo and intensity for now.
So here, tempo is on the x-axis ranging from relaxed to fast, whereas intensity is on the y axis, ranging from light to soaring.
We see that Paul likes the song with fast tempo and soaring intensity, while he dislikes the song with relaxed tempo
and light intensity. So now we know Paul's choices. Let's say Paul listens to a new song. Let's name it as song A. Song A has fast tempo and a soaring intensity. So it lies somewhere here.
Looking at the data, can you guess whether Paul will like the song or not? Correct. So Paul likes this song.
By looking at Paul's past choices, we were able to classify the unknown song very easily, right? Let's say now Paul listens to a new song. Let's label it as song B.
So song B lies somewhere here with medium tempo and medium intensity. Neither relaxed nor fast, neither light nor soaring. Now can you guess whether Paul likes it or not?
Not able to guess whether Paul will like it or dislike it? Are the choices unclear? Correct. We could easily classify song A.
But when the choice became complicated, as in the case of song B, yes, and that's where machine learning comes in. Let's see how.
In the same example for song B, if we draw a circle around the song B, we see that there are four votes for like, whereas one vote for dislike.
If we go for the majority votes, we can say that Paul will definitely like the song. That's all. This was a basic machine learning algorithm also. It's called K nearest neighbors.
So this is just a small example in one of the many machine learning algorithms. Quite easy, right? Believe me, it is. But what happens when the choices become complicated? As in the case of song B.
That's when machine learning comes in. It learns the data, builds the prediction model, and when the new data point comes in, it can easily predict for it.
More the data, better the model, higher will be the accuracy. There are many ways in which the machine learns. It could be either supervised learning, unsupervised learning, or reinforcement learning.
Let's first quickly understand supervised learning. Suppose your friend gives you 1 million coins of three different currencies, say 1 rupee, 1 euro, and 1 dirham. Each coin has different weights.
For example, a coin of 1 rupee weighs 3 grams, 1 euro weighs 7 grams, and 1 dirham weighs 4 grams. Your model will predict the currency of the coin.
Here, your weight becomes the feature of coins, while currency becomes their label. When you feed this data to the machine learning model, it learns which feature is associated with which label.
For example, it will learn that if a coin is of 3 grams, it will be a 1 rupee coin. Let's give a new coin to the machine.
On the basis of the weight of the new coin, your model will predict the currency. Hence, supervised learning uses labeled data to train the model.
Here the machine knew the features of the object and also the labels associated with those features. On this note, let's move to unsupervised learning and see the difference.
Suppose you have cricket dataset of various players with their respective scores and the wickets taken.
When we feed this data set to the machine, the machine identifies the pattern of player performance. So it plots this data with the respective wickets on the x-axis while runs on the y axis.
While looking at the data, you will clearly see that there are two clusters.
The one cluster are the players who scored high runs and took less wickets, while the other cluster is of the players who scored less runs but took many wickets.
So here we interpret these two clusters as batsmen and bowlers. The important point to note here is that there were no labels of batsmen. And bowlers.
Hence, the learning with unlabeled data is unsupervised learning. So we saw supervised learning where the data was labeled and the unsupervised learning where the data was unlabeled.
And then there is reinforcement learning, which is reward-based learning. Or we can say that it works on the principle of feedback.
Here, let's say you provide the system with an image of a dog and ask it to identify it. The system identifies it as a cat.
So you give a negative feedback to the machine saying that it's a dog's image.
The machine will learn from the feedback and finally, if it comes across any other image of a dog, it will be able to classify it correctly. That is reinforcement learning.
To generalize machine learning model, let's see a flowchart. Input is given to a machine learning model, which then gives the output according to the algorithm applied.
If it's right, we take the output as our final result. Else, we provide feedback to the training model and ask it to predict until it learns.
I hope you've understood supervised and unsupervised learning. So let's have a quick quiz. You have to determine whether the given scenarios uses supervised or unsupervised learning. Simple, right?
Scenario 1. Facebook recognizes your friend in a picture from an album of tagged photographs. Scenario 2. Netflix recommends new movies based on someone's past movie choices. Scenario 3.
Analyzing bank data for suspicious transactions and flagging the fraud transactions. Think wisely and comment below your answers.
Moving on, don't you sometimes wonder how is machine learning possible in today's era? Well that's because today we have humongous data available.
Everybody's online either making a transaction or just surfing the internet, and that's generating a huge amount of data every minute. And that data, my friend, is the key to analysis.
Also, the memory handling capabilities of computers have largely increased, which helps them to process such a huge amount of data at hand without any delay.
And yes, computers now have great computational powers. So there are a lot of applications of machine learning out there.
To name a few, machine learning is used in healthcare where diagnostics are predicted for doctor's review.
The sentiment analysis that the tech giants are doing on social media is another interesting application of machine learning, fraud detection in the finance sector,
and also to predict customer churn in the e-commerce sector. While booking a gap, you must have encountered surge pricing often where it says the fare of your trip has been updated. Continue booking.
Yes please, I'm getting late for office.
Well, that's an interesting machine learning model which is used by global taxi giant Uber and others, where they have differential pricing in real time based on demand,
the number of cars available, bad weather, rush hour, etc. So they use the search pricing model to ensure that those who need a cab can get one.
Also, it uses predictive modeling to predict where the demand will be high with the goal that drivers can take care of the demand and search pricing can be minimized. Great.
Hey Siri, can you remind me to book a cab at 6 pm today? Okay, I'll remind you. Thanks. No problem.
Comment below some interesting everyday examples around you where machines are learning and doing amazing jobs.
Artificial intelligence, machine learning, and deep learning represent the evolution of computer science towards creating intelligent systems.
AI is the broader concept, striving to build machines capable of human-like intelligence. ML is a subset of AI, emphasizing algorithms that learn from data to make predictions or decisions.
DL, in turn, is a specialized branch of ML that employs deep neural networks to model complex patterns. Imagine an AI-powered voice assistant like Apple Siri.
It utilizes ML to understand and respond to user queries, learning from interactions over time.
Deep learning comes into play when Siri recognizes speech patterns or interprets natural language, using neural networks to process intricate features.
The better it becomes at understanding diverse accents or refining responses, exemplifying the continuous learning inherent in these technologies.
AI seeks to emulate human intelligence, ML harness data for learning, and DL employs deep neural networks for intricate tasks.
The integration of these technologies manifests in everyday applications, transforming how we interact with and benefit. So without any further ado, let's get started.
So let's start with what is artificial intelligence. Artificial intelligence imparts data and human like intelligence to machines, aiming to create autonomous systems that can emulate human behavior.
These machines learn and solve problems, simulating natural intelligence to tackle complex tasks. Consider an illustration of an AI-driven product, the Amazon Eco.
The Amazon Eco stands as a smarter speaker employing Amazon's virtual assistant AI technology known as Alexa.
This technology enables voice interaction, allowing the device to play music, set alarms, present audiobooks, and provide up-to-date information on topics like news,
weather, sports, and traffic reports, etc. Let's move forward and see what is machine learning.
Machine learning is a subset of artificial intelligence that focuses on developing algorithms and models capable of learning and making predictions or decisions without being explicitly programmed.
ML systems leverage data to recognize patterns, adapt and improve their performance over time. There are several types of machine learning. Number one, supervised learning.
The algorithm is trained on a labeled dataset where each input is associated with the corresponding output. Number two comes is unsupervised learning.
Unsupervised learning deals with unlabeled data to find inherent patterns or structures within the information. And then comes the reinforcement learning.
This type involves training agents to make sequences of decisions by interacting with an environment. And then comes semi-supervised learning.
Semi-supervised learning combines supervised and unsupervised learning elements, typically using a small amount of labeled data and a larger pool of unlabeled data.
Let us move forward and see what deep learning is. Deep learning, a branch of machine learning, focuses on algorithms inspired by the human brain structure and functionality.
It excels in processing vast amounts of both structured and unstructured data. At the heart of deep learning are artificial neural networks, empowering machines to make decisions.
The key distinction between deep learning and machine learning lies in data presentation.
Machine learning algorithms typically demand structured data, while deep learning networks operate through multiple layers of artificial neural networks, allowing them to handle diverse data formats.
So let's start with the difference between artificial intelligence, machine learning, and deep learning. And this will show in a tabular form. So starting with the definition.
So, definition of artificial intelligence. So broad field of machine learning or creating machines with intelligent behavior is artificial intelligence.
And when we talk about machine learning, it is the subset of AI focusing on algorithms learning from data.
And then comes the deep learning, that is specialized subset of ML using deep neural networks. And now we'll see the difference with the learning approach between all these three.
So, in learning approach, artificial intelligence can include rule-based systems, expert system and more. And in machine learning, it learns from data patterns without explicit programming.
And then comes the deep learning, where it learns hierarchical representation using neural networks. And if we talk about scope, it encompasses various techniques beyond learning from data.
And in machine learning, it primarily focuses on learning patterns from data. And then the deep learning, it specifically utilizes deep neural networks for complex tasks.
And now we'll move to the next difference and we'll start with an example. So in artificial intelligence, the example is autonomous vehicles, chat boards, or expert systems.
And for machine learning, it's spam filters, recommendation systems, image recognition. And in deep learning, it is image and speech recognition, natural language processing.
And now we'll see the difference for the data requirements. So it depends on the specific application and problem solving approach.
And in machine learning, it requires labeled or unlabeled data or training. And for the deep learning, it relies on large amounts of labeled data for training deep networks.
And now for the complexity, artificial intelligence addresses a wide range of tasks, including those beyond ML.
And in machine learning, it deals with moderate to complex tasks depending on algorithms.
And for the deep learning, it is well suited for intricate tasks often requiring substantial computational resources. And now see the flexibility.
So for the artificial intelligence, it can be rule based, evolving, and adaptive. And for the machine learning, the flexibility adapts to patterns and the changes in data.
And for the deep learning, it adapts to hierarchical representations and diverse data types.
And then comes the training process. So in artificial intelligence, training process varies based on specific AI techniques used.
And in machine learning, training involves feeding data and adjusting model parameters. And in deep learning, training involves optimizing neural weights and structures.
And now we'll talk about the applications between all these three terms that is AI ML and deep learning.
So for artificial intelligence, the applications are robotics, natural language processing, game playing.
And for machine learning, it's predictive analytics, fraud detection, and healthcare diagnostic. And for the deep learning, that is image recognition, speech synthesis, and language translation.
Now you guys must be thinking, why should I consider a career in AI?
Well, AI is not just a passing trend, it's a seismic shift that is reshaping our world and creating new venues for innovation and discovery.
Now by embracing a career in AI, you become a part of a dynamic field that thrives on solving complex problems, pushing boundaries,
and making a profound impact on society.
The demand for AI professionals is skyrocketing across the industries.
From healthcare, finance, entertainment, transportation, organizations are actively seeking talented individuals who can harness the power of AI and drive their business forward.
But what skills does it take to become an AI engineer?
How can you embark on this thrilling journey?
We have the answer to all your questions.
Some steps are crucial to master the field of AI and become an AI engineer.
Let's go through them real quick. So the first step is to establish a strong foundation in mathematics and programming.
Start by gaining a solid understanding of critical mathematical concepts such as linear algebra, calculus, and probability theory.
Additionally, it is crucial to become proficient in programming languages like Python, which is commonly used in AI and developed coding skills.
Next, you need to pursue a degree in relevant fields, earn bachelor's or master's degree in computer science, data science,
AI, or a related discipline to acquire a comprehensive understanding of AI principles and techniques.
And after that, you need to acquire knowledge in machine learning and deep learning.
Familiarize yourself with ML algorithms, neural network, and deep learning frameworks.
Like, for example, TensorFlow, PyTorch to train and optimize models using real-world data sets.
And afterward, engage in practical projects, gain hands-on experience and demonstrate your skills by working on AI projects.
Building a portfolio of projects that showcase your ability to solve AI problems can make a strong impression on potential employers.
After that, collaborate and network.
This is really important.
Engage with AI communities, attend conferences, and participate in online forums to connect with professionals in this field.
Collaborating with others can enhance your learning experience and open up new opportunities.
Seek internships or entry-level positions where you can gain practical experience through AI internships or entry-level roles in
industry or research institutions.
Now, this will provide valuable exposure and help you further develop your skills.
After that, continuously learn and adapt.
In the fast-paced world of AI, it is very important to stay updated on new developments, explore specialized areas, and embrace emerging technologies and tools.
Continual learning and adaptability are essential for pursuing a successful career as an AI engineer.
Now that you're familiar with the steps involved in the journey of an AI engineer, let's discuss the essential skills you need to know to become an AI engineer.
So here's a breakdown of the skills needed. First one is having strong programming abilities.
This typically refers to expertise in one or more programming languages commonly used in data science and machine learning, such as Python or R language.
Now, proficiency in programming allows you to write efficient and scalable code for data analysis, modeling, and algorithm implementation.
Next, you need knowledge of machine learning algorithms.
This involves understanding and familiarity with a wide range of machine learning algorithms, including both supervised and unsupervised techniques.
You should be able to select and apply appropriate algorithms for specific problems as well as evaluate and optimize their performance.
Next skill is proficiency in statistics and mathematics.
Sound knowledge of statistics and mathematics is fundamental for data analysis and machine learning.
You should be comfortable with statistical concepts, hypothesis testing, regression analysis, probability theory, linear algebra and calculus.
Now, after that, you have acquired a good amount of knowledge of these skill sets. We'll move on to our next skill, which is having familiarity with deep learning frameworks.
Now, deep learning has gained significant popularity in recent years, and familiarity with deep learning frameworks like TensorFlow,
PyTorch, or Keras is valuable.
Now, these frameworks provide tools and libraries for building, training, and deploying deep neural networks for tasks such as image recognition,
natural language processing, and time series analysis.
Next, you need experience with big data technologies. Dealing with large-scale data sets requires knowledge of big data technologies such as Apache Hadoop Spark or distributed computing frameworks.
Understanding how to process, store, and analyze data efficiently in distributed environments is very essential.
Now, after you have got an experience with big data technologies, now it's the time to move on to an ex skill, which is having excellent problem solving and analytical skills.
Now, these skills will enable you to break down complex problems, identify key factors, and develop efficient solutions.
Now you should be able to adapt at critical thinking, troubleshooting, and debugging to handle real-world challenges in data science and machine learning.
So, guys, remember to stay updated with the latest advancements in the field and continue learning to stay at the forefront of data science and machine learning.
Now begin with what has changed in machine learning by 2026.
So you might be wondering what's changed in machine learning and why is it the best time to get into it now?
Well, let's go back a few years. In the past, machine learning was more about building models based on historical data.
It was about training algorithms to predict specific outcomes like classifying emails, spam or not spam, predicting house prices based on past data.
But fast forward to 2026 and the landscape has changed dramatically.
Today, machine learning isn't just about making predictions, it's about building systems that can learn, adapt, and improve over time.
We're no longer creating algorithms to just run experiments offline.
Now, machine learning systems are integrated into real-world operations and are capable of making decisions that impact the business immediately.
Here's an example to make it clearer. In the past, an e-commerce website might use machine learning to predict what products a customer might want based on their past purchases.
Now, the systems can constantly learn from new customer data, continuously refining those predictions in real time as customers' preferences are changing.
The world of machine learning has evolved from theory to practice, and this has created a huge demand for machine learning engineers
who can build scalable systems and make them work in real-world environments.
The impact of machine learning is now directly tied to business outcomes, and machine learning engineers are at the center of that transformation.
You might be thinking, okay, I get it, machine learning is impactful, but what exactly does a machine learning engineer do compared to other roles in tech?
That's a great question.
In the world of machine learning, you'll hear about a few key roles, such as data scientist, machine learning, and AI engineer. Let's break them down so you know exactly where you fit in.
Data scientists are like the detectives of data.
They spend their time analyzing large data sets, finding trends, and trying to extract meaningful insights.
They build models, but their main focus is usually on data exploration and experimenting with various algorithms. They don't typically focus on deploying those models into production environments.
Machine learning engineers. On the other hand, these are architects. They take the models built by data scientists and with scalable, deployable systems.
They work on creating solutions that will not only work in the short term, but can also scale to handle real world data in massive volumes.
The machine learning engineer is responsible for ensuring that machine learning systems are integrated into businesses that can work seamlessly with existing technologies.
AI engineers focus more on the application side of things.
They build AI-powered products like chatbots, voice assistants, and real-time systems.
While their work often overlaps with ML engineers, they are typically more focused on the user-facing product and how machine learning fits into it.
As an ML engineer, your primary focus is to take models and turn them into actionable solutions that are deployed in real-world systems.
We shall now move on to why 2026 is the right time to enter machine learning.
Now that you know the role of an ML engineer, let's talk about why 2026 is the perfect time for you to jump into the field.
You've probably heard that machine learning is a hot topic, but what does that mean for you as someone starting out in this field?
So I'll help you break that down for you.
First, the demand for ML engineers has skyrocketed. The world is full of problems that need solving, and machine learning has proven to be one of the most effective tools to solve them.
From predicting customer preferences to automating critical business functions, machine learning is changing how businesses operate.
Secondly, the tools used to build machine learning systems are more accessible than ever before.
In the past, machine learning was viewed as something experimental, something that required a lot of effort just to set up.
But today, machine learning platforms and frameworks such as TensorFlow, PyTorch, and ScikitLearn have matured significantly.
These tools make it easier to build and deploy models that can scale to handle real-world data.
We shall now move on to why is this the right time for you to get started out as a machine learning engineer?
So, how do you get started? The first step is to build a strong foundation.
You might be excited to start building models and diving into algorithms, but before that, you need to understand the core concepts that drive all the machine learning systems.
These include mathematics, programming, and data handling.
You don't need to be an expert in all of these areas, but you do need to understand the basics.
Think of these as building blocks of everything that you will need to learn machine learning.
Let's start with mathematics. You don't need to be a math genius, but you do need to understand the basics.
There are three main areas of math that will help you get started out as an ML engineer, and those are linear algebra.
This is the study of vectors and matrices which are used to manipulate and process data in machine learning models.
If you've heard terms like feature vectors or matrix operations, that's linear algebra at play.
This is the core of how machine learning algorithms operate.
This is the math behind optimizing models. You'll use calculus to adjust the parameters of machine learning models and minimize the error between predicted and the actual values.
Specifically, derivatives are used to find the best way to fit a model into the data.
Statistics.
Machine learning is all about working with uncertainty, and statistics will help you make sense of it.
Whether you're dealing with probability distributions or hypothesis testing, statistics can help you understand patterns in data and make decisions with uncertain information.
These mathematical concepts will help you build a more accurate model and optimize it effectively.
Let's move on to programming stack.
If you're new to programming, don't worry. Python is the language that you will want to learn.
It's simple to get started with and has a huge ecosystem of libraries, especially designed for machine learning.
The key libraries that you will need to master include NumPy.
This library is used to handle large arrays of matrices and data, which is the backbone of most machine learning algorithms.
If you plan on working with large data sets, you'll be using NumPy a lot.
Pandas, this library is great for data manipulation and analysis.
You'll use pandas to clean, organize, and transform data, making it ready for machine learning models.
ScikitLearn, this library provides simple, easy-to-use tools for building machine learning models.
It covers everything from data pre-processing to models like regression and classification.
Once you're comfortable with these tools, you'll be able to start building machine learning models and working with real-world data.
Next up is SQL, which stands for Structured Query Language.
As an ML engineer, you will be working on lots of data and SQL will help you query databases to retrieve information that you need.
You'll use SQL to extract data, filter it, and join tables together, making sure that you have the right data to your models.
Once you have your data, the next step is data wrangling.
Data wrangling is a huge part of your job, and if you master it, it will save you a lot of time and frustration while building models.
We shall now move on to types of machine learning.
Let's talk about the different types of machine learning.
There are three main categories which are supervised learning, unsupervised learning, and reinforcement learning.
Speaking of supervised learning, this is when you have labeled data. You train your model on data where the answers are already known.
The goal is for the model to learn the relationship between inputs and outputs so it can predict the future outcomes.
Unsupervised learning. In this case, the model works with unlabeled data and it tries to find hidden patterns and groupings in the data.
This is useful for tasks like clustering or anomaly detection.
Reinforcement learning.
This type of learning involves training an agent to make decisions by interacting with its environment and receiving rewards or penalties based on its actions.
This is often used in game AI or robotics.
We shall now move on to feature engineering and evaluation. After cleaning your data, the next step is feature engineering.
This is the process of transforming raw data into meaningful features that help your model make better predictions.
Once you've engineered your features, it's time to evaluate the model. You'll use metrics like accuracy, precision, and recall to see how well your model is performing.
Proper evaluation ensures that your model is ready for real-world applications and that it can handle data in production.
We shall now move on to the 6 month learning plan in order to become an ML engineer in 2026.
So, how do you actually get started?
Here's your 6 month learning plan to guide your journey.
Firstly, focus on learning Python, Mathematics, and SQL.
Dive into machine learning algorithms and hands-on projects.
Then learn deep learning and work with frameworks like TensorFlow or PyTorch. By the sixth month, you can work on a capstone project that covers the full pipeline from data collection to deployment.
We shall now speak about the ML Engineer Tool Stack.
So let's talk about the tools that you will need as a machine learning engineer.
You must be wondering what tools should I be learning to become a successful ML engineer in 2026.
So let's simplify this.
Git and GitHub are the first things on your list.
At first glance, version control might seem like something that only coders need to worry about.
However, it can be really crucial.
Why?
Because version control allows you to track every change that you make to your code, collaborate with teams, and roll back changes if something goes wrong.
Imagine you're working on a huge project and you mess something up. Without version control, you could lose hours of work.
But with Git and GitHub, you could go back and fix to any point and time.
You might be thinking, okay, I get that Git is useful, but what about the tools that can actually help me build and deploy machine learning models? Now that's a great question.
So let's talk about the cloud platforms like AWS, Google Cloud, and Azure.
In the past, machine learning models were often built and tested upon local machines, but we quickly realized that it wasn't scalable.
These cloud platforms give you the ability to handle large data sets, run models on high-powered servers, and scale them as your projects go.
Instead of relying on your personal laptop to do all of the heavy lifting, you can leverage the cloud to train models much faster and handle massive data
sets without worrying about memory limitations.
We shall now move on to the next topic, which is on MLOps lifecycle.
You have now got all of your tools in place. But how do you go from all of these tools coming together in the MLOps lifecycle?
So you might be wondering, what does all of the MLOps lifecycle tools even look like?
And how do I manage the process from starting to finish?
Well, here's the thing MLOps is like a well-oiled machine. It involves a series of stages that ensure that your models remain reliable, scalable, and adaptable to new data over time.
Think of it like a car assembly line.
First, you train the car and then you deploy it into the real world.
After that, you need to monitor it and see if it runs smoothly.
If it breaks down, you will have to retrain it.
Let's break it down into key steps.
Training your model. This is where you create the model using your training data.
This is a very experimental phase where you try different algorithms, tweak parameters, and optimize the model for better performance.
Deploying it to production.
Now that your model is ready, it's time to put it into action.
This means making the model available to users or clients.
Whether it's in a mobile app or a web service, deployment is where the magic happens.
Monitoring performance. Once your model is live, you can't just forget about it.
It's like checking the car's tire pressure after it's been on the road for a while.
You need to continuously track how well your model is doing.
If it starts to slip or underperform, it's time for tweaks and adjustments.
Lastly, we have retraining. Over time, your model may need to be retrained with new data to stay accurate.
This is especially true in industries where the environment is constantly changing, like e commerce or finance. This training ensures that the model stays relevant and continues to provide value.
You may be wondering that this sounds like a lot of work.
And that's true.
That's where MLOps tools like MSRO help you streamline this process.
By automating and managing this lifecycle, you can spend less time dealing with the backend and more time focusing on building innovative solutions.
We shall now move on to experiment tracking.
As you dive deeper into machine learning, you'll quickly realize how important it is to track your experiments.
At first, this might seem a little overwhelming. You might be thinking, I can just run a model and hope for the best, right?
But trust me, tracking your experiments is one of the best habits that you can develop early on. Think of it like logging your workout progress.
Even if you don't track the results, how will you know whether you're improving or not?
The same goes for machine learning.
By using experiment tracking tools, flow and weights and biases, you can keep a detailed record of every model and every hyperparameter and every evaluation metric.
Now imagine you're building a recommendation system for an online store. You try different adjustments, algorithms, and get different results.
With experiment tracking, you can easily compare which configurations work best. You can easily compare which configurations work best and learn from the past mistakes.
You'll always know which experiment gives you the best results and which needs tweaking.
Tracking experiments also helps in collaboration.
If you're working with a team, being able to see everyone's experiments in one place makes it easier to understand their approach and build on each other's work.
We shall now move on to projects and portfolio.
Now that you've got your tools and workflow in place, it's time to focus on building a strong portfolio. You might be thinking, how do I make my portfolio stand out to potential employees?
That's a great question. The answer is simple: real-world projects.
Think about it. Employers want to see what you can do in practice.
They don't just want to see theoretical knowledge, they want to see that you can solve problems and build working systems that can make a difference.
So for that reason, we have mini project examples.
At this point, you're probably itching to start building something yourself.
Well, hands-on projects are the best way to solidify what you've already learned.
For example, you could create a customer churn prediction model or a fraud detection system.
These are practical real-world projects that demonstrate your ability to build solutions from start to finish.
Make sure you document your projects clearly on GitHub and always include a detailed explanation of your approach, challenges, and results.
Remember, the goal is to show that you understand the problem and build a working solution.
now move on to Kaggle and open source.
As you continue to build your portfolio, I highly recommend diving into Kaggle competitions and contributing to open source projects.
Kaggle is an amazing platform where you can work on real-world data sets and solve problems that companies and research institutions are facing.
Not only will you improve your skills, but you'll also have the opportunity to see how top data scientists and machine learning engineers approach similar problems.
Contributing to open source projects is another excellent way to showcase your skills. It shows that you can work well with others, understanding existing systems and contribute to the community.
Plus, it's a great way to gain visibility and make connections with other engineers.
We shall now speak about the resumes which work for you.
Speaking about your resume, when it comes to landing a job as a machine learning engineer, your resume needs to be focused on real-world projects and practical experience.
So be sure to highlight the projects that you've worked on, the tools you've used, and most importantly, the impact that your work has had.
If you build a recommendation engine that boosted product sales by 20%, make sure that you include that.
Employers want to see how your work contributes to solving real business problems.
Don't forget to include links, Kaggle profile, or any other open source contributions that you have made.
Employers love seeing code and showing them your projects is the best way to stand out.
We shall now speak about what interviewers test in 2026.
By now you must be wondering what do employers actually look for in an ML engineer?
So in 2026, interviews are not just about technical knowledge.
Employers just want to see how well you can communicate your thought process and real-world problems.
You'll likely face practical tests that challenge you to build a model or analyze data in real time.
You'll also be tested on how well you explain your approach and justify the decisions that you made during the project.
Prepare to discuss things like why you choose a specific algorithm for a problem, or how you handle issues like data imbalance or overfitting,
along with what metrics you use to evaluate your model's performance.
Being able to communicate clearly your process and how you arrive at your solution is a skill that will set you apart from other candidates.
We shall now speak about the ML trends that you will need to follow.
Machine learning is evolving fast and staying up to date is key to remaining relevant in this field.
So here are a few trends to keep an eye on in 2026.
Generative models. These models can generate new data based on patterns they learn, and they're used for things like text generation, image creation, and even music composition.
AutoML automated machine learning tools are making it easier for non-experts to build machine learning models.
As a result, more people will be able to contribute to this field without needing to become experts.
Privacy first models.
As privacy concerns grow, machine learning models are being designed to work securely and ethically.
And these don't compromise on user privacy.
Staying on top of these trends will help you remain competitive and innovative in the ever-evolving field of machine learning.
So, in conclusion, I will say consistency is key in machine learning.
You don't need to know everything right away, but you must stay committed to learning and building.
Start small, keep experimenting, and keep improving. The road to become a machine learning engineer may seem long, but with the right tools and mindset, you can get there.
Welcome to Math Refresher Probability and Statistics.
In this lesson, we are going to explain the concepts of statistics and probability.
Describe conditional probability, define the chain rule of probability, discuss the measure of variance, identify the types of Gaussian distribution.
Basic of statistics and probability.
Probability and statistics Data science relies heavily on estimates and predictions.
A significant portion of data science is made up of evaluations and forecast.
Statistical methods are used to make estimates for further analysis.
Probability theory is helpful for making predictions.
Statistical methods are highly dependent on probability theory, and all probability and statistics are dependent on data.
Data is information acquired for reference or research
via observations, facts, and measurements.
Data is a set of facts structured in the form that computers can interpret, such as numbers, words, estimations,
and views.
Importance of data, data aids in seeing more about the information by identifying possible connections between two features.
Data assists in the detection of distortion by uncovering hidden patterns.
Based on prior information patterns, data may be utilized to anticipate the future or predict the current state of affairs.
Also, data aids in determining whether two pieces of information have any instance in common or not.
Types of data.
Data might be quantitative.
That is data that can be measured or counted in numbers, or it may be qualitative, which is data which is generally divided into groups or in simpler words,
which cannot be counted or measured in numbers.
Let's consider an example.
A customer information data of a bank may contain quantitative and qualitative data.
Consider this snapshot where we have customer ID, surname, geography, gender, age, balance, has C
or card is active member.
Amongst these variables we can see surname is mostly qualitative as it cannot be counted and measured in numbers.
Geography and gender are also qualitative as they cannot be counted in numbers and are mostly groups.
Has seer card, that is, has credit card and is active member, although are containing numerical in form.
But these are categorical.
That means these have been divided into groups of one and zero
that represent yes and no as an answer.
Hence these two variables are also qualitative.
Customer ID is again, although a numerical data.
However, the significance or intuition behind customer ID is categorical.
Hence, it may be kept in the qualitative data also.
However, age and balance.
These are numerical information which have been measured or counted and numerical operations can be performed on them.
Hence, these are under quantitative data categories.
Introduction to descriptive statistics.
Descriptive statistics.
A descriptive measurement is summary measure that quantitatively portrays the most important features of a set of data.
Allowing for a better comprehension of the information, data can be measured as different levels.
The levels of measurement describe the nature of information stored in the data assigned to the variables.
Qualitative data can be measured as nominal or ordinal.
Quantitative data can be measured in terms of interval and ratio type.
Nominal data.
The data is categorized using names, labels, or qualities.
For example, brand name, zip code, and gender.
Ordinal data can be arranged in order or ranked and can be compared.
Examples include grades, star reviews, position and race, and date.
Interval data is the data that is ordered and has meaningful differences between the data points, example, temperature in Celsius,
and year of birth.
Ratio data is similar to the interval level with the added property of inherent zero.
Mathematical calculations can be performed on both interval as well as ratio data.
For example, height, age, and weight.
Population versus sample.
Before analyzing the data, it's important to figure out if it's from a population or a sample.
Population is a collection of all available items as well as each unit in our study.
Sample is a subset of the population that contains only a few units of the population.
Population data is used for study when the data pool is very small and can give all the required information.
Samples are collected randomly and represent the entire population in the best possible way.
Measures of central tendency.
The central tendency is a single value that aids in the description of the data by determining its center position.
Measures of central tendency are sometimes known as summary statistics or measures of central location.
The most popular measurements of central tendency are mean, median, and mode.
The normal distribution is a bell-shaped, symmetrical distribution in which mean, median, and mode all are equal.
The curve over here shows the bell-shaped curve or the normal distribution of variable x.
The point over here that is x1
is the point which represents the mean, median, and mode of this distribution.
Mean.
Mean is calculated by dividing the sum of all data values by the total number of data values.
It gets affected when there are unusual or extreme values.
It is sensitive to the outliers.
Mean can be calculated as summation over all the values of x in a collection divided by the size of the collection.
For example, we have a collection where we have values as 7, 3, 4, 1, 6, and 7.
We find out the sum of these values which is 28, and there are a total of 6 values.
So 28 divided by 6 gives us a mean value of 4.66.
Median.
It is the middle value in the set of the data that has been sorted in ascending order.
It is a better alternative to mean, since it is less impacted by outliers and skewness.
It is closer to the actual central value.
Median is calculated differently for different sizes of data,
differentiated as if the total number of values is odd,
or if the total number of values is even.
For example, in this case, we have five elements.
After sorting, whatever middle value we get.
That means n plus 1 by 2th term in this case.
5 plus 1 divided by 2.
That is the third term, which is 4 is the median value.
In case when the total number of values is even like here, there are 6 values.
The average or the mean of the two central values is considered as the median.
In this case, the median is the mean of 6 and 4, which is 5.
Mode.
Mode represents the most common value in the dataset.
It is not at all affected by extreme observations.
It is the best measure of central tendency for highly skewed or non-normal distribution.
Mode for categorical data is determined by estimating the frequencies for each categories,
and then the category with the highest frequency is considered to be mode.
Like in this case, 7 has the highest frequency, hence 7 becomes the mode value.
However, in case of continuous data or quantitative data, the calculation of mode is slightly different.
The first step in calculation of mode is dividing the data into classes which are equal with, then getting the frequency of data points lying in within that range of classes,
and finally selecting the class with the highest frequency.
Using the range of that class and the frequencies, we can get the final mode value.
Using the formula L plus
Fm minus F1 multiplied to H divided by Fm minus F1 plus Fm minus F2.
Here L is the lower limit or the lower observation of the mode class.
h is the size of the mode class.
Fm is the frequency of the mode class.
F1 is the frequency of the class proceeding to mode.
And F2 is the frequency of the class succeeding to mode.
This gives us the final mode value.
Mean versus expectation.
Now let's talk about mean versus expectation.
So in general, we use the expected value or expectation when we want to calculate the mean of a probability distribution
that represents the average value we expect to occur before collecting any data.
And mean, on the other hand, mean is basically used when we want to calculate the average value of a given sample.
This represents the average value of raw data that we may have already collected.
We can understand this by using a simple example.
Now, to calculate the expected value of this probability distribution, we can use a specific formula from the previous discussion.
This is going to be the expected value where x is going to be the data value, and this px is the probability of value.
For example, we could calculate the expected value for this probability distribution to be as shown.
So here, it will be 1.45 goals.
So this represents the expected number of goals that the team will score in any given game.
And then if you talk about calculating mean, so we typically calculate the mean after we have actually collected raw data.
For example, suppose we record the number of goals that a soccer team will score in 15 different games.
Now to calculate the mean number of goals scored per game,
we can use the following formula,
where sum of x is basically the sum of all the goals divided by n and the number of records, or we can say the sample size. It
is as shown on the screen.
So this represents the mean number of goals scored per game by the team.
Measures of asymmetry.
The difference between the three distinct curves can be studied in this image.
The central curve is the normal or no skewness curve.
Here mean, median, and mode all lie on the same point.
This normal curve is symmetrical about its mean, median, and mode.
That means the left hand side of the curve is a mirror image of the right hand side of the curve.
However, in case of negatively skewed data,
the tail is elongated on the left hand side,
and the mean is smaller than the mode and the median values, or is on the left hand side of the mode,
hence indicating that the outliers are in the negative direction.
On the other hand, in case of positively skewed the data, is concentrated on the left hand side of the curve,
while the tail is elongated or longer on the right hand side of the curve.
The mean is greater than the mode and median,
or is on the right hand side of the mode and median indicating that the outliers are in the positive direction.
Let's consider an example.
The graph here shows the global income distribution for the year 2003, 2013, and a projection for 2035.
If we see the global income distribution statistics for 2003, it is highly right-skewed.
We can observe in the previous graph that in 2003,
the mean of $3,451
was higher than the median of $1090.
The global income is definitely not evenly distributed.
The majority of people make less than $2,000 each year,
while only a small percentage of the population earns more than $14,000.
Measures of variability.
Dispersion, the measure of central tendencies provide a single value that addresses the full worth.
However, the central tendency cannot depict the viewpoint entirely.
The metric of dispersion helps us focus on the inconsistency in the data spread.
Measures of dispersion describe the spread of the data.
The range, interquartile range, standard deviation, and variance are examples of dispersion measures.
Range.
The range of distribution is the difference between the largest and the smallest amount of data.
The range, for example, does not include all of a series positive aspects.
It concentrates on the most shocking aspects and ignores that aren't considered critical.
For example, for a set 13, 33, 45, 67, 70,
the range is 57.
That is, the maximum of this, which is 70 minus the minimum over here,
which is 13.
Variance.
Variance is the average of all square deviations.
It is defined as the sum of square distance between each point and the mean or the dispersion around the mean.
The standard deviation is used as variance suffers from a unit difference.
Variance can be computed as sigma square summation over x minus mu square
divided by n,
where mu is the mean of the data,
x is the individual data point,
and n is the size of the data.
This representation is for a population data.
For a sample data variance can be computed as x minus
x bar whole square summation
over it divided by n minus one.
Here x bar is the mean of these sample data,
and n is the sample size.
The units of values and variance are not equal,
so another variability measure is used.
Standard deviation.
Standard deviation is a statistical term used to measure the amount of variability or dispersion around a mean.
The standard deviation is calculated as the square root of variance.
It depicts the concentration of the data around the mean of the dataset.
Standard deviation, as indicated previously, can be computed as square root of variance.
For a population data, standard deviation sigma can be computed as square root of summation over xi
minus mu whole square divided by n,
where mu is the mean of the data.
xi are the data points, and n is the size.
Let's consider an example.
Let's find out the mean, variance, and standard deviation for this data.
The data values are 3, 5, 6, 9, and 10.
To find out the mean, we first find the sum of all these data values.
That is 33 and divide it by the count, which is 5.
We get the mean of 6.6.
To compute the variance, we start by computing the deviation.
That is x minus the mean of x.
Here 3 is one of the values of the data, and 6.6 is the mean.
So 3 minus 6.6 square, and we do that
to find out some of all the deviations divided by the count,
which is 5.
We end up getting an overall variance of 6.64.
Standard deviation, as we know, is measured at square root of variance, that is square root of 6.64,
which amounts to 2.576.
Measures of relationship.
Measures of relationship, covariance.
Covariance is the measure of joint variability of two variables.
It measures the direction of the relationship between the variables.
It determines if one variable will cause the other to alter in the same way.
Covariance between variable x and y
can be computed as summation over the product of xi minus x bar
and yi minus y bar the whole divided by n minus one.
Here x bar and y bar are the mean of x and y respectively.
The value of covariance can range from minus infinity to a plus infinity.
Correlation.
Correlation is normalized covariance.
It measures the strength of association between two variables.
The most common measure for correlation is the Pearson correlation coefficient.
Correlation between two variables
x and y can be measured with respect to covariance as covariance between x
and y divided by the standard deviation of x and standard deviation of y.
The value of correlation ranges from a negative one to positive one.
Types of correlation.
Correlation can be either a positive correlation,
zero correlation, or a negative correlation.
The first picture over here represents a perfect positive correlation,
wherein a straight line with a positive slope
is representing the relationship between the two variables.
Zero correlation means that the line representing the relationship between the two variables is horizontal to the x-axis.
Perfect negative correlation can be represented by a straight line with a negative slope.
Correlation equals to one implies a positive relationship.
That is when one variable increases the other variable also increases.
A correlation value of negative one implies a negative relationship.
That is when one variable increases the other decreases.
The correlation coefficient of zero shows that the variables are completely independent of each other.
Let's consider an example.
Here, we have two variables, height and weight.
To compute the correlation between height and weight,
we use the correlation formula as covariance of x
and y divided by standard deviation of x and standard deviation of y.
Here height is the x variable and weight is the y variable.
First to compute covariance, we compute the x minus x bar and y minus y bar values, and then the product of them.
We then compute x minus x bar square
and y minus y bar square values to compute the standard deviations of height and weight respectively.
Correlation, as we know, has been defined as covariance of x and i and y divided by standard deviations of x and y.
This can also be represented as summation over x minus x bar multiplied to y minus y bar
divided by square root of summation over sum of squared deviations.
That is x minus x bar square multiplied to square root of summation over y minus y bar whole square.
That is sum of square deviations for y.
Now, let's find out values to put into this formula.
First, we find out the overall sum of height to get the mean of height,
which is 5.14.
Similarly, we get the sum of weight to get the mean of weight as 50.
We now get the summation over x minus x bar multiplied to y minus y bar to get the numerator for the formula.
Then we compute x minus x bar square summation
and y minus y bar square, that is sum of squared deviation of x and y respectively.
Now we put in the values in this final correlation formula to get a correlation value of 0.889.
This indicates that height and weight have a positive relationship.
It is evident that as height grows, weight also increases.
In this module, we will be talking about expectation and variance.
So the expected value, or we can say mean of a given variable, that we can denote by x is a discrete random variable where it is a weighted average of the possible values that x can take,
and each value is going to be according to the probability of that specific event occurring.
So usually the expected value of x is denoted by a simple formula, where we can define the expectation based on the x parameter,
which is going to be the sum of each possible outcome multiplied by the probability of the outcome occurring.
So, in more concrete terms, the expectation is what we would expect the outcome of an experiment to be on average.
We can take an example for the coin.
If a coin is being tossed 10 times,
then one is most likely to get five heads and five tails.
Same logic can be discussed if we talk about another example of rolling a die.
So there are six possible outcomes when you roll a die, one, two, three, four, five, six.
And each of these has a probability of one by six of occurring.
So we can say that the expectation is going to be one multiplied by the probability of that happening, which is going to be one by six,
plus two by six, plus three by six, plus four by six, plus five by six, plus six by six.
and that is going to give us three.5 as an output.
The expected value is three five.
So if you think about it, 3.5 is halfway between the possible values that I can take.
And this is what we should have expected.
Next, we talk about the concept of variance.
So variance of a random variable allows us to know something about the spread of the possible values of the variable.
So for a discrete random variable x, the variances of x is going to be denoted by using a simple formula that is going to be var
x equals e x minus m, the whole square where m is basically the expected value of the expectation of x.
So this is more like a standard deviation of x, which can also be represented by using this formula.
So the variance does not behave in the same way as expectation when we multiply and add constants to random variables.
So now there are two different type of variants that we can have a fair understanding on.
First of all, we have low variance, and then we have high variance.
So low variance simply means that there is a small variation in the production of the target function, with changes in the trading data set
and at the same time, high variance as we can see here.
High variance shows a large variation in prediction of the target function, with changes in the trading data set.
So a model that shows high variance learns a lot and perform well with the trading data set.
And it does not generalize well with the unseen data set.
And that's why, as a result, such a model gives good results with training data set but shows high error rates on the test data set.
And since the high variance a model learns too much from the data set, it leads to an overfitting of the model.
So model with high variance will be having couple of issues, like it may lead to overfitting, or it may also lead to increase in model complexities.
Next, we have skewness.
So skewness in simple terms is basically a measure of asymmetry of a distribution.
So distribution is asymmetrical when it's left, and right sides are not the mirror images.
Right now, this is a mirrored image, and a distribution can have right positive or we can say negative or it can have zero skewness.
So right skewed in this scenario is basically the distribution is longer on the right side of its peak.
And a left skew distribution is going to be we can say where it is longer on the left side.
So we can see we have this one as a part of right side.
It is more elongated towards the right side.
And this one is more elongated towards the left side.
So we can think of skewness in terms of tails.
A tail is long tampering and the end of a distribution.
So it simply indicates that they are observations at one end of the distribution, but that they are relatively infrequent.
So a right skew distribution has a long tail on the right side, as you can see here.
So the number supports observed.
Let's say we have a data on a per year basis.
So again, we can have a more skewness towards the right side, where data is being dropping as we continue to increase the number of years.
For example, we may have a high sales towards the beginning of year, suppose in 2022.
But again, as we proceed to 2023, second half we are seeing the dip in performance.
So that is rightly skewed.
And same way, let's suppose if we started with the sales figure, it was really less in suppose 2002.
But again, as we proceeded to 2023 now, our sales have been gradually increasing.
So it's more like skew towards the left section as a part of negative skew.
Next we have kurtosis.
So kurtosis is basically a measure of the tailedness of a distribution.
So tailedness is how often the outliers occur and acts as kurtosis.
Is the tailedness of the distribution related to a normal distribution?
So a distribution with medium kurtosis is called as mesocurtic, a distribution with low kurtosis like this one.
This is called as the platycurtic and then distribution with high kurtosis like this one.
This is called as the leptocurtic.
So tails here they are tapering ends on either side of a distribution like this.
So they represent the probability or the frequency of values that are extremely high or extremely low to the mean.
In other words, tails here represents how often the outliers occur.
So there are three types of kurtosis.
We have platycurtic, which is negative, leptocurtic, which is a positive towards the upper end, and then we have mesocurtic, which is a normal distribution.
So mesocurtic is the medium tail, so normal distributions they have a kurtosis of three.
So any distribution with a kurtosis of a prox value of three is going to be mesocurtic, and kurtosis is described in terms of excess kurtosis,
which is kurtosis minus three.
And since normal distribution, they have a kurtosis of three axis kurtosis makes comparing a distribution kurtosis to a normal distribution even easier.
Introduction to probability.
Probability theory.
Probability is a measure of the likelihood that an event will occur.
Let's consider an example of coin toss,
where the chances of getting heads on a coin are 1 by 2 or 50%.
The probability of each given event is between 0 and 1, both inclusive.
Sum of an event's cumulative probability cannot be greater than 1.
Hence the probability of an event x lies between 0 and 1.
This means that the integral of probability of distribution over x equals to 1.
Conditional probability.
Conditional probability of any event A is defined as the probability of occurrence of A,
given that event B has previously occurred.
Condition probability of event A given B can be estimated as probability of A intersection B, that is
probability of both A and B happening together,
divided by the probability of B.
It is also written as that probability of A intersection B equals to probability of A given B multiplied to probability of B.
Let's consider an example.
In a coin, we are doing a two coin flip.
Coin one gets heads, tails, heads, and tails in subsequent flips.
While coin 2 gets tails, heads, heads, and tails in the subsequent flips.
Now the probability that coin 1 will get a head is 2 out of 4.
While the probability that coin 2 will get heads is again 2 out of 4.
The probability that both coin 1 and coin 2 will have a heads is just 1 out of the 4 flips.
Hence the probability that coin 1 will get heads given that coin 2 is already heads can be computed as probability of coin 1
edge intersection coin 2 edge,
that is 1 by 4 divided by probability of coin 2 edge.
That's a given that is 2 by 4, which is going to be 0.5 or 50% based.
Base theorem.
Base theorem calculates the conditional probability of an event based on its prior probabilities.
Basically, base theorem incorporates the prior probability distribution to predict the posterior probabilities. base theorem for conditional probability
can be expressed as: probability of A given B equals probability of B given A divided by probability of B
multiplied to probability of A.
Bayes theorem allows updating the probability values by using new information or evidence.
Here probability of A is known as prior probability.
That is the probability of event before any new data is collected.
Probability of A given B is known as the posterior probability.
It is the revised probability of an event occurring after taking into consideration the new information probability of B given A is known as the likelihood
and probability of B is probability of observing an evidence, Bayes model.
An example.
Consider an example for calculating the likelihood of having diabetes based on frequency of fast food consumption.
Here is the observed data.
Let's say the fast food audience is 20%.
Diabetes prevalence is 10%, and 5% is fast food and diabetes.
The chances of diabetes given fast food that is the conditional probability of D given B can be calculated as probability of diabetes and fast food together divided by probability of fast food.
That means 5% divided by 20%.
That equals 25%.
Define an analysis can state eating fast food increases the chance of having diabetes by 25%.
The multiplication rule of probability.
If events A and B are statistically independent and probability of A intersection B can be given as probability of A
given B multiplied to probability of B.
However, probability of A intersection B is also given as probability of A multiplied to probability of B.
Here, probability of A given B equals to probability of A when we assume that probability of B is non-zero.
Similarly, probability of B equals probability of B given A, assuming probability of A is non-zero.
Chain rule of probability joint probability distributions over many random variables can be reduced into conditional distributions over a single variable.
It can be expressed as probability of x1, x2, so on until xn equals probability of x1 intersection
probability of x i, given probability of x1 till xi minus 1.
For example, the joint probability of A, B, and C can be given as probability of A given B.
C multiply to probability of B given C multiply to probability of C.
Logistic sigmoid.
The logistics function is a type of sigmoid function that aims to predict the class to which a particular sample belongs.
Its outcome is discrete binary value, a probability between 0 and 1.
The logistics sigmoid is a useful function that follows the yes curve.
It saturates when the input is very large or very small.
Logistic sigmoid is expressed as sigma of x equals 1 upon 1 plus e to the power minus x.
The logistic sigmoid can be expressed as sigmoid function of x is given as 1 upon 1 plus e to the power minus x,
where e is the Euler's number.
Gaussian distribution.
The Gaussian distribution is a type of distribution in which data tends to cluster around a central value with little or no bias to the left or right.
It is often referred to as normal distribution.
In absence of prior information, the normal distribution is frequently a fair assumption in machine learning.
Equation.
The formula for calculating Gaussian distribution is described as the normal distribution of x.
That is the function of x, given mean as mu and variance is sigma square, can be calculated as 1 upon sigma square root of 2 pi
e to the power minus half x minus mu divided by sigma whole square,
where mu is the mean or peak value, which also is the expected value of x.
Sigma is the standard deviation, sigma square is the variance.
A standard normal distribution has a mean of zero and a standard deviation of one.
Gaussian distribution can be univariate,
which describes the distribution of a single variable x.
It can also be multivariate where it can just use to describe the distribution of several variables.
It is represented in 3D of ND formats.
Law of large numbers.
Now let's talk about law of large numbers.
The law of large numbers states that an observed sample average from a large sample will be close to the true population average,
and that it will get closer in the larger sample.
So the law of large number does not guarantee that a given sample, spatially a small sample, will reflect the true population characteristics,
or that a sample does not reflect the true population will be balanced by a subsequent sample.
This is for the law of large numbers to express the relationship between scale and growth rate.
So there are multiple examples through which we can understand.
And it is widely used in statistical analysis in working with the central limit theorem in terms of the business growth.
So there are multiple real-time set up in which these are going to be used.
So if you talk about tossing a coin, so tossing a coin in a number of times will give us two different type of outcomes.
The result will spread evenly between head and tails, and the expected average value is going to be half.
That means 50 times tails and 30 times heads.
But again, if you toss a coin 1000 times, then the result can be in different manners, because out of 1000, let's say 850 times it has been head
and only 150 times it has been tails and so on.
So that's why the possibility of one event occurring is going to be changed in large sample sets as compared to a small sample sets, as in let's say 10 times.
So the number of heads and tails unbalanced for lower number of trials, so we can see it is unbalanced.
But again, as soon as we toss more number of coins, more leans towards the balance value, or we can see the observed averages.
Next we have p-value.
So p-value is basically a number calculated from the statistical test that describes how likely we are to have found a particular set of observations if the null hypothesis were true.
So p-values are used in hypothesis testing to help decide whether to reject the null hypothesis.
And the smaller the p-value, the more likely we are to reject the null hypothesis.
So we have a term called as null hypothesis.
So all statistical tests, they have null hypothesis.
So for most tests, the null hypothesis is that there is no relationship between our variables of in first or that there is no difference among groups.
For example, in a two-tail t-test, the non-hypothesis is that the difference between two groups is going to be zero.
So p-value is going to tell us how likely it is that our data could have occurred under the null hypothesis.
It is done by calculating the likelihood of a test statistic,
which is the number calculated by a statistical test using our data. so p-value tell us how often we would expect to see a test statistic as extreme or more extreme
than one calculated by a statistical test.
if the null hypothesis of the test was true.
So there are multiple limitations as well.
So first one is the results can be significant, but again, they may not be practical as we have compared.
It can be based on multiple hypotheses for a game for the healthcare test.
If the test is going to be positive or not, it may show even values of the effect of a variable, but not the magnitude in real life.
What exactly is going to be the application of a drug test being failed in PharmaCompany?
Therefore, it is recommended to use confidence and levels in addition to the p-values to quantify or we can say to give a solid figure to the reserve,
which we are going to get.
The p-values they are interpreted as supporting or we can say refuting the alternative hypothesis.
So p-value can only tell you whether or not the null hypothesis is supported.
It cannot tell us whether our alternative hypothesis is true or why.
So the risk of rejecting the null hypothesis is often higher than the p-value.
So especially when we are looking at a single study or when using small sample sizes.
So this is because the smaller frame of reference, the greater are the chance that as we stumble across a statistically significant pattern completely
by accident.
Key takeaways.
Probability and statistics structure the premise of the data.
The data helps in anticipating the future or gauging in view of the past patterns of information.
The central tendency is a single value that helps to describe the data by identifying these central positions the mean, median,
and mode are the measures of central tendencies.
The distribution where the data tends to be around a central value with a lack of bias or minimal bias towards the left or right
is called as Gaussian distribution.
My name is Richard Kirshner with the Simply Learn team that's get certified, get ahead.
We're going to cover mathematics for machine learning.
So today's agenda is going to cover data and its types.
we're going to dive into linear algebra and its concepts.
Calculus, statistics for machine learning, probability for machine learning, hands-on demos.
And of course, thrown in there in the middle is going to be your matrixes and a few other things to go along with all this.
Data and its types.
Data denotes the individual pieces of factual information collected from various sources.
It is stored, processed, and later used for analysis.
And so we see here just a huge grouping of information, a lot of tech stuff, money, dollar signs, numbers.
And then you have your performing analytics to drive insights.
And hopefully you have a nice share, your shareholders gathered at the meeting and you're able to explain it in something they can understand.
So we talk about data's types of data.
We have in our types of data, we have a qualitative, categorical.
You think nominal or ordinal, and then you have your quantitative or numerical, which is discrete or continuous.
And let's look a little closer at those data types.
Vocabulary, always people's favorite is the vocabulary words.
Okay, not mine.
But let's dive into this what we mean by nominal.
Nominal, they are used to label various uh label our variables without providing any measurable value.
country, gender, race, hair, color, etc.
It's something that you either mark true or false.
This is a label. It's on or off. Either they have a red hat on or they do not.
So a lot of times when you're thinking nominal data labels, think of it as a true-false kind of setup.
And we look at ordinal, this is categorical data with a set order or a scale to it.
Uh and you can think of salary range as a great one. movie ratings, etc.
You can see here the salary range if you have 10,000 to 20,000, number of employees earning that rate is 150, 20,000 to 30,000,
100, and so forth.
Some of the terms you'll hear is bucket.
this is where you have 10 different buckets and you want to separate it into something that makes sense into those 10 buckets.
And so when we start talking about ordinal, a lot of times when you get down to the brass bones, again we're talking true false.
so if you're a member of the 10 to 20k range, so forth.
Those would each be either part of that group or you're not.
But now we're talking about buckets, and we want to count how many people are in that bucket.
Quantitative numerical data falls into two classes, discrete or continuous.
And so data with a final set of values which can be categorized: class strength questions answered correctly, and runs hit and cricket.
A lot of times when you see this, you can think integer and a very restricted integer, i.e., you can only have a hundred questions on a test, so you can
it's very discrete. I only have a hundred different values that it can attain.
So think usually you're talking about integers but within a very small range. They don't have an open end or anything like that.
so discrete is very solid, simple to count, set number.
Continuous, on the other hand, continuous data can take any numerical value within a range.
So water pressure, weight of a person, etc.
Usually we start thinking about float values where they can get phenomenally small in what they're worth.
And there's a whole series of values that falls right between discrete and continuous.
You can think of the stock market. You have dollar amounts, it's still discrete, but it starts to get complicated enough when you have, like, you know, jump in the stock market from $525.33
to $580.67.
There's a lot of point values in there.
It'd still be called discrete, but you start looking at it as almost continuous because it does have such a variance in it.
Now we talk about
we went over nominal and ordinal, almost true-false charts, and we looked at quantitative and numerical data, which we're starting to get into numbers.
Discrete, you can usually, a lot of times discrete will be put into it could be put into true-false, but usually it's not.
So we want to address this stuff, and the first thing we want to look at is the very basic, which is your algebra.
So we're going to take a look at linear algebra.
You can remember back when your Euclidean geometry, we have a line.
Well, let's go through this. We have a linear algebra is the domain of mathematics concerning linear equations
and their representations in vector spaces and through matrices.
I told you we're going to talk about matrices.
so a linear equation is simply
2x plus 4y minus 3z equals 10.
Very linear.
10x plus 12.4y equals z.
And now you can actually solve these two equations by combining them.
and that's where we're talking about a linear equation.
In the vectors, we have a plus b equals c.
Now we're starting to look at a direction.
And these values usually think of an xyz plot.
so each one is a direction, and the actual distance of like a triangle AB is C.
And then your matrix can describe all kinds of things.
I find matrices uh confuse a lot of people, not because they're particularly difficult, but because of the magnitude and the different things they're used
for. And a matrix is a chart or a um, you know, think of a spreadsheet, but you have your rows and your columns.
And you'll see here we have A times B equals C.
Very important to know your counts. so depending on how the math is being done, what you're using it for, making sure you have the same rows and number of columns or a single number.
There's all kinds of things that play in that that can make matrices confusing, but really it has a lot more to do with what domain you're working in.
are you adding in multiple polynomials where you have like uh uh ax squared plus by plus,
you know, you start to see that it can be very confusing versus a very straightforward matrix.
And let's just go a little deeper into these, because these are such primary, this is what we're here to talk about, is these different math uh mathematical computations that come up.
So when we're looking at linear equations, let's dig deeper into that one.
An equation having a maximum order of one is called a linear equation.
so it's linear because when you look at this, we have ax plus b equals c, which is a one variable.
We have two variables ax plus by equals c, ax plus b y plus z
equals d, and so forth.
But all of these are to the power of one. You don't see x squared, you don't see x cubed.
So when we're talking about linear equations, that's what we're talking about.
In their addition, if you have already dived into say neural networks, you should recognize this ax plus b y plus cz
setup plus the intercept, which is basically your neural network, each node adding up all the different inputs.
And we can drill down into that.
Most common formula is your y equals mx plus c.
So you have your y equals the m, which is your slope, your x value plus c, which is your um
y-intercept. We kind of labeled it wrong here.
threw me for a loop.
But the the c would be your y-intercept.
So when you set x equal to zero, y equals c.
And that's your y-intercept right there.
and they just have a reverse value of y when x equals zero, it equals the y-intercept, which is c, and your slope gradient line, which is your m.
So you get your y equals 2x plus 3.
And there's lots of easy ways to compute this.
This is why we always start with the most basic one when we're solving one of these problems.
And then of course one of the most important takeaways is the slope gradient of the line.
so the slope is very important, that m value.
in this case we went ahead and solved this.
If you have y equals 2x plus 3, you can see how it has a nice line graph here on the right.
So, matrixes.
A matrix refers to a rectangular representation of an array of numbers arranged in columns and rows.
So we're talking m rows by n columns. Here a11 is denotes the element of the first row and the first column.
Similarly, A12, and it's really pronounced A11 in this particular setup.
So it's row one, column one.
A12 is a row one, column two, first row and second column, and so on.
And there's a lot of ways to denote this. I've seen these as like a capital letter A, smaller case A for the top row.
Or, you can see where they can go all kinds of different directions as far as the value.
You just take a moment to realize there needs to be some designation as far as what row it's in and what column it's in.
And we have our basic operations, we have addition. So when you think about addition, you have
two matrices of two by two, and you just add each individual number in that matrix, and then when you get to the bottom, you have
in this case the solution is 12, 10 plus 2 is 12, 5 plus 3 is 8, and so on.
And the same thing with subtraction.
Now again, you're counting matrices, you want to check your dimensions of the matrix, the shape.
You'll see shape come up a lot in programming. So we're talking about dimensions, we're talking about the shape.
If the two shapes are equal, this is what happens when you add them together or subtract them.
And we have multiplication.
When you look at the multiplication, you end up with a very uh slightly different setup going.
Now if we look at our last one, we're uh uh we're like why this always gets to me when we get to matrixes, because they don't really say why you multiply matrices.
Um my first thought is one times two, four times three.
But if you look at this, we get one times two plus four times three, one times three plus four times five,
six times two plus three times three, six times three plus three times five.
If you're looking at these matrices, uh think of this more as an equation.
And so we have if you remember when we went back up here for our multiple line equations, let's just go back up a couple slides where we were looking at uh two variable.
So this is a two variable equation, ax plus b y equals c.
and this is a way to make it very quick to solve these variables, and that's why you have the matrix, and that's why you do.
The multiplication the way they do.
And this is the dot product of 1 times 2 plus 4 times 3.
1 times 3 plus 4 times 5.
6 times 2 plus 3 times 3.
6 times 3 plus 3 times 5. And it gives us a nice little 14, 23, 21, and 33 over here.
Which then can be used and reduced down to a sample
formula as far as solving the variables as you have enough inputs.
And then in matrix operations, when you're dealing with a lot of matrices, now keep in mind multiplying matrices is different than finding the product of two matrixes.
Okay? So when we're talking about multiplication, we're talking about solving for equations.
When you're finding the product, you are just finding one times two.
Keep that in mind, because that does come up. I've had that come up a number of times where I am altering data and I get confused as to what I'm doing with it.
Transpose.
Flipping the matrix over its diagonal.
It Comes up all the time where you still have 12, but instead of it being 12, 8, it's now 1214821.
You're just flipping the columns and the rows.
And then of course you can do an inverse, changing the signs of the values across this main diagonal.
And you can see here we have the inverse a to the minus one and it ends up with instead of 12, 8, 14, 12, it's now minus 22 minus 12.
Vectors.
vector just means we have
a value and a direction.
And we have down four numbers here on our vector.
in mathematics, a one-dimensional matrix is called a vector.
so if you have your x plot and you have a single value, that value is along the x-axis and it's a single dimension.
If you have two dimensions, you can think about putting them on a graph.
You might have x and you might have y and each value denotes a direction.
And then of course the actual distance is going to be the hypothesis of that triangle.
Uh and you can do that with three dimensionals, x, y, and z.
Uh and you can do it all the way to nth dimensions.
So when they talk about the k means for categorizing and how close data is together, they will compute that based on the Pythagorean theorem.
So you would take the square of each value, add them all together, and find the square root, and that gives you a distance as far as where that point is,
where that vector exists, or an actual point value.
And then you can compare that point value to another one, it makes a very easy comparison versus comparing 50 or 60 different numbers.
And that brings us up to I-gene vectors and I gene values.
I gene vectors, the vectors that don't change their span while transformation, and I gene values, the scalar values that are associated to the vectors.
Conceptually, you can think of the vector as your picture. You have a picture, it's uh uh two dimensions, x and y.
And so when you do those two dimensions and those two values, or whatever that value is,
that is that point.
But the values change when you skew it. And so if we take and we have a vector a
and that's a set value,
is your you have a and b which is your I-gene vector.
2 is the eigene value. So we're altering all the values by 2. That means we're uh maybe we're stretching it out one direction, making it tall if you're doing picture editing.
that's one of the places this comes in. But you can see when you're transforming your different information, how you transform it is then your eigenvalue.
And you can see here uh vector after line transition, we have 3a, a is the igene vector, 3 is the igene value.
So a doesn't change, that's whatever we started with, that's your original picture, and 3 is skewing it one direction, and maybe
B is being skewed another direction, and so you have a nice tilted picture because you've altered it by the hygien values.
So let's go ahead and pull up a demo on linear algebra.
And to do this, I'm going to go through my trusted Anaconda into my Jupyter notebook, and we'll create a new notebook called Linear Algebra.
Since we are working in Python, we're going to use our NumPy, I always import that as NP our NumPy Array, probably the most popular
module for doing matrixes and things in.
Given that this is part of a series, I'm not going to go too much into NUMPy.
We are going to go ahead and create two different variables, a for a numpy array 1015, and B 29.
We'll go ahead and run this, and you can see there's our two arrays, 1015, 29. And I went ahead and added a space there in between, so it's easier to read.
And since it's the last line, we don't have to put the print statement on it unless you want,
but we can simply do a plus b. So when I run this, we have 101529, and we get 3024, which is what you expect.
10 plus 20, 15 plus 9.
You could almost look at this addition as being
just adding up the columns on here coming down.
And if we wanted to do it a different way, we could also do a dot t plus b dot t.
Remember that t flips them.
And so if we do that, we now get them uh we now have 3024 going the other way.
We could also do something kind of fun. There's a lot of different ways to do this.
as far as a plus b, I can also do a plus b dot t, and you're going to see that that will come out the same, the 3024, whether I transpose
a and b or transpose them both at the end.
And likewise we can very easily subtract two vectors. I can go a minus b
and we run that, and we get minus 10 six. Now remember this is the last line in this particular section, so I don't have to put the print around it.
and just like we did before, we can transpose either the individual or we can transpose the main setup, and then we get a minus 106
going the other way.
Now we didn't mention this in our notes, but you can also do a scalar multiplication.
Let me just put down the scalar so you can remember that.
what we're talking about here is I have this array here, u, and if I go a times
u,
we'll take the value 2, we'll multiply it by every value in here.
So 2 times 30 is 60, 2 times 15.
And just like we did before,
this happens a lot because when you're doing matrices you do need to flip them. You get 6030 coming this way.
So in NUMPY we have what they call dot product.
And uh with this this is in a two-dimensional vectors, it is the equivalent of two matrix multiplication.
remember we were talking about matrix multiplication, where it is the
well let's walk through it.
We'll go ahead and start by defining two
numpy arrays. We'll have 10, 20, 25, 6, or our u and our v.
and then we're going to go ahead and do if we take
the values, and if you remember correctly,
an array like this would be 10 times 25 plus 20 times six.
We'll go ahead and print that.
There we go.
And then we'll go ahead and do the np dot of u, comma
v.
And we'll find when we do this, we go ahead and run this, we're going to get 370, 370.
So this is a strain multiplication where they use it to solve linear algebra when you have multiple numbers going across.
And so this could be very complicated. We could have a whole string of different variables going in here.
But for this we get a nice value for our dot multiplication.
And we did addition earlier, which is just your basic addition.
and of course the matrix you can get very complicated on these, or in this case we'll go ahead and do let's create two complex
matrices.
This one is a matrix of um you know 121046431. We'll just print out A so you can see what that looks like. Here's print A.
When we print A out, you can see that we have a
two by three layer matrix for A.
And we can also put together, always kind of fun when you're playing with print values.
we could do something like this. We could go in here.
There we go.
we could print A, we have it end with equals A, run, and this kind of gives it a nice look. here's your matrix, that's all this is.
Comma and means it just tags it on the end. That's all that is doing on there.
And then we can simply add in what is A plus B, and you should already guess, because this is the same as what we did before, there's no difference.
Uh we do a simple vector addition, we have 12 plus 2 is 14, 10 plus 8 is 18, and so on.
And just like we did the matrix addition, we can also do a minus b and do our matrix subtraction.
And we look at this, we have what, 12 minus 2 is 10, 10 minus 8, where are we?
Oh there we go.
8 minus uh
confusing what I'm looking at, I should have reprinted out the original numbers.
but we can see here 12 minus 2 is of course 10, 10 minus 8 is 2, 4 minus 46 is minus 42, and so forth.
So same as a subtraction as before, we just call it matrix subtraction, it's identical.
Now if you remember up here we had a scalar addition, we're adding just one number to a matrix, you can also do scalar multiplication.
Uh and so simply if you have a single value a and you have b which is your array, we can also do a times b.
When we run that, you can see here we have two times four is eight, five times four is 20, and so forth.
You're just multiplying the four across each one of these values.
And this is an interesting one that comes up. A little bit of a brain teaser is matrix and vector multiplication.
And so when we're looking at this,
we are just do a regular arrays, it doesn't necessarily have to be a numpy array.
We have a
which has our
array of arrays, and b, which is a single array.
And so we can from here
do the dot
a b
and this is going to return two values. And the first value is that is it's you could say it's like
we're doing this array, B array, first with A and then with a second one.
And so it splits it up. So you have a matrix of vector multiplication and you can mix and match.
When you get into really complicated back end stuff, this becomes more common because you're now you've got layers upon layers of data, and so
you'll end up with a matrix and a set of vector matrices that you want to multiply.
Now keep in mind that if you're doing data science, a lot of times you're not looking at this. This is what's going on behind the scenes.
So if you're in the sci kit looking at sklearn, where you're doing linear regression models, this is some of the math that's hidden behind the scenes
that's going on.
Other times you might find yourself having to do part of this and manipulate the data around so it fits right, and then you go back in and you run it through the Scikit.
And if we can do
up here where we did a matrix and vector multiplication, we can also do matrix to matrix multiplication.
And if we run this where we have the two matrices, you can see a very complicated array that of course comes out on there for our dot.
And just to reiterate it, we have our transpose matrix, which is your dot T.
And so if we create a matrix A and then we do transpose it, you can see how it flips it from 5, 10, 15, 20, 25, 30 to 5, 15, 25,
10, 20, 30, rows and columns.
And certainly with the math, this comes up a lot.
It also comes up a lot with XY plotting. When you put it into pyplot, you have one format where they're looking at pairs and numbers and then they want all of X's and all Y's.
So you know the transpose is an important tool both for your math and for plotting and all kinds of things.
Another tool that we didn't discuss is your identity matrix.
And this one is more definition.
The identity matrix, we have here one where we just did two, so it comes down as one zero zero one, uh,
one zero zero zero one zero.
It creates a diagonal of one.
And what that is, is when you're doing your identities, you can be comparing all your different features to the different features and how they correlate.
And of course, when you have feature one compared to feature one to itself, it is always one,
where usually it's between zero and one depending on how well it correlates.
So when we're talking about identity matrix, that's what we're talking about right here, is that you create this preset matrix
and then you might adjust these numbers depending on what you're working with and what the domain is.
And then another thing we can do uh to kind of wrap this up, we'll hit you with the most complicated piece of this puzzle here is an inverse
a matrix.
And let's just go ahead and put the
it's a lengthy description.
Let's go ahead and put the description. This is straight out of the
website for NumPy.
so given a square matrix A, here's our square matrix A, which is 210010121, keep in mind three by three, it's square, it's got to be equal.
It's going to return the matrix A inverse, satisfying dot a
a inverse. So here's our matrix multiplication.
and then of course it equals the dot uh yeah, a inverse of a
with an identity shape of a dot shape zero. This is just reshaping the identity.
That's a little complicated there. so we're going to have our here's our array.
we'll go ahead and run this, and you can see what we end up with is we end up with an array 0.5 minus 0.5 and so forth
with our 211 going down 210010121.
Uh getting into a little deep on the math, understanding when you need this is probably really is is what's really important when you're doing data science
versus handwriting this out and looking up the math and handwriting all the pieces out. You do need to know about the linear algorithm inverse of A.
so if it comes up you can easily pull it up or at least remember where to look it up.
We took a look at the algebra side of it. Let's go ahead and take a look at the calculus side of what's going on here with the machine learning.
So calculus, oh my goodness, and differential equations, you gotta throw that in there because that's all part of the bag of tricks,
especially when you're doing large neural networks, but it also comes up in many other areas.
The good news is most of it's already done for you in the back end. so when it comes up, you really do need to understand from the data science, not data analytics.
Data analytics means you're digging deep into actually solving these math equations.
And a neural network is just a giant differential equation.
So when we talk about calculus, we're going to go ahead and understand it by talking about cars versus time and speed.
So it helps to calculate the spontaneous rate of change.
So suppose we plot a graph of the speed of a car with respect to time.
So as you can see here, going down the highway, probably merged into the highway from an on-ramp, so I had to accelerate, so my speed went way up.
Stuck in traffic, merged into the traffic, traffic opens up, and I accelerate again up to the speed limit, and maybe it peters
off up there.
So you can look at this as
the speed versus time. I'm getting faster and faster because I'm continually accelerating. And if I hit the brakes, it'd go the other way.
So the rate of change of speed with respect of time is nothing but acceleration.
How fast are we accelerating?
The acceleration is the area between the start point of x and the end point of delta x.
So we can calculate a simple if you had x and delta x, we could put a line there, and that slope of the line is our acceleration.
Now that's pretty easy when you're doing linear algebra, but I don't want to know it just for that line and those two points. I want to know it across the whole of what I'm working with.
That's where we get into calculus.
So when we talk about the distance between x and delta x, it has to be the smallest possible, near to zero, in order to approximate the acceleration.
So the idea is that instead of, I mean, if you ever did took a basic calculus class, they would draw bars down here and you would divide this area up, um,
let's go back up a screen. You divide this area of this time period up into maybe ten sections, and you'd use that and you could calculate the acceleration between each one of those ten
sections kind of thing. and then we just keep making that space smaller and smaller until delta x is almost infinitesimally small.
And so we get a function of a equals a limit as h goes to zero of a function of a plus h minus a function of a
over h.
And that is you're computing the slope of the line.
We're just computing that slope under smaller and smaller and smaller samples.
and that's what calculus is.
Calculus is the integral. You can see down here we have our nice integral sign, It looks like a giant s.
And that's what that means is that we've taken this down to as small as we can for that sampling.
so we're talking about calculus, we're finding the area under the slope is the main process in the integration.
Similar, small intervals are made of the smallest possible length of x plus delta x, where delta x approaches almost an infinitesimally
small space.
And then it helps to find the overall acceleration by summing up all the lengths together.
so we're summing up all the accelerations from the beginning to the end.
And so here's our integral we sum of a of x times d of x equals a plus c.
that is our basic calculus here.
So when we talk about multivariate calculus, multivariate calculus deals with functions that have multiple variables.
And you can see here we start getting into some very complicated equations.
change in W over change of time equals change of w over change of z, the differential of z to dx, differential of x to dt.
It gets pretty complicated.
and it really translates into the multivariate integration using double integrals.
And so you have the sum of the sum of f of x of y of d of a equals the sum from c to d and a to b of f of x of y, dx dy equals
the sum of a to b, sum of c to d of f x of y dy dx.
Understanding the very specifics of everything going on in here and actually doing the math is use the calculus 1, calculus 2, and differential equations.
so you're talking about three full-length courses to dig into and solve these math equations.
What we want to take from here is when we're talking about calculus, we're talking about summing of all these different slopes.
And so we're still solving a linear expression. We're still solving y equals mx plus b.
But we're doing this for infinitesimally small x's, and we want to sum them up. That's what this integral sign means the sum of a of x d of x equals a plus c.
And when you see these very complicated multivariate differentiation using the chain rule, when we come in here and we have the change of W to the change of T equals a change of W
dz
and so forth.
That's what's going on here. That's what these means. We're basically looking for the area under the curve, which really comes to how is the change changing?
The Speed's going up, how is that changing?
And then you end up with a multiple layer.
So if I have three layers of neural networks, how is the third layer changing based on the second layer changing, which is based on the first layer changing?
And you get the picture here that now we have a very complicated multivariate integration with integrals.
The good news is we can solve this mathematically, and that's what we do when you do neural networks and reverse propagation.
So the nice thing is that you don't have to solve this on paper unless you're data analysis and you're working on the back end of integrating these formulas and building the
script to actually build them.
So we talk about applications of calculus.
It provides us the tools to build an accurate predictive model.
So it's really behind the scenes. We want to guess at what the change of the change of the change is.
That's a little goofy. I know. I just threw that out there. It's kind of a meta term.
But if you can guess how things are going to change, then you can guess what the new numbers are.
Multivariate calculus explains the change in our target variable in relation to the rate of change in the input variables.
So there's our multiple variables going in there.
If one variable is changing, how does it affect the other variable?
And then in gradient descent, calculus is used to find the local and global maxima.
And this is really big. We're actually going to have a whole section here on gradient descent because it is really.
I mean, I talked about neural networks and how you can see how the different layers go in there, but gradient descent is one of the most key things for trying to guess the best answer to something.
So let's take a look at the code behind gradient descent.
And before we open up the code, let's just do a real quick
gradient descent.
Let's say we have a curve like this, and most common is that this is going to represent your error.
Oops.
Error.
There we go.
Ah, hard to read there.
And I want to make the error as low as possible.
And so what I'm looking at it is I want to find this line here,
which is the minimum value.
So we're looking for the minimum.
And it does that by sampling there.
And then based on this, it guesses it might be someplace here, and it goes, hey, this is still going down.
It goes here and then goes back over here and then goes a little bit closer. And it's just playing a high low until it gets to that spot, that bottom spot.
And so we want to minimize the error.
On the flip note, you could also want to be maximizing something. You want to get the best output of it.
that's simply minus the value.
so if you're looking for where the peak is, this is the same as a negative for where the valley is.
I'm looking for that valley.
that's all that is, and this is a way of finding it. So the cool thing is all the heavy lifting is done.
I actually ended up putting together one of these a while back is uh when I didn't know about sidekick and I was just starting.
boy, it's a long while back.
And it's playing high low. How do you play high low, not get stuck in the valleys, figure out these curves and things like that?
Well, you do that, and the back end is all the calculus and differential equations to calculate this out.
The good news is you don't have to do those. so instead we're going to put together the code.
And let's go ahead
and see what we can do with that.
So, guys in the back put together a nice little piece of code here, which is kind of fun.
some things we're going to note, and this is this is really important stuff because when you start doing your data science and digging into your machine learning models,
you're going to find these things are stumbling blocks.
the first one is current X. Where do we start at?
keep in mind your model that you're working with is very generic. So, whatever you use to minimize it, the first question is where do we start?
Um and we started at this because the algorithm starts at x equals three.
So we arbitrarily picked five.
Learning rate is how many bars to skip going one way or the other.
in fact I'm going to separate that a little bit because these two are really important.
if we're dealing with something like this where we're talking about well here's the function we're going to use, our gradient of our function,
two times x plus five, keep it simple.
So that's the function we're going to work with.
So if I'm dealing with increments of a thousand, point one is going to be a very long time. And if I'm dealing with increments of 0.001,
0.1 is going to skip over my answer. So I won't get a very good answer. and then we look at precision. This tells us when to stop the algorithm. So again, very specific to what you're working on.
if you're working with money and you don't convert it into a float value, you might be dealing with 0.01, which is a penny. That might be your precision you're working with.
and then, of course, the previous step size, max iterations, we want something to cut out at a certain point. Usually that's built into a lot of minimization functions.
And then here's our actual formula we're going to be working with. And then we come in and we go, while previous step size is greater than precision and itters is less than max and max iters.
Say that ten times fast.
we're just saying
if we're still greater than our precision level, we still got to keep digging deeper. and then we also don't want to go past a thousand or whatever this is, a million or ten thousand uh running.
That's actually pretty high. Um we almost never do max iterations more than like a hundred or two hundred.
Rare occasions you might go up to four or five hundred if it's uh depending on the problem you're working with. so we have our previous equals our current, that way we can track time wise.
the current now equals the current minus the rate times the formula of our previous x.
So now we've generated our new version. previous step size equals the absolute current previous.
so we're looking for the change in x.
Iters equals iterations plus one. That's so we know to stop if we get too far.
And then we're just going to print the local minimum occurs at x on here.
And if we go ahead and run this,
you can see right here it gets down to this point and it says, hey,
local minimum is minus 3.3222 for this particular series we created.
this is created off of our formula here, lambda x2 times x plus five.
Now, when I'm running this stuff, you'll see this come up a lot
in uh with the sklearn kit.
And and one of the nice reasons of breaking this down the way we did is I could go over those top pieces.
those top pieces are everything you start looking at these minimization toolkits in built-in code.
And so from
we'll just do it's actually docs.
scipy org. And we're looking at the sci kit.
There we go.
optimize, minimize.
You can only minimize one value.
You have the function that's going in. This function can be very complicated. so we used a very simple function up here.
It could be there's all kinds of things that could be on there, and there's a number of methods to solve this as far as how they shrink down. and your X naught. There's your there's your start value.
So your function, your start value.
there's all kinds of things that come in here that you can look at, which we're not going to.
optimization automatically creates, constraints, bounds.
Some of this it does automatically, but you really the big thing I want to point out here is you need to have a starting point.
You want to start with something that you already know is mostly the answer.
if you don't, then it's going to have a heck of a time trying to calculate it out.
Or you can write your own little script that does this and does a high-low guessing and tries to find the max value.
That brings us to statistics.
What this is kind of all about is figuring things out. A lot of vocabulary and statistics.
So statistics, well, I guess it's all relative. It's definitely not an Edel class. So a bunch of stuff going on statistics.
Statistics concerns with the collection, organization, analysis, interpretation, and presentation of data.
That is a mouthful.
So we have from end to end, where does it come from? Is it valid? What does it mean? How do we organize it?
How do we analyze it?
Then you got to take those analyses and interpret it into something that people can use, kind of reduce it to understandable.
And nowadays you have to be able to present it.
If you can't present it, then no one else is going to understand what the heck you did.
So when we look at the terminologies,
there is a lot of terminologies depending on what domain you're working in. So clearly, if you're working in a domain that deals with
viruses and T cells and
where does that come from and you're studying the different people, then you can have a population. If you are working with
mechanical gear, you know, a little bit different. If you're looking for the wobbling statistics to know when to replace a rotor on a machine or something like that, that can be a big deal.
You know, we have these huge fans that turn in our sewage processing systems.
And so those fans they start to wobble and hum and do different things.
If the sensors pick up, at one point do you replace them instead of waiting for it to break, in which case it costs a lot of money. Instead of replacing a bushing, you're replacing the whole fan unit.
An interesting project that came up for our city a while back. So population.
All objects are measurements whose properties are being observed.
So that's your population, all the objects. It's easy to see it with people because we have our population in large, but in the case of the sewer fans, we're talking about
the fan units, that's the population of fans that we're working with.
You have a parameter, a matrix that is used to represent a population or characteristic.
You have your sample, a subset of the population studied.
You don't want to do them all because then you don't have a, if you come up with a conclusion for everyone, you don't have a way of testing it.
So you take a sample. Sometimes you don't have a choice. You can only take a sample of what's going on. You can't study the whole population.
And a variable, a metric of interest for each person or object in a population.
Types of sampling.
We have a probabilistic approach, selecting samples from a larger population using a method based on the theory of probability.
And we'll go into a little bit more deeper on these. We have random, systematic, stratified.
And then you have a non-probabilistic approach, selecting samples based on the subjective judgment of the researcher rather than random selection.
It has to do with convenience, trying to reach a quota, or snowball.
And they're very biased. That's one of the reasons you'll see this big stamp on it that says biased. So you've got to be very careful on that.
So probabilistic sampling.
When we talk about a random sampling, we select random sized samples from each group or category.
So it's as random as you can get.
So we kind of split it up. This would be like a time setup or our different categories. And you might ask your question what is a category or a group? If you look at, I'm going to go back a window.
Let's say we're studying economics of different of an area,
we know pretty much that based on their culture and where they came from, they might need to be separated. And so, and when I say separated, I don't mean separated from their place where they live.
I mean as far as the analysis, we want to look at the different groups and make sure they're all represented.
So if we had like an 80%
of a group that is, say, Hispanic or Indian, and also in that same area, we have 20%, 20%
who are let's call our expatriates that left America and they're nice and your Caucasian group.
We might want to sample a group that is representative of both.
So we're talking about stratified sampling, and we're talking about groups. Those are the groups we're talking about.
And that brings us to stratified sampling, selecting approximately equal-sized samples from each group or category.
This way we can actually separate the categories and give us an insight into the different cultures and how that might affect them in that area.
So you can see these are very, very different, kind of depends on what you're working with as far as your data and what you're studying.
And so we can see here, just to go a little bit more, we'd have selecting 25 employees from a company of 250 employees randomly.
Don't care anything about them, what groups they're in, which office they're in, nothing. And we might be selecting one employee from every 50 unique employees in a company of 250 employees.
And then we have selecting one employee from every branch in the company office. So we have all the different branches. There's our group or our categories by the branch.
And the category could depend on what you're studying. So it has a lot of variation on there. You see this kind of grouping and categorizing is also used to generate a lot of misinformation.
So if you only study one group and you say this is what it is, then everybody assumes that's what it is for everybody.
And so you've got to be very careful of that, and it's a very unethical thing to kind of do.
So types of statistics. When we talk about statistics,
we're going to talk about descriptive and inferential statistics.
There are so many different terms in statistics to break it up.
So we so we're talking about a particular setup.
So we're talking about descriptive and inferential statistics, the base of the word describe is pretty solid.
You're describing the data. What does it look like?
With inferential statistics, we're going to take that from the small population to a large population.
So if you're working with a drug company, you might look at the data and say, these people were helped by this drug.
They did 80% better as far as their health or 80% better survival rate than the people
who did not have the drug. So we can infer that that drug will work in the greater populace and will help people.
So that's where you get your inferential.
So we are predicting how it's going to affect the greater population.
So descriptive statistics. It is used to describe the basic features of data and form the basis of quantitative analysis of data.
So we have a measure of central tendencies, we have your mean, median, and mode, and then we have a measure of spread, like your range,
your interquartile range, your variance, and your standard deviation.
And we're going to look at all these a little deeper here in a second.
But one of them you can think of is
how the data difference.
Differences, you know, what's the max, min range, all that stuff is your spread.
And anything that's just a single number is usually your central tendencies, measure of central tendencies.
So we talk about the mean, it is the average of the set of values considered.
What is the average outcome of whatever's going on?
And then your median separates the higher half and the lower half of data.
So where's the center point of all your different data points?
So your mean might have a couple really big numbers that skew it, so that the average is much higher than if you took those outliers out,
where the median would, by separating the high from the low, might give you a much lower number. You might look at it and say, oh, that's that's odd. Why is the average so much higher than the median?
Well, it's because you have some outliers, or why is it so much lower?
And then the mode is the most frequent appearing value.
this is really interesting if you're studying economics and how people are doing, you might find that the most common income, like in the US, was uh 1.24,000 a year,
where the average was closer to 80,000.
And it's like, wow, what a difference. Well, there's some people who have a lot of money, and so that skews that way up. So the average person is not making that kind of money.
And then you look at the median income, and you're like, well, the median income is a little bit closer to the average.
so it does create a very interesting way of looking at the data. Again, these are all central tendencies, single numbers you can look at for the whole spread of the data.
And we look at the measure of central tendencies, the mean is the average marks of a student in a classroom. So here we have the mean, some of the marks of the students, total number of students.
And as we talked about the median, uh if we have zero through ten, and we take half the numbers and put them on one side of the line, half the numbers on the other side of the line,
we end up with five in the middle. And then the mode. What mark was scored by most of the students in a test?
In a simple case where most people scored like an 82% and got certain problems wrong, easy to figure out.
not so easy when you have different areas where like you have like the um, oh let's go back to economy,
a little bit more difficult to calculate if you have a large group that scores that makes 30,000, and a slightly bigger group that makes 26,000.
So what do you put down for the mode?
certainly there's a number of ways to calculate that, and there's actually a different variation depending on what you're doing.
So now we're looking at a measure of spread. range. What's the difference between the highest and the lowest value?
First thing you want to look at. You know, it's uh we had everybody in the test score between 60 and 100%. Somebody got 100%, or maybe 60 to 90 It was so hard that a lot of people could not get 100%.
Um you have your inter-quartile range.
Quartiles divide a rank-ordered data set into four equal parts.
Very common thing to do as part of all the basic packages, whether you're working in data frames with pandas, whether you're working in scala,
whether you're working in R. You'll see this come up where they have range, your min, your max, and then it'll have your interquartile range. How does it look like in each quarter of data?
Variance measures how far each number in the set is from the mean, and therefore from every other number in the set.
so you have like how much turbulence is going on in this data.
And then the standard deviation. It is the measure of the variance or the dispersion of a set of values from the mean.
And you'll usually see if I'm doing a graph, I might have the value graphed, and then based on the error, I might graph
the standard deviation and the error on the graph as a background so you can see how far off it is. So standard deviation is used a lot.
So measurement of spread. marks of a student out of 100, we have here from 50 to 63 or 50 to 90.
so the range, maximum marks, minimum marks, we have 90 to 45, and the spread of that is 45, 90 minus 45.
And then we have the interquartile range using the same marks over there.
You can see here where the median is, and then there's the first quarter, the second quarter, and the third quarter based on splitting it apart by those values.
And to understand the variance and standard deviation, we first need to find out the mean.
So here's our you know calculating the average there. We end up at approximately 66 for the average.
And then we look at that in the variance. Once we know the means, we can do equals the marks minus the mean squared.
Why is it squared?
Because one, you want to make sure it's you don't have like if you if you're putting all this stuff together, you end up with an error as far as one's negative,
one's positive, one's a little higher, one's a little lower. so you always see the squared value and over the total observations.
And so the standard deviation equals the square root of the variance, which is approximately 16.
And if you were looking at a predictable model, you would be looking at the deviation based on the error. How much error does it have?
And that's again really important to know if you're if your prediction is predicting something, what's the chance of it being way off or just a little bit off?
Now that we've looked at the tools as far as some of the basics for doing your statistics and what we're talking about,
let's go ahead and pull up a little demo and show you what that looks like in Python code so you can get some little hands-on here.
For that, let's go back into our Jupyter Notebook in Python.
Now, almost all of this you can do in NumPy.
Last time we worked in NumPy. This time we're going to go ahead and use pandas.
And if you remember from pandas on here, this is basically a data frame, rows, columns.
Let's just go ahead and do a printdf.head
and run that.
And you can see we have the name Jane, Michael, William, Rosie, Hannah, and their salaries on here.
And of course, instead of having to do all those hand calculations and add everything together and divide by the total, we can do something very simple on this,
like use the command mean in pandas. And so if I go ahead and do this, print df, pick our column, salary, because we want to find the means of that colory.
We want to find the means of that column.
Uh and we go ahead and print this out, and you can see that the average income on here is 71,000.
Uh and let's just go ahead and do this. We'll go ahead and put in means.
And if we're going to do that, we also might want to find the median.
And the median is very similar,
except it actually is just median.
Uh we're used to means and average, it's kind of interesting that those are the two different words.
there can be in some computations slight differences, but for the most part, the means is the average.
and then the median.
oops, let's put a
median here.
DF salary, that way it displays a little better.
We can see the median is 54,000. So the halfway mark is significantly below the average.
Why? Because we have somebody in here who makes 189,000. Darn you rosy for throwing off our numbers.
but that's something you'd want to notice.
This is this is uh the difference between these is huge, and so is what is the meaning behind that when you're studying a populace and looking at the different data coming in.
And of course, we also want to find out hey, what's the most common
income that people make
in this little tiny sample? And so we'll go ahead and do the mode.
And you can see here with the mode, it's at 50,000.
So this is this is very telling that most people are making 50,000.
The middle point is at 54,000, so half the people are making more than that.
What that tells me is that if the most common income is below the median, then
there's a lot of high salaries going up, but there's some really low salaries in there.
And so this trend, which is very common in statistic when you're analyzing the economy and different people's income, is pretty common.
And the bigger difference between these is also very important when we're studying statistics.
and when you hear someone just say, hey, the average income was, you might start asking questions at that point, why aren't you talking about the median income?
Why aren't you talking about the mode, the most common income?
What are you hiding?
and if you're doing these analyses, you should be looking at these saying, hey, why why are these discrepancies? Why are these so different?
And of course, with any analysis, it's important to find out the minimum and the maximum.
So we'll go ahead, it's just simply uh um dot min will pull up your minimum and then dot max pulls up the maximum.
Pretty straightforward on as far as
translating it and knowing what
your lowest value and what your highest value is here, which you'll use to generate like a spread later on.
And real quick on mode, note that it puts mode zero.
Like I said, there's a couple different ways you can compute the mode.
although the standard one's pretty good.
We can of course do the range, which is your max minus your min. So now we have a range of 149,000 between the upper end and the lower end.
And you might want to be looking up the individual values on all of these. it turns out there is a describe feature in pandas.
And so in pandas we can actually do df salary describe.
And if we do this, you can see we have that there's seven setups.
Here's our mean, our standard deviation, which we didn't compute yet, which would just be a std.
And you gotta be a little careful because when it computes it, it looks for axes and things like that.
we have our minimum value, and here's our quartiles,
our maximum value, and then of course the name salary.
so these are the basic statistics you can pull them up and like just describe.
This is a dictionary, so I could actually do something like
in here I could actually go count and run, and now it just prints the count.
so because this is a dictionary, you can pull any one of these values out of here.
It's kind of a quick and dirty way to pull all the different information and then split it up depending on what you need.
Now, if I just walked in and gave you this information in a meeting, at some point you would just kind of fall asleep.
That's what I would do anyway.
So we want to go ahead and see about graphing it here. And we'll go ahead and put it into a histogram and plot that graph on it of the salaries.
And let's just go ahead and put that in here. So
we do our mapplot inline. Remember, that's a Jupyter's notebook thing.
a lot of the new version of the mapplot library does it automatically.
But just in case, I always put it in there.
import mapplot library, pi plot as plt, that's my plotting.
And then we have our data frame. I guess I really don't need to respell the data frame.
Maybe we could just remind ourselves what's in it. So we'll go ahead and just print DF.
That way we still have it.
And then we have our salary df salary, salary.plot history title, salary distribution, color gray,
plot axv line, salary, the mean value. So we're going to take the mean value,
color violet, line style dash. This is just all making it pretty.
What color, dash line, line width of two, that kind of thing.
And the median.
And let's go ahead and run this just so you can see what we're talking about.
And so up here we are taking on our plot.
So here's the data.
Here's our data frame, printed out so you can see it with the salaries. And we're looking at the salary distribution.
And just look at this, the way the salary is distributed.
You have our, in this case, we did, let's see, we had red for the median, we have violet
for our average or mean. And you can just see how it really here's our outlier. Here's our person who makes a lot of money.
Here's the average, and here's the median.
And so as you look at this, you can say, wow, based on the average, it really doesn't tell you much about what people are really taking home.
All it does is tell you how much money is in this, you know, what the average salary is.
So some of the things you want to take away in addition to this is that it's very easy to plot
an AXV line.
These are these up and down lines for your markers.
And as you display the data, I mean you can add all kinds of things to this and get really complicated. Keeping it simple is pretty straightforward.
I look at this and I can see we have a major outlier out here.
We can definitely do a histogram and stuff like that.
But you know, picture's worth a thousand words.
What you really want to make sure you take away is that we can do a basic describe, which pulls all this information out and we can print any of the individual information from the describe
because this is a dictionary.
And so if we want to go ahead and look up
the mean value, we can also do describe mean. So if you're doing a lot of statistics, being able to
it doesn't have the print on there, so it's only going to print the last one, which happens to be the mean. you can very easily reference any one of these.
And then you can also, if you're doing something a little bit more complicated and you don't need just the basics, you can come through and pull any one of the individual
references from the from the pandas on here.
So now we've had a chance to describe our data.
let's get into inferential statistics.
Inferential statistics allows you to make predictions or inferences from data.
And you can see here we have a nice little picture: movie ratings.
And um, if we took this group of people and said, "Hey, how many people like the movie, dislike, it, can't say ?". And then you ask just a random person who comes out of the movie who hasn't been.
in this study, you can infer that 55% chance of saying liked, 35% chance of saying disliked, or a 10 or 11%
chance of can't say.
So that's real basics of what we're talking about you're going to infer that the next person is going to follow these statistics.
So let's look at point estimation.
It is a process of finding an approximate value for a population's parameter, like mean or average from random samples of the population.
Let's take an example of testing vaccines for COVID-19.
Vaccines and flu bugs, all that, it's a pretty big thing of how do you test these out and make sure they're going to work on the populace.
A group of people are chosen from the population.
Medical trials are performed.
Results are generalized for the whole population.
So here's a protected, here's our small group up here where we've selected them, we run medical trials on them, and then the results work for the population.
Nice diagram with the arrows going back and forth and the very scary COVID virus in the middle of one.
And let's take a look at the applications of inferential statistics.
Very central is what they call hypothesis testing
and the confidence interval, which go with that.
And then as we get into
probability, we get into our binomial theorem, our normal distribution, and central limit theorem.
Hypothesis testing.
Hypothesis testing is used to measure the plausibility of a hypothesis, assumption, by using sample data.
Now, when we talk about theorems, theory, hypothesis, keep in mind that if you are in a philosophy, class,
theory is the same as hypothesis, where theorem is a scientific statement.
that is something that has been proven, although it is always up for debate, because in science, we always want to make sure things are up to debate.
So a hypothesis is the same as a philosophical class calling a theory.
Where theory in science is not the same. Theory in science says this has been well proven.
Gravity is a theory.
So if you want to debate the theory of gravity, try jumping up and down.
If you want to have a theory about why the economy is collapsing in your area, that is a philosophical debate.
Very important. I've heard people mix those up and it is a pet peeve of mine.
When we talk about hypothesis testing, the steps involved in hypotheses testing is first we formulate a hypothesis.
We figure out the right test to test our hypothesis, we execute the test, and we make a decision.
And so when you're talking about a hypothesis, you're usually trying to disprove it.
If you can't disprove it and it works for all the facts, then you might call that a theorem at some point.
So in a use case, let's consider an example. We have four students who are given a task to clean a room every day.
Sounds like working with my kids. They decided to distribute the job of cleaning the room among themselves.
They did so by making four chits, which has their names on it and the name that gets picked.
Up has to do the cleaning for that day.
Rob took the opportunity to make chits and wrote everyone's name on it.
So here's our four people Nick, Rob, Imlia, Imlia, and Summer.
Now Rick, Imlia, and Summer are asking us to decide whether Rob has done some mischief in preparing the chits, i.e., whether Rob has written his name on one of the chit.
For that we will find out the probability of Rob getting the cleaning job on first day, second day, third day, and so on till 12 days.
The probability of Rob getting the job decreases every day, i.e., his turn never comes up, then definitely he has done some mischief while making the chits.
So the probability of Rob not doing work on day one is three out of four. There's a .75 chance that he didn't do work.
two days, three fourths times three fourths equals 0.56.
3 days, you have 3 fourths, 3 fourths, 3 fourths, which equals 0.42.
When you get to day 12, it's 0.032, which is less than 0.05.
Remember this 0.05. Uh that comes up a lot when we're talking about certain values when we're looking at statistics.
Rob is cheating as he wasn't chosen for 12 consecutive days. That's a very high probability when on day 12 he still hasn't gotten the job cleaning the room.
So we come up to our important
terminologies.
We have null hypothesis,
a general statement that states that there is no relationship between two measured phenomena or no association among the groups.
Alternative hypothesis.
Contrary to the null hypothesis, it states whenever something is happening, a new theory is preferred instead of an old one.
And so the two hypotheses go hand in hand.
So your null, this is always interesting when talking about data science and the math behind it, it's about proving that the things have no correlation.
Null hypothesis says these two have zero relation to each other.
Where the alternative hypothesis says, hey, we found a relation, this is what it is.
We have p-value. The p-value is a probability of finding the observed or more extreme results when the null hypothesis of a study question is true.
And the t-value, it is simply the calculated difference represented in units of standard error.
The greater the magnitude of t, the greater the evidence against the null hypothesis.
And you can look at the t-value as being specific to the test you're doing, where the p-value is derived from your t value and you're looking for what they
call the 5% or the 0.05, showing that it has a high correlation.
So digging in deeper, let's assume that a new drug is developed with the goal of lowering the blood pressure more than the existing drug.
And this is a good one because the null value here isn't that you don't have any drug, the null value here is that it's better than the existing drug.
The new drug doesn't lower the blood pressure more than the existing drug.
Now, if we get that, that says our null hypothesis is correct, there is no correlation, and the new drug is not doing its job.
The alternative hypothesis, the new drug does significantly lower the blood pressure more than the existing drug.
Yay, we got a new drug out there, and that's our alternative hypothesis or the H1 or HA.
And we look at the P-value, results from the evidence like medical trials showing positive results which will reject the null hypothesis.
And again, they're looking for a 0.05 or 5%.
And the T value comparing all the positive test results and finding means of different samples in order to test hypothesis.
So this is specific to the test.
What percentage of increase did they have?
And this leads us to the confidence intervals.
A confidence interval is a range of values we are sure our true values of observations lie in.
Let's say you asked a dog owner around you and asked them, how many cans of food do you buy per year for your dog?
Through calculations, you got to know that on an average around 95% of the people bought around 200 to 300 cans of food.
Hence, we can say that we have a confidence interval of 200, 300, where 95% of our values lie in that data spread.
And this the graph really helps a lot.
So you can start seeing what you're looking at here We have the 95%, you have your peak, in this case it's a normal distribution, so you have the nice bell curve equal on both sides,
it's not asymmetrical.
And 95% of all the values lie within a very small range, and then you have your outliers, the 2.5% going each way.
So we touched upon hypothesis, uh and we're going to move into probability.
so you have your hypothesis, once you've generated your hypothesis, we want to know the probability of something occurring.
Probability is a measure of the likelihood of an event to occur.
Any event can be predicted with total certainty and can only be predicted as a likelihood of its occurrence.
So any event cannot be predicted with total certainty, it can only be predicted as a likelihood of its occurrence.
score prediction, how good you're going to do in whatever sport you're in, weather prediction, stock prediction.
If you've studied physics and chaos theory, even the location of the chair you're sitting on has a probability that it might move three feet over.
Granted, that probability is one in like I think we calculated as under one in trillions upon trillions. So it's the better the probability, the more likely it's going to happen.
There are some things that have such a low probability that we don't see them.
So we talk about a random variable. Uh random variable is a variable whose possible values are numerical outcomes of a random phenomena.
So we have the coin toss. How many heads will occur in the series of 20 coin flips?
Probably, you know, the on average they're 10, but you really can't know because it's very random.
How many times a red ball is picked from a bag of balls if there's equal number of red balls and blue balls and green balls in there?
How many times the sum of digits on two dice uh result or five each?
so you know there's how often are you going to roll two fives on your pair of dice?
So in a use case, let's consider the example of rolling two dice. We have a random variable outcome equals y. You can take values two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten, eleven, twelve.
So we have a random variable and a combination of dice.
And instead of looking at how many times both dice will roll five, let's go ahead and look at a total sum of five.
And you have in as far as your random variables, you can have a one, four equals five, four, one, two, three, three, two.
So four of those rolls can be four, if you look at all the different options you have, four of those random rolls can be a five.
And if we look at the total number,
which happens to be 36 different options, you can see that we have four out of 36 chance every time you roll the dice that you're going to roll a total of five.
You're going to have an outcome of five.
And we'll look a little deeper as to what that means.
but you could think of that at what point if someone never rolls a five or they always roll a five, can you say, hey, that person's probably cheating?
we'll look a little closer at the math behind that.
But let's just consider this as one of the cases is rolling two dice and gambling.
There's also binomial distribution.
It is the probability of getting success or failure as an outcome in an experiment or trial that is repeated multiple times.
And the key is is by meaning two, binomial. so passing or failing an exam, winning or losing a game, and getting either head or tails.
So if you ever see binomial distribution, it's based on a truefalse kind of setup. You win or lose.
Let's consider a use case and let's consider the game of football between two clubs. Barcelona and Dortmund.
The teams will have to play a total of four matches, and we have to find out the chances of Barcelona winning the series.
So we look at the total games, and we're looking at five different games or matches.
Let's say that the winning chance for Barcelona is 75% or 0.75.
That means that each game they have a 75% chance that they're going to win that game.
And losing chances are 25% or 0.25. Clearly, 0.75 plus 0.25 equals 1. So that accounts for 100% of the game. Probability for getting K wins in N matches is calculated.
And we're talking like so if you have five games and you want to know if I play how many wins in those five games should I get, what's the percentage on those?
And the probability for getting k wins and n matches is calculated by Px equals K equals NCK P to the K,
Q to the N minus K.
Here, P is the probability of success and Q is the probability of failure.
And so we can do total games of N equals 5, where K equals 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, P, which is the chance of winning, is 0.75,
Q the chance of losing, equals 1 minus P, which equals 1 minus 0.075, which equals 0.25.
The probability that Barcelona will lose all of the matches can then just plug in the numbers, and we end up with a 0.0009765625. So a very small chance they're going to lose all their matches.
And we can plug in the value for two matches.
The Probability that Barcelona will win at least two matches is 0.0878.
And of course we can go on to the probability that Barcelona will win three matches, the 0.26, and of course four matches, and so on.
And it's always nice to take this information and let's find the cumulative discrete probabilities for each of the outcomes.
Where Barcelona has won three or more matches x equals three, x equals four, x equals five.
And we end up with the P equals 0.264 plus 0.395 plus 237, which equals 0.89.
In reality, the probability of Barcelona winning the series is much higher than 0.75.
And it's always nice to
put out a nice graph so you can actually see the number of wins to the probability and how that pans out with our binomial case.
Continuing in our important terminology, location.
The location of the center of the graph depends on the mean value.
And this is some very important things. So much of the data we look at, and when you start looking at probabilities, almost always has a normalized look, like the graph in the middle.
But you do have left skewed where the data is skewed off to the left and you have more stuff happening off to the left, and you have right skewed data.
And so when this comes up and these probabilities come up where they're skewed, it's really important to take a closer look at that.
Mostly you end up with a normalized set of data, but you've got to also be aware that sometimes it's a skewed data. And then the height.
Height of the slope inversely depends upon the standard deviation.
So you can see down here the standard deviation is really large, it kind of squishes it out.
And if the standard deviation is small, then most of your data is going to hit right there in the middle, You can have a nice peak.
And so being aware of this, that you might have a probability that fits certain data, but it has a lot of outliers.
So you're if you have a really high standard deviation, if you're doing stock market analysis, this means your predictions are probably not going to make you much money.
Where if you have a very small deviation, you might be right on target and set to become a millionaire.
Which leads us to the Z-score. Z-score tells you how far from the mean a data point is.
It is measured in terms of standard deviations from the mean.
Around 68% of the results are found between one standard deviation. Around 95% of the results are found between two standard deviations.
And you read the symbols, of course they love to throw some Greek letters in there. We have mu minus two sigma.
Mu is just a quick way, it's a kind of funky u. It just means the mean.
and then the sigma is the standard deviation, and that's the O with the little arrow off to the right, or the little waggly tail going up, the O with a
with the line on it.
so mu minus two sigma is your
95% of the results are found between two standard deviations.
Central limit theorem, this goes back to the skew. If you remember we were looking at the skew values on this previous slide.
Have left skewed, normalized, and right skewed.
When we're talking about it being skewed or not skewed, the distribution of the sample means will be approximately normally distributed, evenly distributed,
not skewed, if you take large random samples from the population with the mean, mu, and the standard deviation, sigma,
with replacement.
And you can see here, of course we have our mu minus two sigma and the spread down here, the mean, the median, and the mode.
And so when you're talking about very large populations,
these numbers should come together and you shouldn't have a skewed value. If you do, that's a flag that something's wrong.
That's why this is so important to be aware of what's going on with your data, where your samples are coming from, and the math behind it.
And if we're going to do all this, we've got to jump into conditional probability.
The conditional probability of an event A is a probability that the event will occur given the knowledge that an event B has already occurred. And you'll see this as Bayes theorem, B-A-Y-E-S, Bayes.
Uh and this is read.
I mean, you have these funky looking little P brackets, A B. This is the probability of A being true while B is already true.
And you have the probability of B being true when A is already true, so P B of A.
The Probability of A being true divided by the probability of B being true.
And we talk about Bayes' theorem, which occurred back in the 1800s when he discovered this. This is such an important formula.
And it's really, it's not if you actually do the math, you could just kind of do
XY equals JK, and then you divide them out, and you're going to see the same math. But it works with probabilities, which makes it really nice.
And so if you have a set you might have eight or nine different studies going on in different areas. Different people have done the studies, they brought them together.
If we look at today's COVID virus, the virus spread, certainly the studies done in China versus the studies the way they're done in the US,
that data is different in each of those studies.
But if you can find a place where it overlaps, where they're studying the same thing together, you can then compute the changes that you need to make in one study to make them equal.
And this is also true if you have a study of
one group and you want to find out more about it. So this formula is very powerful.
and It really has to do with the data collection part of the math and data science and understanding where your data is coming from
and how you're going to combine different studies in different groups.
And we're going to go into a use case. Let's find out the chance of a person getting lung disease due to smoking. And this is kind of interesting the way they word this.
Let's say that according to medical report provided by the hospital, states that around 10% of all patients they treated suffered
lung disease. So we have kind of a generic medical report. They further found out by a survey that 15% of the patients that visit them smoke.
So we have 10% that are lung disease and 15% of the patients smoke.
And finally, 5% of the people continued smoke even when they had lung disease.
Not the brightest choice, but you know, it is an addiction, so it can be really difficult to kick.
And so we can look at the probability of A. Prior probability of 10% people having lung disease.
And then probability B, probability that a patient smokes is 15%.
And the probability of B,
if B, then A, the probability of a patient smokes even though they have lung disease is 5%.
And probability of A is B, probability that the patient will have lung disease if they smoke.
And then when you put the formulas together, you get a nice solution here. You get the probability of A of B, probability that the patient will have lung disease if they smoke.
And you can just plug the numbers right in, and we get a 3.33% chance.
Hence there is a 3.33% chance that a person who smokes will get a lung disease.
So we're going to pull up a little Python code, always my favorite, roll up the sleeves.
Keep in mind we're going to be doing this kind of like the back end way.
So that you can see what's going on.
And then later on, we're going to create
we'll get into another demo which shows you some of the tools that are already pre-built for this.
Let's start by creating a set. So we're going to create a set with curly braces.
This means that our set has only unique values. So you have a list, you have your tuples, which can never change, and then you have in this case the set.
So 4.7, you can't create a 4-7, 4. It'll delete the 4 out. So it's only unique values.
And if you use dictionaries,
quick reminder, this should look familiar because it is a dictionary where you have a value, and that value is assigned to, or that key is assigned to a value.
So you can have a key value set up as a dictionary. So it's like a dictionary without the value, it's just the keys and they all have to be unique.
And if we run this, we have a set of four seven.
We can also take a list, a regular setup, and I'm going to go ahead and just throw in another number in here, 4, and run it.
And you can see here if I take my list 1, 2, 3, 4, 4, and I convert it to a set, and here it is, my set from list
equals set my list.
The result is 1, 2, 3, 4. So it just deletes that last 4 right out of there.
And with the sets, you can also go in there and print here is my set, my set,
3 is in the set, and then if you do 3 in my set,
that's going to be a logic function.
And 1 in my set, 6 is not in the set, and so forth. If we run this,
we get 3 is in the set true, 1 is in the set false, because 3, 5, 7 is another one.
6 is in the set, 6 is not in the set, so not in my set.
You can also use this with a list. We could have just used 3, 5, 7, and it would have the same response on there
usually you do if 3 is in, but 3 in my set still works on just a regular list.
And we'll go ahead and do a little iteration. We're going to do kind of the dice one. Remember
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
And so we're going to bring in the iteration tool and import product as product.
And I'll show you what that means in just a second.
So we have our two dice. We have dice A,
and it's going to be a set of values.
You can only have one value for each one. That's why they put it in a set. And if you remember from range, it is up to 7. So this is going to be 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
It will not include the 7.
And the same thing for our dice B.
And then what we're going to do is we're going to create a list which is the product of A and B. So it's A plus B.
And if we go ahead and run this, it'll print that out, and you'll see in this case when they say product because it's an iteration tool,
we're talking about creating a tuple of the two.
So we've now created a tuple of all possible outcomes of the dice, where dice A is 1, 2, 3, 1 to 6, and dice B is 1 to 6. And you can see 1 to 1, 1 to 2, 1 to 3, and so forth.
You can remember we had a slide on this earlier where we talked about
all the different outcomes of a dice.
We can play around with this a little bit. We can do n dice equals 2, dice faces, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
Another way of doing what we did before, and then we can create an event space where we have a set which is the product of the dice faces repeat equals n
dice. And we'll go ahead and just run this.
And you can see here it just again puts it through all the different possible variables we can have.
And then if we wanted to take the same set on here and print them all out like we had before, we can just go through for
outcome and event space, outcome end equals.
So the event space is creating
a sequence. And as you can see here, when we print it out, it stacks them versus going through and putting them in a nice line.
And we'll go ahead and do something, let's go print.
Since we have the end printing with a comma, that just means it's
not going to hit the return going down to the next line. And we'll go ahead and do the length
of our event space.
And we might want to calculate something like
what about the multiple of three? What if we want to have
the probability of the multiple of three in our setup?
And so we can put together the code for the outcome and event space of xy equals outcome if x plus y
remainder 3. So we're going to divide by 3 and look at the remainder and it equals 0,
then it's a favorable outcome. we're going to pop that outcome on the end there.
And we'll turn it into a set. So the favor outcome equals a set. Not necessary because we know it's not going to be repeating itself, but just in case we'll go ahead and do that.
And if we want to print out the outcome, we can go ahead and see what that looks like. And you can see here these are all multiples of three.
1 plus 2 is 3, 5 plus 4 is 9, which divided by 3 is 3, and so forth.
And just like we looked up the length of the one before, let's go ahead and print the length of our f
outcome.
So we can see what that looks like.
There we go.
And of course I did forget to add the print in the middle because we're looping through and putting an end on the setup on there, so we're going to put the print in there.
And if I run this, you can see
we end up with 12.
So we have 36 total options.
we have 12 that
add up to a multiple of three.
And we can easily compute the probability of this by simply taking the length of our favorable outcome over the length of the event space.
And if we print it out, let me put that in there, probability,
last line, so we can just type it in, we end up with a 0.3333 chance.
And it's roughly a third.
And we might want to make this look nice. So let's go ahead and put in another line there. The probability of getting the sum, which is a multiple of three, is
0.3333.
We can compute the same thing for five dice.
And if we do this for five dice and go ahead and run it, you can see we just have a huge amount of choices.
so it just goes on and on down here.
And we can look at the length of the event space.
And we have over 7,776 choices. That's a lot of choices.
And if we want to ask the question like we did above,
where the sum is a multiple of five but not a multiple of three,
we can go through all of these different options, and then you can see here d1, d2, d3, d4, d5 equals the outcome.
And if you add these all together and the
division by five does not have a remainder of zero, but the remainder is also of a division by three is not equal to zero.
So the multiple of five is equal to zero, but the multiple of three is not, we can just append that on here, and then we can look at that favorable outcome.
We'll go ahead and set that, and we'll just take a look at this. What's our length of our favorable outcome?
It's always good to see what we're working with.
And so we have 904 out of 776,
and then of course we can just do a simple division to get the probability on here.
What's the probability that we're going to roll a multiple of five when you add them together, but not a multiple of three?
And so we're just going to divide those two numbers, and you can see here we get 0.116255 or 11.62%.
And so you can really have a nice visual that this is not really complicated math right here on probabilities.
It's just how many options do you have and how many of those are you possibly going to be able to come up with the solution you're looking for.
And this leads us to a confusion matrix.
A confusion matrix is a table which is used to describe the performance of a classification model on a set of test data for which the true values are known.
And so you'll see on the left we have the predicted and the actual.
And we have a negative, false negative, a positive, true positive,
and then we have false positive and true negative.
And you can think of this as your predicted model.
What does that mean?
That means if you divided your data and you used two thirds of it to create the model, you might then test it against an actual case for the last third to see how well it comes out.
How many times was it true positive versus false positive? You gave a false positive response.
And you can imagine in medical situations, this is a pretty big deal.
You don't want to give a false positive.
So you might adjust your model accordingly so you don't have a false positive, say with a COVID virus test.
It'd be better to have a false negative and they go back and get retested than to have 30% false positives where then the test is pretty much invalid.
So in a use case like cancer prediction, let's consider an example where a cancer prediction model is put to the test for its accuracy and precision.
Actual result of a person's medical report is compared with the prediction made by the machine learning model.
And so you can see here, here's our actual predicted, whether they have cancer or not. You know, cancer, a big one. You don't want to have a false positive.
I mean a false negative. In other words, you don't want to have it tell you that you don't have cancer when you do.
So that would be something you'd really be looking for in this particular domain. You don't want a false negative.
And this is again, you know, you've created a model, you have hundreds of people or thousands of pieces of data that come in.
There's a real famous case study where they have the imagery and all the measurements they take, and there's about 36 different measurements they take.
And then if you run a basic model, you want to know just how accurate it is.
How many negative results do you have that are either telling people they have cancer that don't, or telling people that don't have cancer that they do.
And then we can take these numbers and we can feed them into our accuracy, our precision, and our recall.
So accuracy, precision, and recall, accuracy metric to measure how accurately the results are predicted.
And this is your total true where you got the right results, you add them together, the true positive, the true negative, over all the results.
So what percentage of them were accurate versus what were wrong.
When we talk about precision, is a metric to measure how many of the correctly predicted cases are actually turned out to be positive.
So we have a precision on true positive.
Again, if you're talking about like uh COVID testing with the viruses, you really want this to be a high number. You want
that to be the center point where you might have the opposite if you're dealing with cancer, where you want no false negatives.
so this is your metric on here. Precision is your test positive, true positive plus false positive.
And then your recall, how many of the actual positive cases we were able to predict quickly with our model?
so test positive is the test positive plus the false negative on there.
And we'll want to go ahead and do a demo on the naive Bayes classifier. Before I get too far into uh naive Bayes classifier, because we're going to pull it from the SK Learn or the SciKit.
let's go ahead.
Kind of an interesting page here for classifiers. When you go into the SK Learn Kit, there's a lot of ways to do classification. And I'll just zoom up in here so you can see some of the titles.
there's everything from the nearest neighbor, linear.
but we're going to be focusing on the naive Bayes over here.
And this is just a sample data set that they put together, and you can see how some of these have a very different output.
The naive Bayes remember, is set up as probably the most simplified calculator or set of predictions out there.
And so what we've been talking about with the true false and stuff like that, where there's a uh
And then uh belief that there is a independent assumption between the features, where the features are very assumed to have some kind of connection, uh
then we can go ahead and use that for the prediction. And so that's what we're using as a naive Bayes classifier versus many of the other classifiers that are out there.
For this, we're going to use the social network ads. It's a little data set on here.
And let me go ahead and just open that up the file.
here we go.
It has user ID, gender age, estimated salary purchased.
And so we have you can see the user ID mail 19,
estimated salary 19,000, and purchase zero.
so it's either going to make a purchase or not.
So look at that last one, zero one. We should be thinking of binomials, we should be thinking of uh simple naive Bayes classifier kind of setup.
So if we close this out, we're going to go ahead and import our NUMPy as NP.
We're gonna be nice to have a good visual of our data, so we'll put it in our mapplot library.
Here's our pandas, our data frame.
and then we're going to go ahead and import the data set. And the dataset's gonna be we're gonna read it from the social network ads.csv.
Then we're going to print the head just so you can see it again, even though I showed you it in the file.
And x equals the data set iLocation,
two, three values, and y is going to be the four, column four.
Let me just run this so it's a little easier to go over that.
you can see right here we're going to be looking at 0, 1, 2 is age and estimated salary, so 2, 3.
And that's what iLocation just means that we're looking at the number versus a regular location.
regular location you'd actually say age and estimated salary.
And then column 4 is did they make a purchase? They purchased something.
so those are the three columns we're going to be looking at when we do this. And we've gone ahead and imported these and imported the data, so now our data set is all set with this information in it.
And we'll need to go ahead and split the data up. so we need our from the SK Learn model selection, we can import train test split.
this does a nice job. We can set the random state so it randomly picks the data. And we're just going to take 25% of it's going to go into the test, our X test and our Y test, and the 75% will go to X
train and Y train.
That way, once we create our model, we can then have data to see just how accurate or how well it has performed with our prediction.
The next step in pre-processing our data is to go ahead and do feature scaling.
Now, a lot of this is starting to look familiar. If you've done a number of the other modules and setup, you should start noticing that we bring in our data, we take a look at what we're working with,
we go ahead and split it up into training and testing.
in this case, we're going to go ahead and scale it.
Scale it means we're putting it between a value of minus one and one,
or someplace in the middle ground there.
This way, if you
don't have this huge setup, if we go back up to here where salary, the salary is 20,000 versus age 35.
Well, there's a good chance with a lot of the back-end math that 20,000 will skew the results and the estimated salary will have a higher impact than the age
instead of balancing them out and letting the calculations weigh them properly.
And finally, we get to actually create our Naive Bayes model.
and then we're going to go ahead and import the Gaussian naive Bayes.
And the Gaussian is the most basic one.
That's what we're looking at now.
It turns out though, if you go to the SK Learn Kit, they have a number of different ones you can pull in there. There's
Bernoulli, I've never used that one, categorical, um complement, and here's our Gaussian.
so there's a number of different options you can look at.
Gaussian, when you come to the Naive Bayes, is the most commonly used.
so we're talking about the Naive Bayes, that's usually what people are talking about when they're pulling this in.
And one of the nice things about the Gaussian, if you go to their website to SK Learn, the Naive Bayes Gaussian, there's a lot of cool features. One of them is you can do partial fit on here.
that means if you have a huge amount of data, you don't have to process it all at once you can batch it into the Gaussian
NB model.
And there's many other different things you can do with it as far as fitting the data and how you manipulate it.
We're just doing the basics. So we're going to go ahead and create our classifier.
We're going to equal the Gaussian NB.
And then we're going to do a fit. We're going to fit our training data and our training solution, so X train, Y train.
And we'll go ahead and run this. it's going to tell us that it ran the code right there.
And now we have our trained classifier model.
So the next step is we need to go ahead and run a prediction.
We're going to do our y predict equals the classifier.predict x test.
So here we fit the data, and now we're going to go ahead and predict.
And now we get to our confusion matrix. so from the SK Learn Matrix you can import your confusion matrix, just as saves you from doing all the simple math that does it all for you.
And then we'll go ahead and create our confusion matrix with the Y test and the Y predict.
So we have our actual and we have our predicted value.
And you can see from here, this is the chart we looked at. Here's predicted. So true positive, false positive, false negative, true negative.
And if we go ahead and run this, there we have it.
65, 3, 7, 25.
And in this particular prediction, we had 65 we predicted the truth as far as a purchase.
They're going to make a purchase, and we guessed three wrong, and then we had 25 we predicted would not purchase, and seven of them did.
So there's our confusion matrix.
At this point, if you were with your shareholders or a board meeting, you would start to hear some snoozing if they were looking at the numbers, and you say, Hey, here's my confusion
matrix.
So let's go ahead and visualize the results.
We're going to pull from the mapplot library colors, import listed color map.
And this is actually my machine's gonna throw an error because this is being
because of the way the setup is. I have a newer version on here than when they put together the demo.
And we need our x set and our y set, which is our x train and y train.
And then we'll create our x1, x2,
and we'll put that into a grid.
and we set our x set minimum stop and our x set max stop.
And if you come all the way over here, we're going to step .01. This is going to give us a nice line, is what that's doing.
And then we're going to plot the contour, plot the x limit, plot the y limit, and put the scatter plot in there. And let's go ahead and run this.
to be honest, when I'm doing these graphs, there's so many different ways to do that.
There's so many different ways to put this code together.
To show you what we're doing, it's a lot easier to pull up the graph and then go back up and explain it.
So the first thing we want to note here when we're looking at the data
is this is the training set.
And so we have those who didn't make a purchase, we've drawn a nice area for that, it's defined by the naive Bayes setup,
and then we have those who did make a purchase, the green.
And you can see that some of the green dots fall into the red area and some of the red dots fall into the green. So even our training set isn't going to be 100%.
we couldn't do that. And so we're looking at our different data coming down.
we can kind of arrange our X1, X2 so we have a nice plot going on, and then we're going to create the contour.
That's that nice line that's drawn down the middle on here with the red green.
That's what this is doing right here with the reshape. And notice that we had to
do the dot T. If you remember from NumPy, if you did the NUMPy module, you end up with pairs, you know, X uh X1, X2, X1,
X2, next row, and so forth. You have to flip it so it's all one row. You have all your X1s and all your X2s. So this is what we're kind of looking for right here on this setup.
and then the scatter plot is of course your scattered data across there. We're just going through all the points. That puts these nice little dots onto our setup on here.
And we have our estimated salary and our a, and then of course the dots are did they make a purchase or not?
And just a quick note, this is kind of funny. You can see up here where it says x set y set equals x train y train, which seems kind of a little weird to do.
this is because this is probably originally a definition.
so it's its own module that could be called over and over again, and which is really a good way to do it because the next thing we're going to want to do is do the exact same thing,
where we're going to visualize the test set results.
that way we can see what happened with our test group, our 25%.
And you can see down here we have the test set, and if you look at the two graphs next to each other, this one obviously has
75% of the data, so it's going to show a lot more.
This is only 25% of the data.
You can see that there's a number that are kind of on the edge as to whether they could guess by age and income they're going to make a purchase or not.
But that said, it still is pretty clear, it's pretty good as far as how much the estimate is and how good it does.
Now, graphs are really effective for showing people what's going on, but you also need to have the numbers.
And so we're going to do from SK Learn, we're going to import metrics, and then we're going to print our metrics classification report from the Y test and the Y
predict.
And you can see here we have precision, uh precision of zeros is 90. There's our recall 0.96, we have an F1 score and a support, and we have our precision, the recall on getting it right,
and then we can do our accuracy, the macro average, and the weighted average. so you can see that it pulls in pretty good as far as how accurate it is.
You could say it's going to be about 90%, is going to guess correctly that they're not going to purchase, and we had an 89%
chance that they are going to purchase. and then the other numbers as you get down have a little bit different meaning, but it's pretty straightforward on here.
Here's our accuracy, and here's our micro average and the weighted average and everything else you might need.
And if you forgot the exact definition of accuracy, it is the true positive, true negative over all of the different setups.
Precision is your true positive over all positives, true and false.
And recall is a true positive over true positive plus false negative.
And we can just real quick flip back there
so you can see those numbers on here. here's our precision, here's our recall, and here's our accuracy on this.
Welcome to this exciting journey into the world of statistics for data science. Have you ever wondered how data transforms from raw numbers into powerful insights that drive decisions?
Well, statistics is the magic behind it all.
Today, we will uncover how statistical methods help us summarize data, model uncertainty, test hypothesis, and find relationships that can predict the future.
So, buckle up, we are about to turn numbers into knowledge. Without any further ado, let's get started. Now, to start off, here's a key question. What are statistics in data science?
Now, statistics is the science of collecting, analyzing, and interpreting data. By applying statistical methods, we can uncover patterns in the data and make informed decisions.
Now, as we continue, you notice how these essential concepts will form the backbone of many data science practices.
Let's explore the key functions of statistics in data science. First, statistics helps summarize data using measures like mean, median, and variance.
Next, it models uncertainty with probability and distributions so we can better understand risk and variability in our data.
It also tests hypotheses such as when we use A B testing to compare different outcomes.
Statistics finds relationship through methods like regression and correlation, revealing how variables impact each other.
And finally, all these tools enable data-driven decision making, turning raw numbers into actionable insights.
Now let's talk about why does statistics matter in data science?
Statistics form the backbone of data science, providing the mathematical framework needed to make sense of data and draw reliable conclusions.
Without statistics, it would be impossible to turn raw data into meaningful insights or make confident evidence-based decisions.
Now let's have a look at the main branches of statistics.
Descriptive statistics and inferential statistics. So first let's talk about the definition. Then we have got methods and measures.
Now in the case of descriptive statistics, now let's have a look at the main branches of statistics. So basically, there are two core branches: descriptive statistics and inferential statistics.
Descriptive statistics summarizes and describes data using measures like mean, median, mode, range, and standard deviation.
Its purpose is to organize and present data typically with charts, graph or summary tables.
The scope of descriptive statistics is limited to the sample data itself.
on the other hand, inferential statistics makes inferences about populations based on samples.
It uses methods like hypothesis testing, confidence intervals, and regression.
The purpose here is to draw conclusion and make predictions with common examples including A B testing and survey analysis.
The scope of inferential statistics extends beyond the sample to the larger population. Understanding both these branches is essential for analyzing and interpreting data in any data science project.
Now let's take a closer look at the descriptive statistics, starting with measures of central tendency.
The first measure here is mean, which is the average of all the values simply calculated as the sum of all the data points divided by the total count.
Next is the median, which represents the middle value when the data is sorted from lowest to highest. This is especially useful when dealing with skewed distributions.
And finally, the mode is the most frequently occurring value in the data set, helping us identify common patterns or repeated outcomes.
Let's continue our deep dive into descriptive statistics by looking at the measures of variability.
First, we've got the range.
This is simply the difference between the maximum and minimum value in a data set, showing us the spread of our data, which measures the average of the square differences from the mean.
This tells us how much the values in our data set differ from the average.
Closely related is the standard deviation, which is the square root of the variance.
It gives us a more intuitive sense of how much the values typically deviate from the mean.
And finally, we've got the interquartile range, or we say IQR.
This shows us the range of the middle 50% of our data, helping us understand how data is distributed across the center and avoid the effect of outliers.
Understanding these four measures allows us to summarize not just the center of our data but how spread out and varied our data set is.
Now let's look at some practical applications of descriptive statistics.
One major use is the data exploration and summarization, where we quickly get an overview and basic understanding of complex data sets,
helping track performance and detect problems early in fields like manufacturing or operations.
And finally, they are central to business reporting and dashboards, where concise summaries are essential for managers to review trends and make data-driven decisions.
So, in short, descriptive statistics help transform raw data into clear, actionable information across many business,
scientific, and operational contexts. Let's explore the first type of data in statistics qualitative or categorical data.
This type of data includes descriptive information that cannot be measured numerically, such as categories or labels and yes or no responses.
These are all about qualities or characteristics rather than quantities. Qualitative data can be further divided into two types: nominal, where the categories have no specific order, and ordinal,
where the categories do have an order or ranking.
Recognizing and classifying qualitative data is very important as it affects how information is analyzed and interpreted in statistics.
Now let's discuss the second main type of data and statistics, which is quantitative or numerical data.
This type of data includes information that can be measured and expressed with numbers, making it ideal for mathematical analysis. Quantitative data is further divided into two main categories.
First, there is discrete data.
These are countable values with specific fixed points such as the number of students, cars sold, or website clicks.
Second, there is continuous data, which includes infinite possible values within a given range. Examples of continuous data include height, weight, temperature, or time.
Understanding the distinction between discrete and continuous data is very important as it determines which statistical methods and visualizations
will be most appropriate.
Now let's dive into the fundamentals of probability. Probability measures the likelihood of an event occurring and it's always expressed as a value between 0 and 1.
Here are some key concepts. If the probability or p equals to 0, that means the event will never occur.
If p is equals to 1, the event will always occur.
And if p is equal to 0.5, the event has an equal chance of occurring or not occurring. It's truly a 50-50% scenario.
Now understanding these basic principles help us quantify uncertainty and make informed predictions about future outcomes.
Now let's look at the different types of probability. First, there's classical probability. This is based on equally likely outcomes such as flipping a fair coin or rolling a balanced die.
Next, empirical probability, which relies on observed frequency.
It's calculated from actual data, such as the proportion of rainy days over the past month. Let's say for example, the probability of it's raining today given that it's cloudy.
Understanding these three types helps us choose the right approach for different situations whether we are predicting outcomes,
analyzing data, or making decisions under uncertainty.
Now, probability has a wide range of powerful applications in data science.
First of all, it is used in predictive modeling and machine learning where algorithms estimate future outcomes based on existing data.
Probability also plays a key role in risk management and decision making, helping businesses and researchers evaluate the likelihood of different scenarios and plan accordingly.
Conditional probability calculating the chance of one event given that the another has occurred. This is crucial in fields like healthcare, fraud detection, and marketing analytics.
And finally, probability is foundational in A B testing and experimental design, allowing us to measure the effectiveness of new strategies
or products. These applications show how probability enables smarter, evidence-driven progress in modern data science.
Let's look at one of the most common probability distributions, the normal distribution.
This distribution is famous for its bell-shaped symmetric curve, which shows that most values cluster around the mean,
with fewer and fewer values appearing as you move away from the center.
Now many natural phenomena like heights, test scores, and measurement errors tend to follow this pattern, making the normal distribution a key concept in statistics.
It's characterized by two main parameters: the mean which determines the center of the curve and the standard deviation which controls its spread.
Recognizing the distribution helps analysts make predictions, calculate probabilities, and apply statistical techniques to real-world data.
Next, let's explore the binomial distribution, which is another common probability distribution.
The binomial distribution is discrete and is used for situations with binary outcomes like success or failure.
It is based on a fixed number of trials where each trial has a constant probability of success, such as flipping a coin a certain number of times
or tracking pass fail rates.
Examples of binomial experiment includes coin flips and measuring how many students pass or fail a test.
This distribution helps us model and analyze outcomes when only two possibilities exist in each trial. Now let's focus on the poison distribution, another key type of probability distribution.
The poison distribution is a discrete distribution specifically used to model rare events.
It's particularly helpful for modeling events that occur independently over a fixed interval of time or space.
For example, it predicts how many times an event like a customer arriving on a website receiving a visit might happen in a certain period.
Typical examples include customer arrivals at a store, defect rates in manufacturing or counts of website visits over a set period.
This distribution is a great tool for understanding and predicting random independent events that don't happen very often but are important to track.
It's a branch that allows us to make inferences, predictions or generalizations about a larger population using sample data. Here are some key concepts.
First is the population versus sample. The population represents the entire group we want to know about, while the sample is the subset we actually collect data from.
Next concept is sampling distribution, which refers to the distribution of a statistic across multiple samples from the same population.
Standard error measures how much the sample statistic is expected to vary due to random sampling.
And finally, margin of error tells us how much we can expect our estimates to differ from the true population value.
Together, these concepts form the foundation for drawing reliable insights from sample data in inferential statistics.
Let's review some of the main techniques used in inferential statistics. First, we've got hypothesis testing.
This method allows us to test claims or ideas about population parameters based on sample data, helping us determine if observed results are statistically significant.
And reliability of our estimate. Next are confidence intervals. These provide a range of likely values for a population parameter, giving us a sense of possible variation, reliability of our estimate.
And lastly, regression analysis is used to model and analyze the relationships between variables, allowing us to make predictions,
uncover trends, and understand how changes in one factor might affect another.
Now let's work through the hypothesis testing process. The first step is to formulate hypothesis. Start with null hypothesis represented as H0, which states that there is no effect or difference.
Then there's the alternative hypothesis represented as H1, which suggests that an effect or difference does exist.
Now, after setting up the hypothesis, the next step is to choose a significance level noted by alpha.
Common choices for significance levels include 0.05, 5%, 0.01, 1%, 0.010, which is 10%.
The significance level is important because it controls the likelihood of making a type 1 error, also known as false positive.
And now each step in the process is critical for ensuring that statistical results are both meaningful and reliable.
The next step is to collect and analyze sample data. Ensure the data is represented by choosing a good sample. Then calculate the appropriate and test statistic for your hypothesis test.
Once that's done, it's time to make a decision. Compare the p-value to the chosen significance level alpha.
Now if the p-value is less than or equals to alpha, you reject the null hypothesis. If the p-value is greater than alpha, you fail to reject the null hypothesis. And finally, interpret your results.
Draw your conclusions with respect to the context and problem at hand, always keeping the bigger picture in mind.
Following these steps helps ensure your hypothesis test is robust, clear, and meaningful.
Let's review the common types of hypothesis test using statistics.
The one sample test compares the mean of a sample to a known value, and the one sample Z test is used when the population standard deviation is known.
Next, we have two sample tests. The independent samples t test compares to the means of two different groups, while paired samples t-test compares before and after measurements for the same subject.
For categorical data test, the she squared test checks for the independence or goodness of fit.
And Fisher's exact test is useful for small sample sizes. And lastly, non-parametric tests such as the Man Whitney U test and Wilcox On signed RANG test serve as alternatives to the T
test when data doesn't meet certain parametric assumptions. Choosing the right hypothesis test depends on your data type and the specific question you want to answer.
Let's explore the central limit theorem or CLT of foundation for inferential statistics.
The central limit theorem states that as the sample size increases, the distribution of sample means approaches a normal distribution,
even if the original data isn't normally distributed.
This sample works for any population distribution, making it incredibly powerful.
Now for good results, the sample size should typically be 30 or more.
What's interesting is the sample mean distribution, which will have the same mean as the population.
The standard error which measures variability by the sample mean equals sigma divided by the square root of n, and this gets smaller as the sample size grows.
And finally, the formula shown here, which is z is equal to x minus minus nu divided by sigma.
Divided by sigma over the square root of n. Let's standardize and compare sample needs. The CLT makes most parametric statistics possible and is the backbone for many statistical tests.
Let's review the main types of regression analysis which are used to model and understand relationships between variables. First up is linear regression.
This technique analyzes the relationship between a continuous variable and another variable, resulting in a straight line. It's commonly used in predicting sales or prices.
Next is logistic regression. Unlike linear regression, this method is used for binary outcomes, helping estimate probabilities such as whether an email is spam
or a patient has a disease. Moving to multiple regression, this allows us to account for the effect of several variables at once, modeling more complex relationships
like determining house prices. Lastly, polynomial regression, which is used for non-linear relationships.
The resulting curve rather than a straight line lets us capture growth trends and other patterns that aren't linear.
Understanding these types of regression help analysts choose the right model for the data and business's problem at hand.
Let's clarify the important differences between correlation and causation. Correlation is statistical measure of how two variables move together. Correlation values range from minus 10 to plus 1.
But remember, correlation does not imply causation.
On the other hand, causation means that one variable actually causes changes in another.
Establishing causation requires controlled experimentation and is much stronger relationship than simple correlation. Always be careful when interpreting results.
Just because two variables move together doesn't mean one caused the other.
Let's look at some common problems with interpreting correlation and causation.
First is the third variable problem, which happens when a hidden variable affects both variables in a question, leading to a misleading connection.
There's also this directionality problem where it's unclear which variable is causing others to change. But both are actually caused by a third variable, which is the hot weather.
This demonstrates that correlation does not mean one variable causes the other, so always look for hidden factors before assuming causation.
Let's talk about statistical errors, specifically type 1 and type 2 errors.
Type 1 error, also called as false positive, occurs when we reject the true null hypothesis.
In other words, we wrongly conclude there's an effect when there's actually isn't. The probability of making this error is equal to the significance level alpha.
For example, concluding a drug works when it actually doesn't.
On the other hand, type 2 error is false negative, means failing to reject a false null hypothesis, that's when we miss a real effect or difference.
The probability of type 2 error is beta, for example, missing the real effect of a drug and saying it doesn't work when it actually does.
Understanding these errors is key for designing good experiments and interpreting statistical results properly.
Let's look at three common sampling methods used in statistics. The first one is random sampling. Here, every individual in the population has an equal chance of being selected.
Where every Nth individual is chosen, random sampling is crucial for ensuring representative sample. Next is stratified sampling.
The population is divided onto homogeneous subgroups or strata, and then a random sample is drawn from each group. This approach makes sure all the groups are represented in the sample.
And finally, cluster sampling divides the population into clusters, often based on geography.
Entire clusters are then randomly selected. It's cost effective and useful for large spread-out populations.
Choosing the right method ensures the data truly represents the whole population and strengthens the study's conclusions.
So, guys, let's wrap up with some real-world applications of statistics. In business analytics, statistics are used for A B testing to optimize websites, customer segmentation, and targeting,
sales forecasting and demand planning and quality control, and also process improvement. These techniques help businesses make smarter, data driven decisions every day.
Statistics play a vital role in healthcare and medicine as well. They are key for analyzing clinical trial results, conducting epidemiological studies, evaluating treatment, effectiveness,
and identifying risk factors. By using these approaches, healthcare researchers and practitioners can improve patient outcomes in public health from businesses to medicine.
Statistics transform raw information into actionable insights that create real impact.
Statistics has a huge impact in technology, data science, and finance and power recommended systems that personalize what users see.
In finance, statistics help with risk assessment and management, optimizing investment portfolios, determining credit scores,
and supporting market research and analysis. Now these applications show how statistical techniques help make smarter decisions and solve complex challenges across
high impact industries. Are you one of the many who dreams of becoming a data scientist?
Keep watching this video if you're passionate about data science because we will tell you how does it really work under the hood.
Emma is a data scientist.
Let's see how a day in her life goes while she's working on a data science project.
Well, it is very important to understand the business problem first.
In our meeting with the clients, Emma asks relevant questions, understands and defines objectives for the problem that needs to be tackled.
She is a curious soul who asks a lot of eyes, one of the many traits of a good data scientist.
Now, she cares up for data acquisition.
To gather and scrape data from multiple sources like web servers, logs, databases, APIs, and online repositories.
Oh, it seems like finding the right data takes both time and effort.
After the data is gathered, comes data preparation.
This step involves data cleaning and data transformation.
Data cleaning is the most time-consuming process as it involves handling many complex scenarios.
Here, Emma deals with inconsistent data types, misspelled attributes, missing values, duplicate values, and whatnot.
Then, in data transformation, she modifies the data based on defined mapping rules.
In her project, ETL tools like Talent and Informatica are used to perform complex transformations that helps the team to understand the data structure better.
Then understanding what you actually can do with your data is very crucial.
For that, Emma does exploratory data analysis.
With the help of EDA, she defines and refines the selection of feature variables that will be used in the model development. But what if Emma skips this step?
She might end up choosing the wrong variables, which will produce an inaccurate model.
Thus, exploratory data analysis becomes the most important step.
Now she proceeds to the core activity of a data science project, which is data modeling.
She repetitively applies diverse machine learning techniques like KNN, decision tree, knife base to the data to identify the model that best fits the business requirement.
She trains the models on the training data set and tests them to select the best performing model.
Emma prefers Python for modeling the data.
However, it can also be done using R and SAS.
Well, the trickiest part is not yet over.
Visualization and communication.
Emma meets the clients again to communicate the business findings in a simple and effective manner to convince the stakeholders.
She uses tools like Tableau, Power BI, and ClickView that can help her in creating powerful reports and dashboards.
And then finally, she deploys and maintains the model.
She tests the selected model in a pre production environment before deploying it in the production environment, which is the best practice, right?
After successfully deploying it, she uses reports and dashboards to get real time analytics.
Further, she also monitors and maintains the project's performance.
Well, that's how Emma completes the data science project.
we have seen the daily routine of a data scientist is a whole lot of fun, has a lot of interesting aspects, and comes with its own share of challenges.
Now, let's see how data science is changing the world.
Data science techniques along with genomic data provide a deeper understanding of genetic issues and reaction to particular drugs and antiseasons.
Logistic companies like DHL, FedEx have discovered the best routes to ship, the best suited time to deliver, the best mode of transport to choose,
thus leading to cost efficiency.
With data science, it is possible to not only predict employee attrition, but to also understand the key variables that influence employee turnover.
Also, the airline companies can now easily predict flight delay and notify the passengers beforehand to enhance their travel experience.
Well, if you're wondering, there are various roles offered to a data scientist, like data analyst, machine learning engineer, deep learning engineer,
data engineer, and of course data scientist.
The median base salaries of a data scientist can range from $95,000 to $165,000.
So that was about the data science.
Are you ready to be a data scientist?
If yes, then start today.
The world of data. Picture this, you're shopping online and suddenly you see a product that feels like it was made just for you. How did they know? It's not by chance, it's data science.
Data science helps businesses understand what you like, predict what you need next, and improve the way we shop and use technology.
And here's the best part data science isn't just about watching Netflix, it's one of the fastest growing careers in the world right now.
In fact, the US Bureau of Labor Statistics says that data science jobs are expected to grow 36% by 2033. Way faster than most of the other jobs.
Companies everywhere are using data to make smarter decisions. That means the demand for data scientists is huge.
And let's talk about the salary. You're probably wondering how much can I earn actually.
Well, for entry-level position, data scientists in the US are earning around 152,000 dollars per year right now. And by 2025, some can make as much as 230,000.
And in India, starting salaries range from 50,000 rupees to 1 lakh per month, and experienced professionals can earn more than 5 lakh rupees per month. That's impressive, right?
But the best part is as a data scientist, you won't just stop here.
The skills you develop in this role, like machine learning, data visualization, and statistics, are highly transferable and crucial for moving into AI roles.
So whether it's becoming an AI engineer or an AI specialist, the foundation you build in data science will help you level up and pursue exciting,
high paying opportunities in the AI field. Now, if you're thinking this sounds great, but where do I even start?
Well, that's exactly what the professional certificate course in data science from IT Kanpur and Simply Learn is designed to do.
It will get you started and make sure you're ready for this booming industry.
In this 11-month live online interactive program, you will learn the skills you need to become a data science professional. No more theory, no more fluff.
You get hands on projects, live classes, and mentorship from IT Kanpur faculty plus real world industry expert who will help you build your skills.
So, this course comes with exciting, amazing features that make learning even more impactful. eight times higher interaction in live online classes with industry expert.
Regular live online classes conducted by experienced professionals who bring real world knowledge into every session.
You'll also get to master 13 plus key skills including generative AI, prompt engineering, chargeability, expendable AI, conversional AI, NLP, and many more.
These are the skills that top companies use every day, and you'll gain hands-on experience with 14 plus industry tools like Python, SQL, Tab,
DALI2, Midjourney, TensorFlow, and more. And by the end of this course, you will be ready to tackle real world challenges using these powerful tools and techniques.
But we are not just talking about textbook and theory. You'll work on 25 plus real world projects, giving you hands-on experience with the tools and skills you'll use in the industry.
For example, our first project would be about sales analysis.
You'll use Python to analyze a clothing company fourth quarter sales data across Australian state, helping the company make informed decisions.
The next project would be about employee performance analysis, where you learn how to build machine learning models to understand the factors influencing employees'
turnover. Our third project would be about e-commerce, which will help Amazon improve its recommendation engine to offer better recommendation to customers.
Upon successful completion, you'll receive a program certificate directly issued by the EI City Academy IT Kanpur within 45 days of completing your cohort.
This prestigious certificate will help you boost your resume and show potential employees that you have mastered the skills needed to succeed.
You'll also benefit from masterclasses delivered by distinguished IT Kanpur faculty who bring their deep expertise in this course.
Plus, you will be exposed to trending tools like Charge B2, Gen AI, and prompt engineering. Now, if you're wondering who will be teaching all of this, then the IT Kanpur faculty is here for you.
These experts have been in this field for years and have worked with the top companies. You'll also get masterclasses from them and they will guide you through the learning process.
You're not just learning from a textbook, you are learning from the people who have been there and done that.
And the best part is, once you have learned the skills, Simptilearn's career assistance team will help you take to the next step, which will help you to build a killer
resume, show you how to stand out top recruiters, and even give you access to mock interviews.
Plus, you will also gain access to exclusive networking events and hackathons to connect with industry professionals.
Along with Simptile's job assistant, you'll also get access to ID Concourse career services, helping you connect with top recruiters and learn interviews with leading tech companies.
So upon finishing this course, you'll be ready for top data science roles like data scientist, machine learning engineer, AI specialist, and business analyst.
The good news is top companies like Amazon, EY, Fidelity Investment, Johnson Johnson, Vodafone, Accenture, Infosys and Nvidia
is looking for professionals just like you. And with salaries in the US hitting around $230,000 plus and in India reaching up to 5 lakh per month, your career outlook looks great.
So what will you be actually learning in this course?
So here's a sneak peek of the syllabus which you'll be learning in this course, which is the foundation in Python, SQL and Mathematics, Core Data Science like Machine Learning,
Data Visualization, NLP, special topics like Gen AI, ChatGPT, prompt engineering, and you'll also work on industry projects which we have already mentioned before.
You'll also have the option to choose electives like data storytelling with power BI and Business Analytics with Excel to tailor
your learning experience and focus on the areas that interest you the most. So don't wait, hurry up, and enroll now and. Find the course link in the description box below and in the pinned comments.
Have you ever wondered how your favorite online store seems to know exactly what you are looking for?
Every time you browse, add to cut or wish list an item, you are leaving clues about your style, favorite colors, brands, and even shopping times.
Data scientists jump in, analyze these patterns, and create a super personalized shopping experience.
Suddenly the store is showing you just the right pieces at just the right time, almost like it's reading your mind. That's data science, turning your clicks into a shopping spree crafted just for you.
Hello everyone. Welcome back to Simply Learn's YouTube channel. If you're already a data science enthusiast or just got curious about this exciting field, you're in the right place.
Today in this video, I am diving into 10 essential steps to help you become the next in demand data scientist and land that dream job.
No more waiting, let's dive right in and get you on the path to your future in data science.
So let's see the 10 essential steps to become the next data scientist in demand.
Step number one is programming languages.
Starting with Python is a beginner is a great move because it's simple, versatile, and widely used in data science.
Python's straightforward syntax makes it beginner friendly, helping you grasp programming basics quickly and dive into data science libraries like Pandas,
NumPy, and Matplotib with ease.
Adding R to your skill set is valuable because it excels at statistical analysis and data visualization, two essential parts of data science.
You can be comfortable with Python and R within a month or two.
So, moving on to the next step that is version control system.
Learning a version control system like Git is essential because it allows you to track, manage, and collaborate and code effectively.
With Git, you can save different versions of your work, making it easy to backtrack if something goes wrong or to experiment without losing progress.
This is especially useful when working with complex data science projects where you might try out different models of analysis techniques.
One or two weeks for practice along with Python and R is good to get started. Now moving on to the third step that is data structures and algorithms.
Learning data structures and algorithms is crucial for becoming a data scientist because they provide the foundation for efficient data handling and problem solving.
Data structures like arrays, stacks, queues and trees help you store and organize data in ways that make it easier and faster to access, process, and analyze.
Algorithms, on the other hand, give you strategies to perform tests like searching, sorting, and optimizing data operations, which are essential for handling large data sets.
While many candidates struggle with DAC, mastering it gives you an age helping you stand out in the interviews and shine as a skilled data scientist capable of tackling the toughest data problems.
Spend about two months in this, you will get in the shape for sure.
Now moving on to the step number four that is SQL.
Learning SQL is essential for data scientists because it enables you to access, manage, and manipulate data directly within databases where most real-world data resides.
With SQL, you can create new tables, alter existing ones, delete unnecessary records and run queries to filter,
sort and aggregate data.
These abilities allow you to retrieve, clean and organize data effectively, core skills needed for any data science role.
It's easy and you don't have to spend more than a month to have a deep understanding of it.
Now moving on to the fifth step that is mathematics and statistics.
Mathematics and statistics are essential for data science because they form the backbone of data analysis, model building and interpretation.
Topics like linear algebra, calculus, probability, and statistics gives data scientists the tools to understand data patterns, perform accurate analysis, and make data-driven decisions.
Mastering these areas enables you to build robust models, validate results, and tackle complex problems confidently, making you a well-rounded and skilled data scientist.
Make sure you spend two months to grasp these topics.
Now moving on to the step number six that is data pre-processing and visualization.
Learning data pre-processing and visualization is essential for a data scientist because these skills make you data accurate, insightful, and easy to understand.
Python libraries like NumPy and Pandas are crucial for manipulating and creating data, enabling you to handle missing values,
filter out noise, and prepare data for analysis.
Once the data is ready, visualization lets you uncover patterns and communicate results effectively.
Libraries like Matplottip and Cbone help create clear, impactful visuals, allowing you to interpret trends and convey insights in a way that's easily understood by others.
Together with these tools, make data pre-processing and visualization fundamentals for effective data science.
If you have a solid foundation on Python and mathematics, you will get a good understanding of data pre-processing and visualization in a month or two.
Now moving on to the seventh step that is machine learning fundamentals.
Machine learning fundamentals involve understanding how algorithms enable computers to learn from data and make predictions on decisions without explicit programming.
The two main categories are supervised learning and unsupervised learning.
In supervised learning, models are trained on labeled data to make predictions, while in unsupervised learning, models find patterns in unleveled data.
Popular tools like TensorFlow, PyTorch help build and train complex models, especially for deep learning, while SkyKit Learn is essential
used for simpler machine learning algorithms and data pre processing. These tools make it easier to implement machine learning fundamentals effectively and build intelligent data driven decisions.
Dedicate about three months to understand the core of machine learning.
Now, coming to the next step that is deep learning. Deep learning is a subset of machine learning that focuses on algorithms inspired by the structures of the human brain called neural networks.
Deep learning uses neural networks with multiple layers, often dozens or hundreds, to learn complex patterns from large data sets.
Specialized types like convolutional neural networks, that is CNNs, are great for image processing, while recurrent neural networks RNNs
are used for sequence data like text or time series.
Essential tools like TensorFlow, PyTorch, make building training and deploying deep learning models more accessible, allowing you to create powerful AI solutions across various domains.
I think it will take about two months to have a good hold on deep learning concepts and how to implement them.
Now moving on to the ninth step that is specializations.
Once you have grasped the deep learning, it's like reaching a new level as a data scientist.
Just as doctors specialize in areas in nephrology and cardiology. Data scientists often choose to specialize in fields like natural language processing or computer vision.
Natural language processing focuses on teaching machines to understand and generate human language, enabling applications like chatbots,
sentiment analysis, and language transition.
It's about making computers read, write, and even interpret human emotions through text or speech.
Computer vision, on the other hand, is all about enabling machines to see and interpret images or videos.
This field powers innovations like facial recognition, object detection, and autonomous driving.
Now you don't need to learn both.
You can choose what interests you the most.
Now spend one two months diving deep into one of these areas.
Now moving on to the last but not the least step that is big data.
Big data refers to extremely large volumes of data generated rapidly from sources like social media and sensors.
For data scientists, learning to handle big data is crucial as it requires specialized tools like Hadoop and Spark to analyze and extract insights effectively.
With companies relying on data-driven decisions, big data skills make you a highly in-demand professional in the field.
Focus for about two months and you will be able to spot trends and patterns from datasets very easily.
Once you are ready, it's time to build a killer resume, path with projects that showcase your new skills.
Start applying to jobs on platforms like Nocry and Indeed and supercharge your LinkedIn, connect with data scientists, see what skills they are mastering and learn from their journeys as well.
Keep sharpening your own skills, and when the time comes, you will be ready to crush those interviews and land your dream data scientist role in 2025. Yeah, step by step we will go through all of this
and we will make sure that we learn everything and we bring everything together towards the end.
Right?
Without further ado, let me just
straight away deep dive to business, right?
to learn
data science,
right?
And with this data science, there is also something which is prefixed, which is applied data science.
And suffix for this is
right? applied data science with Python, right?
So there are there are two key concepts which are going to be a part of this course.
The first one is the knowledge about data science, that what data science is, and then because we are doing an applied course, right?
We are doing an applied course, I will try to tie up these concepts which we will understand in data science with a tool, right, which is Python for
you, right?
We already know about uh 60 65% of Python, right, which is the fundamental Python, and now we will be moving
to the next step
to advanced Python.
Right.
And using Python, right, leveraging Python, we will be solving a lot of problems of data science, right? Using this.
Okay.
So the first few sessions, right? The first few sessions will be about making you abreast with Python, what Python is, right? What are and what packages do we have? How do they work in reality?
And all those things.
And then we will be coupling it up with data science concepts.
And then finally, towards the end of the session in the last few classes, we will be doing uh, we will be taking a real data set.
And on that data set, we will be applying all these concepts,
To understand the data better, and we will be drawing inferences from that to convert that into information to take actionable insights.
or Using that actionable insights, taking a better decision, right?
We'll do all of that in the
actual way.
Okay.
So now, guys, if you understand this, then the next point of contention is
data science.
Right?
One of the most famous keywords on the planet right now, right? One of the most famous keywords in the planet right now.
Do you think that these two things?
Okay, let me put it differently.
What do you think that can be the possible
explanation about this term data science?
You know data, you know science.
What do you think is going to follow in these sessions?
What is data science to you
as per these two words?
Okay, so this is people made up of two words, right? Data and science, right?
So
what we are trying to do is we are
trying to understand data.
Right, we are trying to understand data, right?
And then do something to it, right?
Understanding its science, understanding the nature, the behavior of this data, and converting it in something called as information.
Right?
Do we know the difference between data and information?
Data is something which is completely raw.
Okay, it is completely raw, it has no meaning.
Right? It has no meaning, isn't it?
For example,
I give you these stats of some player, like suppose say Dhoni.
I give you stats of Mahindra Singh Dhuni, right?
That what were his scores?
Uh, what is his name?
What is his age, and you know, all those things.
Now
everything is there, right?
But we don't know what to do about it, right?
Do you think the score of Dhoni has any context, people?
It has any context?
No, right?
But when I deep down, but I when I go and deep dive about it, right? What is the first thing you find out of scores?
What is the first thing you find out of scores?
You try to find the average of score, isn't it?
That in last 10 innings,
right? In last 10 innings, before this, also you need something which is called as a problem statement, isn't it?
Now, for example, the problem statement is selectors want to understand, selectors want to understand that whether Mahindra Singh Dhoni
should be picked up.
So there's a problem now, right?
Selectors want to
see that whether dhoni is fit for the next tournament or not.
So, what we will do, we will now try to take the mean of the scores, right?
For last 10 innings.
And if this score is suppose X, we will try to compare this with Y.
What is Y? Y is a reference.
Right? Y is a reference that we want to compare it against.
Now, when you are doing this comparisons, when you are applying these techniques to the score, this is now slowly becoming information,
right?
And at the end of the day, once you have the strike rate, once you have the mean score of Dhoni, once you have his age,
once you have his fitness score, all those things will now help you to take this particular decision. because now what you have is called as information, right? Because this has context,
right? This has meaning.
And this is usually processed.
Right. This is usually processed, right? This is usually processed.
Now, what did we do?
Now, what did we do here?
If you will go and read about data science, data science says.
Data science says
it is the art of collecting,
cleaning,
analyzing,
modeling,
improving,
right?
And visualizing.
Right. Visualizing
the data.
Right.
If a person is adept in doing all these things, this person people is cumulatively called a data scientist.
That person is called a data scientist. Right.
So before going to the definition of data scientist now, I will give you some more examples, right? I'll give you some more examples.
Data science people, as I said, is a combination of these things, right? You have to collect the data.
You have to collect the data.
And this has a lot of things.
Data can be collected from two types in two types.
One is primary.
And the second one is secondary.
What is the primary way of collecting data from your IoT devices, From sensors,
from your inbuilt machines.
Right.
Then from your surveys,
which you float, right?
Questionnaires.
Right? All these things are primary ways. What is the secondary way of collecting data?
Purchasing data.
Right?
Using internet data.
Because you have not generated it. You are just using someone else's data.
Right?
Something like transfer learning.
What is transfer learning?
Transfer learning is a technique where suppose I am bank A
and you are bank B, So bank A has created some model,
Trained on their data.
Now you are going to use the exact same model, right? You're going to use the exact same model, right?
Maybe you are not seeing the data, but you are just using the property of data, like mean, median, mode, and a lot of modeling things which will come,
we will learn about them.
And you use this model on your particular data, right?
So in a way you did not have enough data to create the model yourself, but you are now using someone else's model to run your data on it, right? So this is called as transfer learning.
So this kind of collection is basically secondary data collection.
So you can collect the data,
right?
Then you can perform
right? You can perform data analysis, right? How will you perform this data analysis?
Using complex
right? Using complex algorithms, right?
Some statistics,
right?
You can use artificial intelligence.
You can use machine learning,
right?
You can use all these things for data analysis.
Then you can transform
transform
the
patterns
into predictions.
Right, which can be used for business
Right. For business decision making.
Then you can validate the results,
right?
And present the results.
The first one is
domain knowledge.
Right.
So what is domain knowledge?
First of all, I told you, right, there will be a problem, right?
You will be solving a problem in any project of data science, you will be trying to solve a problem, right? And the problem will be belonging to a particular domain.
Even if you are working for yourself, Even if you are an entrepreneur, then also you will be solving a problem.
So this domain knowledge part includes things like understanding.
It's a very important diagram.
Understanding client requirement.
Understanding the client requirement,
Important criterions,
right? Important
criteria knowledge.
Right.
For example, to give an example, suppose we have created a machine learning model, okay. Understanding the data.
We have created a machine learning model whose accuracy is 90%, right?
Is 90% a good accuracy?
Yeah, fairly decent accuracy.
Yes.
Suppose you have to predict sales, right? You are selling something.
Suppose you are selling clothes and you want to predict what will be the sales for the next week.
When you use this model, whatever the output model gives you, what is going to be the accuracy of your output using this model?
How much accuracy?
90%.
But my question is
model is 90%.
But my question to you is that if 90% accuracy is on sales data, a person like me will be very, very happy.
Okay, very, very happy.
I'll be probably dancing, right?
But if you try to apply the same model, right, for a medical diagnosis case,
will you be interested in getting operated in such a hospital or an institution where the accuracy is coming as 90%?
Domain knowledge, right? Domain knowledge.
We need to understand what are the exact requirements. We need to understand what are the exact expectations, right?
And we need to know how much do we need to pivot, right?
So the first thing in data science is these accuracies and everything are subjective, right? They are subjective.
So for that, you need domain knowledge.
Domain knowledge part, very important, guys. Very important these three things, which I'm going to tell you.
Second part is people,
the game changer, right?
The second part is
computer science.
Now, if I take you back in history, okay, if I take you back in history in the 1980s or somewhere, then do you okay? How many of you think that data science is a new concept?
How many of you think that data science is a new concept?
I hope you all know it's not a new concept.
Everyone knows that.
Yep, it has been happening for ages.
Just like
you guys will be shocked if you already don't know.
AI was coined in the year 1956.
1956 at the University of Darmouth AI was coined by Paul McCarthy.
Right?
And we saw the boom of AI in the year 2010, right?
Such a long journey.
Same case with data science.
Because people, back in the day, data science was called as
data mining.
Everyone heard about it?
Data mining, knowledge databases.
Yeah.
We need to we used to mine the data.
Now, what were the problems?
What were the hiccups of data mining?
The hiccups for data mining was that we were doing everything,
everything
manually.
Right now, if I give you 100 points, can you calculate the mean?
Or let's say if I give you two points to multiply, two multiplied by three,
how much time will you take?
Two seconds?
Yep.
How much time a computer will take?
Two seconds?
If I give you to multiply two,
two, four, eight, nine multiplied by 200.
How much time will you take to calculate this?
Say five seconds.
How much time computer will take?
Two seconds.
Now, if I give you to multiply two, four, eight, nine into one five, one, nine, five, four, three, eight, six.
How much time will you take to calculate this manually?
Maybe say one minute?
80 seconds, one minute.
How much time a computer will take?
Still two seconds.
Right?
And if I give you to calculate this over 200 times, you will take 200 minutes, right? Using parallel computing, computer will still take about three to five seconds.
Right? So are you understanding the power of computer?
Do you understand this concept in this relationship?
What was happening back then?
What computer science did people was it revolutionized the way data mining was happening.
And that thing now is called as that again, that thing now is called as data science, in which computer science is one of the most important contributors.
So this is just one reason.
Now, manually, right? Manually, if I give you, say, one million rows of data, right? One million rows of data, right?
So how many pages will you wait pages will you need
to store this data?
Suppose your notebook is like this,
right? These boxes, and here you are storing the data, one million.
So maybe you can buy n number of notebooks,
but now do you think it's as easy in storing something in computer?
Because back in the day, people, we had memory issues,
isn't it?
Memory constraints.
So there is something called as Murray's law, right?
Which says as the
advancement in microprocessors will increase, the price of microprocessor will decrease, right? So this is what is happening right now.
Back in 1980s, if I show you, right, guys, right? Yeah, 2.5 kg exactly, right? It was the size of a fridge, hard disk, but now it fits in your palm, right?
So this was enabled the storage techniques, right? The processing techniques, the infrastructure, right?
Things like big data.
What kind of data do you think we will be dealing with, people in data science?
You all know the term.
Very famous term.
The kind of data,
big data, right? Everyone knows about big data. What is big data?
Yes, a data which is fast, right?
It has velocity, veracity,
variety, right?
So this kind of data needs to be stored. This kind of data needs to be processed.
So which thing brought all these things into data science?
It was given to us by computer science, right? So computer science people included things like database management,
data validation, data infrastructure.
Then we had
languages, computer languages,
which is Python right now for us,
Again, do you think when you do this thing manually, right?
Suppose you do this thing manually, how easy do you think it will become using something like Python or any other computer language to create complex models?
How easy it will be to do that?
To create the complexity in models, right?
Where you can capture the non-linear nature,
isn't it, people?
Isn't it?
For example, for example, let me tell you this
two, four, six, eight, ten.
dash.
What do you think is the next number, guys?
12. If I tell you to define this to me
in okay, let's leave that.
What do you think is going to be the next number here?
What is the next number?
11.
Next number?
25.
Perfect. Now guys, if I ask you to write these numbers, right, the way you predicted them, can you give me a function?
F of x is equal to
what is the f of x here?
It's 2x, right?
It's 2x.
F of x is equal to 2x.
If I tell you to create a function, it will be f of x is equal to 2x.
What will be the function here, guys?
F of x
will be equal to
x plus 1.
Yeah. X plus 1.
Yeah.
And here f of x
will be equal to
x square.
Yeah.
Now the last example.
Right? Last example.
What is the next number here?
I don't want the number. I want the function.
I want this so that I can generalize.
Isn't it?
How did you reach this figure?
How many of you think it's not possible to determine this?
How many
of
you
think
it is not
possible
to determine this?
Yeah.
How many of you think?
What if I just change this question and ask you how many of you think it is not possible to determine this
manually?
Same response, but now I say how many of you think it is not possible to determine this
with computers?
Will your answer still remain no?
Do you think I cannot approximate this function using computers?
We have something called as deep
neural networks.
And they are called as universal function approximators.
So this is the problem, people. This is the problem, I will show this to you when the time comes, I will remember this example and I will show this to you.
But now what I am trying to tell you is the things which seemed impossible manually were solved by what?
It was solved by computers.
The distribution of this is like this.
Can you figure it out yourself?
No, right?
We cannot, isn't it?
We cannot do that.
So this kind of approximation will be given by what?
It will be only given by machines, right?
And this is people what data science is all about, right? It is what computer science did inside data science, right? I hope this is clear.
I'm assuming a lot of you will be going for interviews and everything after this course, right? So this will be a very, very important thing for you to know, right?
Often it is asked why data science is having computer science in it, right? The reason is this.
Okay.
So this is the role of computer science inside data science.
Now, people, the third thing, the third circle, which is one of the most
parts, is
maths
and stats,
right?
Mathematics, statistics, which was optimization.
Right? Optimization of your models, right.
Design
of model
right now, guys. If you look carefully, if you look carefully, in order to approximate this, what will you be playing with?
You will be playing with a lot of data.
You will be playing with a lot of mathematical
concepts, and statistical concepts, isn't it?
what do you call this? This is maths, right?
This is statistics and mathematics.
Finding mean, median, mode, standard deviations, probability, statistics, all these will lead to this kind of result,
isn't it?
So this becomes the third wheel of this particular uh of this particular diagram, and this point of intersection,
right?
The sweet point of intersection is basically data science. So
yeah,
is particularly data science.
So now people, this point, okay, this point
is basically representing data engineering.
Data engineering is people the part of data science which enables us to capture the correct data,
how the data will flow, how the data will be stored, how the data will be cleaned, right?
All this is done by home.
It is done by data engineering.
Just because, so am I right, guys? You will go for interviews, right? After this, and try to fetch yourself jobs in this domain, data science, AI, ML.
If my understanding is correct, is that the aim? Yes.
So now, guys, there will be three types of companies.
Or let's say to simplify it, let's say two types.
One is small
and the other one is big, right?
So, in a small organization, if you become a part of a small organization and you are the data scientist there, you can be involved in all of these things,
right? All of these things possible, right?
Your bosses and your management will expect you to construct all these flows, right?
No computer science, you should know maths and stats, and you should have the domain knowledge, and you will be asked to do all of this.
But if you are going to become a part of a big organization, usually all these roles are fragmented.
All of these roles are fragmented, right?
There is a separate data infrastructure team, there's a separate data governance team.
Now, guys, when you go on to collect the data, can you collect any sensitive data about is it possible?
Ethically, it's not right and legally also it's not right.
My question to you is who will look after this compliance?
Whose responsibility indeed it is to look after this compliance?
Data scientist.
So this is about fragmentation. If you are part of a big organization, this thing will be taken by someone else, right?
But if you are a part of a small organization, you will be expected to do this all by yourself.
if you are part of a big organization, then do you think you need to have this domain knowledge?
The answer is no.
Why?
Because there will be separate set of people who are called as what?
Who are called as business analyst.
Have you heard about this position, people?
Business analyst.
What is a business analyst role?
It is basically a technical translator, right?
Who knows technical, who knows domain.
And that person goes and talks to the client, talks to the client in a layman language, convert it into technical requirement coupled with the domain knowledge, and give you the document.
This is basically a medical engineering problem.
So we need this, this, this, this, this, and you need to fulfill this, this, this, this criteria.
But again, if you're part of a small organization, who needs to take care of that?
Who needs to make sure that you know everything about a domain?
Right? You yourself.
Right?
Then, people, this area
usually represents whom?
This area represents research.
And analysis.
Why?
Because they we have people who have domain knowledge and we have people who are knowledge of math stats.
Have you heard about a position called as actuary
in the world?
Actuarial science.
For example, finance domain, right?
Finance is all about numbers.
So there we go, actuarial science, and we have math stats, optimization, model development, all of those things happening there.
We are also at this point of time, people belonging to which section research and data analysis, right?
And then people, there is the third intersection, right? There is a third,
the third intersection, which is this part, and this people is called as machine learning.
Right? Machine learning. Why machine learning?
If you can combine the power of maths, stats,
right? And you can combine the power of computer science, you will find yourself to be in a position where you can call yourself a machine learning engineer.
How does a machine learning engineer becomes a data scientist?
When they couple it up with the domain expertise, right?
So in this course, people, in this course, we will teach you computer science, we will teach you a little bit about math stats, but what we cannot teach you is domain knowledge.
Yeah?
And making the base of what we are about to do very, very important to understand.
Right? If you understand this, then half the battle is won.
Right?
So now to answer the question which was posted earlier, uh answer to the question which was posted earlier, there are different things in the world of data science,
right?
So you can pick and choose anything or you can do everything by yourself.
If you guys are engineers, then I think you can be at this sweet spot going forward in life if you choose a domain for yourself.
For example, you choose to be a part of automobile industry, you choose to be a part of medical industry, you choose to be a part of, say, retail industry,
you choose to be a part of aeronautics industry, right?
You choose to be a part of finance industry, right?
So, whatever you will choose, this thing will get developed over time, right? This is the most difficult out of these three.
Try to give you the example, right?
My domain was agricultural industry, right?
The agri products.
I have worked extensively in agricultural industry, right?
So, again, for now, in my current role, this is something which I don't have.
I have this expertise, I have this expertise.
So, same will be with you, and you guys will develop this knowledge over the time.
Now, I will try to give you an example, right?
Elections to make you understand how data science can be used in one particular use case. Okay, maybe we can extend that to a lot of other use cases and examples, right?
Talking about election season, right? Talking about the election season, right?
We will we will try to understand how do we use data science because it is very extensively used in this data science, right?
Now, let me talk about the first phase.
Let's say this is pre-election phase.
Right.
Right, this is pre-election phase.
In this pre-election phase, what do you think will be the tasks with which an agency like election commission of India will be doing?
The first task can be that they will be
doing the voter
registration,
voter,
right? Voter registration and data management, isn't it?
Yeah, it will start with that.
And what will be the things inside this?
The first thing will be data collection.
Right? First thing will be data collection.
So you will collect the data from all the registered voters, right?
Maybe it can be their demographic information, where they live, what is their age, what is their gender, right?
What is their past polling behavior, have they turned out previously or not?
Right?
All these details we can collect.
Then can we also do data cleaning?
Because I have told you, right, that there can be a lot of redundancies.
Some person's name can appear twice, right?
Some people can be uh mismatched. Suppose, for example, we have learned this in Python Raghav.
Raghav.
Right. All these are what people.
This is belonging to the same name.
Right? This is me.
But for a computer, for a computer, how many Raghavs are there?
Different ones? All are different.
Right?
So, example like this, right? Some people might have died, they might not be existing anymore.
Right.
So, all this part will be taken care where people in the data cleaning process, right? Removing the duplicates, updating the new addresses, right?
Correcting the information about every voter, all those things, right?
And now, lastly, we can also include a flavor of data analytics.
Right? What will data analytics include in this?
We can analyze the demographic data to identify eligible voters, isn't it?
Yeah, people.
Till now we haven't understood this.
Why it is not automated?
How will you pick up all the how will you pick up all the details and nuances?
Suppose you are filling a form, right? By mistake, you have suppose you are 25 years of age.
Suppose you have written 250.
So does that mean I remove this?
I remove this entry of yours?
Because by mistake you have written your age as 250.
Is age 250 possible in our current world?
Never, right?
So I will have to tell the machine that because this is a mistake, please convert it to 25.
Isn't it?
This is called as imputation.
So this is mostly a manual task, not manual, but you have to understand the problem manually and then code it on
computer.
Suppose someone has written their state
as
EDLHI?
And country
as
I D I N, right? So what is this state referring to? What is this country referring to?
The humans are very smart.
India, right? We can say this is India.
And if this is India, then what is this pointing out to
Delhi?
Just because you said and it's a it's a leading question.
I wanted to explain this.
Tell me, is it possible to do this automatically?
No, right?
We have to employ manual rules, right?
We have to tell because we who's more intelligent, humans or machines?
Humans, right?
Machines are just more optimized, right? So we know through human intelligence that this is pointing to Delhi and this is not EDLHI.
So this is data cleaning, right?
Lastly, we have data analytics.
So do you think people, based on these data points, we can understand that who are the eligible voters
and maybe who are not registered yet, maybe who have not voted in the past.
Can we do all those analytics
and reach out to those peoples
and persons?
That's the first part.
This is just the first part pre-election phase.
Now, moving on to the second part, right? Moving on to the second part.
Let's say
we say public
opinion
regarding the polling,
The polling which is about to happen.
The first thing will be you want to collect information about people, right?
So can can you go out and reach all 1.8 billion people in this country?
That what is their likable vote
for which party?
Is it possible?
1.8 billion.
Do you think it's possible for 1 billion?
Do you think it's possible for 500 million?
Do you think it's possible for 100 million?
No, right?
So basically, I'm talking about what I have something which is called as a population.
Right?
And if I have to study about this population, which is 1.8 billion people, which is impossible, which you just said, what do I need to do? Should I stop my process?
No, right?
I will go and collect something which is called a sample.
Right?
We always work in samples, right?
Suppose someone says that a Coca-Cola bottle does not contain 500 ml of liquid, which it claims,
right?
Suppose someone has put this allegation. Possible that Coca-Cola bottles do not have
500 ml liquid which they promise.
Now there are two ways to deal with this.
Right? There are two ways to deal with this.
Either I go and collect all the bottles of Coca-Cola in the world.
Possible?
Never right.
So what will I do? I will go and pick up handful of bottles.
Right?
Handful of bottles.
So what is that handful of bottles?
Those are called as samples.
One last thing.
Suppose someone says that because of an industry,
all the fishes of the lake are dying or they are infected.
Is it possible to go and collect and check all the fishes in the pond or lake?
No, right?
What will we do?
We will collect again handful of fishes and we will test them.
Right?
Again, samples.
Now,
how does the raw data collected?
Raw data hasn't.
I hope you understand this.
This is no more about population.
With this step being told, now you're dealing with samples.
So now do you want to ask me how is sample created?
Yeah.
Now I'm coming to that.
Now, guys, there are a lot of second point is
how to sample.
Right? How to sample.
Right?
So we have sampling techniques, people. One is called as probabilistic, and one is called as non-probabilistic.
I will not go in detail right now. I just want to tell you an overview.
Probabilistic is suppose uh you are manufacturing t-shirts, right? You are manufacturing t-shirts, right?
And suppose you created
100 lots
of
thousand t-shirts,
right? So this is box one, box two, box three, box four, up to up to hundred, right? Hundred boxes.
And in each box, how many t-shirts are there?
Thousand, right?
Now, suppose you are a quality inspector.
You are a quality inspector.
Is it possible you for you to go over all the 100 lots with all checking all the thousand t-shirts one by one?
No, right? What will you do?
You will sample again. You will sample.
Now, the most common way of sampling these kind of problems is probabilistic sampling.
What is probability? What is the probability of getting heads or tails when you spin the when you flip the coin?
Equally likely, one by two and one by two.
What is the probability of getting one, two, three, four, five, six on a roll of a dice?
One by six.
Now, what is the probability of picking any t-shirt from this first lot out of 1000 t-shirts?
One by thousand.
Yes?
So do you think all the t-shirts have equally probable equal probability of being picked up without any bias?
If you decide to draw five t-shirts, right, from each of this box, right? And suppose say two are defective and three are not defective.
What will you do? Will you accept the lot or reject the lot?
We have majority of t-shirts of non-defective.
Or let's say we will reject the lot. We will reject the lot.
We will reject the lot.
Let's say we will reject the lot.
Okay.
Though this is basically subjective as per the company policies.
But let's say we reject it.
Now,
people, my question to you is what if this entire batch had only two defected t-shirts?
But now what will happen?
The entire batch will be rejected.
Yes.
Let's say you sampled one t-shirt.
let's change the use case.
I say you sampled only one t-shirt and that t-shirt was defected.
Now you will reject the batch.
And that is equally likely case.
So this is called as probabilistic sampling, people.
And there is no way you can go back.
There is no way. You cannot say that, hey sir, please allow this batch to pass because there is a chance that rest of the t-shirts are not defective.
No, it is not the way that happens, it happens randomly. So, right, this is called as random sampling.
Right, random sampling.
Now, suppose you are doing a cancer research, right? You're doing a cancer research.
Right.
So, for your cancer research people, what kind of people will you need?
People who had had cancer in the past, isn't it?
To know more about their problem, to know more about their medical condition.
So, is it possible, people, that in this use case you can go and pick up any person from the population
and ask them questions?
No, right?
That is not possible.
So now is the probability equally likely or it has changed when you pick the sample.
It has changed.
Now there is a bias which is introduced
that you only want people who had cancer, right?
So that kind of sampling people is called as non-probabilistic sample,
Right?
Non-probabilistic sampling.
Clear?
Now, sampling technique,
right? Now, third thing in this same scheme can be people what it can be the data collection, right?
Data collection mode,
right? That how do you collect the data?
You can float a survey
on
say internet.
You can go and stand outside a mall
or office.
Isn't it? How will you how will you you can probably interview someone?
Right? Interview someone, right? You can have a group discussion.
Yeah, all these techniques.
Yes, no, maybe, right? In the same part, public opinion polling, right now, guys.
so this was a brief introduction, right?
And this can be extended to any industry, right?
As of now, you can have example in the medical science,
right? You can have an example in automobile,
right? You can have an example in retail,
right?
Right.
Then you can have example in manufacturing,
right?
You can have example in education,
You can have example in sports,
IPL analysis, cricket analysis, all these sports analysis, These are the most famous domains, right? They are the most famous domains.
They are not topics, they are domains, In which data science is used extensively. So I'm just going to check, guys. In automobiles, there's a biggest example, self-driving cars.
Yeah,
autonomous driving.
How do you think that's possible?
Data science again,
like Tesla.
Absolutely.
Tesla is level three.
We have five levels.
Level three is narrow AI, level four is AGI, and level five is super AI.
We are going to move first, right, with the technical aspect, right? With the technical aspect in our data science course, right?
Right, which is based on Python,
right, because that is our base language, which we have learned so far, right?
So in Python people, we will start and cover four of the packages
right now, and as we move on to machine learning and other deep learning and everything, you will explore more and more packages.
The first package we have to cover will be numpy.
Right, I'll explain you in detail what numpy is, then we will cover pandas.
Then we will cover matplotlib.
And then finally, we will cover something called as C bond.
Right? We will cover something called as C bond.
So these four packages inherently we have to cover in Python
to make sure we are able to reduce
the time
Right. We are able to reduce the time encoding.
And using these packages immediately help us in getting the desired results. Right. I hope you all remember the concept of modules
we have covered in Python.
Do you all remember functions and modules?
You can use Jupyter Notebook.
If your Jupyter notebook is not installed, you can use something which is called as Google Colab.
Right? Go to Google, type
Right? Let's say you write collab.
Right.
And then you will see this option.
Click on Google Colab and it will allow you to code in Python.
Right?
So we are now going to discuss about the numpy package in Python. Okay, numpy package in Python.
So numpy is a
fundamental
package
for
data science
in
Python.
Right? It is one of the most fundamental packages for
practicing data science in Python.
Right.
Why is that? Why is so why is numpy so fundamental? What is so special?
Numpy package
gives us
a new data type
for handling
data
in Python
called as
N
D
arrays.
right? N D arrays, which stands for
this stands for
arrays, right? N dimensional arrays, right? This stands for n-dimensional arrays.
So till now,
till now we have studied
about
list,
integer
tuples,
strings, etc.
Right.
Out of which
the data types,
such as list,
tuples,
have been used to store data,
and
range
used for
generating
new data, which is primarily sequential,
Now there is one now there is one problem, right? There is one problem, and there should be a question that
there should be a
question.
Why do we need a new
data type
to work
with data science?
Right?
Why do we need this?
So the answer to this question, people, the answer to this question uh lies in a small explanation, right?
Yep.
Lies in a small explanation, which is that
python
is a
high
level
Python is a high level language, right?
And
A high level language
is usually
very
distant
from
hardware.
A high level language is close to hardware or distant from the hardware?
Did you not attend the Python programming essentials?
What is the type of programming language which is closest to hardware?
A low level language?
If this is my hardware,
yeah.
This is my OS.
This is my application layer, right? So hard level language, high-level languages here, and low level languages here, right? Which is closest.
So binary languages,
assembly languages,
right?
All these are closest to the hardware.
Because where is the processing happening? Where is the processing happening of the data?
At the hardware,
isn't it?
Processing of data
is happening
at hardware.
No hurry. Actually, it is happening at hardware, right? What is processing?
Processing is signals of zeros and ones, right?
What are zeros and ones? These are electric signals.
These are the electric signals, right?
Which is basically on and off,
right? And it is communicated to the hardware through the help of resistors
and microprocessors,
Isn't it right? Why a computer only knows zeros and ones?
Because zero is off and one is on, which is the electric current.
Right?
Electric current to activate or deactivate certain things, right? True and false gates.
Right? So it is happening in hardware.
So now, people,
if you understand this part, then try to logically connect it to what I'm going to say.
When you are studying data science,
what kind of data you will be dealing with?
Big data.
Right? And as the name suggests, it will have a lot of volume,
It will have a lot of volume, other than a lot of other things, right?
It will be very, very big.
And on this
large volume of data, you will be doing processing.
You will be doing processing.
What does processing means?
What is processing means? Operations.
So where is this operation happening? This is happening in hardware.
And for hardware, which is the closest language to hardware?
A low-level language.
But now, people, but now we have a situation in front of us.
What is the situation?
That what are we trying to do data science with?
What are we trying to do data science with
Python?
Right?
And Python is what?
A high level language,
isn't it?
Yeah.
So there's a discrepancy.
Yeah, a big one.
Because hard level, high level language, these
are
slow
Right, these are very slow in processing.
So, for these kind of languages to handle this kind of data and these kind of operations,
is very difficult.
So let's let's keep let's keep this part aside if you understand this.
Now let's go to the second point.
when you learned Python
on a scale of 1 to 10, how easy was it?
The ease of use of Python?
It's relatively a higher number, right?
Relatively a higher number.
So now guys, when I talk about data science, right? When I talk about
data science, okay,
right? When I talk about data science,
my thing is that this will be used by masses,
right?
Will be used by masses, a lot of people, managers, programmers, business analysts, data analysts,
possible, right?
Who are from non-technical background, who don't know coding, they also can do data science because data science is a general thing, isn't it?
Understanding the data, it should not be limited by your capability to understand the technicalities of a very complex language.
So for these people, which language is suitable?
Which is Python, right?
It is easiest to understand, it's a high-level language, almost like English.
Yeah?
So Python is a simple language. So in this part, people, Python fits the bill, right? Which is a bigger thing.
In the second part, when we talk about the operations,
we talk about the operations.
In this part, there is a problem, right?
Python fails,
right?
right? Because it's a high-level language.
We said that okay, there is a language called as C, right? Which is a middle level language.
Right?
And C language people is used to create OS operating systems, it is used to create networks,
networking applications,
it is used to create games,
right?
All the things which are close to hardware,
C is used, right?
So C fits this bill, right?
C fits this bill.
said that okay, if C fits the bill, and Python is written
in C, written on C, right? It's written on top of C language.
Now what happened was Python said, okay, if my intrinsic data types, my intrinsic processing is not suitable for data science,
but my high-level nature is let's do one thing.
Let's take C language and use its power, right? Use its power that it is very close to hardware, and let's create a new data type, right?
Let's create a new data type
which is written on top of C and which can integrate with Python seamlessly.
And people, this new data type
was called as array.
And this was given to you by something called as numpy package, right? Numpy package.
It defined a new data type which was array, and along with defining the array, it gave various operations.
Right, it gave various operations one could
perform
on
Right, one could perform on arrays.
It's simple, right? Program the the power of processing lied with C, right? It was lying with C.
So we developed a new data type using C on top of Python, and that new data type was called as array.
And this array was defined in a new module, which was called as numpy module, which told you how to create the arrays
and then how to manipulate those arrays
for doing data science.
We had options like Java, we had options like C,
We had options like Fortran to be used for data science, but we chose Python because of its simplicity and the simple syntaxes
that people from non-programming background could also use Python to do data science.
now, the limitation was that because it is slow, because of being high level, we needed something which could make it fast, and that was using an external data type
which is not internal to Python, and that was array.
And this array is defined inside a new module or a library called as numpy, which is numerical python,
right? Numerical Python
back to the programming, right?
Where we have understood right about this question,
so
NumPy
essentially is
based on top of
C
language, which is
compatible
with Python.
It leverages the power of closeness of C with hardware,
right?
C with hardware,
which eventually
makes the processing
faster in
Python, right?
So this is what the first part is, right? This is what a first part is,
Now the second thing is people, so this is about the performance bit, right? These are the performance bit.
The above
is about
the
performance
of
it, right now coming to the next part, which is the memory
efficiency, right? Memory efficiency,
right?
So,
arrays created
by
numpy in
python
are less memory
exhaustive
than lists in Python.
And I will prove these points later on to you through code, right?
In list, right? In list,
each item is
an object, right? Each item is an object, right? I hope you remember this, guys.
Each item is an object,
and
it holds
meta information
like
references
and types,
etc.
A lot of information. it holds.
This
makes
list
consume
more
memory,
but
arrays in
numpy
are contiguous.
Which means
that
they do not
create objects,
but rather
directly store
the data
continuous
memory
blocks.
One after
another, right?
Also, the arrays are homogeneous in nature, right? You can only store the homogeneous data in array, unlike lists.
In lists you could store different data types, right? But in arrays you cannot, right? You have to store the same kind of data in the array, homogeneous.
So it's a contiguous memory block, which is meaning that you can store data in continuity, right? One after another in the memory block.
So the access is faster, the memory location and the memory efficiency is very higher, right? As compared to the native data type like lists or tuples in Python.
Arrays
are basically
right? I'll talk to about talk about to you with vectors. What are vectors, right? They are the vectorized operations, and they are way more convenient
to deal with
as compared to list
in python, In list you have to go through a lot of loops, right? We saw that we have to go through the list comprehension, but you will see in Python pandas, sorry, in Python numpy,
the vectorized operations are very, very simple, right? They are very, very simple, right?
Again, for all this, I will give you examples, but it will take some time
because you have to understand what arrays are first,
then
the most important
other packages,
which are
pandas,
matplotlib,
cbond,
sklearn, psypy.
all are written
on top
of
numpy package.
That's the reason.
For this reason,
it's called as
fundamental
package.
All the other packages which make your life easier as a data scientist, where you don't have to worry about code.
All these packages
make our data science
journey smooth
because
we have to worry
less about code and more about
logic.
Yes?
So for these understand for the understanding of these packages, it's very important that we understand numpy first and then we move forward.
Right
now,
then let's get started.
So the first step, right? The first step which you have to
see, right? The first step which you have to see while using numpy package is basically from where will you import the package, right? From where you will you import the package.
So to import
the
package, numpy, we write import
numpy as np, right?
Where np
is an alias, right?
It's an alias.
Right?
So please do this.
Import numpy as np.
Right.
If you don't get any result for this, then you can write pip install numpy.
Right? Pip install numpy and just execute this.
Right.
When you will execute this, it will give you this message, or it will give you, it will download this package for you, right?
Pip stands for
python
index package,
right?
It is basically like Play Store,
App Store,
Or Windows Store
for Python.
We are just going to these Play Store
Windows Store App Store of your Python and asking them to download this for you,
It is also called as the
package manager.
Right? Pip.
If it is done, you can also check the version.
You can say np dot underscore underscore version underscore underscore and it will give you the version of numpy.
Right.
Numpy is an open source
package.
Right?
Yeah, that's about it.
Yeah, it's an open source package, people.
Right? Open source package.
And if
you want to see the code,
you can go to GitHub.
Go to Google, write
the code for numpy.
It will show you it on GitHub.
Right?
Done.
So let's say I okay.
So I say
we have when we so okay.
Before this, let me come to a little bit of theory before I do this with you.
So now, guys, I said that numpy
has arrays
as
data type,
right?
And this is written on C, which runs directly
on hardware.
Also, this numpy array
is basically a vector.
Right? It's basically a vector.
Now, what is a vector, people?
What is a vector?
A vector is a
quantity which has sine
plus magnitude.
It has a sine and magnitude.
If I say this is a Cartesian space, this is I, this is j, and I say this, this is
3i
and 4j,
3i cap, 4j cap.
So this is a vector, right?
And this is the direction,
guys. If you have studied elementary maths,
you would know this.
Yes, people.
This is a vector.
If I draw another like this,
then this is another vector.
So I will call this say
2i and 5j.
Yep, this is another vector, and this is the theta,
This is the direction.
This is the direction, and what is the magnitude?
3i 3 square plus 4 square, which is 9 plus 16, which is 25 under root, which is 5.
So the magnitude of vector is 5 and direction is equal to theta.
This is a vector quantity.
Now,
what is this?
What is this?
This is a scalar.
This is a scalar, yeah, only magnitude,
isn't it?
This is scalar, only magnitude, and then I have 2, 3.
Right?
This is what
this is a vector.
It has two dimensions
or one dimension,
only one dimension,
right?
This is one dimension vector.
Yep, one dimension vector.
Now, if I say this two, three, four, five,
what is this called?
right? This is called a matrix, which is what collection of vectors,
and this collection of vectors matrix is called as two-dimensional, right? It is called as two-dimensional.
Now, if you have this,
so these are stacked behind each other.
This is one, this is two, this is three, right?
So we have three layers
in matrix.
So, how many dimensions will be this people?
One dimension, two dimension, and three dimension.
This is a three dimension matrix,
right? Or three dimension vector
or three dimension array.
I'll repeat once again.
What is a single value?
A single value is called as a scalar, right? It only has magnitude.
Now, when you have multiple values, right?
This is called as a vector. It has a direction, it has a magnitude, and this is single dimension.
Now, multiple
vectors, right? Like this, or maybe you can say like this, right?
Are you understanding why I'm calling it one dimension? It can be either this dimension or it can be this dimension.
In any dimension, you stack two vectors, you will get yourself a matrix,
right? You will get yourself a matrix, which is now two dimensions.
It has rows
and it has columns.
Right
now, if you stack multiple such matrix one after another, right?
This becomes a three-dimensional matrix.
And this can go up to how many dimensions, people? How many dimensions can this go up to?
It can go up to
this,
can
go
up to n dimensions,
right? N dimensions,
right?
So now do we get it? Why do we call it n d
arrays?
Yeah, n dimension arrays.
Right. That why are we calling something water?
Right?
N dimension arrays.
We are only capable of viewing three dimensions, people.
It can go up to 100 dimensions, 500 dimensions, thousand dimensions, any dimensions.
Scalars are least important.
Vectors are more important.
So now
we have
multiple
dimensions in
arrays,
namely 0D,
1D,
2D,
3D, and so on. till the N D, right? N D arrays.
Right now, let's create our first array.
Right. Let's create our first array.
And this will be a zero
dimension
Right. Zero dimension array.
How will you create this?
You will say arr0
is equal to np.array.
And you will mention what a scalar value is.
What is a scalar value?
It is a simple value.
I say 2, right? np.array equal to 2.
And when you will now check or print the type of
arr0, it will tell you class numpy nd array.
Right?
It is a zero dimension array.
And if you want to check
the dimension,
you just have to write arr0.ndim.
Right. And it shows you that there is zero dimensions present.
So what is this in short?
This
is a scalar.
I have entered a single value, people, to 200, 500, whatever you want to enter.
And the syntax is np.array.
np.array.
You are instructing numpy package to fetch the function array on method array and convert this into that particular
data type.
Right? Array zero.
And when you check the type, type is nd array.
But what is the dimension of this nd array? This is zero, which is nothing but a scalar.
Right?
We have created this.
This is what we have created.
Right.
Now guys,
if I created this list, right?
Say LIS is equal to.
Yeah.
So this was
this was a list, right? This was a list, and this was this is what people, what is this that we have
just studied according to that? What dimension is this list?
So what I'm trying to do is
I will create a
1D
array with a or let's say from a list.
Right?
Let's let me show you how do we do that.
Okay.
So I say
hurry, read the error.
Name arr not defined. Why?
Because you have created array from AAR0.
Come on, hurry.
Right?
I will create a one-dimensional array. How will I do that?
People, I will say arr1 is equal to np dot array.
And can I pass 1D list inside this?
Or can I say I can pass L I S inside this?
When I do this, people now see what will happen.
Arr1
will be equal to this, And if you say, let me say print
arr1,
it will be like this.
This is your
arr1 dot indim.
You will see that it gives you one,
This is a one dimension array.
One dimension array.
Yes, so for example,
when I say
right? When I say scalar, I say
thirty-five, right?
When I say vector
one D, I say
so these are suppose my marks,
right? Now I say thirty-five,
forty,
fifty, right?
So now what are these?
My marks in three subjects.
Yeah, marks in three subjects.
This is my say Hindi, this is English, and this is maths, right? Or let's say science,
because not everyone has Hindi.
Science, English, and maths, right, guys?
Now, if I have to create a matrix
of two dimension what will I write?
So that means this is one student.
This is one student, people,
isn't it, guys?
Yes, no, maybe.
So now in matrix, we will have what?
We will have multiple students.
Yes, no, maybe.
In a matrix, people will have multiple students.
Suppose this was S1. Now you will have S1, S2, S3, S4, like this,
and each student will have their own individual list of marks.
So, can I say that I'm making a nested list?
Can I say that, people?
I'm making a nested list.
So now let's make it okay.
From a
Nested list.
Okay, a nested list.
So I'll say arr2 is equal to np dot array list. I will have to create a list first.
LIS2 is equal to.
So this is my first bracket.
What is this bracket representing? This bigger bracket.
Now I will put another bracket inside this and I will write 112233.
I'll put a comma again, right? A comma.
Then I will say
4 4 5 5 6 6 comma
seven, seven, eight, eight, nine, nine.
Right? I'll do this
now. I will say list should
when you will do this, you will see that an array like this has been created.
Right.
Like this ARR2.
Right?
This has been created.
When we check the dimension, it is two-dimension array.
Right?
Yep.
Marks of three different students in three different subjects.
And this is the same technique you can create a three dimension array. How will you create a three dimension array, people?
If I go here, how will you create a three dimension array now?
Now, suppose I have data in this, and
this is my master list.
In this, I have data,
and this can be represented like this.
This is my
first matrix, isn't it?
And this is the vector inside this
v1, v2, v3.
Then this can be called as M1.
And now to create a three dimension setup, how many M1s do you need?
You need multiple M1s,
isn't it?
You need M1, M2, M3, multiple matrix, like this, people,
like this,
matrix one, matrix two, matrix three.
So what will you do?
You will have, you will have what people?
You will have another yellow.
Right?
And you will have inside this yellow multiple purples.
Isn't it
right?
Again, like this.
Yeah,
like this, you will have it, people.
So, can I say, people, can I say that as I am increasing the dimensions, as I am
increasing
the dimensions,
I am putting one D.
sorry, zero D, right? And okay, again in this V1, in this V1, do you think you will have multiple scalars, people?
Can I say that?
Can I say multiple scalars create a vector?
Multiple vectors create a matrix, and multiple matrix create one three dimensional matrix.
Can I say that?
Let me talk to you about an image, right?
Image, right?
What is an image made up of people?
What is an image made up of?
Pixels?
Yes or no?
No,
not frames.
Frames is basically videos.
Pixels are creating an image, right? So we have how many pixels here? One, two, one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten, eleven, twelve, thirteen, fourteen, fifteen, sixteen.
Right?
Suppose
this is one vector, right? This is one vector.
And this is one scalar.
Right? Scalar one, scalar two, scalar three, scalar four.
And this will make vector v1.
This is v2, v3, v4.
And together, together, can I call this
M1 and call this blue?
So for a colored image, how many channels are there, people? How many channels are there? What do we call it?
We call it the image as
RGB,
RGB image.
That means red,
green,
blue.
So this is blue part.
So similarly, you will have a red part in front of it.
Then you will have a green part.
And then finally, you will have a blue part.
Yeah?
Are you understanding, guys?
Why do we require three-dimensional arrays?
Yes.
Suppose now you want to make a change at this pixel.
So you will go to the third layer, which is the blue layer.
Then you will go to the third column, which will go to the third column and third row.
And this is how you will reach this pixel, everyone?
Yes, no, maybe.
Yes.
So this is the reason why we need to create a 3D array.
Right?
Right? To ingest information like this.
So we can create a 3D array also.
Right. And how did I tell you how many brackets will I have? Squared brackets?
I will have three squared brackets. So now this is just one student.
Right.
Now I'll put a comma here.
Right. I'll put a comma here.
And I will start.
Right. I'll do this.
I'll say this list three.
Air three.
List three.
ARR3.
AirR3.
Right. And now you will see that there is a three-dimension array.
Right, guys?
Right, this is a three-dimensional
array.
Yep.
Moving on.
There are multiple ways
to create arrays, right?
The first one we have done.
So we have done
from lists.
From list we have done.
Then second will be
from
we can create a zero array.
Right.
We can create
ones array.
Right.
Then we can create custom array.
I will show this all to you.
Right. I'll show this all to you.
So let's start with the ones array.
Sorry, zeros array.
Right. What do you have to do?
You have to write, so let's say zero underscore arr0. Okay, a zero dimension, zero array.
So you say np dot zeros,
right?
And you create
a two.
And if I say
zero
dot n dim,
right, you will see it is a one-dimension array.
It is a one-dimension array,
so two is by default taken as.
So let me just show this to you.
It will look like this, right? It is taken as horizontal. What is the dimension of this, guys? A vector.
What is the dimension of this vector?
No, no, no. It's one.
It is basically two cross one, right?
Two, comma one.
Sorry, one, comma two.
My bad.
One, comma two, isn't it?
Now, what if you had to create a two cross one?
what if you had to create a two cross one?
Right?
So let me just show that to you.
So I say, wait.
Like this.
Okay.
Now when I do this, I say arr1
and I say here
two,
one.
Right?
I say two,
one.
Now you will see people what will happen to this.
Now,
because you have created right specified two dimensions, right? What will this be converted to now?
What will this be converted to?
This will be converted to
a
two-dimension vector.
By default, it was this, right? Which was this vector.
Right? By default, it was this vector.
Right? What is the dimension of this vector?
One cross how many values you put here, right?
One cross two, like this.
So we call this only one dimension.
We call this only one dimension.
But now when I will run this one, you will see
yes, two cross one.
And now you will see this is
two dimension, right? You see this is two dimension now.
Clear people, just the orientation has changed, but now you see the brackets. There are two brackets now.
Because what have you now instructed?
You have now instructed Python and rather uh numpy
to create the vector as two cross one.
So you have said give me this zero and give me this zero here.
So the moment you do this, you are now specifying the rows and columns.
Now this two one, right?
Let's say this is two one.
Now let me create another two cross two dimension matrix for you.
Let me call this 10,
10, right?
So, how many rows and columns will it have, people?
How many rows and columns will it have?
I will say 210.
It will have 10 rows and 10 columns, like this.
You saw this?
Yeah, 10 rows and 10 columns.
Right?
By default, it is 1 cross 2, like this. It is a one dimensional vector, and this is a two dimensional vector.
What about a three dimensional vector?
0 dot 0 underscore uh arr three
is equal to np dot zeros, right? Np dot zeros,
right?
Should I just write three, three, three
and I should check for this?
Yeah, you will have a three cross three vector, three cross three matrix with three matrix stacked behind each other.
Right?
If I say four,
this will be four.
So, how do we need this?
Number of layers,
number of rows, and number of columns.
So, can you help me with a syntax?
Can you help me with a syntax which can create me a 3D matrix of five layers,
three rows and three columns?
What will I write?
Five layers, three rows and three columns.
Five, three, three.
You will get five layers, one, two, three, four, five.
Like this.
Suppose you have to represent
an image
with,
say,
RGB channel
say, 256 and 256 pixels.
How will you create this?
So I will say img right image is equal to np dot
zeros, and I will say inside this
three channel 256 frost 256.
Right?
And when you will just run this image, it will be like
this, right? It will be like this.
This is one channel,
this is two channel, and this is three channel.
And we understood that numpy is a fundamental package for data science in Python, right?
This package gives us a new data type to work with, which is called as n-dimensional arrays, right?
Now, what are arrays?
What are arrays?
Arrays are nothing but vectors, right, which are stored in a contiguous block of memory, which means they are stored continuously one after another,
and they do not get converted into the object, unlike the list, and they are way faster, they are more memory efficient than list.
I will prove this part to you today with the help of example through the help of code, right?
So, why numpy wire is?
Because numpy is a package which is built on top of C language, which is compatible with Python, and C being a middle level language,
interacts directly with the hardware.
So, whatever operation you run, in a fact that is getting directly executed on the hardware itself, right?
That is the reason why the uh performance is way better when we try to use the n-dimensional arrays.
Along with this, the syntaxes, the type of syntaxes we used to type uh in list.
I will show that to you also today with the help of example, are way simpler when you try to do them with nd arrays, right?
So arrays are basically vectorized operations, right?
And they're also very convenient to deal with as compared to lists and other native data types in Python, right?
And the most important part is that in our data science journey, whatever other packages we will use, right?
Again, what are packages? They have predefined things stored for you so that you can leverage them and focus less on code and more on logic, right?
You need to be aware about the logic more than the knowledge of the code, right?
So we have packages for that which contains methods inside them which you can use, and without any further calculations, you can work with them directly,
right.
So that is how we started with numpy, right? And the syntax to import numpy was import numpy as np, where np was an alias, right?
Uh you could do pip install numpy if someone did not have access to numpy. If numpy was not coming by default, you can use pip install numpy, which is python index package, right?
And this is like Play Store, App Store, Windows Store for Python.
All the packages are stored in pip, and you can call pip, you can ask pip to download that package for you so that you can use that, right? It's basically the package manager.
So numpyy is an open source, and if you want to see the code, you can go to GitHub and check the code out for yourself, right?
In numpy, we have n-dimensional arrays. Now the question arises, people, that why do we need numpy? Right? So, my answer to this particular question is that when you will deal in data science, right?
When you will become a data scientist, you will be dealing with data, right?
Now, my question is how will you ingest, how will you make the machine ingest the data, right?
There has to be a way, right?
For you to input the data to the machine, right?
To make manipulations to the data, to read the data.
So all this is started as the base package of numpy arrays, right?
Other than that, it becomes very difficult and cumbersome for us to deal with that.
And this provides us a lot of ease and flexibility to deal with such massive amounts of data, which you will see along with me as we will move forward in this particular course.
Yeah, perfect.
Now, people, let me just uh pull up the PPTs.
This is what we're discussing, people.
We start with something which is called as scalar, right?
We start with something which is called as scalar, which is a quantity which only has magnitude, right? In numpy language, this is also called as zero d, right? It is called as zero dimension.
Then, people, we have vector, right? And vector has a constant dimension, it has only one dimension, right?
You can interpret it as a row or you can interpret it as a column, it doesn't really matter because this is only one single dimension, So usually it will be written as five,
blank, right? There will be nothing written in front of it.
So this in numpy terminology and nomenclature is called as one dimension,
right?
When you move on, then you get combined couple of vectors, you get a shape, and now that is called as a matrix.
And in numpy terminology, it is called as two-dimensional, right?
And when you try to stack multiple 2-dimension matrices, one before where one after each other or one before each other, then they become something called as three-dimensional.
And now in my capability, I don't know what 4-dimension looks like, but there is a high possibility that you have n-dimensional data, right? It has it has n we are dealing with n-dimension data,
Suppose with this, I also add time, right?
At t equal to one, at t equal to two. That will serve as the fourth dimension for this data. But how does it look like?
I don't really know that, Because humans are only capable of visualizing 3D, three dimensions at max, So you can go to n dimensions
and hence the name n dimensional arrays, nd arrays.
Post this, we moved on to create certain things, and I tried to explain you the data, right?
So the data
will look to you like this, right? You might have a scalar quantity, which is marks, right?
One marks, right now.
If I go on to vectors in one D, it can be marks of one student,
Marks of one student in science,
English,
and maths, right?
35,
40, and 50 out of say 50, right? Three subjects.
So this will be characterized as a vector, right?
What will be the dimension written for this?
It will be three, comma, nothing.
This will be zero, right?
Shape will be zero.
For this matrix, suppose we have one, two, three, four students, and each student will have
Right, each student will have three marks.
So, what will be the shape of this?
We have four rows
and three columns, right? So, this will be the shape of this 2D matrix.
Right.
And now, if you stack images right one behind each other, then it will be like this, RGB image. I gave you an example.
So this has four cross four pixels.
So the shape will be three x four x four.
This will be the shape for this particular 3D matrix.
Right, guys.
So this is how you input the data.
Just to tell you a little bit more, since generative AI is very popular these days.
so what if I tell you the fact that the chat GPT,
which you use or you might have used,
has
never seen
a single
word
in its lifetime.
All it sees
is numbers,
right? Only numbers.
How do we see numbers? Suppose I say my
name
is
Raghav.
Raghav
is a
nice
name, right?
So these are two data, right?
These are two data points.
Now we all know that computers do not understand these, right? Computers do not understand these, right?
There is nothing, no understanding for computers to know what text is, right? It only knows zero and one. Yes, Dharnika.
Right?
It only knows zeros and ones. So see how we will convert this. So there is something called as vocabulary,
right?
So vocabulary are nothing but the unique words,
How many unique words do I have in this?
My name is Radha 4.
This is not unique, this is repeating, this is repeating five,
six, and this is repeating. So I have six words.
So now, guys, I will do something called as word to vec,
right? Where I will convert these words into vectors. How will I convert them? Look at
this. So I will have suppose this is S1,
this is S1, and this is S2.
So I will represent
S1 as
I will have a vector
of
size 6.
How?
I will say 100000.
Right?
100. How many elements does it have? Six elements, right?
Name will be 0 1 0 0 0 0,
Is will be 001000
and Raghav will be 000100.
Right? This is S1. My name is Raghav.
Now when it comes to S2,
When it comes to S2, how will I enter this?
S2
000100. Raghav.
What is is here?
001000.
What is a 000010?
A
nice is 0 0 0 0 0 1 and name will be 010000.
Right now, this will be the vector representation of these two sentences.
Just to tell you a fact,
GPT 3, right? GPT 3 model,
right?
GPT 3 or GPT 3.5, they have vocabulary
of 30,000 words, right? 30,000 words, and each word, right, each word
has a
dimension
of
12,500
numbers, right? What do I mean? Suppose I say raghav.
So it will be one word and it will be represented by eleven,500 different numbers.
Right. And like Raghav, there will be 30,000 words in this GPT model.
Right.
30,000 words in this GPT model.
And this total number of parameters which get trained in the neural network, which we will learn later on neural networks, they are almost close to 1.75
billion parameters.
So why I'm telling you all this? Because to showcase to you that what is the importance of vectors, In the entire machine learning and data science.
Yeah, people. So this is the reason, people. Now my question is how will you create these vectors?
How will you read these vectors?
Right?
The answer is through numpy package because it is the base package.
Clear people?
I hope today's class will be interesting for you because you will know the context.
Why are we doing it?
Yeah. So I'll try to show that to you how we convert things to vectors.
Right?
Okay.
Let me go here now.
Let me go here.
So, people,
we started using numpy. So I started with the zero dimension arrays, right? Zero dimension arrays.
So zero dimension is nothing but a scalar.
So I created ARR0, which was np dot array, and I entered a single word, single element inside this, which is nothing but a scalar, and then I checked the type of
uh ARR0 also, right? And then I check the dimension also.
So the answer was to class was numpy nd array, and the dimension was zero, right?
Exactly what I had mentioned in my PPP.
Right,
it will be having a zero dimension like this, right?
Same thing has been proven,
right?
Because it's a scalar.
Now coming on to one dimension, right? Coming on to one dimension, I create a list which is nothing but a one dimension data type.
Right now I create an array which is arr1 from array from this particular list LIS and then I check the type of
print arr1, check the type of arr1 and the dimension, right? So when I execute,
right, then you will see that it was this numpy array and the dimension was one, right? Exactly like this. So if I show you something else,
say print
arr1 dot shape,
you will see it's four, comma empty, right? And I show it to you here.
It will be empty, right?
Empty, and this will be comma one,
So this means that it has only four elements, right? If I increase these elements to say 55, 66, 77,
then it will become seven, comma blank, right? which means it has seven elements as a vector.
Now we create something with a nested list, right? Which is like this.
So with a nest, I want one bracket which is running outside, Then inside this, I have one, two, and three lists inside one list,
So this is a nested list.
This is marks of first student, second student, and the third student,
So I do this, and you see it is
this, right?
And I will show you the shape also.
Right? It will be three cross three, three rows and three columns.
Three rows and three columns.
Right now, similarly, we can also create a
3D matrix.
Right.
With
two levels, right? Level one and level two and three cross three.
So the shape will be what people? Can someone guess the shape?
What will be the shape of this?
I have shown you here.
Right?
If this is three, four, four, then what will be this?
Three rows and three columns, right?
So when you will execute, you will get two, three, three.
Right?
Two, three, three.
Right.
Right now, people, there are multiple ways, right? There are multiple ways to create arrays, and we should know them because all of these comes very, very handy.
Not right now.
I don't have enough context to give you right now, but later on, you will see with me or with some other trainer that how these will be used in deep learning specifically, right?
They are the key of deep learning algorithms, right? Where we initialize some weights, we initialize some biases, and those initializations are nothing but multidimensional numpy arrays, right?
Numpy arrays.
Okay.
Right, for example,
suppose I have this.
I have to multiply this with some random numbers, right?
So how will you generate these random numbers? You will generate them through numpy, and you can generate them in a specific kind of
shape, right? Which is 2 cross 3, and then you can multiply them, you can multiply the matrices, and you can get your output for yourself,
right?
So this is the way they are used.
So we saw the first thing from list we have already covered.
Then now we are moving on to creating zero arrays, right?
So I create a zero array of one dimension, right? Of one dimension, which is zero, zero. They are represented in floats, right? They are represented in floats zero dot zero, right?
Now you can create a two-dimensional zero array, right? You can create a two-dimensional zero array, which is you have to mention just the shape inside two cross one.
So it will have two rows and one columns, right? Two rows and one columns.
The difference here is the difference here is that these are one dimension and these are two dimensions, right? You have explicitly mentioned the rows and columns.
So you can expand this to 10 cross 10 also.
Right, you can expand in 10 cross 10 or 10 cross six, whatever you feel like yourself, right?
It will have 10 rows and six columns,
right?
Now you can also create
the 3D arrays, 3D zero arrays,
right?
Which is five, three, comma three. What does five means?
What does five means?
First element represents the number of layers, so you have five layers, right?
It's five layer deep, then you have three rows and three columns, right? So it will look something like this
one.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
Right? Like this.
Something like this.
Right? It will look like this.
Start.
One, two, three, one, two, three, one, two, three.
Right? Five, three, three.
Okay.
Yes, the number of matrices, hurry.
What I represented.
Right.
Layers,
rows,
Right. Layer, rows, and columns.
Clear.
So now when you execute this, you will get an arrangement like this.
Okay.
I try to show you this thing with another example, right?
Which is I created an image of an RGB image of 256 cross 256 pixels, right? Which have all zeros inside them.
And this is how it was created.
Right. Three layers RGB 256256.
So this is how the image will look like.
Right.
This is how it will look like.
Now you can also create
arrays with ones.
Right. Exactly the same way. You created it with zeros. I'll give it to you. I'll give you five minutes time to create them. I'll show you one.
So I say
a1 is equal to np
ones.
And inside I pass
two.
I check a1. So this is an
Right? It is an array like this.
Now you create
create two dimension
and
three dimension
arrays of one.
It is basically
Sorry, it's represented as a floater, right? It's represented as a float.
Okay.
Right.
Perfect.
Also, guys, with this, right? Also, with this, you can create the custom arrays, right? You can create the custom arrays, right?
How do we create custom arrays, people?
How do we create the custom arrays?
You have created now zeros.
You have created now ones.
Now what is left
that you create the custom arrays?
Uh forget about this.
I will come to this later on.
Right?
Let's create
custom arrays, right?
So the syntax remains the same, right? I say cus underscore arr is equal to
np dot full, right? This is the syntax, np dot full, right? And you will say six cross six.
And suppose you want an array of all fours, right? This is the dimension six plus six, and this value after comma is basically the value which you want.
You execute this and you copy this, paste this, and you will get the arrays of fours for yourself,
right? If you want of 10, you will get of 10.
If you want 10.3, you will get 10.3, right? Anything which you want.
If you want case, you will get case, right?
All the examples.
So let me just show that to you.
Yeah, like this
now guys, how did we create
or how did we use
range in Python?
Can you use
range to generate
numbers between 20 to 50?
Right? 20 to 50.
Can you give me the syntax quickly?
How did you do that in range?
How do we do that?
We said r is equal to
range
20 to 51, right?
And then I said
I in R
print I.
Right. And this is how I got the numbers, right?
So similar
to range in Python,
we have
a range in numpy.
Right. How do we use a range? I say
underscore arr is equal to np dot a range,
And then same syntax, I will say 20 to 51, 20 to 51, and that's it. And when I will check my arr
range arr, you will see I have generated myself numbers between 20 to 50 and a range in numpy.
Right? A range in numpy.
Yes, if you want an interval, so you can use this,
say a range one, and after comma, you pass the third argument. Suppose it's three.
So now it will jump
three times, right?
20, 23, 26, 29, 32, 35, like this, up till 50.
Now, guys, there is something which is called as lens space.
Right? What is lens space?
It stands
for
linear spacing,
which means
between two given numbers.
this function will fit the required number of
numbers.
For example,
suppose, for example,
we need to create
an interval
from
0 to 1.
People, there are infinite numbers I can have between 0 to 1, isn't it?
Infinite numbers I can have between 0 to 1.
0.000000000001.0000010101.
Right? I can go in the infinite manner, right now. For example,
you need to create numbers between 0 to 10, right? And you want to create and want to have
10 numbers in it, right?
So how will you do this?
It's not float, it's about the number theory, right? Between 0 and 1, you have infinite numbers,
right? So you say length space is equal to
np dot length space, right? np dot length space.
You mentioned from 0 to 10, you want to have 10 numbers, right? And when you will create length space,
you will see that these are the numbers are there which have been created, right?
These are the numbers which have been created.
Right?
Nine numbers now. I say 100 numbers. I want evenly spaced 100 numbers, right? Evenly spaced 100 numbers.
How are they even?
You can simply subtract one number from another, and the difference for all the numbers will be exactly the same.
Subtract any two numbers, it will be 0.010101.
Right? Where do we need this?
We need this to plot the accesses, right? When you will plot graphs, you will need access between this interval. You need five values that works like this.
Okay.
Suppose you want from 0 to 10 five different values, right?
You will have five different values like this,
Between the gap of 0.5.
If I say 1 to 10,
you will have values like this.
Clear 100 values like this.
Yeah?
Clear, guys. How do we use length space?
Suppose you want from 0 to 10, interval from 0 to 10, and 10 will be included. 0 will not be included.
Right? We'll start from 1.
So I go to 1, it will be from
1. Why is 0 not included then?
Yeah, 0 is included. Right?
0 is also included and 10 is also included.
100 numbers between them.
Right?
Clear? This is what linspace is.
Now guys,
now
suppose you
Logeshwaran lint space is basically used
if you want to create n numbers between the range of numbers, right?
Between 0 to 1, right? Suppose between 0 to 1, you are trying to plot a graph.
and your values are 0.2, 0.3, 0.6?
And you want to draw a graph.
So you will have to mark the axis, right? The x-axis and the y-axis.
So you can use length space there.
And what will it do? It will take the range, it will take the interval in between you want to add the equal space numbers.
And then the third argument here will be that how many numbers do you want between them?
So this syntax tells you that
from
0 to 1
give me 100 numbers.
How are these numbers?
Equally
spaced
Equally spaced numbers.
So when you will execute this, you will see that all there are 100 numbers which have been generated, 100 numbers.
And all the numbers are equidistant from each other because difference of every single number from the next number is 0.010101.
Yep.
That's what it does.
Right
now, guys, now suppose we want to
generate random numbers, right? You want to generate random numbers, right? Now we are interested in generating random numbers.
So we have something called as random
dot random, right?
What will it do?
Random dot random will generate
random
float numbers
Random float numbers between zero to one.
How will this happen?
You will say
rand underscore rand is equal to np dot random dot random and inside you will mention what is the dimension that you seek.
Suppose I want six cross six.
So when you will check this, you will have all numbers for six cross six dimension, right?
Six cross six matrix.
Right now, every time you rerun this, the numbers will change because all of these are random numbers.
Right? All of these are random numbers.
Now I say 100 multiplied by rand underscore rand.
You will see all of them, all these numbers will be multiplied by 100.
All of them
in one shot.
Now just like this,
we can also create
random integers.
How will we create random integers?
I say, rand int underscore rand int is equal to np dot random dot rand
int.
Right.
And here you will specify that what is the range of numbers you want from. So I say between 20 to 25.
I need random numbers, and then I want it from in a 3 cross 3 formatter.
Right. And now when you will check your rand,
you will get random numbers generated like this.
random numbers generated like this.
If
you say three cross three cross three, you will get a three cross three cross three matrix.
Even if you will only say three, you will get a one D.
Right, guys.
You can change the dimension.
So this is the range from which you want to choose the random numbers, and this is the dimension you want this matrix or vector to be in.
Now, guys, we'll move on to the next part, which is basically properties and
again there are a lot of operations, you'll have to see it yourself, right?
Properties and
attributes
arrays, right? Property and attributes of numpy arrays.
Okay.
Now, guys, the first one in this scheme of things is shape of array, right? Shape of array.
What is shape of array?
It tells you
dimensions of the
array
stored in a
couple.
For example,
I say arr zero,
right?
Arr one,
arr
two,
arr three, right?
And then I say
print this
dot shape,
Like this.
And you will see that it will give you the shape of each array.
0D, 1D, 2D, and 3D.
Right, people.
Shape of the array.
Please try it out.
We have used it one or two times, but this is what shape of array actually means.
Second is people,
endim.
Right?
Is end dim.
Right? Endim of array.
It tells you
the rank of the array, whether it's one dimensional, two dimensional, zero dimensional, three dimensional, four dimensional.
So again, I will do the same thing.
I'll say ndim and you will see it will give you zero, one, two, three.
Zero dimension, zero rank, one rank, two rank, and three rank.
And it can go all the way up to end rank.
Before this, I should have also
printed these arrays.
These are the arrays.
These
are the arrays which we have, and these are the subsequent things.
Rank of the array.
Then, guys, the third thing is
the
size of
array.
It tells you
the number of elements inside.
How many elements do we have inside this array?
In ARR1, how many elements do we have?
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.
How many elements do we have in this 2 cross 2 ar2?
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, which is rows multiplied by columns, 3 multiplied by 3.
And how many elements do we have in this 3D?
Which is 2 multiplied by 3 multiplied by 3, which is 18.
So now when you copy this, you can use this
and say
size.
it will say 1, 7, 9, 18.
Fourth stable
the D type
of array
tells you
the data type of the array, right? And I've told you we place only
homogeneous
data in array, right? What will happen if we don't do this? I will show that to you also, right?
So we do this, right?
And we say
D type.
And you will see in 64 all of them are integers, right?
All of them are integers.
That's the reason we are getting in 64.
Right.
Suppose I create a new array, arr underscore new, right?
Let me say head
rightogenous.
And I say it is like np dot array.
Let's say like this.
Right, like this.
Now, people, when you will check
arr.d type, you will see it will give you float.
Just because of one floating point number inside this entire array, it gets converted to float.
Between all the integers, if you put one float, then it will be taking float directly.
now,
let me just copy this and let's say heterogeneous one.
And let me add another value which is string and say rather.
Right.
And when you will execute this, it will give you u32. U32 here is representing strings, It is all called as objects, These are all string values,
So precedence is strings greatest, then float, and then your
integers, right? If you place the heterogeneous data inside the numpy array,
You only need to put homogeneous data in the array
now.
Fifth is the item size
of array, What is item size?
It gives you
the byte
by each element of an array, right? Because we assume that elements will be homogenous, it will give you the byte occupied by each element of the array, only one element.
Okay, so how will it happen?
So let's say arr zero
or they say arr one dot item size,
right? And you will get eight, right?
So why eight? Because
each data point, right? Each data point is occupying
the result
is
eight bytes.
Let me put this here.
Eight bytes,
because each element
in ARR1 is occupying
64 bits,
which are equivalent to
eight bytes.
One byte is equal to eight bits.
So 64 bits will be equal to eight bytes, right? That is how it is giving you the result.
Now, if you are interested in knowing the entire bytes, right? Entire bytes, then you say n bytes
will
give you the
total bytes
occupied
by the elements of the array,
right? You say print
arr1 dot
n bytes,
And write
bytes.
It will be
56 bytes.
Why? Because how many elements do we have in our ARR1?
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven.
Seven eights are 56.
56 total bytes are being occupied with by ARR1.
Now, guys, the seventh one
is
as type, right?
In array.
This will help you
change the data type
of the array, right? Change the data type of the array.
Suppose I have arr1 dot d type,
which is
so I say print
d type, right?
This is n64, right?
And now what I do is I say print
wait, let me give you a structured way print
arr one, right?
Let me say:
array
arr one,
right? D type of array.
Now,
arr two.
Sorry, arr one is equal to arr one
dot as type, right? Dot as type, and let's say I want to convert this in np dot
right np dot
uh
int
32, right? I want to create and convert this in arr
int 32, right? When I do this,
and now when I will copy these same things,
you will see for yourself, right?
Now the d type was in 64, and now the d type is int 32, right?
If I want, I can do this conversion in float also,
float 64, right?
And then I will just copy this
and I will paste it here,
right? And now you will see now the floating point has been activated,
right? It has been now activated.
We can go till int, we can go till int 8.
Right.
I can go to 16,
right?
And I can do this.
I can go to int
yeah like this int eight also.
64, 32,
so first one has to be
thirty-two to close.
Whatever, right?
Like this.
Okay,
you can convert this.
Also, people, this is later on conversion.
You can define the data type
of the array while
creation time also. How would you do that? Suppose you are creating arr11 and you say np.array, right? And suppose you take it from a list and then you just put a comma and say d type.
So what will be the default data type here, people?
If I just do this, if I just execute this,
what will be the default data type?
N64 is the default,
isn't it?
But now suppose I want to change it right here. I say data type is equal to float 32.
Right?
Sorry, float 64.
NP dot.
Sorry.
My bad.
Float 64. Right.
And I say arr11 and this will be float 64. If you want float 32, it will also become float 32.
Right? Right here while you define.
Instead of using as type, you can do it right here.
These things will come in very handy, people, because you will have to save memory.
Because when your data becomes very, very big, you will be always in a crunch for memory.
Like this, you want integers, then integers will be like this.
Random dot rand, like this.
Suppose you want to generate 0 to 6,
And suppose you want to generate
say 100 numbers
like this, 0 to 6.
The scores
one to six, like this
randomly.
Suppose you want to generate
100 scores for
five different batsmen randomly.
It will be like this: batsman number one, batsman number two, batsman number three, four, and fifth.
Right?
Yep.
Understand the data, guys. Now it's the time to understand the data.
Now, guys, we have methods in
numpy arrays, right? Methods in numpy arrays.
So, what are these methods now?
The first method we have to learn is called as reshape, right? Reshape.
Yeah, so reshape is you can use this to create.
You can use this to create
a new shape of the array. Very, very powerful, guys.
Very powerful. One of the most powerful methods in numpy is the reshape, right?
And how do we use reshape?
Suppose
we have a 1D array of 20 elements, right?
Now to reshape this,
reshape it, we need to find the factors,
right? Factors of 20.
They are what?
1, 20, 4, 5,
2, 10.
Right?
Here are the factors.
Now see what will I do, right? Now see what will I do.
Let me create a say random array, right? Random array.
I say
underscore arr is equal to np dot random
dot rand int, right?
And let me say I want to create it from 1 to 50, right? And I want it to be having 20 elements, right?
So I say random dot arr.
So you will have random values inside this, right? Random 20 values now. see,
Now reshape.
First.
I will
reshape in one cross twenty, right? One, comma 20.
How will I do that?
You just have to write
print
arr.
Sorry, random dot arr random underscore arr
dot reshape dot reshape and you just pass in the dimension. I say one comma 20.
Right.
And when you will do this, you will see it is coming now in one comma twenty format, right?
So let me just also write print
2D
one, 20.
Right.
And now what I'll do is I'll copy this
and I will paste this and say
20, 1.
Right?
You will see it will be like this 20, comma 1 immediately with reshape, right?
Let me copy this.
Let me say 2D. I'm still at 2D.
Let me say
2, comma 10.
Right?
And you will see this is 2, comma 10.
Now I can reshape it in
10, comma 2.
Right?
10 comma 2.
Right.
Then I can reshape the same thing
in
4 comma 5.
And I can reshape this in 5, comma 4.
Right?
Like this.
Guys, are you able to see the power?
One dimension. I am able to create two dimensions.
And now I will take it a step further and I will write it in three dimensions.
Right? How will I write it in three dimension?
Let me say this
one, comma
two, comma ten, right? This will also be three dimensions. Let's sorry, two, comma two, comma, five.
Let me say this.
And now you will see I can have this in
three dimensions,
right?
Yep.
I can also say
in three dimensions, like this.
I want to have five layers
with two rows and two columns, So you will have it like this also,
So this is how people we can reshape the array very powerful, very, very powerful,
right?
Very, very powerful.
Right. And you can take this
and say print
random dot this and you can say print
dot shape.
Right?
So this was the first one.
like this.
Also, people, if you want to visualize, we can also go this route.
We can have 10,
2, 1.
Right?
It will look like this.
Ten layers.
Right? Ten layers you can have.
Great now.
Second method which we have to learn is called as
transpose.
Transpose method, right? What does that do?
It interchanges the
dimensions
like rows and columns, right?
Yes, absolutely.
Right.
Suppose you have a matrix, right? Which is
22, 33, 44, 55, 66, 77.
Right? This is a.
So now when you will a transpose it, right?
The dimension right now, the shape right now is 3, 2.
Now this will become 2 comma 3. And how this will happen?
Rows will now become columns, and columns will now become rows.
Right. So let's make
column the rows, right? Sorry, columns the rows.
It will be 22, 44, 66,
33, 55, 77.
Right?
So people in transpose, no information is lost.
It is just a change in the view, right?
Which is happening, right?
22, 44, 66,
33, 55, 77.
Why do we need
transposition?
Suppose we have two matrix.
This is 11th class mathematics, right? One has
a dimension of n cross m and the second has dimension of A cross b.
If you
want to multiply
these two matrix,
say
M1 and M2.
There needs to be a satisfaction of condition.
M should be equal to A. This should be equal to this. And the resultant vector, the resultant matrix which you will get will be of N cross B dimension.
Right.
So oftentimes suppose this is N cross M.
This is N cross M.
Right. M cross N.
And you know that M is equal to A.
So what will you do? You will transpose this matrix, right? You will transpose this matrix, then it will become N cross M. And then M can be equivalent to A.
Right. For example, what I am saying, we have one matrix which is 2 cross 3.
And this matrix is 2 cross 5.
Right.
So can you multiply these matrix, people?
Is 3 equal to 2?
Right? The answer is no.
So what will you do? You will just transpose this and this will become 3 cross 2.
And this is 2 cross 5.
And now you can multiply this, and the resultant will become 3 cross 5 matrix.
So for operations like these, we need transposition.
So how do we transpose it?
How do we transpose it?
So let us say again
arr2, This is arr2, and I want to transpose it. So I say arr2 underscore t is equal to
np dot transpose.
Sorry, sorry, arr2 dot
transpose,
And now when you will see arr2 underscore t you will see rows and columns have interchanged, right? Rows and columns have interchanged with each other.
Or let me give you one more example.
if this is not clear,
let me pick up
this again.
Right now I say
dot three shape
into say
Right, this is two cross ten. And now, when you want to transpose this, so I will say this: underscore t is equal to this dot
transpose.
and
we can check this now,
and it will be this
. sorry, guys.
So this is going to be
it will be like this, right?
Transpose.
And now
if you want to see
this,
this was the original shape, right?
Rows and columns have now been interchanged, transposed with each other
now, guys. The third
method,
the third method which is there with us is called as flatten, right? It is called as flatten,
right? What does flatten do?
It reduces
the dimension to one dimension, right? Any dimension you have, it reduces it to one dimension. For example, I have this
right.
and now when I say
dot underscore f, this will become
this dot
flatten.
and when you will check this up,
you will see that it has now become one dimension.
No matter how many dimensions you have, it will become one dimension.
Let me take this again to show you one more example.
And
here I say dot reshape into
five cross two cross two, I do this.
My random arr is this: it has five layers, two rows and two columns.
So now I say this
underscore flatten is equal to this dot flatten,
and if you will check it now again, you will see it has now flattened it up.
Now, why do we need this? We need this for a lot of statistical operations. We need this to feed the data into the algorithms, As we will move forward, you will understand the use of flattening,
now, guys.
Moving on, and as discussed, let me now show you
the power of
numpy,
right? Numpy
over
lists and other
data types, right? I will not take a lot of examples
just a second, guys.
Yeah,
okay
now, guys.
I told you
that
lists
take up
much more
memory
as compared
to numpy arrays, right? And I'm gonna prove this to you right
now.
Let me use,
let me create a random sequence of random numbers using range in Python, right?
And say I create range of 10,000 numbers, right? Range of 10,000 numbers. So, what will this give me?
This will give me numbers from 0 to 9999, right?
Continuous numbers, right? So this is range.
I will use
a range in
numpy
to create
a similar.
Series of numbers,
right?
So let's say array is equal to np dot arange.
Right.
Same thing, same done by both, right? I've shown you above also.
Now let me import sys
library, right?
Syspackage.
And I will use something called as get size or right. Get size of.
What does this do?
Get size of.
It's a method
which calculates
the bytes
occupied
by a single
element in
vanilla python. What is vanilla python? It is the traditional Python.
Right? Vanilla Python.
So let me just show that to you.
I'll use this and I will say print.
Now, guys, if I get
size of any random number from this range, right? Any random number.
Say I get size of 5, right? And I then multiply that bytes with the length of random.
Right?
With the length of random, this ran,
right?
Right. With the length of random.
Do you think I will get the bytes for the entire
data structure?
What am I saying is suppose
I used range
5. So what will this give me?
0, 1, 2, 3, 4.
Right? This will be the output.
So now I say get
size of say I say 2, right? So suppose 2 is x, and then I multiply this with the length of this series, which is 5.
So do you think I will get 5x?
Which will represent the number of bytes occupied by the entire data type?
Anything randomly, any random number.
This can be 3, right?
Why not hurry?
Why not?
All of these are integers.
So integers all of 64 bits,
assuming. So if you calculate the side of size of this, and if you multiply with the total number of numbers, you will get the total size,
isn't it?
Index is in tangent.
No, no, no, it's not about that. It's about the element, right? Homogeneous elements inside this.
I am saying when you use range 5, what is going to be the output?
0, 1, 2, 3, 4, right now, all these are elements.
Elements of range,
right? All of them are elements of range, right?
Now I am saying if I fetch the
size of one element and multiply it with the length of the entire range, will I get the bytes
occupied by the entire range?
For example, if I do this, right? If I do this,
this is 28, right? 28 bytes, people, 28 bytes
are occupied
by
one element of range, right?
One element of
range, right?
Now if I just I am saying, I'm just saying if I multiply to find how many numbers range has.
How many numbers
range has
equal to 10,000?
Right?
So total
memory occupied
will be how much?
It will be
28 multiplied by 10,000, which will be equal to 28,000.
Yeah, and how will you find this?
You will say print
this multiplied by length of RAM.
Right, 28,000 bytes.
Clear now?
Yes.
Now this is for the range. Now let me use another thing.
So, how will you calculate the length of this array?
What
uh property and attribute will you use, people?
N bytes, right?
N bytes will give you total bytes occupied by the elements of the array, right? We will use n bytes here.
So I come back down and I say
using n bytes for arrays, right?
And you will see what the result come.
Print
uh
array.n bytes,
right? And I say bytes.
Are you ready to see the result?
Do you see what has happened?
How many bytes this was taking?
It was taking 28,000 bytes.
How many bytes this is taking?
This is taking 80,000 bytes.
This was taking 2 lakh 80,000. This is taking 80,000.
2 lakh extra bytes of memory is taken by range.
Ran is range.
And if I just go to million numbers,
right?
Million numbers in both.
See the difference it becomes.
Right? This is now 33
million bytes it is taking, and it is taking 8 million bytes.
20 million extra bytes are occupied, right?
Now, people, do you believe me?
Yeah, that numpys are way more efficient in memory management as compared to the traditional data types of python.
Yes.
Okay, that's the first part.
Now, second is people, performance, right? Performance.
So what I'm going to do is what I'm going to do is I am going to
import
time, right? It's a it's a module in Python, right? Suppose, I say x is equal to range
this much,
and then I have y is equal to
range.
say
this
to
this.
Both of them will have equal amount of numbers, same numbers, both of them will have, right?
This will have say uh
one, two, three, one, two, three, ten million values, ten million values.
This will also have ten million values,
right? Both of them will have ten million values.
Now, what I'm trying to do is I want to add them up, right? Byte bit by bit. I want to add them up, right?
I want to add first element of this to first element of this, second of this to second of this, third of this to third of this, like this.
Okay, I want to do this now. What I will do is I will run a counter, right? I will run a counter which is the start time,
right? And this is given by time dot time, right?
Which will give you the
this
will give you the
current time, right?
After this, I will run the operation. I will say c is equal to x plus y
for x, comma y
in zip
right in zip x, comma y right.
Add x plus y
bit by bit, element by element for x and y in zip. Zip is a function, right, which allows you to do this operation sequentially, right? Sequentially, right?
Add the
elements
of x and y
element by
element, right? Element by element.
Right element by element.
Right.
And then I am going to print right. So start time will start, and now I will say time dot time, which is now the end time minus start time.
So this will give me the time taken for execution, isn't it, guys?
Will give me
delta of time,
which is equal to time taken for operation
seconds,
right? These many seconds will be taken,
right?
So let me run this and it takes around say
4.3 seconds, right? To do this, right? 4.3 seconds now, guys.
See what happens.
You had to write this complex syntax in the traditional Python.
Now let me show this on arrays, right?
What will happen on arrays? I will say a is equal to np dot arange,
And inside arrange, I will pass the same values what I have taken above, right? And I will say b is equal to np dot
a range, and I will pass the same values inside,
right? Exactly the same.
Now what I will do is I will say
same thing.
Right.
Just I will change the execution of C.
Will now simply become people A plus B.
What is simple?
This or this?
This or this
to write? Do you see the power?
If not, I will show this to you again, right? Later on, and let me run this.
And you see the difference.
Now let me just increase a couple of zeros, right? A couple of zeros.
Two zeros I am increasing in both the use cases.
It is going on and on, right?
Let's see how much time it will take
to add,
say two million, one billion numbers.
One billion numbers I have asked my system to add,
and I want to see how much time it takes.
Running, running, running.
yeah kernel has died.
Kernel has died, people.
I'll have to restart.
Right?
I will have to import
NumPy
as entry.
So let me just remove one zero
from both.
It is taking four seconds, removing one zero from here also.
Right.
And when I do this,
it takes one second.
Do you see, guys,
what is the difference in performance, also,
For both of these.
And if you didn't understand this, let me give you an example.
Range five.
This is five to ten,
right?
And this is basically
adding elements.
Right.
7 9 11 13.
So this will be what will be output of this?
This will be 0, 1, 2, 3, 4.
And this will be output what?
5,
6, 7, 8, 9.
Right. So 0 plus 5, 5, 6 plus 1, 7, 7 plus 2, 9.
8 plus 3, 11. 9 plus 4, 13.
And the same thing if I do here.
Then what will happen? I say 5.
I say 5 and 10.
Right. And I say c is equal to a plus b and I say c.
Same thing you get here. Right. We can move on.
Right.
The next bit, guys, which we have to understand.
The next bit which we have to understand is called as the indexing in numpy arrays.
Right. Indexing in numpy arrays.
Right. How do we index the elements?
Indexing in
numpy
Right. Indexing in numpy arrays.
So again, you know indexing from basic Python.
So let's start with 1D for 1D arrays.
Right. I will use ARR1.
Yeah.
This is ARR1 now, right? This is ARR1.
Okay.
Now, people, what I want to do is, what I want to do is I want to fetch, right?
I want to fetch. Right. You can slice and dice.
Let's say dice.
33. Right.
So again, as per our normal indexing of list, what is 33?
What is the index of 33 people?
2. So you will say the same thing. Print.
Right.
Arr 1 squared bracket 2.
And you will get 33 by yourself.
Right?
If you wish to slice, same thing, right?
33 to say 66.
What is the index?
33 is 2, 2.
Which one?
3, 4, 5, and 6.
Right? You will write 3 to 6, Not 5, hurry.
5 is not included. Remember?
So print
arr 1.
2 is to 6.
And you will get 33, 44, 55, 66.
Right?
Simple indexing.
Please try it out.
And if you want, you can have this code also.
You can write this code.
You will always have clarity that why do we use it?
Moving on, people. Moving on. Let's see indexing
in a 2D array.
Right. And before I explain this to you, let me take you here, right?
So a 2D array will be what?
Right. This is a 2D array.
It has three rows
and three columns, right? Rows, columns.
So now for rows, indexing will start from zero.
So if you have to
fetch this particular row,
right?
So what will be the index?
It will be row zero.
If you have to fetch this particular row,
the index will be one.
And if you have to fetch this particular row, this index will be
two.
Similarly, for column, if you have to fetch this particular column, right?
You will have column is equal to zero.
This particular column, column equal to one,
this particular column, column equal to two, right?
Indexing will start from minus one again, right? 0, 1, 2.
So let me just show that to you, right?
Let's say I call arr2.
this is my arr2.
Now
indexing
first
row, right? How will I do that? I will say print
arr2 and I will write how?
How will I write this?
I will write row 0, right? Row zero.
So what will this give me? This will give me this, right? The syntax is
row space column, right?
So now if you just pass one, it will give you only rows, right?
Row one, row two, row three.
Right? Similarly,
if you want to create it for columns,
right?
What will you say?
Sorry.
Uh
columns
it was
zero.
Column one,
column two,
column three, right?
Right.
So what is my column one? 76, 89, 98,
76, 89, 98,
Right? And if you want column two.
sorry.
If you want column two, this is the column two and this is column three.
Right, guys?
90, 99, 99.
Independently.
Now, if I ask you to fetch me a particular element.
Element, right?
Say I want you to fetch me
78. Right? How will you fetch 78? You will say print arr2.
What is the row for 78?
Which row does it belong to?
012?
To which row 78 belongs?
One row.
Which column it belongs to?
012.
1.
Hurry check again.
Whether it belongs to 0 column, first column, or second column.
Right?
And you will get uh sorry.
01. So this is 2.
Right? 78. Right?
Right. Second row, first column.
How to define it as in
this is your
matrix.
Right now, what are the index positions for
this? This row is zero row, first row, second row.
This is your zeroth column, first column, second column.
Yeah.
Yes, no, maybe.
Are we understanding this?
This much is clear.
The indexing of rows and columns.
Now, now if you have two, so the syntax is
say this is matrix A.
So you will say A in this A matrix, you will write row, comma, column.
Right?
Suppose I want to access only zeroth row.
So there will be no column.
So what will you get? Row number zero.
Right?
Row number zero, and you will just put it like this, or you can put a comma and put colon.
Colon means what? Take everything.
So I want all three columns together.
Zero row and all three columns.
So this will be your.
so Let me show that to you.
Right?
See this zeroth row and all the columns.
So what will be your answer? 76, 88, 90.
Right?
Then if you want to access the second row, 89, 90, 99. 89, 90, 99.
1 and like this.
Clear?
Now, similarly, for columns, what will happen?
You will take all the rows,
comma which column do you want? If you say 2, what will be the result for this?
What numbers will you get for this?
colon comma two
You will get 33, 66, 99.
Now, coming to the element, right?
Suppose now you want to fetch 55, right? So what will you write?
You will write which row does it belong to?
Follow this syntax.
It belongs to the first row.
Which column does it belong to?
First column. So what will you get?
55. Come to come to this example. Now you want 78 in this particular array or matrix, right?
Where is 78? Which row does it belong to?
Is it first row?
Check carefully.
Zeroth row,
first row, second row.
Yeah?
So I put two here. Now which column does it belong to?
First column, second column. Sorry, zeroth column, first column, second column.
Belongs to the first column.
So I put one here.
So when you put this syntax, you will get 78.
Clear?
Now the third thing is slicing
through
the array.
Right now, for this, I want I want 90, 99, 78, 99.
That means what?
I want this,
this, this, and this.
Let me take you to the PPT first.
Now, what I'm asking you to fetch me?
I'm asking you to fetch me these four numbers.
Right? These four numbers.
So here, what will you write? Which rows are included in this, people?
Which rows are included in this?
Row one to all.
Right? One to all.
Yeah.
Not two. One to all.
Right?
And you leave everything like this.
If you have the last row, you leave it empty after the colon.
Comma.
Which columns do you want
for this?
One and two.
Right?
And when these will intersect, when these will intersect, you will get this area. You will get this shaded area, green shaded area. So I will say
I need from column one
to all the columns, right?
So what will this fetch you? What will this fetch you? This will fetch you
44,
55, 66,
and 77, 88, 99.
Right?
What will this fetch you?
This will fetch you 22, 55, 88,
33, 66, 99.
What are the commonalities between both of these?
Access,
both of these slices. What are the commonalities?
It is only this much.
Right?
55, 66, 88, 99.
So do you think you will get your result?
Yeah, let's check it here.
Right. I say print
arr2, right? And this I say.
I need row 0, sorry, row 1 to empty, and then column 1 empty, and you will get 90, 99,
78, 90.
Indexing.
Yeah.
Now guys, let's check it for
three dimensions, right? 3D.
I say arr three, right? This is my ARR3.
Right?
So let me just put an example here.
Suppose my arrays are 11, 2, 2, 3, 3,
4, 4, 5, 6, 6,
7, 7, 8, 8, 9.
Right. This is my first.
Then behind this, I have another matrix which is
uh
111 222 333
444 555 666
777 888 999.
Right?
And in my
Third one.
I have 1111 2222 3333
4444 5555 6666
999.
Is that is it qualifying for a 3D array?
Can you access anything on this particular array if given a chance separately?
Like this one.
Now, people, if you want to move between layers, right?
If you want to move between layers, do you think I have told you one particular access?
Which is what?
Which is the layers.
So what number will be given to this layer?
Layer number 0,
layer number 1,
and layer number 2.
So now if you have to access this 555, which layer will you go to first?
You will go to first layer.
Then which row will you go to?
You will go to
first row and first column.
So if you pass this syntax, what will you get? You will get 555.
Right?
Problem solved.
The only bottleneck was the layers part, and you have additional parameter or argument for this layer.
So if I come back to my example and if you have to access this 555, right? How will you do that?
I say print
arr2, arr3 right? And this I say, and in this I say what?
I have to access this 555.
which layer number is this?
This is layer number 0, right? This is layer number 0 and this is layer number 1.
So I say layer number 1.
Which row is this?
In this particular layer, it is layer number.
Sorry, it is row number 1 and column number 1. And when you do this, you will get 5 by 5.
Right?
If you want 999, what you will do?
You will change this to 2,
right?
If you want 777, or let's say if you want 98, what will you do for 98?
Layer number 0, row number 2, column number 0.
And you will get this 98.
Clear, guys.
Yep.
Layer row column. In the same way you will slice it.
Right?
You will slice it.
Yep.
Right. I'll write the syntax
so that you don't get confused.
It is array
squared bracket
layer row
column.
Right. Layer
row
column.
Right. This is the syntax.
Perfect.
Right.
Great.
We can also perform some operations, right?
Plus, minus multiplication, division between two arrays very, very easily.
Right.
It should not pose any problem to us.
Right. We can do all the operations which we want to, right? Between two arrays, right?
For example, right, you had you have
operations on arrays.
So let's say
uh
let's see as a list,
right?
List.
So we have list is equal to one, two, three, four, five.
Right now, suppose you want to square
each element of the list, right?
What will you do?
You will say
sq underscore l
is equal to
x to the power of two
for x in
l, right?
And then you will say print
sq underscore l and you will get the squared of list, right?
Original list squared list. Now
in array, what will happen?
Suppose I say
a1
is equal to np dot array and l. I create the same array out of this list.
I say print
original
array.
Right. I say a1.
Right. This is my original array.
Same as this.
Now I want to square it.
Square the elements of arrays.
Very, very simple.
Nothing you require. You just say, you just say
sq underscore a1 is equal to sq underscore a1 is equal to a1 to the power of two.
Right. A1 to the power of two.
Right. And then you print the
square. Right.
You get the squared r.
Suppose
you want to find the mean of
the mean of numbers
using list.
Right. So what will you do?
You will say
mean is equal to
sum of
L right list divided by length of list,
right?
And you will get the mean,
right? Which is three for this one, right? This original list.
Now let me show you in arrays.
Right. How will you do this?
You will say mean is equal to np dot mean and you will just pass a1.
Right. And when you will check mean, you will get 3.0.
Right?
Nothing like this directly.
Right. Direct like this.
Right. You can you have I've already showed you add, I've already showed you uh square, and then I believe you can understand that
what all operations are possible using the arrays, right? Leveraging the power of arrays,
Also, guys, in the arrays, right? In the arrays, what you can do is you can perform
you can
perform some
string operations, right? Very powerful string operations, right?
So for example, let's say I have a I have I have an array, right?
I have an array of names of people,
So I say names is equal to
np array,
And I say
Radhav.
Uh then I say
Dinesh,
And then I say
Madhu, right? These three names I had, right? So you can check the names, they will be like in the array, right? And the data type will be U6, which is a representation of strings, right now, guys.
Suppose you want to capitalize, you wish to
capitalize the names,
right?
Of people.
What will you do?
You will say, print me
np.car.
Capitalize.
And inside this, you will pass names
and you will see all the names have been capitalized.
You see this?
R has been capitalized, D has been capitalized, m has been capitalized.
Right.
You can convert them into upper if you want.
Print
np.car.upper
names and you will have all of them in caps lock.
You can say print np.car
You will have them in lower.
Right.
You can put the title, right? Suppose I say uh
T I T L E title is equal to np array, and I say
rather.
Voyel,
right.
Then I say
Dinesh
Tenapati.
Right.
And I say
Madhut
Varma.
Right.
I say these three things.
Now, if I say print
np.car.title,
right? And I say
titles, you will see that all the words will be in capitalized mode. Raghav Goyal, D and S of Dinesh Senapati, M and V of Madhu Varma are now capitalized.
I can also
replace something if I wish to suppose I want to replace Madhu with say survi.
Right? I will say
print
right np dot care.
Replace right. And you will say
where you want to replace, I say title.
And in this, I want to replace
Madhu
with
Surbhi.
And you will say it will be Surbi underscore one.
Surbi one.
Right. Madhu has been replaced with Survi.
Right. If you want to calculate
the characters of strings,
right, you can do that.
Print
np.car
dot str underscore length of
titles, and you will get 11 characters are there in here.
15 are there here, and 11 are here
in this particular thing.
You can do much more powerful things also.
Let me show you one complex function, Suppose I have
fname
is equal to np.array?
And we have
Raghav,
Dinesh,
madhu.
And we have L underscore name.
Right. We have these two things.
Now I can create a new array,
full underscore name, by simply right, by simply saying np car
add
right.
And I say
fname,
right.
comma,
L underscore name, right?
Plus
full name.
Yeah, Raga. Well, I just was trying to add a space
in between.
Anyway, right?
We can do that.
You can also people
search in arrays, right?
Very powerful again.
Search in arrays using where.
Right.
You can say suppose a2 is equal to
np dot array.
Right. And I'll say 1122 3344 5566.
Right. And now you have to say a is equal to np dot where
right. And in this you say a2 greater than 20.
Right. And when you will check a
uh it's giving me the index.
Why is it giving me the index?
Does it always return index?
One more thing is you can
find uh
you can find an
uh
right through a letter. You can find an element
through
a letter, guys. These are all some tricks which you should know because you will be dealing with data and you need to pull data, right?
You need to pull data a lot, right, based on condition and based on things.
Suppose you want to find out the names which have g in them,
Or R A in them.
So how will you do this? I will say print, And I will say
np dot care
dot find, And I will say find this inside full underscore
names, right? And find me R A.
Right?
R A.
True, false, false.
Right, it returns true because it has found it here.
Right.
So I don't want to tell you indexing through this, but anyway, you should know this.
Just just assume this that I am telling you to write this, okay, because this is much easier when we will go to pandas.
Right?
Just write it as a syntax,
okay?
Greater than equal to zero.
I hope this is clear. So let's start with the data science interview questions and answers.
And the number one problem we would be facing is real-world problem solving.
And the question one is handling missing data in predictive modeling.
So imagine you have given a data set where 30% percent of the data for key predictive variable is missing. This variable is crucial for a predictive model.
How would you handle this situation to ensure the integrity and performance of the model?
And please describe your approach step by step.
So, starting with the answer, you can start with handling missing data set is a common challenge in data science, and it's important to address it carefully to maintain the accuracy of the model.
And here's how you could approach this situation. The number one point would be identify the missing data. So, first you need to understand where the missing values are in your dataset.
You can do this by using a simple code in Python with libraries like mandas.
For example, you can use the data.isnal.sum function that will show you the count of missing values in each column.
Then you can analyze the pattern, determine if there's a pattern to the missing data.
Is it random or is it missing for a reason?
This can affect your approach. If the data is missing at random, the methods you use might be different than if the data is missing systematically.
So choosing a method for imputation.
Let's see the next method that is choosing a method for imputation.
So if the missing data is numeric, you might replace missing values with the mean or median of that column.
This is simple and effective, but can be used primarily when the data is missing completely at random.
Then comes model based imputation.
Sometimes you can use other variables in the data to predict missing values using a regression model.
This can be more accurate, but is also more complex.
Then we'll use the knearest neighbor's can algorithm.
But before that, we have a code snippet here that could be used for the implementation of imputation.
You could use Python or R.
And now moving on, we'll see the K-nearest neighbors algorithm. So this method predicts the missing values based on how closely related the data points are to each other.
So after imputation, it's crucial to check how your changes have affected the overall data set and model performance.
Sometimes filling in too many missing values can introduce bias.
And then we have visualization.
To help understand before and after the imputation, you could visualize the distribution of the variable using histograms or box plots.
This helps in seeing how the imputation has changed the statistical properties of the data.
And by following these steps, you can handle missing data thoughtfully and maintain the integrity of your predictive model.
Now moving to the question number two that is based on evaluating model overfitting.
So the question is you have developed a predictive model, but you suspect it might be overfitting the training data.
How would you test and address the issue? Please explain your steps and the techniques you would use. So you could start the answer by explaining what is overfitting.
So overfitting is a common problem where model performs well on training data but poorly on unseen data, indicating it's too closely fitted to the training data's specific details and noise.
So now we'll see a step-by-step guide on how to address this.
The number one step is cross-validation.
So one effective way to test for overfitting is by using cross-validation technique.
Cross validation involves splitting your training data into multiple smaller sets that is faults and then training a model on some of these set and validating it on the others.
So this helps you understand if the model's good performance is consistent across different subsets of data.
For example, in Python you can use the cross underscore value underscore score function from sklearn.model underscore selection.
So this is the code and this is the code snippet of Python that you can use for the cross validation.
And here we are importing from sklearn that is the module, and we are importing cross underscore well underscore score.
And here we have used the cross val score function, and then we have printed the average cross validation score.
And the next step we will do is running cross validation model.
So this is your predictive model that we have already built using scikit learn.
And here's the X train, these are the X input features of your training data, and Y train these are the output labels of training data. So we are running cross validation model here.
This is your predictive model that you have already built using scikit-learn.
So X train here that means these are the input features of your training data. And Y train here means these are the output labels of training data and C V equal to 5.
This parameter tests the function to split the data into five parts that is false and the model is trained on four of these parts and the remaining part is used for testing.
So this process rotates until each part has been used for testing once. And the printing results that is score.mean.
So this calculates the average of the scores obtained from each cross validation fold. This average score gives you an idea of how well your model is likely to perform on unseen data.
A consistent score across different folds suggests your model is generalizing well rather than overfitting to the training data.
So now moving to the next point that is training versus validation error.
Support the training and validation errors as a function of training epochs or complexity of the model.
A model that overfits will show a low error on training data and a high error on validation data as it trains further.
Then we have pruning the model. If you confirm that the model is overfitting, consider simplifying it.
This might mean reducing the number of parameters by selecting fewer features.
Using regularization techniques like lasso or ridge or choosing a less complex model. After this step, we will move to regularization technique step.
So these techniques add a penalty to the loss function used to train the model, which can discourage complex models that overfit.
Then we have common methods that include L1, that is lasso, and L2, ridge regularization.
And here's how you can add L2 regularization in Python. So this is the code snippet here. And what we have done here is we are creating the ridge model and we have applied alpha equal to 1.0.
So this parameter controls the strength of the regularization.
A higher alpha value increases the regularization effect, which helps reduce model complexity and combat overfitting.
The alpha value can be tuned to find the optimal balance between bias and variance.
And now coming for the fitting the model.
So model.fit and in that we have X train and Y train that trains the ridge model on the training data.
It adjusts the weight of the feature in X train to predict the Y train while also considering the regularization term.
This helps prevent the model from fitting too closely to the noisy aspects of the training data.
And then we are re-evaluating the model.
After making adjustments, it's important to re-evaluate the model again using the same cross-validation technique to see if the issue of overfitting has improved.
And then we have visualization. To help illustrate overfitting, you could create a plot showing the training and validation errors or the number of epochs or model complexity.
So by using these techniques, you can identify if a model is overfitting and take steps to correct it, ensuring it performs well not only on the training data but also on new unseen
data.
So now move to the next question that is question number three, and it is based on real-time data stream processing.
And the question is you are tasked with building a model to predict stock prices in real time.
The data comes in every second, and you need to update your predictions accordingly.
Describe how you would set up your system to handle this type of data effectively and what tools and techniques would you use and why.
So you could start answering this question with handling real-time data.
So handling real-time data, especially for something as volatile and fast-paced as stock prices, requires a robust system that can process and analyze data quickly and accurately.
So here's how you could approach this. We will set up such a system and we'll have some steps.
So starting with the steps.
So the first step is choosing the right tools.
The right tool would be Apache Kafka.
So this is a popular tool for handling real-time data that streams because it allows you to publish and subscribe to streams of records that is data.
And it can handle high throughput with low latency.
Kafka acts as a buffer and manages the flow of data, ensuring that your system doesn't get overwhelmed. And you can also use Apache Spark.
Especially Spark streaming is excellent for processing the data.
It can process data in real time and perform complex operations like windowing, grouping data into chunks of a specified time period and aggregating, that is,
summarizing data.
So you can modify it and perform the predicting of stock prices.
And then the step is data processing pipeline.
And the first step comes here is ingestion.
Data first enters the system typically through Kafka, which collects data sent from the stock market.
And then we do the processing. So Spark streaming takes over here. Here you can apply transformations and run your predictive models on the data.
For example, you might calculate moving averages or other indicators that feed into your stock price prediction model. And then comes the output. Finally, the predictions are outputted.
This could be to a dashboard for traders, an automated trading system, or even stored for further analysis.
And then we develop the model. Now comes the model development. You would likely use a machine learning model that can update quickly and incorporate new data as it arrives.
Models such as ARIMA for time series forecasting or more complex machine learning models like correct and neural networks, RNNs, can be suitable.
The model should be retrained or fine tuned periodically with new data to ensure it stays accurate. Now we'll come to scalability and reliability.
So ensure your system can scale as data volume increases. This might mean adding more servers or optimizing your data processing code.
Implement monitoring to catch any issues early, like delays in data processing or model performance drops.
And now we'll see the step that is visualization and monitoring.
Consider setting up a real time dashboard that shows key metrics like prediction accuracy and processing time.
This helps in quickly spotting when something goes wrong.
By setting up your system with these tools and strategies, you can effectively handle the challenge of predicting stock prices in real time.
So now we'll move to the next question that is question number four, and this will be based on scalable data analytics.
So we have covered two questions that were a bit code-based questions, and now we'll see other questions that would be based on scalable data analytics
or they might be on different areas. And with the 13th question, we will start again with the coding ones.
So moving with the question 4 that is based on scalable data analytics.
And the question is given a scenario where your organization suddenly needs to scale its data analysis capabilities due to an influx of data
that would be 10 times the normal volume.
How would you handle this situation to ensure your data analytics processes remain efficient and accurate? What technologies would you consider and what steps would you take?
So you can start answering this question with handling a sudden increase in data volume requires a strategic approach to scaling your analytics
infrastructure without compromising on efficiency or accuracy.
So we'll see some steps from that you could effectively manage this scenario.
That you would start answering the interviewer that we can start by evaluating the current infrastructure's ability to handle increased loads.
This includes assessing your databases, servers, and analytical tools to identify potential bottlenecks or limitations.
Then you could move to the next step that would be choosing scalable technologies.
To manage the increased data volume, consider leveraging cloud-based solutions such as Amazon Web Services, Google Cloud Platform, or Microsoft Azure.
These platforms offer scalable resources which can be adjusted accordingly to the data load, ensuring you only pay for what you use.
Integrate big data technologies like Apache Hadoop for distributed storage and Apache Spark for fast data processing.
These tools are designed to handle massive volumes of data efficiently and can scale up to meet standard increase demands.
Now we move to the next step that would be optimizing data processing.
So implement data partitioning and indexing strategies to improve the efficiency of data queries.
This will help in managing large data sets by breaking them into smaller, manageable chunks and speeding up search operations.
And use real-time data processing frameworks like Apache Kafka or Apache Flink, which can handle high throughput and provide timely insights from large data streams.
And the next step would be automation and monitoring. Automate routine data processing tasks to reduce the manual effort and speed up the analysis.
This can be done through scripting or using workflow automation tools.
Set up comprehensive monitoring systems to track the performance of your data processes.
Tools like Prometheus for system monitoring and Grafana for analytics and monitoring dashboards are useful here.
They help ensure that the system is running smoothly and alert you to potential issues before they become critical.
And the next step will be regular evaluation and scaling.
Continuously evaluate the performance of analytics infrastructure. As your data grows, keep adjusting and scaling your resources to maintain optimal performance.
Plan for periodic reviews of your technology stack and infrastructure to ensure they remain aligned with your data needs and organizational goals.
By following these steps, you can ensure that your data analytics processes are prepared to handle sudden surges in data volume effectively, maintaining the integrity and speed of insights.
So, this was all for the question 4. Now moving to the question 5, and this is based on integrating machine learning models into production.
And the question is you have developed a machine learning model that performs well in testing environment.
Now you need to integrate it into your production environment where it will be used in real-time applications.
What steps would you take to ensure the successful deployment and operations of the model in production?
So we'll start answering this by successfully deploying a machine learning model into production involves several critical steps to ensure it
performs as well in real-time operations as it does in testing.
So you would have a clear pathway to make the interviewer understand.
We will start with the pathway with the first step that would be model validation.
So before moving anything into production, revalidate your model's performance using a separate validation data set.
This helps confirm that the model generalizes well to new unseen data.
The next step will be preparing the production environment. Ensure that the production environment is ready to handle the model.
This includes setting up the necessary hardware and software, ensuring that it can handle the expected load and that all dependencies are correctly installed and configured.
Then the next step comes that is model wrapping.
Wrap your model in an API, that is application programming interface, making it accessible to other parts of your software infrastructure.
Frameworks like Flask for Python can be used to create a simple web server that listens for data inputs and provides model outputs.
Then comes the next step that is deployment strategies.
Consider using containerization tools like Docker which can help encapsulate your model and its environment, ensuring that it works uniformly across different development and production settings.
And then we'll use deployment strategies like blue-green deployment or canary releases to minimize downtime and reduce the risk of introducing a faulty model into production.
And then comes the next step that is monitoring and logging.
Implement logging and monitoring to track the model's performance and health in real time.
Tools like Prometheus for monitoring and ELK.
Elasticsearch, logstatch, Kibana for logging help in quickly identifying and diagnosing issues in production.
And then comes the next step that is performance tuning.
Monitor the model's performance over time.
If the model's performance degrades or if new data shows different patterns, you may need to retrain or fine-tune the model to maintain accuracy.
And after this step, there's a step or feedback loop.
Set a feedback loop where predictions and outcomes can be compared.
This feedback is crucial for continuously improving the model and catching any drift in data or changes in external conditions that affect the model.
And after this comes a last step that is legal and compliance checks.
Ensure all the data used by the model in production complies with privacy laws and regulations.
This is crucial for maintaining trust and legality, especially when handling sensitive information.
So by carefully planning and executing these steps, you can smoothly transition your machine learning model from a testing environment to a fully functional component of a production system.
So this was all about the question number five. Now moving to the question number six, that would be based on data-driven decision making.
And the question is your company wants to shift towards more data-driven decision making.
You have been tasked with developing a strategy to implement this.
What steps would you take to ensure that the data at all levels of the organization is utilized effectively to make informed decisions?
And what challenges might you face and how would you address them?
So you can start answering this by implementing a data-driven decision-making strategy that will require a comprehensive approach to ensure that
reliable data is accessible and effectively used across all levels of the organization.
And now we can develop and deploy this strategy, and similarly, you could tell this strategy to the interviewer.
So the number one step will be assessing current data infrastructure.
Start by evaluating the existing data infrastructure to understand what data is available, how it is stored, and how it is currently used.
This assessment will help identify gaps in data collection, storage, and access that need to be addressed.
Now we'll move to the next step that is developing a data governance framework.
Implement a data governance framework that defines who can access data, how it can be used, and who is responsible for maintaining its quality.
This framework ensures data integrity and security, which are critical for making reliable decisions.
Now we'll move to the next step that is training and empowerment.
So train employees at all levels on the importance of data-driven decision making and provide them with the tools and knowledge necessary to analyze and interpret data.
This might include training sessions, workshops, and ongoing support to ensure everyone can use data effectively.
Now move to the next step that is implementing analytical tools.
So deploy user friendly analytical tools that can integrate seamlessly into the daily workflows of employees.
Tools like Tableau, Microsoft Power BI, or even advanced Excel techniques can provide powerful data analysis capabilities without requiring extensive technical knowledge.
After this, we'll move to the step that would be creating a centralized data platform.
Developer centralized data platform where all organizational data can be accessed and analyzed. This platform should be scalable and secure, providing a single source of truth for the organization.
And then we have the promoting a data-driven culture. So foster culture that values data-driven decision making.
Encourage experimentation and learning from data-driven initiatives.
Celebrate successes and learn from failures to continually improve the use of data-driven in decision making.
And there would be some challenges and solutions for that. So one major challenge we know here is resistance to change, as some employees may prefer traditional decision-making methods.
So address this by demonstrating the tangible benefits of data-driven decisions through pilot projects and success stories.
So data silos can also hinder effective data use, promote close department collaboration, and integrate disparate data sources to overcome this challenge.
After that, you can monitor and do continuous improvement.
So by systematically implementing these steps, you can transform your organization into one that leverages data at all levels to make informed and effective decisions.
And after answering in these steps, you could make the interviewer have a truth and a faith in you that you could make these models.
Now move to the next question, that is question number seven, and that is based on handling large data sets.
And the question is your project involves analyzing extremely large data sets potentially exceeding terabytes in size.
What strategies would you use to manage and analyze such large data sets effectively?
Describe the tools and techniques you might employ, and you could start this with answering that working with large data sets, especially those in terabyte range,
presents unique challenges in terms of storage, processing, and analysis.
So we'll have a structured approach to handle these challenges effectively.
We'll start with the data storage that would be used distributed file systems.
Consider using a distributed file systems like Hadoop Distributed File System, HDFS or Amazon S3.
These systems are designed to store vast amounts of data across many servers, offering high availability and poor tolerance.
And then comes the next step that is data processing.
Leverage big data processing frameworks, tools like Apache Spark are ideal for processing large data sets because they handle distributed computing effectively.
Spark can perform data processing tasks much faster than traditional disk-based processing due to its in-memory computing capabilities.
And next we could start with efficient data sampling.
So there are many sampling techniques that we can use.
So when the data set is too large to handle, even with powerful tools, consider using data sampling techniques to reduce the size to a manageable level without losing significant insights.
Ensure that the sample represents the whole data set accurately.
And then comes optimization of data queries.
Indexing and partitioning. Optimize your data queries by implementing indexing and partitioning.
This can drastically reduce the time it takes to perform queries by limiting the amounts of data scan.
And then we can do scalable analytics. And then we'll move to the next step that is scalable analytics.
And in that we could start with the parallel computing.
Use parallel computing capabilities of frameworks like Spark or Dask to analyze data across multiple nodes. This helps in scaling up your analytics operations to handle large data sets effectively.
And now we'll move to the cloud-based analytical tools.
So consider using cloud services like Google BigQuery or AWS Redshift, which are designed to handle massive datasets and complex analytics with ease.
And after this step, we'll move to data cleaning and pre-processing.
Here we will automate pre-processing tasks.
We'll use automated tools to clean and pre-process data. This includes handling missing values, normalizing data, and removing duplicates, which can be particularly challenging with large data set.
And after this step, we'll move to the step that will visualize large data set.
So we'll use specialized tools. That tools could be Tableau or Power BI that can handle large data set by aggregating data and using efficient backend technologies.
for more detailed exploration, tools like plotly or Bouquet can be used as they offer capabilities to interactively visualize large volumes of data.
And after that, there would be steps for regular maintenance and updates. That could be continuously monitoring.
The data quality. As new data comes in, you can continuously monitor its quality.
And after this step, you could integrate all these strategies and tools into your workflow, and you can effectively manage and extract valuable insights from extremely large data sets, thereby
supporting robust data-driven decision making. And you could answer the whole strategy to the interviewer.
Now move to the question number eight that is based on optimizing machine learning models.
And the question is during model development, you have noticed that your machine learning model is underperforming.
What steps would you take to diagnose the problem and optimize the model's performance? What techniques and tools would you use?
So you can answer this by starting with the optimizing, and optimizing a machine learning model that is underperforming involves several steps to diagnose and improve its accuracy and efficiency.
And here we will have structured approach to tackle this issue.
And you could start this with the number one step that is diagnosing the problem.
Evaluate model metrics.
Start by thoroughly evaluating the performance metrics of your model.
for classification task, look at accuracy, precision, recall, and the F1 score. For regression task, consider R squared, mean squared error, that is MSE, and mean absolute error, that is ME.
And then you can move to the next step. That is, use plots like ROC curves for classification models and residual plots for regression to visually assess if the model is going wrong.
After that, we'll move to the next step, that is data quality and quantity check.
Inspect the data. That is sometimes the quality and quantity of data can be the root cause of poor model performance. Ensure the data is clean, well pre-processed, and sufficient.
Look for issues like missing values, outliers, or imbalanced classes.
And after this, we'll move to the feature engineering step that would be experiment with creating new features or transforming existing ones to provide better predictive
power. And then we have the next step that is model tuning and configuration.
After feature engineering, we'll move to the next step that is model tuning and configuration.
So hyperparameter tuning.
Use techniques like grid search or random search to find the optimal settings for your model's parameters.
Tools like ScikitLearns, Grid Search CV, or randomized search CV can automate this process.
And there's a cross-validation that would implement cross-validation to ensure that the model's performance is consistent across different subsets of the data set.
And then we have the next step that is trying different models.
So experiment with algorithms here.
If initial models are underperforming, try different algorithms that might be better suited for the problem.
For instance, if you started with linear regression and it's not performing well, consider more complex models like random forest or gradient boosting machines.
And after this, we have ensemble methods that we can use, techniques like bagging, boosting, or stacking to combine the predictions of multiple models to improve overall performance.
After this step, we have feature selection that includes reduce dimensionality.
Use techniques like principal component analysis, that is PCA, to reduce the number of features, which might help in improving model performance by removing noise and redundancy.
And then we have select important features.
So use model-based technique to identify and keep only the most important features that impact the outcome. And then comes the last step that is regular updates and retraining.
So here you can monitor and update that could be continuously monitoring the model's performance over time.
As new data becomes available, update and retrain the model to adapt to any changes in underlying patterns.
And after that, you could have a consultation and collaboration work with the other teams.
And by methodically addressing each of these areas, you can diagnose why your machine learning model is underperforming and can take steps to optimize its accuracy and efficiency.
So this was all about question number eight. So let's start with the question number nine, and this is based on handling unstructured data.
So the question is you are given a large amount of unstructured data, including text, images, and videos.
What strategies would you use to manage and analyze this type of data effectively? Describe the tools and techniques you might employ.
So you can start answering this question by describing that dealing with unstructured data can be challenging due to its lack of predefined format or structure.
However, with the right strategies and tools, you can effectively manage and analyze it to extract valuable insights, and there will be a approach
how you can do that. So we will discuss the approach here and starting with the steps.
So the number one step will be data categorization and organization. So the number one step in this step will be sorting and tagging.
We will begin by categorizing the data into types that will be text, images, or videos.
Use tagging to add metadata, which helps in organizing the data and makes it easier to access and analyze later.
Then, and after that, particularly for text data, we'll use natural language processing NLP. We will employ NLP techniques to extract useful information from text.
Tools like NLTK, Spacey, or even more advanced models like BERT can help you perform tasks such as sentiment analysis, entity
recognition, and topic modeling.
After that, we will do text indexing.
We can use Elasticsearch or Apache Sole to index large volumes of text.
These tools provide powerful search capabilities and can handle complex queries efficiently.
And after that, we'll move to image data. And to structure image data, we'll use image processing.
we will use libraries like OpenCV for basic image processing tasks such as filtering and transformations.
For more advanced image analysis, consider deep learning models using frameworks like TensorFlow or PyTorch.
And then we'll feature extraction, apply techniques to extract features from images such as edges, textures, or key points, which can be used for further analysis or machine learning.
And then we'll come to video data.
And here we'll do video processing and we'll use the tools like FmPEG that can be used for basic video processing tasks such as format conversion or extracting frames.
For analyzing video content, look at machine learning models that can classify or recognize activities in the video.
And after this, we'll move to temporal analysis. For videos, temporal components are important.
Techniques like sequence modeling or recurrent neural networks
can be useful to analyze sequences of frames for activities or events.
And then we'll move to data storage and management.
Here we will use the given volume and complexity of unstructured data and use big data platforms like Hadoop or cloud services like AWS S3 for storage.
These platforms can scale up to handle large data sizes and provide the necessary infrastructure to store and retrieve unstructured data efficiently.
And then we have visualization and reporting.
Custom dashboards that we will create here.
We'll develop custom dashboards using tools like Tableau or Power BI, which can integrate different data types and provide a unified view of the analyzed data.
And after that, we will do data summarization. Tools that provide summarization capabilities can help in considering large volumes of unstructured data into more manageable and interpretable forms.
And after that, we'll leverage these strategies and tools and can effectively manage, analyze, and derive insights from unstructured data,
which can be crucial for making informed decisions in various applications. And this is the path that you can explore and explain to the interviewer if this question has been asked.
Now moving to the question number 10, and that will be based on scaling AI solutions in enterprise.
And the question is your company wants to scale its AI operations from a few initial pilot projects to enterprise-wide implementation.
What are the key considerations and steps you would take to ensure the successful scaling of AI solutions across the organization?
And what challenges might you face and how would you address them?
So you can start answering this question with the scaling AI solutions.
You could answer him that scaling AI solutions across an enterprise requires careful planning and strategic implementation to ensure success and alignment with business objectives.
And there should be a strategic approach to implement this.
So starting with the approach, and the number one step will be in that will be strategic alignment. So identify business objectives.
Start by identifying the business objectives that the AI solutions are intended to support.
This ensures that the AI initiatives are aligned with the company's strategic goals and can demonstrate clear business value.
And then comes the stakeholder engagement.
So engage stakeholders from various departments early in the process to gather input and build support. This helps in understanding diverse needs and ensures broader acceptance of the AI solutions.
And after that comes the infrastructure and technology. So there's an option that is assess and upgrade infrastructure.
Evaluate whether your current IT infrastructure can support the expanded use of AI.
You might need to upgrade hardware, invest in cloud solutions, or adopt technologies that facilitate AI processing and data handling. And after that, we have standardization of tools.
Standardize the tools and platforms used for AI development to ensure compatibility and ease of maintenance across the organizations.
And after that, we'll move to data management.
So robust data governance that is to implement a strong data governance framework to manage enterprise data effectively.
This includes policies for data quality, security, and compliance, especially important when scaling AI solutions that rely on vast amounts of data. And after that, we will come to data accessibility.
So ensure that data is accessible across the organization but also secure against unauthorized access.
This involves setting up secure data lakes or warehouses that centralize data while allowing controlled access.
And then we come to the next step that is talent and training.
So build AI competency, that is, develop in-house AI expertise through training programs and hiring.
So this builds the necessary skills within the organization to develop, manage, and scale AI solutions.
And after that, you can also perform cross-functional AI teams that could be forming cross-functional teams that include data scientists, IT professionals, and domain experts.
So this fosters collaboration and ensure that AI solutions are developed with a comprehensive understanding.
And after forming these collaborative teams, we will move to scalable deployment models.
So pilot test and phased rollout. Before a full-scale rollout, conduct pilot test to gauge the AI solution effectiveness and integration capabilities based on feedback,
adjust and then gradually deploy the solutions across the organization. And then we have modular and flexible design.
So design AI systems to be modular and scalable, allowing for adjustments and expansions as needs, and then we'll monitor and do the continuous improvement.
So there will be performance metrics that would establish metrics to regularly assess the performance of AI systems.
We will monitor these systems to ensure they met expected outcomes and adapt as necessary.
And after that, we have next step that is addressing challenges.
So there could be cultural resistance that there could be employees that would be resisting to the changes.
But we have to address this through continuous education and by showcasing successful AI use cases within the organizations.
And by carefully considering these aspects and methodically implementing steps, you can successfully scale AI solutions across your enterprise, driving significant business value and innovation.
And that's all for question number 10. Now we'll move to question number 11, and that is based on ethical considerations in data science.
So the question is in your data science projects, how do you ensure that ethical considerations are addressed?
Describe the steps you take to identify and mitigate ethical risk in your projects.
What frameworks or guidelines do you follow?
So you could start answering this question with ethical considerations that they're crucial in data science to ensure that the solutions and analysis do not
advertently cause harm or bias.
Here's how you can ensure that. So there are some steps, and we will discuss those steps, starting with the number one.
That is, educate on ethical standards. So stay informed about the ethical standards in data science, such as fairness, accountability, transparency, and privacy.
Organizations like the Data Science Association and the ACM have codes of ethics that we refer to as guidelines.
And then we have ethical risk assessment. Identify potential ethical issues that would be at the beginning of each project, conduct a thorough assessment to identify any potential ethical risk,
such as biases in data or impact on vulnerable groups.
This involves reviewing the source of data, the methodologies used for data collection, and the intended use of the data analytics results.
And then we have stakeholder analysis.
Engage with stakeholders to understand the diverse perspectives and potential impact of the project.
This helps in identifying ethical issues that may not be apparent from a purely technical standpoint.
And then we'll move to mitigation strategies.
Implementing bias mitigation techniques, we will use statistical and machine learning techniques to detect and mitigate biases in data.
This might involve techniques like resampling, reweighing, or using algorithms designed to be fair.
And then we have privacy preserving methods.
employee methods such as data anonymization, encryption, or differential privacy to protect individual privacy when analyzing sensitive data.
Then we have other methods that is transparency and explainability.
There we have model explainability and after that coming to documentation and reporting.
So we have to maintain thorough documentation of data sources, model decisions and methodologies.
And then we have continuous monitoring and feedback.
There you have to monitor outcomes and the feedback mechanism should be applied.
And then we have the panels, that is collaboration and advisory panels.
Then we have ethical review boards.
So for complex projects, setting up or consulting with an ethical review board can provide oversight and diverse perspectives on the ethical implications of project methodologies.
So by proactively addressing ethical considerations through these steps, you can ensure that your data science projects uphold high ethical standards and
positively contribute to society while minimizing harm.
So this was all about question 11. Now moving to question number 12 that is based on time series forecasting for business decisions.
So the question number 12 is you are tasked with forecasting monthly sales for a retail company using time series data from the past five years.
What steps would you take to prepare and analyze this data to make accurate forecast?
What specific tools or techniques would you use and why? So we can start answering this by time series forecasting.
And we could address them that it's a powerful tool for predicting future events based on past data, especially in business context like retail sales.
So we'll have a structured approach here and we'll start with data collection and cleaning.
First, we will gather data and ensure that you have collected all relevant data, including monthly sale figures from the past five years,
and also considering including external factors that might affect sales, such as economic indicators, holidays, and promotional activities.
And then we'll proceed to clean data. We will check for and handle any inconsistencies or missing values.
And then we have data visualization.
We'll use plotting libraries like matplotlib or Cbone in Python to visualize the data. This will help in identifying patterns, trends, and seasonality.
And then we have decomposition of data. So there's a seasonal decomposition, and we'll use statistical techniques to decompose the data into trends seasonally and residuals.
So this can be accomplished with tools like the seasonal decompose function from the stats models library in Python.
And we'll understand these components separately and can improve the accuracy of our forecast.
And then the next step is model selection and forecasting.
So there are two models that is ARIMA and SARIMA models. So we have to choose appropriate forecasting models based on data's characteristics.
For instance, ARIMA, that is autoregressive integrated moving average.
It is effective for non-season data, while SARIMA, that is seasonal ARIMA, that is suitable for data with seasonal patterns.
And after choosing the model, we will move to cross-validation. We will implement time series specific cross-validation techniques like time based splitting to evaluate model performance.
And this will ensure your model generalizes well on unseen data.
And then we have model fitting and diagnostics.
We will fit the model, that is, by using the Cinemax class from stat models that will fit your model to the data. And then we will carefully select parameters based on AIC, that is.
A cake information criterion that scores or thorough-grid research technique.
And then we can do the diagnostics and forecast and validation.
And after forecast validation, we'll move to iterative improvement.
So there's a feedback loop that should be mandatory and there should be a regular update for the model with new sales data and refining the
model as needed.
So this continuous improvement cycle helps adapt to changing patterns in sales data.
And by following these steps and using these tools, you can create a robust forecast that has the retail company plan better and make informed decisions.
So this was all about question number 12. Now moving to question number 13, that is based on customer segmentation using machine learning.
So the question is you are given a data set containing demographic and purchasing behavior data for a group of customers.
Your task is to segment these customers into distinct groups based on similarities in the purchasing behavior and demographics.
So what steps would you take to perform this segmentation and can you provide a sample Python code snippet to illustrate the initial stages of data handling and modal application?
So we can start this by explaining customer segmentation, that it's a powerful approach to tailor marketing strategies and improve customer service by
identifying distinct groups based on their behavior and characteristics. And here also we have a detailed approach for this task.
So we'll start with number one step that would be data exploration and pre-processing.
So there will be initial exploration, that is beginning by examining the data set to understand the features available such as age, income,
purchase frequency, etc. Then we'll look for missing values or anomalies and decide how to handle them.
That could be using imputation.
And then we'll move to feature engineering.
We will create new features that might be useful for segmentation, such as customer lifetime value or average transaction amount.
We'll also use normalization, that is, normalize the data to ensure that one feature doesn't disproportionately influence the model due to its scale.
We'll use standard scaling or min-max scaling as appropriate.
So then we'll come to the next step that is choosing the segmentation technique.
And here we have K-means clustering.
So this is a popular method for customer segmentation.
Here we will decide on the number of clusters by using techniques like the ALMO method or Silverte analysis to determine the optimal cluster count.
And then we have model implementation, and in that we will use data preparation and we will prepare the data by selecting the relevant features and applying any final transformations.
And then we have model fitting.
We will fit the k-means clustering model to the data and evaluate and interpret analyzing clusters.
And after analyzing clusters, we'll move to the next step that is strategic insights.
We will provide actionable insights based on cluster characteristics such as targeted marketing strategies for each segment.
And then we have iterative refinement that is feedback incorporation, and we'll use business feedback to refine the segmentation.
If additional data becomes available, incorporate it to enhance the model.
And now we'll see the sample Python code.
So for this, first we'll import the libraries and modules. As you can see on the screen, we have imported pandas, random forest classifier, train test split, standard scalar, classification report.
And after that, we will load the data.
And for that, we have used the pandas to read the data, that is read underscore SSV.
And after that, we are processing the data that is data preprocessing, we are handling missing values and using the forward fill or FIL to fill missing values in the dataset.
And then we are featuring scaling, that is normalizing the selected features that is feature one, feature two, and feature three using standard scalar.
And then we'll move to the next step that is data splitting. We'll split the data set into training and testing sets.
So that test size equal to 0.2 parameters specifies that 20% of the data will be used for testing.
And then we'll train the model, we'll initialize and train a random forest classifier with 100 trees and a random state for reproductibility.
And then we'll evaluate the model, we'll make predictions on the test set that is X underscore test using the train model and print a classification report showing precision,
recall, F1 score, and support for each class.
So this code demonstrates the process of loading, pre-processing, training, and evaluating a machine learning model that is random forest classifier
for predicting equipment failures in a manufacturing plant.
The use of techniques such as data pre-processing and splitting along with the random forest classifier highlights a standard flow for building predictive maintenance models.
So this was all about the question number 13. So now moving to the question number 14 that is based on predictive customer churn.
And the question is you are tasked with developing a model to predict which customers are likely to churn from a subscription service.
So what steps will you take to build this model and can you provide a sample Python code to illustrate the data preparation and model training process?
So we'll start answering this question about depicting what is predicting customer churn.
So predicting customer churn is crucial for businesses to implement detention strategies proactively.
And we'll have a detailed approach for building a predictive model for this purpose, starting with data collection and exploration.
And in this we will collect data, and after that, we'll perform the exploratory data analysis that is EDM. We'll perform an initial analysis to understand patterns and trends.
And then we have feature engineering, we'll create new features and derive new features that might influence churn, such as change in usage pattern or service upgrades.
And then we'll handle the missing values if we found any. And then we'll encode categorial variables. We'll use techniques like one hot encoding or label encoding for categorial variables.
And then we have scale features to normalize or standardize numerical features to ensure they contribute equally to the model's performance.
And then we'll select the model, that is, we'll choose the appropriate model and start with for the knowing handling binary classification task.
That could be with logistic regression, random forest, or gradient boosting machines.
And after selecting the model, we'll train the model and evaluate it.
So fit your model on the training data, and after that, evaluate the model using appropriate metrics like accuracy, precision, recall, advanced score,
and ROC to gauge its performance.
And then we'll optimize the model using hyperparameter tuning.
We'll optimize the model parameter using grid search or random search to improve performance.
And then we have feature importance that is analyze and rank features by the importance in predicting churn to refine the model further.
And then and the last step is deployment and monitoring.
We'll deploy the model.
Once validated, deploy the model into a production environment where it can predict real-time churn.
So after deploying the model, regularly monitor the model to ensure it remains effective over time as new data comes in.
So now we'll see the sample Python code for this example.
So starting with the importing of libraries, we will import pandas, numpy, scikit learn, sklearn, tensorflow, and the tensorflow
keras and callbacks.
And after importing the modules, we will start with data loading. we will load the dataset from a CSV file named equipment underscore data dot CSV and that too with the pandas data frame.
And after that, we will do the data preprocessing, we'll handle missing values, and for that we'll use forward fill to fill missing values in the dataset.
And then we have feature scaling that will normalize the selected features that is feature one, feature two, feature three, using standard scalar.
And after that, we'll use the data splitting.
We'll split the dataset into training and testing sets.
And the test size will be equal to 0.2.
And this parameter specifies that 20% of the data will be used for testing.
And after that, we'll start with building the model.
First, we'll see sequential model that initializes a sequential model technique.
And then we have dense layers that adds two dense layers with 64 units and RELU activation function.
Then we have dropout layers that adds two dropout layers with a dropout rate of 0.5 to reduce overfitting.
After that, we'll do the model compilation, we'll compile the model using the Adam optimizer and binary cross entropy loss function for binary classification.
And there will be an early stopping that will define an early stopping callback to stop training when the validation loss metric has stopped improving after three epochs.
And after training the model, we will evaluate the model and evaluating the model on the test data and print the loss and accuracy metrics.
So this code demonstrates the process of loading, pre-processing, building, compiling, training, and evaluating a deep learning model using TensorFlow and Keras
for predicting equipment failures in a manufacturing plant.
So the use of techniques such as data pre-processing, dropout, regularization, and early stopping helps in building a robust deep learning model for predictive
maintenance.
So that's all with question number 14. Now we'll start with question number 15 that is based on deep learning in NLP.
And your question is you are tasked with developing a sentiment analysis model using deep learning to understand customer opinions from reviews. So what steps would you take to build this model?
And can you provide a sample Python code snippet to illustrate how you would pre-process data and train a simple deep learning model?
So we'll start answering this with sentiment analysis.
That sentiment analysis using deep learning allows businesses to coach customer sentiment from text data like reviews or comments effectively.
And we'll have a detailed approach for building a sentiment analysis model. We'll start with data collection and cleaning.
We'll collect the data, gather a substantial data set of text reviews and their associated sentiments, typically labeled as positive, negative, or neural.
And then we'll clean the data, pre-process the data by removing noise such as HTML tags, special characters, and so words.
And we'll normalize the text by converting into lowercase.
And then we have text preprocessing.
We'll convert text into tokens, words or phrases.
And then we have vectorization that transforms tokens into numerical format using techniques like word embeddings or TFIDF that is term frequency
inverse document frequency.
And then we'll use the padding. And then we have the option of model selection.
We'll choose a model architecture based on a basic approach and user RNN or more advanced architecture like LSTM, that is long
short-term memory, or GRU, that is gated recurrent units, which are effective for sequence data like text.
And then we have model training.
We'll compile the model, define the model architecture, and compile it with the loss function suited for classification like categorical, cross and dropping,
and an optimizer like Adam.
And then we'll train the model, will fit the model on our pre-processed data. will evaluate and optimize it.
Evaluating model performance here use the metrics such as accuracy, precision, recall, and F1 score to assess the model.
And then we have hyperparameter tuning. We'll optimize the model by adjusting parameters like learning rate, number of layers, and units per layer. And then coming to deployment.
We'll deploy the model and integrate the model into the existing review processing pipeline so it can automatically classify new reviews.
So let's see the sample Python code and we'll have a basic approach for that.
Here we'll import numpy tensor flow sequential embedding LSTM dense dropout.
So embedding converts positive integers that is indexes into dense factors of fixed size.
and LSTM that is long short-term memory layer that is used for learning dependencies in sequence data.
And then we have dense, that is a regularly dense connected NN layer.
And then we will import pad underscore sequences.
And after that, we have the dataset and the sample text data representing customer reviews that will store in variable text.
And then we have labels that has binary labels indicating sentiment one for positive, zero for negative.
And now we'll start with the pre processing of data. Here we have declared that tokenizer.
We will initialize a tokenizer that will help only the top thousand most frequent words.
And then we have fit underscore on underscore text that is update the internal vocabulary based on the list of text.
It essentially creates a dictionary of word to index pairs. And then we have text to sequences that will transform each text in text to a sequence of integers.
And then we have pad sequences that will ensure all sequences have the same length by padding shorter sequences with zeros up to the maximum length.
And then we'll start building the model.
Here we have sequential model that will set up a linear stack of layers, and then we have embedding layer that will map each word index to an embedding vector of size 64.
So the input length is set to 10, that is the length of the input sequences.
Then we'll start with LSTM layers.
So two LSTM layers are added. The first one returns sequences to allow the next LSTM layer to process these sequences.
And after that, we have the dropout layer that applies dropout with a rate of 0.5 or the first LSTM layer to reduce overfitting.
And after that, we'll come to dense layer that has output of a single scalar that represents the predicted settlement and using sigmoid activation to output a probability.
And now we'll start with model compilation and training.
So we'll configure the model for training and we'll use binary cross entropy as the loss function that is suitable for binary classification and the atom
optimizer and tracks constantly accuracy as a metric.
And then we have the fit that trains the model for a specified number of epochs, that is, iterations or the entire data set. And then we'll predict the model.
That is after training, the model can predict the sentiment of the reviews in the dataset.
This is useful for checking how the model performs on the training data itself.
So this breakdown explains each step of the coding process, detailing how the data is prepared and how the model is configured.
And then we'll compile it and use for training and prediction. So its detailed explanation should help in understanding how to implement a simple LSTA model for sentiment analysis in TensorFlow.
Now moving to the question number 16.
So let's start with question number 16 that is based on anomaly detection in transaction data.
So the question is you are tasked with identifying unusual transactions in a company's financial data that might suggest fraudulent activity.
So what steps would you take to develop an anomaly detection model and can you provide a sample Python code snippet to illustrate how you would pre-process the
data and apply an anomaly detection technique?
So we'll start answering this with anomaly detection technique.
That is, anomaly detection is essential for preventing fraud by identifying transactions that deviate significantly from typical patterns.
And now we'll see the structured approach to building an anomaly detection model for transaction data.
We'll start with data collection and cleaning and we'll collect all the compiling transaction data, which should include details like transaction amount, time, user ID, and transaction type.
Then we'll move to feature engineering and develop features that capture the essence of transaction such as time of day and the day of the week.
And then we have data normalization.
We'll use scaling techniques such as min max scaling or standardization to ensure that the model is perfectly normalized.
And then we have choosing the anomaly detection technique.
So here we have to choose the technique which is effective for high dimensional data sets and works for isolating anomalies instead of profiling normal data points.
After choosing the anomaly technique, we'll train anomaly identification.
We'll fit the chosen model to the data, and the anomalies that would have been chosen will be those transactions that the model identifies.
And after this, we come to the last step that is review in action.
Here we have manual review, that is, transactions flagged as potential anomalies should be reviewed manually to confirm fraudulent activity.
And then we have continuous improvement.
That is, we can regularly update the model with the new data and feedback from the review process to improve accuracy.
And now moving to the prediction, that is, after training the model, we can predict the sentiment of the reviews in the dataset.
And this is useful for checking how the model performs on the training data itself.
Now we'll see the Python code to see how you can set up this model for anomaly detection.
We'll start by importing the libraries and module, and after that, we'll load and prepare data.
That is, we'll load transaction data from a CSV file into the Pandas data frame.
And after that, we'll convert the transaction time column to date time format, which allows the extraction of additional time-based features.
And after that, we'll perform feature engineering that will extract the hour of the day from the transaction time column.
This feature can be important as transactions occurring at unusual hours may be indicative of fraud.
And then we'll move to the normalization of data.
This will apply standard scaling to the amount and hour of the day feature.
This normalization process involves subtracting the mean and dividing by the standard deviation for each feature,
ensuring that the feature contributes equally to the analysis and improving the performance of many machine learning algorithms.
And after that, we'll start with anomaly detection with isolation forest.
That's a technique.
We will initialize an isolation forest model with 100 trees, that is, n estimators equal to 100, setting the proportions of outliers, that is,
contamination, to 1% of the data.
So this parameter is crucial as it influences the threshold of marking and observation as an anomaly.
Then we'll fit the model to the scaled amount and R of the data and predict the anomaly status for each transaction. And then we'll start with filter and display anomalies.
We'll filter out transactions identified as anomalies, that is, anomaly equal equal to minus one.
We'll display these transactions which can be reviewed manually to determine if they represent actual fraudulent activity.
So this code snippet provides a systematic approach to detecting anomalies in transaction data, leveraging the isolation forest
algorithm's ability to handle complex and high-dimensional data set effectively.
So the pre-processing steps ensured that the data is appropriately formatted and normalized for optional model performance.
So this was all about question number 16. Now moving to question number 17, and that is based on integrating machine learning models into web applications.
And your question is you have developed a machine learning model to predict real estate prices based on various features like location, size, and amenities.
How would you integrate this model into a web application to allow users to get real-time price predictions?
Can you provide a sample Python code snippet to illustrate how you would prepare the model for integration and handle user requests?
So, starting with the approach, that is integrating a machine learning model into a web application.
This will involve several steps to ensure the model is accessible and perform well in a live environment.
So here's how you can approach this task.
We could divide into steps and we'll start with number one step that is model preparation.
We'll finalize and save the model.
So once your model is trained and validated, save it using a format that can be easily loaded into a web application.
So Python's Pickle module or TensorFlow's same model format are commonly used for this purpose.
Then we can use web application backend setup.
For this, select a suitable web framework.
So Flask is popularly known for its simplicity and effectiveness in integrating Python-based machine learning models.
And after that, we'll develop the API.
After developing the API within your Flask app, that you can receive user inputs for model features, load the model, make prediction, and return the result.
And after this, we'll develop the UI.
We'll design a user-friendly interface, we'll create a simple and intuitive UI that lets users input the feature like location, size, and submit them for prediction.
And after that, we'll move to the deployment phase.
We'll use a cloud platform like Heroku, AWS, or Google Cloud to deploy your Flask application.
And then we have the maintenance and updates. We'll monitor and update regularly for the performance and use the model as needed based on user feedback.
So now move to the Python code and see how this model can be created.
So here we'll start importing the libraries and module, and we are using Flask, Prequel, and JSONify.
And we will start with app initialization.
We'll initialize a new Flask web application that would be a special variable which gives Python files a unique name to differentiate between them when they are imported into other scripts.
And after that, we'll load the model. So loading a pretend machine learning model from the file system. So this model is assumed to be saved in the same directory as this script.
So the model is loaded in RB mode, which stands for read binary.
And after that, we'll move to API route and prediction function.
So we will define an API endpoint at predict that listens for post request.
This is the URL that the front end of the web application will call to send data to the backend.
after that, we'll start with predicting the function.
And here we have extract features that retrieves data sent into the JSON format from the POST request.
That is request.get underscore JSON and the force we have set it as true here and forcefully formats the request data into JSON
ensuring compatibility.
And then we'll extract the relevant features that is location, size, and amenities from the JSON object and store them in a list as expected by the model.
And after preparing the features, we'll make the prediction, will use the loaded model to make a prediction based on the provided feature. And then we have the return prediction method.
and we will convert the prediction result into JSON format using JSON Ify and send it back to the client, and this will ensure that the response can be easily handled by the client application.
So this was all about the question number 17.
Now move to the question number 18, that is based on analyzing. And now we'll move to the question number 18 that is based on analyzing geospathical data.
And your question is you are tasked with analyzing geospatel data to help a city improve its public transportation system.
The data includes GPS coordinates of bus stops, ridership numbers, and traffic patterns. What steps would you take to analyze this data?
And can you provide a sample Python code snippet to illustrate how you might visualize bus stop location and ridership?
So you can start answering this question that JUISPAL data analysis can provide critical insights into how effectively a public transportation system
serves its city and guide improvements.
And there's a detailed approach for this, and we can start with data preparation, and in this, we'll do data collection and data cleaning.
And after this step, we'll move to the next step that is exploratory data analysis.
And in this, we'll have statistical summary, we'll generate descriptive statistics, and then we have correlation analysis.
And after moving that, we have geospatial visualization that is mapping bus stop.
We'll plot the locations of bus stop on a map to visually assess their distribution across the city.
And after that, we have heat maps that will create ridership data to identify hot sports and areas with potential service gaps.
And after geospatial visualization, we'll move with spatial analysis.
We have proximity analysis that will analyze the proximity of bus stop to key areas like commercial centers or residential areas.
And now moving to the fifth step that is optimization and recommendation.
So we'll have a route optimization that will suggest modifications to route based on traffic patterns and ridership demand
and the policy recommendations that will provide actionable recommendations for improving bus frequencies. Now move to the sample Python code where we can define this model and use it accordingly.
And here we will start importing the libraries and modules, and here we will start with importing geo pandas and matprolib.pyplot.
And after importing, we'll start with data loading.
So we will declare a variable bus underscore stops and load the bus stops data from a shapefile. So shapefiles are popular geospatial vector data formats for geographic information system software.
And then we have the ridership that will load ridership data from a CSV file, which includes columns for longitude, latitude, and ridership levels.
And after that, will create geodata frame that will convert the ridership data frame into a geodata frame.
And this step involves creating a geometry column from the longitude and latitude columns.
And then we have the plotting one.
Here we will plot the graphs that would be figures and axis and create a figure for the single subplot with a specified size that is 10 x
10 inches.
And then we have city underscore map dot plot.
It is assumed that there is a base map of the city loaded as a geodata frame named City Map.
This is plotted first with the light gray color to serve as a background for the other layers.
So this was all about question number 18. Now moving to question number 19 that is based on predictive maintenance using machine learning.
And the question is you are tasked with developing a predictive maintenance system for a manufacturing plant that relies heavily on automated machinery.
So the data available includes machine operational parameters, maintenance history, and failure incidents.
What steps would you take to develop a predictive model and can you provide a sample Python code?
So you can start with predictive maintenance that is essential in manufacturing as it helps prevent equipment failures, reducing downtime and maintenance cost.
And here you have a detailed approach or predictive model for this, starting with data collection and integration.
Then you can do EDA, that is exploratory data analysis, and then we can perform feature engineering and then move to data pre-processing task
and then the selection model and training.
And after that, we have model evaluation and deployment technique that we can do for the model using appropriate metrics such as precision, recall, and F1 score.
So this was all about question number 19. So now move to question number 20 that is based on personalization using machine learning.
And your question is you are tasked with developing a machine learning model to personalize content recommendations for users on a media streaming platform.
The data available includes user demographic details, viewing history, and ratings.
So what steps would you take to build a model for personalized recommendations? And can you provide a sample Python code for that?
So you can start answering this with creating a personalized recommendation systems.
This would be essential for engaging users by providing content that is relevant to their interest.
And there will be a systematic approach or personalized content recommendation.
We'll start with data collection and integration, and after that, we'll perform EDA that is exploratory data analysis, and then we have feature engineering.
In this, we'll interact features and the temporal features.
We'll include time-based features to capture trends and seasonality in viewing behavior.
And then we'll select the model that is by collaborative filtering and hybrid models.
And then we'll train the model and validation and implement and monitor them.
Welcome to math refresher linear algebra.
In this lesson, we are going to explain the concepts of linear algebra, solve a linear system of equations, describe matrix,
forms of matrix and matrix operations, and define vectors and list down its properties.
Introduction to linear algebra.
Linear algebra.
Linear algebra refers to study of linear combinations.
For linear transformations to be carried out, a study of vector spaces, lines, and planes, as well as some mappings is necessary.
It contains linear functions, vectors, and matrices.
It is an examination of characteristic of linear set transformations, linear equations.
Linear algebra's major goal is to establish systematic techniques for solving systems of linear equations.
A linear equation with $n$ variables can be represented as
$a_1x_1$ plus $a_2x_2 $, plus $a_3x_3$ and so on.
till $a _n x_n$ equals to $b $, where $x_1, x_2, x_3 ,$ and so on. till $x_n$ are the unknown quantities that are to be found.
While a1, a2, a3, and so on, until a in, are the coefficients.
b here is a constant term.
A linear equation with two variables, x and y is a linear connection between x and y.
The value of one variable often y is determined by the value of the other.
That is x.
The independent variable in this situation is x while the term dependent variable refers to y.
Since it depends on x, let's consider some examples for linear equations.
Linear equations in one variable can be written as 3x plus 5 equals 0, or 3 by 2 of x plus 7 equals to 0,
or 98x equals to 49.
Linear equations in two variables.
Examples can include y plus 7x equals to 3, or 3a plus 2b equals to 5,
6x plus 9, y minus 12 equals to 0.
Linear equations can also be written with 3 variables as x plus y plus z equals to 0.
a minus 3b equals to c.
3x plus 12y equals to half of z,
identifying linear and nonlinear equations.
Linear equations present themselves as a straight line on a graph.
However, nonlinear equations represent themselves as a non-straight line on the graph.
Here, equations like y equals to 8x minus 9
or y plus 3x minus 1 equals to 0 are examples of linear equations.
However, y equals to x square minus 7 is a nonlinear equation, because x is raised to the power 2.
Hence, denoting a nonlinear relationship or a non-straight line relationship between x and y.
Similarly, square root of y plus x equals to 6 or y raised to the power 2 minus x equals to 9
are examples of nonlinear equations as y is raised to the power half and 2 respectively.
Forms of linear equation.
Linear equations can be represented in three forms, a standard form, a slope intercept form, or a point slope form.
Linear equation in standard form.
A linear equation in standard form for a single variable can be represented as a x plus b equals to zero, where a and b are real integers
and x is the variable.
While a linear equation in standard form for two variable can be represented as ax plus by equals two c where ab
and c are real integers, while x and y are the variables.
To summarize a linear equation for variables can be written as
ax plus by equals to c where x and y are the variables.
C is the constant and a and b are the coefficients of x and y respectively.
Linear equation in the slope intercept form.
A linear equation slope can be calculated to see how one variable varies in response to a unit change.
In another variable, it is represented as y equals to mx plus b,
where m is the slope, b is the intercept on the y axis and x, and y are the line's distance from the x and the y axis respectively.
Consider this example.
The lines point x, y represents the distance from the x and the y-axis respectively.
While the line intercept on the y-axis is at point zero, comma b.
Linear equation slope.
The slope indicates how steep a line is with respect to y-axis.
When seen from left to right, it indicates whether the line goes up or down.
The slope describes how independent variable has been changed, while the dependent variable is changing.
Types of slope.
There are four types of slopes based on the relationship between the two variables x and y.
The first is the positive slope here as x increases.
Y is also increasing in a negative slope as x increases.
Y decreases.
If a line is parallel to x-axis, it is a zero slope.
On the other hand, if the line is parallel to y axis, then the slope is undefined.
Linear equation in point slope form.
A straight line is represented in point slope form by its slope, and a point on the line.
It is represented as y minus y1 equals to m of x minus x1,
where x1 and y1 are the coordinates of the point.
Linear equation forms some examples.
Consider solving the linear equation given as 2x minus 10 divided by 2 equals to 3x minus 1.
First we will clear the fraction.
In this example, we can see only left hand side we have 2x minus 10 divided by 2.
If from the numerator we take 2 as common,
we will be left with 2 times x minus 5 divided by 2, hence x minus 5 on the left hand side.
On the right hand side, we still have 3 times x minus 1.
Now, as a part of next step, we simplify both sides of the equation that is open up the brackets.
When we do that on the right side, we end up getting 3x minus 3 by multiplying 3 to x minus 1.
Solving further, we can write as x equals to 3x plus 2.
Finally, we try to clear the fraction to solve for x.
We can rearrange the equation as x minus 3x equals to 2.
Solving it further, we get minus 2x equals to 2.
And then we solve for x as minus 1.
System of linear equation.
A system of linear equations is a finite collection of linear equations, usually involving the same variables.
It can be represented as a11x1 plus a12x2, and so on equals to b1 A21X1 plus A22X2,
so on equals to B2 and so on.
Here this example is for n variables.
A system of m equations.
A linear system can have unlimited number of solutions, one solution or no solution at all.
In case of a single linear equation, a consistent linear system has a solution while an inconsistent linear system has no solution.
Solving a linear equation.
Solving linear system of equations.
Various methods can be used to solve linear system of equations, which include graphic method, substitution method,
linear combination or elimination method, or a matrix method.
Graphing method.
Let's try and solve these two linear equations using the graphic method.
The first equation is defined as y equals 0.5x plus 2.
And the second equation is y equals to minus 2x minus 3.
The two equations as we can see are in the slope intercept form.
The first line has a slope of 0.5 and a y-intercept of positive 2, while the second line has a slope of negative 2 and a y
intercept of negative 3.
Let's have a look at these lines through a plot.
Here, the blue line is the first line represented by y equals 2.5x plus 2.
And the red line is represented by y equals to negative 2 of x negative 3.
These two lines intersect at a point at negative 2 comma 1.
Hence we can say that x equals to negative 2 and y equals to 1.
Solving systems of linear equation using substitution.
For substitution we start by putting one of the equations in the form of variable equals to.
We then substitute that variable in the other equation in its place.
Take the other equation to solve.
If there are more than two variables involved, we repeat the process from steps 1 through 3.
Let's consider an example.
Let's consider the equation 3x plus 2y equals to 19 and x plus y equals to 8.
We could begin with any equation and variable.
In this case, let's look at the second equation with variable y.
We start with subtracting x from both sides of x plus y equals to 8.
And we end up getting y equals to 8 minus x.
The first equation still retains its form.
Now we take the value of y that is 8 minus x and substitute in the first equation in place of y.
We end up getting the equation 3x plus 2 times 8 minus x equals to 19.
We further simplify and solve this equation using algebra method to get 3x plus 16 minus 2x equals 290.
We solve this equation further, and we end up getting x plus 16 equals to 19, and finally x equals to 3.
Now we take the value of x and substitute in the new reformed second equation as y equals to 8 minus x.
That gives us y equals to 8 minus 3, hence y equals to 5.
The final answer remains x equals to 3 and y equals to 5.
Solving systems of linear equation using elimination.
In this case, we start by multiplying an equation by a constant anything other than 0.
We then add or subtract an equation onto the other equation.
Let's consider the same example of 3x plus 2 y equals 219 and x plus y equals 8.
We first start by multiplying the second equation by 2,
and we get 2x plus 2, y equals 216.
Now we subtract the second equation from the first equation.
That is 3x minus 2x,
2y minus 2y, and 19 minus 60.
On solving this, we end up getting x equals to 3.
Now using these steps of substitution, we put the value of x in the original second equation, that is x plus y equals to 8,
and achieve a value of y equals to 5.
Hence the answer remains x equals to 3 and y equals to 5.
We can verify the solution by using the graph.
Here again, the blue line represents the point at which 3x plus 2y equals to 19 is true,
while the red line represents the point where x plus y equals to eight is true.
The solution is found at the point where x equals to three
and y equals to five.
This is the point where both lines intersect.
Introduction to matrices.
Matrix.
A matrix is rectangular array or table with rows and columns of numbers, symbols, expressions
used to represent a mathematical object or an attribute.
For example, here A is a matrix of two rows and three columns
as two one three minus one, two, and four.
Well, B is a squared matrix with two rows and two columns given as two, one, three, four.
Matrix size.
The matrix size is expressed as M cross n, where m is the number of rows, and n is the number of columns.
A matrix with two rows and three columns can be referred to as two by three matrix or a two cross three matrix,
or a matrix of dimension two cross three.
Notation of a matrix.
A matrix with m rows and n columns can be presented as this.
Here each element will be identified by its row number and column number.
For example, the element over here is in the third row and the first column.
Hence it is identified as a 3 1.
Forms of matrix.
The matrix is termed as a squared matrix.
If n equals to m, that is the number of rows and number of columns are equal.
An element's entry in the matrix of from AI i is located on the diagonal.
Hey is called a diagonal matrix.
If he ij equals to zero,
when i is not equals to j,
that is in a square matrix.
Apart from diagonal at all places, we have zero as a value.
Matrix operations.
Addition.
Addition of two matrices is adding their corresponding elements, as in A11 plus B11, A12 plus B12,
A21 plus B21,
A22 plus B22, and so on.
Consider the example over here.
We have a matrix A as 22, 32, 11, 16, and matrix B as 13, 8, 13, and 16.
Matrix A is of the order 2 x 2, and matrix B is also of the same order, 2 x 2.
Hence the corresponding elements can be quickly added as 22 plus 13,
32 plus 8,
11 plus 13, and 16 plus 16, giving us the result in matrix of 35, 40, 24, and 32.
Addition rules.
Only matrices with the same size can be added.
That is the two matrices should have same number of rows and same number of columns.
Matrix addition follows commutative property.
That means A plus B is equals to B plus A.
Subtraction.
Matrix subtraction is same as matrix addition.
It is subtracting the corresponding values.
Let's consider the same example of matrix A and B.
The result of A minus B can be given as 22 minus 13.
That is A11 minus B11.
32 minus 8.
That is A12-B12, 11-13, A21-B21, and 16 minus 16
that is A22 minus B22,
giving us result as 9, 24, negative 2, and 0.
Subtraction rules.
Only matrices with the same number of rows and columns can be subtracted.
Matrix subtraction does not follow commutative property.
That means A minus B is not equals to B minus A.
Multiplication.
Matrix multiplication results in what is called as a product matrix.
In matrix multiplication, each row of the first matrix is multiplied to each column of the second matrix.
To compute each of these elements in the matrix, the values are then added.
For example, consider the matrix A and B.
To get the first element, we will multiply the first row of matrix A to the first column of matrix B,
and then add the individual elements, that is 22, multiplied to 13, and 32 multiplied to 13,
and then add them up to get this particular element.
For the second element, we multiply the first row of A to the second column of B,
hence getting 22 multiplied to 8 plus 32 multiplied to 16.
Similarly, we compute all the remaining elements, that is the second row multiplied to the first column,
and added 11 multiplied to 13 plus 16 multiplied to 13.
And the second row now multiplied to the second column, that is 11 multiplied to 8 plus 16 multiplied to 16.
This gives us the resulting matrix as 702, 688, 351, and 344 for multiplication rules.
Let us say C equals to AB.
Here, C is our product matrix,
which can be computed as summation over A at IJ dot Bjk
for a matrix of size ij, matrix B of size JK,
to calculate the value of each member
in the i cross k matrix of C.
The matrix product AB is defined only when the number of columns in A equals to the number of rows in B.
The matrix product of BA is defined only when the number of columns in B is equals to the number of rows in a
B is not always equals to B.A.
Transpose.
A transpose is a matrix form by turning all the rows of a given matrix into the columns and vice versa.
The transpose of a matrix A is denoted as AT.
For example, if the matrix A is 22, 32, 11, and 16, the transpose of A would be 22,
11, 32, and 16.
Here we can see the row has been converted to column.
Inverse, if it is a non-singular square matrix,
there exists $n cross n matrix, a minus one known as $A$'s inverse,
that satisfies $A dot. A inverse
equals to A inverse.a equals to $I
$, where $I$ is the identity matrix.
And identity matrix is characterized as a diagonal's one and all other elements are zero.
Also A B equals to B dot A
equals to In
where I N denotes the N cross N identity matrix
special matrix types.
Symmetric matrix A matrix A is set to be symmetric.
If A is equals to transpose of A, diagonal matrix, A matrix D is diagonal only if Dij
equals to zero.
For all i not equals to j,
identity matrix.
Identity matrix is denoted as ion, where a ion equals to ion dot a equals to a
tensors.
Tensors are arrays with more than two axes.
A tensor can have in dimensions.
A ijk is the value in the tensor A at coordinates ij and k.
The principal component analysis PCA,
which is a statistical technique used to reduce the number of dimensions in a given data set while we preserve its variability.
So there are different use cases of PCA in real-time scenarios.
One of the major use cases is in the healthcare domain, so technically known as the spike-triggered covariance analysis.
It uses the principle of PCA in neuroscience to identify the specific properties of a stimulus that increase a neuron's probability of generating an action potential.
So it is using reduction techniques, which is going to be really helpful in detecting the coordinated activities of large neuronal ensembles.
So it is basically used for identifying a neuron from the shape of its action potential.
Then in terms of quantitative finance.
So PCEA help us in reducing the dimensionality of a complex problem.
Let's say a fund manager has 200 stocks in his portfolio.
Now to analyze these stocks quantitatively, a stock manager will require a correlational metric of a size 200 by 200,
which makes the problem very complex.
However, if he has to extract 10 principal components, which best represents the variance in the stock price.
This will reduce the complexity of the problem while still explaining the movement of all 200 stocks.
So we use it for analyzing the shape of the yield curve in terms of forecasting the portfolio returns, developing the asset allocation algorithms,
and so on, and it is also widely used in image compression.
So PCA is also used for image compression.
So if we go ahead and use any of the PyCharm IDE, so here we can work with matplotlib, imagepyplot, and the numpy as np.
And here we can also import from sklearn.
And we can import the PCA.
So basically we are trying to print the shape of the image by reading the image.
This is a sample logo.png, which has been placed in the same directory.
We are trying to print the image.
So if we run this particular code,
then we will be able to see the shape of the image.
Return to us first the current shape based on the image which has been deducted, which is 156, 94, and 3.
So what does this mean?
This means image is in the form of 156 rows, and each row containing 194 pixels, and then having three channels, which is red,
green, and blue.
So we had to resize the image so that it is in a format required for PCA input, which is 196 by 3,
which is going to be 582.
So here we can see we have performed a simple operation as image R, where we are using the NumPy library for reshaping the image.
And then we are printing the shape of the image again.
So here we can see 156 and 582 has been returned as a response.
Now running the PCA with 32 principal components, we can use this fit for the image that has been reshaped, and then we are trying to train the transform image.
So with these 32 components, we are able to express 98.7% of the variance.
So inverse transforming the PC output and reshaping the visualization can also be done forward.
And that's how PCA is widely used as a part of the medical and the other sciences.
For example, is used for object detection model for the healthcare domain for the transportation, aviation, and location-based services.
Introduction to vectors.
Objects with both magnitude and direction are called as vectors.
The magnitude of the vector determines its size.
It is represented as a line with an arrow, where the length of the line indicates the vector's magnitude and the arrow points in the desired direction.
Other names for it include Euclidean vector, geometric vector, spatial vector, or simply vector.
Its length is indicated by the symbol double bar V double bar
and it begins at the original zero, comma zero.
Notation of a vector.
A vector can be represented in a standard form as a equals to a i cap plus bj cap plus c
k cap, where a, b, and c are numeric values.
The unit vectors along the xyz axis are i, j, and k cap respectively.
Do you know how AI has become so fast? It's now replacing entire teams in some industries? Yes, it's true. Over 50% of companies are already using AI to automate jobs.
AI tools are writing emails, creating content, and even giving job interviews. And while some people are worried AI will take the job, I'll let you in on a secret.
AI is also creating tons of high-paying roles. The catch, you need the right skills to get in.
And that starts with learning with the right programming language.
Now, I've tested a whole bunch of them: Python, C, R, Java, you name it.
And in this video, I'm breaking down the top 5 programming languages for AI that you need to know if you want to build a career,
learn real jobs, and actually stay relevant in the age of AI.
We will cover what each language is best at, how to start learning, what kinds of AI jobs they lead to, and yes, how much you can earn with each one. Alright, first up, we've got Python.
And honestly, this one is the most valuable player of the AI development. Just like the star player in a sports team.
Python is the go-to language that everyone relies on when it comes to building AI system. So why is Python the AI king? Let me break it down.
Simplicity and readability.
Now Python is super easy to learn. It's almost like writing in plain English. You don't have to worry about complicated code.
If you're just starting out in programming, that is definitely the language you are going to feel most comfortable with.
It's got this user-friendly vibe that makes it simple even for people new to coding. Second of all, it has got endless libraries. Now Python is packed with tools.
We call it libraries like TensorFlow, PyTorch, and ScikitLearn. Think of these libraries as pre-made toolkits that make AI development way easier.
They save you a lot of time because instead of building everything from scratch, you can use these libraries to quickly train your models and run algorithms.
It's like having a shortcut to building AI system. It has also got rapid prototyping. If you need to test your ideas quickly, Python is perfect for that.
You can build a model, a simple version of your AI system in no time.
So whether you're working on machine learning models or neural networks, fancy word for AI system that learn like the brain, Python let
you prototype or build a quick model fast.
So I know you must be wondering now what kind of AI jobs can Python land me? It's a great question.
With Python, you could land jobs like data scientist, machine learning engineer, or an AI researcher. Now these jobs typically pay between around 6 lakh to 15 lakh per annum. That's the salary range.
But the best part is, as you gain more experience and expertise, that number will go way higher.
So, how do you start learning Python? You don't have to break the bank to learn Python. You can get started with free platforms and YouTube channels.
Simply Learn even offers a free comprehensive course in Python, and I'll leave the link for you to check it out.
And the best part is Python has got huge community. So if you ever feel stuck, there's always someone out there who's ready to help you. Next, we'll talk about C.
Now, C isn't as beginner-friendly as Python, but it's a beast when it comes to performance-heavy applications.
If you're working on real-time AI like self-driving cars or high frequency trading algorithms, then C is where you want to be. But why did we choose C for AI?
First of all, because of its speed and efficiency. Now, C is all about its speed. It's the language you want when you're working with large data sets or AI applications that need to be super fast.
Second of all, it has got low-level memory management.
Now C gives you full control over memory, which is essential when you're building AI systems that require extensive computation and real-time performance.
But isn't C more complex than Python? Definitely yes. But if you're diving into AI applications that require high performance, think computer vision or robotics, C is unmatched.
It's a bit trickier to learn, but if you want to build real-time AI systems, it's worth the effort. Roles like AI Software Developer or Computer Vision Engineer are your go-to with C.
The salary range for these roles is around 8 lakh to 20 lakh per annum, depending on the project's complexity and your experience.
Third on a list is Java.
This one's a workhorse in the world of AI. And if you're aiming to work on enterprise level AI projects, then Java is definitely a language you want to know.
Now it's not the first choice for small scale AI projects, but when it comes to big scalable systems, Java is untouchable. So why Java for AI? Because of its scalability.
Now you can think Java as a base when it comes to handling large-scale applications.
If you're working on AI system that need to process huge data sets or manage complex computations, then Java can handle it all without breaking a sweat.
It's designed to scale, which makes it perfect for enterprise-level AI projects where big data is involved. Platform independence.
One of the best things about Java is its write once run anywhere feature. It doesn't matter which platform you're using, whether it's Windows, Mac, Linux, Java can run all of it without issue.
This is a huge win when you're building AI systems that need to operate across multiple platforms.
Mature libraries. Java has been around for decades and because of that, it's packed with reliable libraries for AI.
Libraries like Queka, H2O make implementing machine learning models or building AI systems a lot smoother.
These libraries we tried and tested, so you know you're working with solid tools. Let's talk about what jobs can you actually land with Java.
Now with Java, you're looking at some big roles in the AI world.
Think of AI Solution Architect or AI backend developer. These positions are not just highly respected, but it also comes with a solid salary range, typically between 7 lakh to 18 lakh per annum.
And with experience, well, let's just say that number can easily climb higher.
Now you must be thinking, how do I get started with Java?
Now, if you're already familiar with object-oriented programming, learning Java will be a breeze. And if you're new to it, don't worry.
You can start with some great resources like a YouTube channel or LinkedIn Learning. There are plenty of courses that will teach you how to use Java for AI from the ground up. Now let's talk about R.
This one's for all data science enthusiasts out there. If you're diving into statistical AI and the language built specifically for handling massive data and performing complex statistical analysis,
R is your go-to do. So why R for AI? Because of its statistical power. R is packed with tools for statistical modeling.
So if you're working on AI projects that need data analysis before you even start applying machine learning, R makes it a breeze.
It's got everything you need for analyzing trends, finding patterns, and building strong predictive models. It has also got a feature of its data exploration and visualization.
One of the R strength is its data exploration and visualization capabilities. You can easily plot, chart, and analyze your data to uncover insights.
This makes R perfect for the data-driven side of AI development, where understanding your data is just as important as building the models.
But wait, can you still work in AI if I learn R or is it just for data analysis? Absolutely. R is fantastic for AI projects that rely on statistical methods and data analysis.
It's actually the language of choice for roles like AI data analyst or quantitative analyst, where you'll be building predictive models or analyzing data trends to make decisions.
Now these roles are in high demand, and the salary range typically falls between 6 lakh and 12 lakh per annum. But with experience, you can definitely push those numbers higher.
Now to get started with R, you can find tons of free resources on our platforms and even YouTube.
And trust me, once you get the hang of it, R will open up a world of possibilities in the AI and data science world.
Also, just a quick information, guys, if you are interested in growing your career in AI and machine learning, then this course is a great way to start.
The professional certificate in AI and machine learning by Simply Learn, Purdue University Online and IBM help you master the key AI skills like ChatGPT, LLMS,
Deep Learning, and agentic AI through live classes and hands-on projects.
So in just six months, you'll work on real-world industry projects using 18 plus popular tools like Python and TensorFlow, and you'll also earn certificates from Purdue and IBM.
So guys, hurry up and enjoy now and you can find the link below. Now finally, let's talk about Julia, the new kid on the block that's growing fast in the AI space.
It's relatively young compared to Python or C,
but trust me, it's making a huge impact, and here's why.
Now Julia was created back in 2012 by a group of researchers who wanted a programming language that could handle the complex calculations required for scientific computing
and they nailed it. But why did Julia grow so fast? Well, it's been picking up speed because it combines the performance of C with the readability of Python.
You get the speed and efficiency that C is known for, but with Python's clean and easy to write code, it's like the best of both the worlds. Let's talk about why did we choose Julia for AI.
Because of its speed and simplicity. Now Julia speed is one of the biggest advantages. It's designed for high performance computing.
So if we need to run complex AI models or process tons of data, Julia will do it in a fraction of the time it would take in other languages.
And the syntax, it's also super easy to read and write. So you're not sacrificing convenience for performance.
It has also got the feature of scientific computing. Now Julia is optimized for AI tasks like deep learning and numerical analysis.
You can think AI applications in robotics, data science, and scientific research. Now, if you're working on projects that require heavy computations or advanced AI models, Julia's is your go to.
So why isn't everyone using Julia yet? It's still growing, but the Julia community expanding rapidly, and more libraries and frameworks are being developed every day.
It's quickly becoming a top choice for high performance AI and it continues to evolve. And of course, I expect to be even more popular. So is Julia better than Python or C?
Now the answer is it depends. if you're building scientific AI applications that require high performance, Julia is a fantastic option.
It's still growing, but the community expands, Julia will quickly become more powerful in the AI space. Julia is perfect for roles like AI developer in the scientific or numerical computing space.
Salaries can range from 7 lakh to 15 lakh per annum, especially if you're working with advanced AI. So, guys, there you have it, the five best programming languages for AI.
Hello and welcome to Machine Learning Tutorial Part 1.
This is part one of a machine learning series put on by Simply Learn.
My name is Richard Kirschner.
I'm with the Simply Learn team. That's www.simplylearn.com.
Get certified, get ahead.
What's in it for you today?
Well, we'll start off with a brief explanation of why machine learning and what is machine learning.
And then we'll get into a few of the types of machine learning.
Machine learning algorithms, linear regression, decision trees, support vector machine, and finally we'll do a use case where we're going to classify whether recipes
of a cupcake or a muffin using the SVM or the support vector machine.
Sounds like a delicious way to explore machine learning.
So why machine learning?
Why do we even care about having these computers come up and be able to do all these new things for us?
Well, because machines can now drive your car for you.
still very in the infant stage, but it's just exploding, as we see with uh Google's Waymo and then Uber had their program, which unfortunately crashed.
They know that this is huge. This is going to be the huge industry to change our whole transportation infrastructure.
Machine learning is now used to detect over 50 eye diseases. Do you know how amazing that is to have a computer that double checks for the doctor for things they might miss?
That's just huge in the health industry.
Pretty soon they actually do already have that in some areas where, maybe not for eyes, but for other diseases where they're using the camera on your phone to help
pre-diagnose before you go in and see the doctor.
And because the machine can now unlock your phone with your face.
I mean, that's just cool, having it be able to identify your face or your voice and be able to turn stuff on and off for you depending on where you're at and what you need.
Talking about an ultimate automation, the world we live in.
And as we dig in deeper, we have a nice example of Facebook.
As you can see here, they have the Facebook post with Halloween.
Comment yes if you want it.
Order here. Nobody likes spam posts on Facebook that annoy them into interacting with likes, shares, comments, and other actions.
I remember the original ones were all, if you don't click on here, you will have bad luck or some kind of fear factor.
Well, this is a huge thing in social media when people are getting spammed, and so this tactic, known as engagement bait,
takes advantage of Facebook's newsfeed algorithm by choosing engagement in order to get the greater reach.
to eliminate engagement bait, the company reviewed and categorized hundreds of thousands of posts to train a machine learning model that detects different types of engagement bait.
So in this case we have, we're using Facebook, but this is of course across all the different social media they have different tools they're building. And the Facebook scroll, gif will be replaced.
Kind of like a virus coming in there. It notices that there's a certain setup with Facebook and is able to replace it.
And they have like vote baiting, react baiting, share baiting, and they have all these different these are kind of general titles.
But there certainly are a lot of way of baiting you to go in there and click on something.
So they fed all this. This data was fed into the machine.
And then they have the new post. The new post comes up that takes over part of the Facebook setup. And that's what you're looking at.
You're looking at this new post that's replaced, like a virus has replaced that.
So what Facebook did to eliminate this is they start scanning for keywords and phrases like this and checks the click-through rate.
So it starts looking for people who are clicking through it without even looking at it or clicking through it and it's not something that normally would be clicked through.
Once Facebook has scanned for these keywords and phrases, it is now able to identify the spam coming in.
And this makes your life easier, so you're not getting spammed, it's not like walking through an airport, and a lot of countries you have like hundreds of people trying to sell you timeshare.
Come join us, sign up for this. eliminates that annoyingness, so now you can just enjoy your Facebook and your cat pictures, or maybe it's your family pictures. Mine is family.
Certainly people like their cat pictures too.
Another good example is Google's Deep Mind Project, Alpha Go.
A computer program that plays a board game Go has defeated the world's number one Go player, and I hope I say his name right, Keiji.
The ultimate Go Challenge game of three of three was on May 27, 2017. So that's just last year that this happened.
And what makes this so important is that you know Go is just is a game, so it's not like you're driving a car or something in our real world,
but they are using games to learn how to get the machine learning program to learn.
They want it to learn how to learn.
And that is a huge step.
A lot of this is still in its infant stage as far as development, as we saw what happened with the, as I referred to earlier, the Uber cars.
They lost their whole division because they jumped ahead too fast.
So still an infant stage, but boy, is this like the beginning of just an amazing world that is automated in ways we can't even imagine what tomorrow's going to look like.
We've looked at a lot of examples of machine learning, so let's see if we can give a little bit more of a concrete definition.
What is machine learning?
Machine learning is the science of making computers learn and act like humans by feeding data and information without being explicitly programmed.
we see here we have a nice little diagram where we have our ordinary system.
Your computer, nowadays can even run a lot of the stuff on a cell phone, because cell phones have advanced so much.
And then with artificial intelligence and machine learning, it now takes the data and it learns from what happened before.
And then it predicts what's going to come next.
And then really the biggest part right now in machine learning that's going on is it improves on that. How do we find a new solution?
So we go from descriptive where it's learning about stuff and understanding how it fits together to predicting what it's going to do to postscripting, coming up with a new solution.
And when we're working on machine learning, there's a number of different diagrams that people have posted for what steps to go through.
A lot of it might be very domain specific. So if you're working on photo identification versus language versus medical or physics, some of these are switched around a little bit
or new things are put in. They're very specific to the domain.
This is kind of a very general diagram.
First, you want to define your objective.
Very important to know what it is you're wanting to predict.
Then you're going to be collecting the data.
So once you've defined an objective, you need to collect the data that matches.
You spend a lot of time in data science collecting data and the next step preparing the data.
You've got to make sure that your data is clean going in.
There's the old saying bad data in, bad answer out, or bad data out.
And then once you've gone through and we've cleaned all this stuff coming in, then you're going to select the algorithm.
Which algorithm are you going to use? You're going to train that algorithm. In this case, I think we're going to be working with SVM, the support vector machine.
Then you have to test the model.
Does this model work?
Is this a valid model for what we're doing?
And then once you've tested it, you want to run your prediction.
You want to run your prediction or your choice or whatever output it's going to come up with.
And then once everything is set and you've done lots of testing, then you want to go ahead and deploy the model.
And remember I said domain specific. This is very general as far as the scope of doing something.
A lot of models you get halfway through and you realize that your data is missing something, and you have to go collect new data because you've run a test in here someplace along the line,
you're saying, hey, I'm not really getting the answers I need.
So it's a lot of things that are domain specific that become part of this model.
This is a very general model, but it's a very good model to start with.
And we do have some basic divisions of what machine learning does that's important to know.
For instance, do you want to predict a category?
Well, if you're categorizing thing, that's classification.
For instance, whether the stock price will increase or decrease. So in other words, I'm looking for a yes-no answer. Is it going up or is it going down?
And in that case, we'd actually say, is it going up? True.
If it's not going up, it's false, meaning it's going down.
This way it's a yes-no, zero, one.
Do you want to predict a quantity?
That's regression.
So remember we just did classification, now we're looking at regression. These are the two major divisions in what data is doing.
For instance, predicting the age of a person based on the height, weight, health, and other factors.
So based on these different factors, you might guess how old a person is.
And then there are a lot of domain specific things. Like, do you want to detect an anomaly?
That's anomaly detection.
This is actually very popular right now.
For instance, you want to detect money withdrawal anomalies. You want to know when someone's making a withdrawal that might not be their own account.
We've actually brought this up because this is really big right now.
If you're predicting the stock, whether to buy stock or not, you want to be able to know if what's going on in the stock market is an anomaly.
Use a different prediction model because something else is going on, You got to pull out new information in there.
Or is this just the norm?
I'm going to get my normal return on my money invested.
So being able to detect anomalies is very big in data science these days.
Another question that comes up, which is what we call untrained data, is do you want to discover structure in unexplored data?
And that's called clustering.
For instance, finding groups of customers with similar behavior given a large database of customer data containing their demographics and past buying records.
And in this case, we might notice that anybody who's wearing a certain set of shoes goes shopping at certain stores or whatever it is. They're going to make certain purchases.
By having that information, it helps us to market or group people together so that we can now explore that group and find out what it is we want to market to them if you're in the marketing world.
And that might also work in just about any arena.
You might want to group people together, whether they're based on their different areas and investments and financial background,
whether you're going to give them a loan or not.
Before you even start looking at whether they're a valid customer for the bank, you might want to look at all these different areas and group them together based on unknown data.
So you're not, you don't know what the data is going to tell you, but you want to cluster people together that come together.
Let's take a quick detour for quiz time. Oh, my favorite.
So we're gonna have a couple questions here under our quiz time, and we'll be posting the answers in the part two of this tutorial.
So let's go ahead and take a look at these quiz times questions, and hopefully you'll get them all right, and we'll get you thinking about how to process data and what's going on.
Can you tell what's happening in the following cases?
Of course, you're sitting there with your cup of coffee and you have your checkbox and your pen trying to figure out what's your next step in your data science analysis.
So the first one is grouping documents into different categories based on the topic and content of each document.
Very big these days.
You know, you have legal documents, you have maybe it's a sports group documents, Maybe you're analyzing newspaper postings,
But certainly having that automated is a huge thing in today's world.
B. Identifying handwritten digits and images correctly. So we want to know whether they're writing an A or capital A, B, C. What are they writing out in their hand digit their handwriting?
C.
Behavior of a website indicating that the site is not working as designed.
D.
Predicting salary of an individual based on his or her years of experience.
Wait, HR hiring uh setup there.
So stay tuned for part two. We'll go ahead and answer these questions when we get to the part two of this tutorial.
Or you can just simply write at the bottom and send a note to Simply Learn, and they'll follow up with you on it.
Back to our regular content.
And these last few bring us into the next topic, which is another way of dividing our types of machine learning, and that is with supervised,
unsupervised, and reinforcement learning.
Supervised learning is a method used to enable machines to classify, predict objects, problems, or situations based on labeled data fed to the machine.
And in here you see we have a jumble of data with circles, triangles, and squares. And we label them.
We have what's a circle, what's a triangle, what's a square, and we have our model training, and it trains it. So we know the answer.
Very important, when you're doing supervised learning, you already know the answer to a lot of your information coming in.
So you have a huge group of data coming in, and then you have a new data coming in. So we've trained our model.
The model now knows the difference between a circle, a square, a triangle.
And now that we've trained it, we can send in, in this case, a square and a circle goes in and it predicts that the top one's a square and the next one's a circle.
And you can see that this is being able to predict whether someone's going to default on a loan, because I was talking about banks earlier.
Supervised learning on stock market, whether you're going to make money or not.
That's always important.
And if you are looking to make a fortune in the stock market, keep in mind it is very difficult to get all the data correct on the stock market.
It
fluctuates in ways you really hard to predict.
So it's quite a roller coaster ride if you're running machine learning on the stock market, you start realizing you really have to dig for new data.
So we have supervised learning, if you have supervised, we should need unsupervised learning.
In unsupervised learning, machine learning model finds the hidden pattern in an unlabeled data.
So in this case, instead of telling it what the circle is and what a triangle is and what a square is, it goes in there, looks at them, and says, for whatever reason, it groups them together.
Maybe it'll group it by the number of corners.
And it notices that a number of them all have three corners, a number of them all have four corners, and a number of them all have no corners.
And it's able to filter those through and group them together.
We talked about that earlier with looking at a group of people who are out shopping.
We want to group them together to find out what they have in common.
And of course, once you understand what people have in common, maybe you have one of them who's a customer at your store, or you have five of them are a customer at your store,
and they have a lot in common with five others who are not customers at your store. How do you market to those five who aren't customers at your store yet?
They fit the demographs of who's going to shop there, and you'd like them to shop at your store, not the one next door.
Of course, this is a simplified version, you can see very easily the difference between a triangle and a circle, which might not be so easy in marketing.
Reinforcement learning.
Reinforcement learning is an important type of machine learning where an agent learns how to behave in an environment by performing actions and seeing the result.
we have here where the, in this case a baby, it's actually great that they used an infant for this slide, because the reinforcement learning is very much in its infant stages.
But it's also probably the biggest machine learning demand out there right now or in the future, it's going to be coming up over the next few years,
is reinforcement learning and how to make that work for us.
And you can see here where we have our action.
In the action on this one, it goes into the fire. Hopefully the baby didn't it was just a little candle, not a giant fire pit like it looks like here.
When the baby comes out and the new state is the baby is sad and crying because they got burned on the fire.
And then maybe they take another action.
The baby's called the agent, because it's the one taking the actions. And in this case they didn't go into the fire, they went a different direction, and now the baby's happy and laughing and playing.
Reinforcement learning is very easy to understand because that's how, as humans, that's one of the ways we learn.
We learn whether it is, you know, you burn yourself on the stove, don't do that anymore. Don't touch the stove.
In the big picture, being able to have a machine learning program or an AI be able to do this is huge. Because now we're starting to learn how to learn.
That's a big jump in the world of computer and machine learning.
And we're going to go back and just kind of go back over supervised versus unsupervised learning.
Understanding this is huge because this is going to come up in any project you're working on.
We have in supervised learning we have labeled data.
We have direct feedback.
So someone's already gone in there and said, yes, that's a triangle.
No, that's not a triangle.
And then you predict an outcome.
So you have a nice prediction. This is this this new set of data is coming in and we know what it's going to be.
And then with unsupervised training, it's not labeled.
So we really don't know what it is.
There's no feedback.
So we're not telling it whether it's right or wrong. We're not telling it whether it's a triangle or a square. We're not telling it to go left or right.
All we do is we're finding hidden structure in the data, grouping the data together to find out what connects to each other.
And then you can use these together.
So imagine you have an image and you're not sure what you're looking for.
So you go in and you have the unstructured data, find all these things that are connected together.
And then somebody looks at those and labels them.
Now you can take that label data and program something to predict what's in the picture.
So you can see how they go back and forth and you can start connecting all these different tools together to make a bigger picture.
There are many interesting machine learning algorithms. Let's have a look at a few of them.
Hopefully, this gives you a little flavor of what's out there.
And these are some of the most important ones that are currently being used.
We'll take a look at linear regression, decision tree, and the support vector machine.
Let's start with a closer look at linear regression.
Linear regression is perhaps one of the most well-known and well-understood algorithms in statistics and machine learning.
Linear regression is a linear model.
For example, a model that assumes a linear relationship between the input variables x and the single output variable y.
And you'll see this if you remember from your algebra classes, y equals mx plus c.
Imagine we are predicting distance traveled y from speed x.
Our linear regression model representation for this problem would be y equals m times x plus c, or distance equals m times speed plus c,
where m is the coefficient and c is the y-intercept. And we're going to look at two different variations of this. First we're going to start with time is constant.
And you can see we have a bicyclist, he's got a safety gear on, thank goodness.
Speed equals ten meters per second.
And so over a certain amount of time, his distance equals 36 kilometers.
We have a second bicyclist who's going twice the speed, or 20 meters per second.
And you can guess if he's going twice the speed and time is a constant, then he's going to go twice the distance.
And that's easily to compute. 36 times two, you get 72 kilometers. And so if you had the question of how fast would somebody is going three times that speed, or 30 meters per second is,
you can easily compute the distance in our head, we can do that without needing a computer.
But we want to do this for more complicated data.
So it's kind of nice to compare the two, but let's just take a look at that and what that looks like in a graph.
So in a linear regression model, we have our distance to the speed, and we have our m equals the VE slope of the line. And we'll notice that the line has a plus slope.
And as the speed increases, distance also increases, hence the variables have a positive relationship.
And so your speed of the person, which equals y equals mx plus c distance traveled in a fixed interval of time,
and we could very easily compute either following the line or just knowing it's three times ten meters per second, that this is roughly 102 kilometers distance that this third bicyclist has traveled.
One of the key definitions on here is positive relationship.
So the slope of the line is positive, as distance increase, so does speed increase.
Let's take a look at our second example where we put distance as a constant.
So we have speed equals ten meters per second, they have a certain distance to go, and it takes them 100 seconds to travel that distance.
And we have our second bicyclist who's still doing 20 meters per second.
Since he's going twice the speed, we can guess that he'll cover the distance in about half the time.
50 seconds.
And of course you could probably guess on the third one, 100 divided by 30, since he's going three times the speed.
You could easily guess that this is 33.333 seconds time.
We put that into a linear regression model or a graph.
If the distance is assumed to be constant, let's see the relationship between speed and time.
And as time goes up, the amount of speed to go that same distance goes down. So now your m equals a minus VE slope of the line.
As the speed increases, time decreases, hence the variable has a negative relationship.
Again, there's our definition, positive relationship and negative relationship dependent on the slope of the line.
And with a simple formula like this, and even a significant amount of data, let's see with the mathematical implementation of linear regression.
And we'll take this data. So suppose we have this data set where we have xy x equals one, two, three, four, five, standard series, and the y value is three,
two, two, four, three.
When we take that and we go ahead and plot these points on a graph, you can see there's kind of a nice scattering, and you could probably eyeball a line through the middle of it.
But we're going to calculate that exact line for linear regression.
And the first thing we do is we come up here and we have the mean of x i.
And remember mean is basically the average. So we added five plus four plus three plus two plus one and divide by five.
And that simply comes out as three.
And then we'll do the same for y.
We'll go ahead and add up all those numbers and divide by five, and we end up with the mean value of y of i equals two eight, where the x
i references as an average or means value, and the yi also equals a means value of y.
And when we plot that, you'll see that we can put in the y equals two eight and the x equals three in there on our graph,
we kind of give it a little different color so you could sort it out with the dashed lines on it.
And it's important to note that when we do the linear regression, the linear regression model should go through that dot.
Now let's find our regression equation to find the best fit line.
Remember we go ahead and take our y equals mx plus c, so we're looking for m and c.
So to find this equation for our data, we need to find our slope of m and our coefficient of c.
And we have y equals mx plus c, where m equals the sum of x minus x average times y
minus y average, or y means and x means, over the sum of x minus x means squared.
That's how we get the slope of the value of the line.
And we can easily do that by creating some columns here. We have x, y.
Computers are really good about iterating through data, and so we can easily compute this and fill in a graph of data.
And in our graph you can easily see that if we have our x value of one, and if you remember the xi or the means value is three,
one minus three equals a negative two, and two minus three equals a negative one, so on and so forth.
And we can easily fill in the column of x minus xi, y minus yi, and then from those we can compute x minus xi
squared and x minus xi times y minus yi.
And you can guess it that the next step is to go ahead and sum the different columns for the answers we need.
So we get a total of ten for our x minus xi squared, and a total of two for x minus xi times y minus yi.
And we plug those in, we get two tenths, which equals 0.2. So now we know the slope of our line equals 0 two.
So we can calculate the value of c.
That'd be the next step is we need to know where it crosses the y-axis.
And if you remember I mentioned earlier that the linear regression line has to pass through the means value, the one that we showed earlier.
We can just flip back up there to that graph.
And you can see right here there's our means value, which is three x equals three and y equals two eight.
And since we know that value, we can simply plug that into our formula, y equals point two x plus c.
So we plug that in, we get two eight equals 0 two times three plus c, and you can just solve for c.
So now we know that our coefficient equals two two.
And once we have all that, we can go ahead and plot our regression line y equals 0 two times x plus two two.
And then from this equation, we can compute new values. So let's predict the values of y using x equals 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 and plot the points.
Remember the 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 was our original x values.
So now we're going to see what y thinks they are, not what they actually are.
And we plug those in, we get y of designated with y of p.
You can see that x equals 1 equals 2.4, x equals 2 equals 2.6, and so on and so on.
So we have our y predicted values of what we think it's going to be when we plug those numbers in.
And when we plot the predicted values along with the actual values, we can see the difference.
And this is one of the things that's very important with linear regression in any of these models is to understand the error.
And so we can calculate the error on all of our different values. And you can see over here we plotted x and y and y predict.
And we draw in a little line so you can sort of see what the error looks like there between the different points.
So our goal is to reduce this error. We want to minimize that error value on our linear regression model.
Minimizing the distance.
There are lots of ways to minimize the distance between the line and the data points, like sum of squared errors, sum of absolute errors, root mean square error, etc.
We keep moving this line through the data points to make sure the best fit line has the least square distance between the data points and the regression line.
So to recap with a very simple linear regression model, we first figure out the formula of our line through the middle, and then we slowly adjust the line to minimize the error.
Keep in mind this is a very simple formula.
The math gets, even though the math is very much the same, it gets much more complex as we add in different dimensions.
So this is only two dimensions, y equals mx plus c, but you can take that out to x, z, ijq, all the different features in there,
and they can plot a linear regression model on all of those using the different formulas to minimize the error.
Let's go ahead and take a look at decision trees, a very different way to solve problems than the linear regression model.
Decision tree is a tree-shaped algorithm used to determine a course of action.
Each branch of a tree represents a possible decision, occurrence, or reaction.
We have data which tells us if it is a good day to play golf.
And if we were to open this data up in a general spreadsheet, you can see we have the outlook, whether it's rainy, overcast, sunny, temperature,
hot, mild, cool, humidity, windy, and did I like to play golf that day, yes or no?
So we're taking a census.
And certainly I wouldn't want a computer telling me when I should go play golf or not.
But you could imagine if you got up in the night before you're trying to plan your day, and it comes up and says tomorrow would be a good day for golf for you in the morning,
and not a good day in the afternoon, or something like that.
This becomes very beneficial, and we see this in a lot of applications coming out now where it gives you suggestions and lets you know what would
fit the match for you for the next day or the next purchase or the next whatever, you know, next mail out. In this case, is tomorrow a good day for playing golf based on the weather coming in?
And so we come up and let's determine if you should play golf when the day is sunny and windy.
So we found out the forecast tomorrow is going to be sunny and windy.
And suppose we draw our tree like this. We're going to have our humidity, and then we have our normal, which is if it's if you have a normal humidity, you're gonna go play golf.
And if the humidity is really high, then we look at the outlook. And if the outlook is sunny, overcast, or rainy, it's going to change what you choose to do.
So if you know that it's a very high humidity and it's sunny, you're probably not going to play golf because you're gonna be out there miserable,
fighting off the mosquitoes that are out joining you to play golf with you.
Maybe if it's rainy, you probably don't want to play in the rain.
But if it's slightly overcast and you get just the right shadow, that's a good day to play golf and be outside out on the green.
Now in this example, you can probably make your own tree pretty easily because it's a very simple set of data going in.
But the question is, how do you know what to split? Where do you split your data? What if this is much more complicated data where it's not something that you would particularly understand?
Like studying cancer, they take about 36 measurements of the cancerous cells, and then each one of those measurements represents how bulbous it is, how extended it is,
how sharp the edges are.
Something that as a human we would have no understanding of.
So how do we decide how to split that data up?
And is that the right decision tree?
so that's the question that's going to come up is this the right decision tree?
For that, we should calculate entropy and information gain.
Two important vocabulary words there are the entropy and the information gain.
Entropy.
Entropy is a measure of randomness or impurity in the dataset.
Entropy should be low.
So we want the chaos to be as low as possible.
We don't want to look at it and be confused by the images or what's going on there with mixed data.
And the information gain, it is a measure of decrease in entropy after the data set is split, also known as entropy reduction.
Information gain should be high.
So we want our information that we get out of the split to be as high as possible.
Let's take a look at entropy from the mathematical side.
In this case, we're going to denote entropy as i of p of and n, where p is the probability that you're going to play a game of golf,
and n is the probability where you're not going to play the game of golf.
Now you don't really have to memorize these formulas. There's a few of them out there depending on what you're working with.
But it's important to note that this is where this formula is coming from, so when you see it, you're not lost when you're running your programming,
unless you're building your own decision tree code in the back.
And we simply have a log squared of p over p plus n minus n over p plus n times the log squared of n of p plus n.
But let's break that down and see what actually looks like when we're computing that from the computer script side.
Entropy of a target class of the data set is the whole entropy.
So we have entropy play golf.
And we look at this, if we go back to the data, you can simply count how many yeses and no in our complete data set for playing golf days.
In our complete set, we find we have five days we did play golf and nine days we did not play golf.
And so our i equals, if you add those together, nine plus five is 14.
And so our i equals five over 14 and nine over 14. That's our P and N values that we plug into that formula.
And you can go with uh five over 14 equals 0.36, nine over 14 equals 0.64.
And when you do the whole equation, you get the minus 0.36 log root squared of 0.36 minus 0.64
log squared root of 0.64.
And we get a set value, we get 0.94.
So we now have a full entropy value for the whole set of data that we're working with.
And we want to make that entropy go down.
And just like we calculated the entropy out for the whole set, we can also calculate entropy for playing golf and the outlook. Is it going to be overcast or rainy or sunny?
And so we look at the entropy, we have p of sunny times e of three of two, and that just comes out how many sunny days yes and how many sunny days
no over the total, which is five. Don't forget to put the we'll divide that five out later on, equals p overcast equals four comma zero plus rainy equals two comma three.
And then when you do the whole setup, we have five over 14.
Remember I said there was a total of five, five over 14 times the i of three of two plus four over 14 times the four comma zero and five 14
over i of two three.
And so we can now compute the entropy of just the part it has to do with the forecast, and we get 0.693.
Similarly, we can calculate the entropy of other predictors like temperature, humidity, and wind.
And so we look at the gain outlook. How much are we going to gain from this? Entropy play golf minus entropy play golf outlook.
And we can take the original 0.94 for the whole set minus the entropy of just the rainy day and temperature,
and we end up with a gain of 0.247.
So this is our information gain. Remember we define entropy and we define information gain. The higher the information gain, the lower the entropy, the better.
The information gain of the other three attributes can be calculated in the same way.
So we have our gain for temperature equals 0.029.
We have our gain for humidity equals 0.152, and our gain for a windy day equals 0.048.
And if you do a quick comparison, you'll see the 0.247 is the greatest gain of information, so that's the split we want.
Now let's build the decision tree. So we have the outlook. Is it going to be sunny, overcast, or rainy? That's our first split because that gives us the most information gain.
And we can continue to go down the tree using the different information gains with the largest information.
We can continue down the nodes of the tree where we choose the attribute with the largest information gain as the root node,
and then continue to split each sub node with the largest information gain that we can compute.
And although it's a little bit of a tongue twister to say all that, you can see that it's a very easy-to-view visual model.
We have our outlook, we split it three different directions.
If the outlook is overcast, we're going to play.
And then we can split those further down if we want. So if the outlook is sunny, but then it's also windy, if it's windy, we're not going to play. If it's not windy, we'll play.
So we can easily build a nice decision tree to guess what we would like to do tomorrow and give us a nice recommendation for the day.
So we want to know if it's a good day to play golf when it's sunny and windy.
Remember the original question that came out? Tomorrow's weather report is sunny and windy?
You can see by going down the tree we go outlook sunny, outlook windy, we're not going to play golf tomorrow. So our little smartwatch pops up and says, I'm sorry, tomorrow's not a good day for golf.
It's going to be sunny and windy.
And if you're a huge golf fan, you might go, uh-oh, it's not a good day to play golf.
We can go in and watch a golf game at home.
So we'll sit in front of the TV instead of being out playing golf in the wind.
Now that we looked at our decision tree, let's look at the third one of our algorithms we're investigating.
Support vector machine.
Support vector machine is a widely used classification algorithm.
The idea of support vector machine is simple.
The algorithm creates a separation line which divides the classes in the best possible manner.
For example, dog or cat, disease or no disease.
Suppose we have a labeled sample data which tells height and weight of males and females.
A new data point arrives and we want to know whether it's going to be a male or a female.
So we start by drawing a line.
We draw decision lines, but if we consider decision line one, then we will classify the individual as a male.
And if we consider decision line two, then it will be a female.
So you can see this person kind of lies in the middle of the two groups, so it's a little confusing trying to figure out which line they should be under.
We need to know which line divides the classes correctly, but how.
The goal is to choose a hyperplane, and that is one of the key words they use when we talk about support vector machines.
Choose a hyperplane with the greatest possible margin between the decision line and the nearest point within the training set.
So you can see here we have our support vector, we have the two nearest points to it, and we draw a line between those two points.
And the distance margin is the distance between the hyperplane and the nearest data point from either set.
So we actually have a value, and it should be equally distant between the two points that we're comparing it to.
When we draw the hyperplanes, we observe that line one has a maximum distance. So we observe that line one has a maximum distance margin, so we'll classify the new data point correctly.
And our result on this one is going to be that the new data point is MEL.
One of the reasons we call it a hyperplane versus a line is that a lot of times we're not looking at just weight and height.
We might be looking at 36 different features or dimensions.
And so when we cut it with a hyperplane, it's more of a three-dimensional cut in the data or multi-dimensional. It cuts the data a certain way.
And each plane continues to cut it down until we get the best fit or match.
Let's understand this with the help of an example.
Problem statement.
Classifying muffin and cupcake recipes using support vector machines. So the cupcake versus the muffin.
Let's have a look at our data set.
And we have the different recipes here. We have a muffin recipe that has so much flour. I'm not sure what measurement 55 is in, but it has 55 maybe it's ounces.
But uh has a certain amount of flour, certain amount of milk, sugar, butter, egg, baking powder, vanilla, and salt.
And so based on these measurements, we want to guess whether we're making a muffin or a cupcake.
And you can see in this one, we don't have just two features. We don't just have height and weight as we did before between the male and female.
In here we have a number of features.
In fact, in this we're looking at eight different features to guess whether it's a muffin or a cupcake.
What's the difference between a muffin and a cupcake?
Turns out muffins have more flour, while cupcakes have more butter and sugar.
So basically the cupcake's a little bit more of a dessert where the muffin's a little bit more of a fancy bread.
But how do we do that in Python? How do we code that to go through recipes and figure out what the recipe is?
And I really just want to say cupcakes versus muffins, like some big professional wrestling thing.
Before we start in our cupcakes versus muffins, we are going to be working in Python.
There's many versions of Python, many different editors.
That is one of the strengths and weaknesses of Python, is it just has so much stuff attached to it and it's one of the more popular data science programming packages you can use.
In this case, we're going to go ahead and use Anaconda in Jupyter Notebook.
The Anaconda Navigator has all kinds of fun tools. Once you're into the Anaconda Navigator, you can change environments.
I actually have a number of environments on here. We'll be using Python 3.6 environment. So this is in Python version 3.6.
Although it doesn't matter too much which version you use.
I usually try to stay with the 3x because they're current, unless you have a project that's very specifically in version 2x. 2.7, I think, is usually what most people use in the version 2.
And then once we're in our Jupyter Notebook editor, I can go up and create a new file. And we'll just jump in here.
In this case we're doing SVM muffin versus cupcake.
And then let's start with our packages for data analysis.
And we almost always use a couple there's a few very standard packages we use.
We use import oops import.
Import
numpy.
That's for number python.
they usually denote it as np, that's very comma.
That's very common.
And then we're going to import pandas as PD.
And NumPy deals with number arrays. There's a lot of cool things you can do with the NumPy setup.
As far as multiplying all the values in an array, in a NumPy array, data array.
Pandas, I can't remember if we're using it actually in this data set. I think we do as an import.
It makes a nice data frame.
And the difference between a data frame and a numpy array is that a data frame is more like your Excel spreadsheet.
You have columns, you have indexes, you have different ways of referencing it, easily viewing it, and there's additional features you can run on a data frame.
And pandas kind of sits on NumPy, so they you need them both in there.
And then finally we're working with the support vector machine. So from SK Learn, we're going to use the SK Learn model,
import SVM, support vector machine.
And then as a data scientist, you should always try to visualize your data.
Some data obviously is too complicated or doesn't make any sense to the human.
But if it's possible, it's good to take a second look at it so that you can actually see what you're doing.
And for that, we're going to use two packages. We're going to import matplotlibrary.pyplot as plt.
Again, very common.
And we're going to import c born as SNS. And we'll go ahead and set the font scale in the SNS right in our import line.
That's what this semicolon followed by a line of data.
We're going to set the SNS.
And these are great because the the C born sits on top of Mapplot Library, just like Panda sits on Numpy.
So it adds a lot more features and uses and control.
We're obviously not going to get into Mapplot Library and CBON, that'd be its own tutorial.
We're really just focusing on the SVM, the support vector machine from sklearn.
And since we're in Jupyter Notebook, we have to add a special line in here for our Matplot library.
And that's your percentage sign or amber sign Matplotlibrary in line.
Now, if you're doing this in just a straight code project, a lot of times I use like Notepad,
and I'll run it from there.
You don't have to have that line in there, because it'll just pop up as its own window on your computer, depending on how your computer's setup.
Because we're running this in the Jupyter Notebook as a browser setup, this tells it to display all of our graphics right below on the page.
So that's what that line is for.
Remember the first time I ran this, I didn't know that, and I had to go look that up years ago.
It was quite a headache. So Mapplot Library inline is just because we're running this on the web setup.
And we can go ahead and run this, make sure all our modules are in. They're all imported, which is great.
If you don't have an import, you'll need to go ahead and pip, use the PIP or however you do it. There's a lot of other install packages out there, although pip is the most common.
And you have to make sure these are all installed on your Python setup.
The next step, of course, is we got to look at the data. You can't run a model for predicting data if you don't have actual data.
So to do that, let me go ahead and open this up and take a look.
And we have our cupcakes versus muffins, and it's a csv file or.csv, meaning that it's comma separated variable.
And it's gonna open it up in a nice spreadsheet for me.
And you can see up here we have the type. We have muffin, muffin, muffin, cupcake, cupcake, cupcake, and then it's broken up into flour, milk, sugar, butter, egg, baking powder, vanilla, and salt.
So we can do is we can go ahead and look at this data also in our Python.
Let us create a variable recipes equals. We're gonna use our pandas
module.readcsv. Remember it was a comma-separated variable.
And the file name happened to be cupcakes versus muffins. Oops, I got double brackets there.
There we go.
Cupcakes versus muffins.
Because the program I loaded, or the the place I saved this particular Python program is in the same folder, we can get by with just the file name.
But remember if you're storing it in a different location, you have to also put down the full path on there.
And then because we're in pandas, we're going to go ahead and you can actually in line you can do this, but let me do the full print. You can just type in recipes.head
in the Jupyter Notebook.
But if you're running in code in a different script, you'd need to go ahead and type out the whole print recipes.head.
And pandas knows is that's going to do the first five lines of data.
And if we flip back on over to the spreadsheet where we opened up our CSV file,
you can see where it starts on line two. This one calls it zero, and then two, three, four, five, six is going to match.
Go and close that out because we don't need that anymore.
And it always starts at zero.
And these are it automatically indexes it since we didn't tell it to use an index in here. So that's the index number for the left hand side.
And it automatically took the top row as labels. So pandas using it to read a CSV is just really slick and fast.
One of the reasons we love our pandas, not just because they're cute and cuddly teddy bears.
And let's go ahead and plot our data.
And I'm not going to plot all of it.
I'm just going to plot the sugar and flour.
Now, obviously, you can see where they get really complicated if we have tons of different features.
And so you'll break them up and maybe look at just two of them at a time to see how they connect.
And to plot them, we're going to go ahead and use Seaborn.
So that's our SNS.
And the command for that is sns.lmplot.
And then the two different variables I'm going to plot is flour and sugar.
Data equals recipes.
The hue equals type.
And this is a lot of fun because it knows that this is pandas coming in.
So this is one of the powerful things about pandas mixed with CBORN in doing
graphing.
And then we're going to use a palette set1.
There's a lot of different sets in there. You can go look them up for CBORN.
We'll do a regular a fit regular equals false, so we're not really trying to fit anything.
And it's a scatter KWS.
A lot of these settings you can look up in Corn. Half of these you could probably leave off when you run them.
Somebody played with this and found out that these were the best settings for doing a CBORN plot.
let's go ahead and run that.
And because it does it in line, it just puts it right on the page.
And you can see right here that just based on sugar and flour alone, there's a definite split.
And we use these models because you can actually look at it and say, hey, if I drew a line right between the middle of the blue dots and the red dots,
we'd be able to do an SVM and a hyperplane right there in the middle.
Then the next step is to format or pre
process our data.
And we're going to break that up into two parts.
We need a type
label, and remember we're going to decide whether it's a muffin or a cupcake. Well, a computer doesn't know muffin or cupcake, it knows zero and one.
So what we're going to do is we're going to create a type label.
And from this we'll create a numpy array np where,
and this is where we can do some logic. We take our recipes from our panda, and wherever type equals muffin, it's going to be zero.
And then if it doesn't equal muffin, which is cupcakes, it's going to be one. So we create our type label.
This is the answer.
So when we're doing our training model, remember we have to have a training data?
This is what we're going to train it with is that it's zero or one. It's a muffin or it's not.
And then we're going to create our recipe features.
And if you remember correctly, from right up here, the first column is type.
So we really don't need the type column because that's our muffin or cupcake.
And in pandas, we can easily sort that out.
We take our value
recipes.columns, that's a pandas function built into
pandas.values, so converting them to values. So it's just the column titles going across the top.
And we don't want the first one.
So what we do is since it always starts at zero.
We want one
colon till the end.
And then we want to go ahead and make this a list, and this converts it to a list of strings.
then we can go ahead and just take a look and see what we're looking at for the features. Make sure it looks right.
go ahead and run that.
And I forgot the S on recipes, so we'll go ahead and add the S in there and then run that.
And we can see we have flour, milk, sugar, butter, egg, baking powder, vanilla, and salt.
And that matches what we have up here.
we printed out everything but the type.
So we have our features and we have our label.
Now the recipe features is just the titles of the columns, and we actually need the ingredients.
at this point, we have a couple options. One, we could run it over all the ingredients.
And when you're doing this, usually you do. But for our example, we want to limit it so you can easily see what's going on. Because if we did all the ingredients, we have, you know, that's what,
seven, eight different hyperplanes that would be built into it. We only want to look at one so you can see what the SVM is doing.
And so we'll take our recipes and we'll do just flour and sugar.
Again, you can replace that with your recipe features and do all of them. But we're going to do just flour and sugar, and we're going to convert that to values.
We don't need to make a list out of it because it's not string values. These are actual
values on there.
And we can go ahead and just print
ingredients, and you can see what that looks like.
And so we have just the amount of flour and sugar, just the two sets of plots.
And just for fun, let's go ahead and take this over here and take our recipe features.
And so if we decided to use all the recipe features, you'll see that it makes a nice column of different data. So it just strips out all the labels and everything, we just have just the values.
But because we want to be able to view this easily in a plot later on, we'll go ahead and take that and just do flour and sugar.
And we'll run that and you'll see it's just the two columns.
So the next step is to go ahead and fit our model.
We'll go ahead and just call it model.
And it's a SVM.
We're using a package called SVC.
In this case, we're going to go ahead and set the kernel equals linear. So it's using a specific setup on there.
And if we go to the reference on their website for the SVM,
you'll see that there's about there's eight of them here.
Three of them are for regression,
three are for classification.
The SVC support vector classification is probably one of the most commonly used.
And then there's also one for detecting outliers, and another one that has to do with something a little bit more specific on the model.
But SVC and SVR are the two most commonly used, standing for support vector classifier and support vector regression.
Remember, regression is an actual value, a float value or whatever you're trying to work on.
And SBC is a classifier, so it's a yes, no, true, false.
But for this, we want to know 0, 1, muffin cupcake.
We go ahead and create our model.
And once we have our model created, we're going to do model.fit. And this is very common, especially in the SKLearn. All their models are followed with the fit command.
And what we put into the fit, what we're training with it, is we're putting in the ingredients, which in this case we limited to just flour and sugar,
and the type label. Is it a muffin or a cupcake?
Now, in more complicated data science series, you'd want to split into, we won't get into that today, we split it into training data and test data.
And they even do something where they split it into thirds, where a third is used for where you switch between which one's training and test.
There's all kinds of things that go into that, and it gets very complicated when you get to the higher end.
Not overly complicated, just an extra step, which we're not going to do today, because this is a very simple set of data.
And let's go ahead and run this, and now we have our model fit.
And I got an error here, so let me fix that real quick. It's capital SVC, it turns out.
I did it lowercase.
Support vector
classifier. There we go. Let's go ahead and run that.
And you'll see it comes up with all this information that it prints out automatically.
These are the defaults of the model.
You notice that we changed the kernel to linear.
And there's our kernel linear on the printout.
And there's other different settings you can mess with.
We're going to just leave that alone for right now for this. We don't really need to mess with any of those.
So, next we're going to dig a little bit into our newly trained model.
And we're going to do this so we can show you on a graph.
And let's go ahead and get the separating.
So we're gonna say we're gonna use a w for our variable on here.
We're gonna do model dot coefficient underscore zero.
So what the heck is that?
Again, we're digging into the model. So we've already got a prediction and a train.
This is the math behind it that we're looking at right now.
And so
the w is gonna represent two different coefficients. And if you remember we had y equals mx plus c.
So these coefficients are connected to that, but in two dimensional.
It's a plane.
We don't want to spend too much time on this because you can get lost in the confusion of the math. So if you're a math whiz, this is great.
You can go through here and you'll see that we have a equals minus w of zero over w of one. Remember there's two different values there.
And that's basically the slope that we're generating.
And then we're going to build an xx. What is xx?
We're going to set it up to a numpy array. There's our np, dot line space.
So we're creating a line
of values between 30 and 60.
So it just creates a set of numbers for x.
And then if you remember correctly, we have
our formula y equals the slope times x
plus the intercept.
Well, to make this work, we can do this as yy
equals the slope times each value in that array.
That's the neat thing about numpy. So when I do a times xx, which is a whole numpy array of values, it multiplies a across all of them.
And then it takes those same values and we subtract the model intercept. That's your
we had mx plus c, so that'd be the c from the formula, y equals mx plus c.
that's where all these numbers come from.
A little bit confusing because it's digging out of these different arrays.
And then we want to do is we're going to take this and we're going to go ahead and plot it.
So plot the parallels to separating hyperplane that pass through the support vectors.
And so we're going to create b equals a model support vectors.
Pulling our support vectors out there.
Here's our yy, which we now know is a set of data, and we have, uh, we're going to create yy down, equals a times xx plus b1
minus a times b zero.
and then model support. vector b is going to be set that to a new value. the minus one setup, and yy up equals a times xx plus b1 minus a times. b zero.
And we can go ahead and just run this to load these variables up.
If you want to know understand a little bit more of what's going on, you can see if we print
yy, let me just run that.
You can see it's an array, it's this is a line. It's going to have, in this case, between 30 and 60 so it's going to be 30 variables in here.
And the same thing with yy up, yy down.
And we'll plot those in just a minute on a graph so you can see what those look like.
You just go ahead and delete that out of here and run that. So it loads up the variables, nice clean slate.
I'm just going to copy this from before.
Remember this? Our SNS dot our cborne plot, lm plot, flower, sugar.
And I'll just go ahead and run that real quick so you can see what remember what that looks like. It's just a straight graph on there.
And then one of the neat things is because seaborne sits on top of pi plot, we can do the piplot for the line going through.
And that is simply plt dot plot.
And that's our xx and yy, our two corresponding values, xy.
And then somebody played with this to figure out that the line width equals two and the color black would look nice.
So let's go ahead and run this whole thing with the pi plot on there.
And you can see when we do this, it's just doing flour and sugar on here.
Corresponding line between the sugar and the flour and the muffin versus cupcake.
and then we generated the support vectors, the yy down and yy up.
So let's take a look and see what that looks like.
So we'll do our PL plot,
and again this is all against xx, our x value, but this time we have yy
down.
And let's do something a little fun with this.
We can put in a k- dash dash.
that just tells it to make it a dotted line.
And if we're gonna do the down one,
we also want to do the up one.
So here's our yy
and when we run that, it adds both sets of line.
And so here's our support, and this is what you expect. You expect these two lines to go through the nearest data point.
So the dashed lines go through the nearest muffin and the nearest cupcake when it's plotting it.
And then your SVM goes right down the middle. So it gives it a nice split in our data, and you can see how easy it is to see, based just on sugar and flour, which one's a muffin or a cupcake.
Let's go ahead and create a function
to predict
muffin or cupcake.
I've got my recipes I pulled off the
internet, and I want to see the difference between a
muffin or a cupcake.
And so we need a function to push that through.
And create a function with depth.
And let's call it muffin or cupcake.
And remember, we're just doing flour and sugar today. We're not doing all the ingredients.
And that actually is a pretty good split. You really don't need all the ingredients to know it's flour and sugar.
And let's go ahead and do an if L statement. So if model predict
is a flour and sugar equals zero.
So we take our model and we do it run a predict. That's very common in sklearn where you have a dot predict, you put the data in, and it's going to return a value.
In this case, if it equals zero, then print you're looking at a muffin recipe.
Else, if it's not zero, that means it's one, then you're looking at a cupcake recipe.
That's pretty straightforward for a
function, or def for definition. DEF is how you do that in Python.
And of course, we're going to create a function, you should run something in it.
And so let's run a cupcake and we're gonna send it values 50 and 20, a muffin or a cupcake, I don't know what it is.
And let's run this and just see what it gives us.
And it says, oh, it's a muffin.
You're looking at a muffin recipe.
So it very easily predicts whether we're looking at a muffin or a cupcake recipe.
Let's plot this, there we go, plot this on the graph so we can see what that actually looks like.
And I'm just gonna copy and paste it from below, where we're plotting all the points in there.
So this is nothing different than what we did before. If I run it, you'll see it has all the points and the lines on there.
And what we want to do is we want to add another point,
and we'll do pltplot.
And if you remember correctly, we did for our test, we did 50 and 20.
And then somebody went in here and decided we'll do uh YO for yellow, or it's kind of an orange as yellow color is going to come out.
Marker size 9.
Those are settings you can play with. Somebody else played with them to come up with the right setup so it looks good.
And you can see there it is graphed clearly a muffin.
in this case in cupcakes versus muffins the muffin has won and If you'd like to do your own muffin
cupcake contender series, you certainly can send a note down below, and the team at Simular will send you over the data they use for the muffin and cupcake.
And that's true of any of the data.
We didn't actually run a plot on it earlier. We had men versus women.
You can also request that information to run it on your data setup so you can test that out.
So to go back over our setup, we went ahead for our support vector machine code.
We did a predict 40 parts flour, 20 parts sugar.
I think it was different than the one we did, whether it's a muffin or a cupcake.
So we have built a classifier using SVM, which is able to classify if a recipe is of a cupcake or a muffin.
which wraps up our cupcake versus muffin
So the key takeaways, what is machine learning?
We discussed that with some of the different aspects of machine learning on there.
We went into types of machine learning.
If you memorize, we have supervised, unsupervised, and reinforcement learning.
We discussed regression line or best fit, and we did the building a decision tree and what the logic is behind that.
And finally, we did classification using SVM, support vector machine, and we did the code in there.
Today we are diving into machine learning, the technology behind things like Netflix recommendations, Siri, and even the face unlock of your phone.
Machine learning helps devices get smarter by learning from data and predicting what we might like or need.
And here's why machine learning is huge for your career.
Right now, machine learning jobs are among the fastest growing roles worldwide.
Companies in every industry, tech, healthcare, finance, and more are looking for people with machine learning skills to improve their products,
automate tasks, and make smarter decisions.
Machine learning engineers in the US earn around $112,000 on average, with plenty of room for growth as you gain experience.
So if you want to jump into this exciting field, learning machine learning can open doors to high-paying in-demand jobs.
So in this video, I'll guide you through the ultimate roadmap to master machine learning in 2025, one step at a time.
So let's get started.
So in the first month, start with the foundations of programming.
So programming is a language you'll use to communicate with your computer and bring machine learning algorithms to life.
So this month is all about Python, the language of choice for most machine learning practitioners.
So here's what to focus on.
First, learn Python basics.
Begin with Python's fundamentals like variables, data types, loops, and functions.
So spend time writing small programs daily to get comfortable.
After that, explore the key libraries like NumPy, Pandas, and ScikitLearn.
So NumPy is for numerical operations.
It makes handling large data sets faster and easier.
And pandas is to manipulate and analyze data.
So pandas allow you to filter, sort, and reshape data in a breeze.
And then scikit learn is for implementing algorithms in just a few lines of code.
So now you might have heard about R, another language using machine learning.
But don't stress about it now. Python will serve you well, especially as a beginner, because it's simpler and more flexible.
So aim to spend an hour or two each day coding.
By the end of this month, you'll have a solid base to build on.
Now in the second month, get organized with version control and data structures.
So this month is about learning how to organize and manage your code effectively and sharpening your problem solving skills with data structures and algorithms.
So first is version control with Git.
So think of Git as your project history tracker.
So imagine working on a big project and making changes, then realizing something went wrong.
You want to go back to an earlier version, right?
So that's where Git comes in.
And here's what you should practice.
Number one is committing changes.
So save different versions of your work as you progress.
And then branching, which means work on separate features without affecting your main code.
And then comes merging, which means combining changes from different versions once they are ready.
So you have to set up an account on GitHub or GitLab to store your projects online.
So not only will this be super useful, but it will also start building your portfolio.
Now next is data structures and algorithms.
So think of data structures like tools in a toolkit.
So each one like arrays, stacks, queues, etc., serves a specific purpose.
So here's how to approach them.
one, arrays and lists.
Now arrays and lists are for storing data in sequence.
After that, you can get familiar with stacks and queues.
So stacks and queues are for tasks that need order data access.
And then you have sorting and searching algorithms.
So these make your programs more efficient, and that's super important in machine learning where data can get massive.
So the goal here is to build up your problem solving skills, which are key to machine learning success.
So take it slow, practice daily, and you'll see progress.
Now in the third month, learn to access data with SQL.
So in machine learning, a lot of work involves accessing and organizing data from databases.
So SQL, a structured query language, is your ticket to getting the data you need for training ML models.
So here's what you should focus on.
Select and where.
So these commands help you pull specific pieces of data.
And then you can move on to joins.
Joins usually combine data from different tables.
So this is so powerful that you'll use it all the time.
And then comes group by and aggregate functions.
They are great for summarizing data to find patterns.
So spend time working with sample databases you can find online and practice writing queries.
Being comfortable with SQL will save you time when preparing data for your models.
Now after completing the third month, you can move on to mathematics, which is building your analytical mind.
So this month we are tackling the math behind machine learning.
So don't worry, you don't need to be a math genius, but understanding certain concepts will make everything feel less mysterious.
So in this month you have to focus on linear algebra.
So this is the math behind how models see data.
So you can study vectors, matrices, and operations like multiplication.
Next comes calculus.
So you'll use calculus to help your models learn.
So you have to focus on derivatives and gradients, which help minimize errors in your model.
And then you can move on to probability and statistics.
So understanding probability helps you make sense of data.
So learn about distributions like normal distribution, binormal distribution, and then variance and standard deviation.
So once you have learned maths, next you'll be moving on to data handling and visualization, which is the heart of machine learning as you all know.
So with math under your belt, it's time to dig into data handling and visualization.
So data preparation is vital because your model is only as good as the data you feed it.
So number one comes data manipulation.
So using pandas and numpy, you'll clean and organize your data.
You might be removing missing values like clean up messy data so it doesn't confuse your model, and then you'll learn transforming variables like converting data into formats that work for models.
And then you will move on to encoding categorical data, like changing text data like female or male into numbers.
Now, once you are done with data manipulation, next comes data visualization.
So visualization is how you get to see your data before training a model.
So here you have to learn Matplotlib and Seaborn.
So you can create line charts, histograms, scatter plots, and heat maps.
So this lets you explore patterns and spot outliers.
So understanding these patterns in your data is crucial for building effective models.
Now, in the sixth month, you will be moving on to the machine learning fundamentals.
So now it's time to start building your own models.
So you will focus on two main types of machine learning this month.
Number one comes the supervised learning.
So, this is when you train a model on label data where the outcome is already known.
So, you will work with algorithms like linear regression, which predicts a continuous outcome.
Then you will work with decision trees, which breaks down decisions into a tree structure, and then you have support vector machines under supervised learning, which separates data into classes.
Now, after supervised learning comes unsupervised learning.
So here your model identifies patterns and data without labeled outcomes.
So two popular techniques in unsupervised learning is number one clustering, like K means clustering, which means group similar data points, and then you have dimensionality reduction.
This reduces data complexity by focusing on key features.
So you can use Scikit Learn to try out these algorithms on sample datasets.
So this will give you hands-on experience with model training and you will learn to fine-tune them to get better results.
Now before moving on, if you are interested in advancing your career in the field of AI and machine learning, Simply Learn's postgraduate program, Delivery in collaboration with Purdue
University and IBM, is a perfect opportunity.
This highly ranked program offers a comprehensive curriculum covering essential topics like machine learning, deep learning, NLP, computer vision,
reinforcement learning, generative AI, prompt engineering, and many more.
With hands-on experience to 25 plus projects and access to 20 plus cutting-edge tools, you will gain the skills needed to excel in today's competitive job market.
So join now and elevate your expertise with the backing of Purdue's Academic Excellence and IBM's industry leading insights.
You can find the course link in the description box and in the comments.
Now moving on to the seventh month, you'll be building and training models with advanced libraries.
So by now you have experimented with some basic models.
So let's step it up with advanced tools like TensorFlow and PyTorch.
So these libraries offer more flexibility and power. So TensorFlow and PyTorch, so here you can start with simple models and work your way up.
So these libraries allow for building neural networks, which you will be studying more on the next month.
Now once you have become familiar with TensorFlow and PyTorch, you can move on to model training and evaluation.
So you have to learn to split data into training and testing sets and evaluate models using metrics like accuracy and precision.
So your goal this month should be to get comfortable with these libraries and understand how they handle data and model training behind the scenes.
So once you are done with this, you will be moving on to the eighth month where you will be dealing with advanced machine learning.
So this month's concept will be number one on ensemble learning, which means combining multiple models to get better predictions.
So here you'll be learning about bagging.
For example, random forests.
Here multiple decision trees make predictions and then you have boosting like ADI boost, XG Boost.
So models learn from each other's mistakes over here.
And after ensemble learning comes deep learning.
So here you explore neural networks which mimic the human brain.
So you'll learn about neural network basics.
So you can start with simple, fully connected networks, and then you can move on to backpropagation and gradient descent.
So these helps your model learn and improve.
So you can use TensorFlow or PyTorch to practice building neural networks.
you can work on projects to reinforce these concepts.
Now moving on, you have to specialize on topics like NLP and computer vision.
So machine learning applications are so powerful, and here you'll get a taste of two major fields, which is NLP or natural language processing.
So here they work with text data for tasks like sentiment analysis and text classification.
So you can start with basic pre-processing like tokenization, stop word removal, and move to building simple NLP models.
After that, you can try out computer vision.
So for image data, you have to learn CNNs, convolutional neural networks.
So these networks analyze visual patterns, making them ideal for image classification.
So you practice with open data sets like text, documents, or images and apply the concepts you will learn to see results in real world applications.
Now in the 10th month, you'll be dealing with model deployment, which is bringing your models to life.
So here you will be using Flask or Django, so you can use these frameworks to create a web API so users can interact with your model.
For example, build a web app that lets people upload images for classification.
And then you can also try Docker so package your model and its dependencies so it can run on any machine.
So this is super helpful for deploying models without compatibility issues.
So by the end of this month, you'll be able to show your models to the world.
So moving on to the 11th month, you'll be starting with cloud and production.
So this month you'll learn how to deploy models on the cloud and ensure they perform well in real-world environments.
So you'll be dealing with cloud platforms like AWS, Google Cloud, or Azure.
So you have to learn to deploy models on the cloud for wider accessibility and scalability.
And then comes monitoring and maintenance.
So understand how to track your model's performance over time and update it as needed.
So these skills are essential for maintaining models in production and ensuring they still reliable.
And finally, you will be creating real-world projects and portfolio building.
So here you have to choose topics that interest you and showcase your skills.
So first you can start with full projects.
So complete projects that go from data cleaning and model building to deployment.
So ideas could be a sentiment analysis tool or an image recognition app.
And then you have to build your portfolio.
So organize and document your projects, host them on GitHub, and create an online portfolio to share with potential employers or collaborators.
So by following this roadmap, you'll be well prepared to handle real-world machine learning challenges and have an impressive portfolio to showfer it. Welcome to Machine Learning Tutorial Part 2.
My name is Richard Kirschner with the Simply Learn team.
That is www.simplylearn.com.
Get certified, get ahead.
Today in our second tutorial, we're going to cover K-means and linear regression, along with going over the quiz questions we had during our first tutorial.
What's in it for you?
We're going to cover clustering.
What is clustering?
K-means clustering, which is one of the most common used clustering tools out there, including a flow chart to understand k-means clustering and how it functions.
And then we'll do an actual Python live demo on clustering of cars based on brands.
Then we're going to cover logistic regression.
What is logistic regression?
Logistic regression curve and sigmoid function.
And then we'll do another Python code demo to classify a tumor as malignant or benign based on features.
And let's start with clustering.
Suppose we have a pile of books of different genres.
Now we divide them into different groups like fiction, horror, education, and as we can see from this young lady, she definitely is into heavy horror.
You can just tell by those eyes and the maple Canadian leaf on her shirt.
But we have fiction, horror, and education, and we want to go ahead and divide our books up.
Well, organizing objects into groups based on similarity is clustering.
And in this case, as we're looking at the books, we're talking about clustering things with known categories.
But you can also use it to explore data. So you might not know the categories, you just know that you need to divide it up in some way to conquer the data and to organize it better.
But in this case, we're going to be looking at clustering in specific categories.
And let's just take a deeper look at that.
We're going to use k-means clustering.
K-means clustering is probably the most commonly used clustering tool in the machine learning library.
K-Means clustering is an example of unsupervised learning.
If you remember from our previous thing, it is used when you have unlabeled data. So we don't know the answer yet. We have a bunch of data that we want to cluster to different groups.
Define clusters in the data based on feature similarity.
So we've introduced a couple terms here. We've already talked about unsupervised learning and unlabeled data.
So we don't know the answer yet. We're just going to group stuff together and see if we can find an answer of how things connect.
We've also introduced feature similarity, features being different features of the data.
Now with books, we can easily see fiction and horror and history books, but a lot of times with data, some of that information isn't so easy to see right when we first look at it.
And so k means is one of those tools where we can start finding things that connect that match with each other.
Suppose we have these data points and want to assign them into a cluster.
Now when I look at these data points, I would probably group them into two clusters just by looking at them. I'd say two of these group of data kind of come together.
But in k-means, we pick k clusters and assign random centroids to clusters, where the k clusters represents two different clusters.
We pick k clusters and sign random centroids to the clusters, then we compute distance from objects to the centroids.
Now we form new clusters based on minimum distances and calculate the centroids.
So we figure out what the best distance is for the centroid, then we move the centroid and recalculate those distances.
Repeat previous two steps iteratively until the cluster centroids stop changing their positions and become static.
Repeat previous two steps iteratively until the cluster centroids stop changing and the positions become static.
Once the clusters become static, then k means clustering algorithm is said to be converged.
And there's another term we see throughout machine learning is converged. That means whatever math we're using to figure out the answer has come to a solution or it's converged on an answer.
Shall we see the flow chart to understand?
Make a little bit more sense by putting it into a nice easy step by step.
So we start, we choose K, we'll look at the elbow method in just a moment.
We assign random centroids to clusters, and sometimes you pick the centroids, because you might look at the data in a graph and say, oh, these are probably the central points.
Then we compute the distance from the objects to the centroids.
We take that and we form new clusters based on minimum distance and calculate their centroids.
Then we compute the distance from objects to the new centroids.
And then we go back and repeat those last two steps. We calculate the distances.
So as we're doing it, it brings into the new centroid, and then we move the centroid around and we figure out what the best which objects are closest to each centroid.
So the objects can switch from one centroid to the other as the centroids are moved around.
And we continue that until it is converged.
Let's see an example of this.
Suppose we have this data set of seven individuals and their score on two topics, A and B.
So here's our subject, in this case referring to the person taking the test.
And then we have subject A where we see what they've scored on their first subject, and we have subject B and we can see what they score on the second subject.
Now let's take two farthest apart points as initial cluster centroids.
Now remember we talked about selecting them randomly, or we can also just put them in different points and pick the furthest one apart so they move together.
Either one works okay, depending on what kind of data you're working on and what you know about it.
So we took the two furthest points, one and one, and five and seven, and now let's take the two farthest apart points as initial cluster centroids.
Each point is then assigned to the closest cluster with respect to the distance from the centroids.
So we take each one of these points in there, we measure that distance, and you can see that if we measure each of those distances, and you use the Pythagorean theorem for a triangle in this case,
because you know the x and the y and you can figure out the diagonal line from that.
Or you can just take a ruler and put it on your monitor.
That'd be kind of silly, but it would work if you're just eyeballing it.
You can see how they naturally come together in certain areas.
Now we again calculate the centroids of each cluster.
So cluster one and then cluster two, and we look at each individual dot, there's one, two, three, we're in one cluster, the centroid then moves over. It becomes one eight, comma, two three.
So remember it was that one and one.
Well, the very center of the data we're looking at would put it at the one point roughly two, two, but one eight and two three.
And the second one, if we wanted to make the overall mean vector, the average vector of all the different distances to that centroid, we come up with four, one
and five, four.
So we've now moved the centroids.
We compare each individual's distance to its own cluster, mean, and to that of the opposite cluster, and we find, build a nice chart on here,
that the as we move that centroid around, we now have a new different kind of clustering of groups, and using Euclidean distance between the points and the mean,
we get the same formula you see as new formulas coming up. So we have our individual dots, distance to the mean, centroid of the cluster, and distance to the mean centroid of the cluster.
Only individual three is nearer to the mean of the opposite cluster, cluster two, than its own cluster one.
And you can see here in the diagram where we've kind of circled that one in the middle.
So when we've moved the centroids of the clusters over, one of the points shifted to the other cluster because it's closer to that group of individuals.
Thus, individual three is relocated to cluster two, resulting in a new partition.
And we regenerate all those numbers of how close they are to the different clusters.
For the new clusters, we will find the actual cluster centroids. So now we move the centroids over, and you can see that we've now formed two very distinct clusters on here.
On comparing the distance of each individual's distance to its own cluster mean and to that of the opposite cluster, we find that the data points are stable,
hence we have our final clusters.
Now if you remember I brought up a concept earlier, k mean on the k-means algorithm, choosing the right value of k will help in less number of iterations.
And to find the appropriate number of clusters in a dataset, we use the elbow method.
And within sum of squares, WSS is defined as the sum of the squared distance between each member of the cluster and its centroid.
And so you see what we've done here is we have the number of clusters.
And as you do the same k-means algorithm over the different clusters, and you calculate what that centroid looks like,
and you find the optimal, you can actually find the optimal number of clusters using the elbow of the graph is called as the elbow method.
And on this, we guessed at two just by looking at the data.
But as you can see, the slope, you actually just look for right there where the elbow is in the slope, and you have a clear answer that we want two different to start with k means equals two.
A lot of times people end up computing k-means equals two, three, four, five until they find the value which fits on the elbow joint.
Sometimes you can just look at the data, and if you're really good with that specific domain, remember domain I mentioned that last time, you'll know where to pick those numbers
and where to start guessing at what that k-value is.
So let's take this, and we're going to use a use case using k means clustering to cluster cars into brands using parameters such as horsepower,
cubic inches, make, year, etc.
So we're going to use the dataset cars data having information about three brands of cars, Toyota, Honda, and Nissan.
We'll go back to my favorite tool, the Anaconda Navigator with the Jupyter Notebook.
And let's go ahead and flip over to our Jupyter Notebook.
And in our Jupyter Notebook, I'm going to go ahead and just paste the basic code that we usually start a lot of these off with.
We're not going to go too much into this code because we've already discussed NumPy, we've already discussed Mapplot Library and Pandas, NumPy being the number array, pandas
being the pandas data frame, and mapplot for the graphing.
And don't forget since if you're using the Jupyter Notebook, you do need the Mapplot library in line so that it plots everything on the screen.
If you're using a different Python editor, then you probably don't need that because it'll have a pop-up window on your computer.
And we'll go ahead and run this just to load our libraries and our setup into here.
The next step is of course to look at our data, which I've already opened up in a spreadsheet.
And you can see here we have the miles per gallon, cylinders, cubic inches, horsepower, weight pounds, how heavy it is, time it takes to get to 60.
My card is probably on this one at about 80 or 90.
What year it is. So this is you can actually see this is kind of older cars, and then the brand Toyota, Honda, Nissan.
So the different cars are coming from all the way from 1971, if we scroll down to the 80s. we have between the 70s and 80s the number of cars that they've put out.
And let's we come back here, we're gonna do importing the data. So we'll go ahead and do dataset equals.
And we'll use pandas to read this in, and it's uh from a CSV file.
Remember you can always post this in the comments and request the data files for these.
Either in the comments here on the YouTube video or go to simplylearn.com and request that.
The CARS CSV, I put it in the same folder as the code that I've stored. So my Python code is stored in the same folder so I don't have to put the full path.
If you store them in different folders, you do have to change this and double check your name variables.
And we'll go ahead and run this, and we've chosen dataset arbitrarily because you know it's a dataset we're importing, and we've now imported our cars CSV into the dataset.
As you know, you have to prep the data. So we're going to create the X data. This is the one that we're going to try to figure out what's going on with.
And then there is a number of ways to do this, but we'll do it in a simple loop so you can actually see what's going on. So we'll do 4i nx dot columns.
So we're going to go through each of the columns and a lot of times it's important I'll make lists of the columns and do this because I might remove certain columns,
or there might be columns that I want to be processed differently.
But for this, we can go ahead and take x of i and we want to go fill in a. And that's a pandas command.
But the question is what are we going to fill the missing data with? We definitely don't want to just put in a number that doesn't actually mean something.
And so one of the tricks you can do with this is we can take x of i.
And then in addition to that we want to go ahead and turn this into an integer, because a lot of these are integers. So we'll go ahead and keep it integers. And we add the bracket here.
And a lot of editors will do this. They'll think that you're closing one bracket.
Make sure you get that second bracket in there if it's a double bracket.
That's always something that happens regularly.
So once we have our integer of x of y, this is going to fill in any missing data with the average.
And I was so busy closing one set of brackets I forgot that the mean also has brackets in there for the pandas.
So we can see here we're going to fill in all the data with the average value for that column. So if there's missing data, it's in the average of the data it does have.
then once we've done that, we'll go ahead and loop through it again and just check and see to make sure everything is filled in correctly.
And we'll print, and then we take x is null, and this returns a set of the null value or the how many lines are null, and we'll just sum that up
to see what that looks like. And so when I run this, and so with the x, what we want to do is we want to remove the last column because it had the models.
That's what we're trying to see if we can cluster these things and figure out the models.
There is so many different ways to sort the x out. For one, we could take the x and we could go dataset, our variable we're using, and use the iLocation, one of the features that's in pandas.
And we could take that and then take all the rows and all but the last column of the dataset.
And at this time we could do values. We just convert it to values.
So that's one way to do this. And if I let me just put this down here and print X, it's a capital X we chose.
And I run this, you can see it's just the values.
We could also take out the values and it's not gonna return anything because there's no values connected to it.
What I like to do with this is instead of doing the ILocation, which does integers, more common is to come in here and we have our dataset,
and we're gonna do data set dot.
or data set dot columns. And remember that lists all the columns. So if I come in here,
let me just mark that as red, and I print data set dot columns.
You can see that I have my index here. I have my mpg cylinders, everything, including the brand which we don't want.
So the way to get rid of the brand would be to do data columns of everything but the last one, minus one.
So now if I print this, you'll see the brand disappears.
And so I can actually just take dataset columns minus one,
and I'll put it right in here for the columns we're gonna look at.
And let's unmark this
and unmark this.
And now if I do an x dot head, I now have a new data frame, and you can see right here we have all the different columns except for the brand at the end of the year.
And it turns out when you start playing with the dataset, you're gonna get an error later on, and it'll say cannot convert string to
float value.
And that's because for some reason these things the way they recorded them must have been recorded as strings.
So we have a neat feature in here on pandas to convert.
And it is simply convert objects.
And for this we're gonna do convert oops convert underscore
numeric numeric equals true.
And yes, I did have to go look that up. I don't have it memorized the convert numeric in there. If I'm working with a lot of these things, I remember them.
But depending on where I'm at, what I'm doing, I usually have to look it up.
And we run that, oops, I must have missed something in here. Let me double check my spelling.
And when I double check my spelling, you'll see I missed the first underscore in the convert objects.
And when I run this, it now has everything converted into a numeric value.
Because that's what we're going to be working with is numeric values down here.
And the next part is that we need to go through the data and eliminate null values.
Most people, when they're doing small amounts, you're working with small data pools, discover afterwards that they have a null value and they have to go back and do this.
So you know be aware, whenever we're formatting this data, things are going to pop up and sometimes you go backwards to fix it.
And that's fine. That's just part of exploring the data and understanding what you have.
And I should have done this earlier, but let me go ahead and increase the size of my window one notch.
There we go.
Easier to see.
So we'll do 4i in working with x dot columns. We'll page through all the columns.
And we want to take x of i and we're going to change that we're going to alter it.
And so with this we want to go ahead and fill in x of i.
Pandas has the fill in a
and that just fills in any non-existent missing data.
And we'll put my brackets up, and there's a lot of different ways to fill this data.
If you have a really large data set, some people just void out that data because if and then look at it later in a separate exploration of data.
One of the tricks we can do is we can take our column and we can find the means.
And the means is in other our quotation marks.
So we take the columns, we're going to fill in the non-existing one with the means.
The problem is that returns a decimal float. So some of these aren't decimals.
Certainly, we need to be a little careful of doing this, but for this example, we're just going to fill it in with the integer version of this.
It keeps it on par with the other data that isn't a decimal point.
And then what we also want to do is we want to double check.
A lot of times you do this first part first to double check, then you do the fill, and then you do it again just to make sure you did it right.
So we're going to go through and test for missing data.
And one of the ways you can do that is simply go in here
and take our x of i column.
So it's going to go through the x of i column that says is null.
So it's going to return any any place there's a null value, it actually goes through the all the rows of each column is null, and then we want to go ahead and sum that.
So we take that and we add the sum value, and these are all pandas. So is null is a panda command, and so is sum.
And if we go through that and we go ahead and run it.
And we go ahead and take and run that, you'll see that all the columns have zero null values.
So we've now tested and double checked, and our data is nice and clean, we have no null values, everything is now a number value, we turned it into numeric.
And we've removed the last column in our data.
And at this point, we're actually going to start using the elbow method to find the optimal number of clusters.
So we're now actually getting into the sklearn part.
the k means clustering on here.
I guess we'll go ahead and zoom it up one more knot so you can see what I'm typing in here.
And then from sklearn, we're going to or sklearn
cluster,
we're going to import k
means.
I always forget to capitalize the k and the m when I do this.
So it's capital K, capital M, K means.
And we'll go ahead and create a um array, WCSS equals we'll make it an empty array.
If you remember from the elbow method from our slide,
within the sum of squares, WSS is defined as the sum of squared distance between each member of the cluster in a centroid.
So we're looking at that change in differences as far as a squared distance.
And we're going to run this over a number of k mean values.
In fact, let's go for i in range, we'll do eleven of them.
Range zero of eleven.
And the first thing we're going to do is we're going to create the actual we'll do it all lowercase.
so we're going to create this object
from the k-means that we just imported.
And the variable that we want to put into this is in
clusters.
we're going to set that equals to i.
That's the most important one because we're looking at how increasing the number of clusters changes our answer.
There are a lot of settings to the k-means.
Our guys in the back did a great job just kind of playing with some of them.
The most common ones that you see in a lot of stuff is how you init your k-means.
So we have k-means plus plus plus.
This is just a tool to let the model itself be smart how it picks its centroids to start with, its initial centroids.
We only want to iterate no more than 300 times. We have a max iteration we put in there.
We have the nth init, the random state equals zero.
You really don't need to worry too much about these when you're first learning this. As you start digging in deeper, you start finding that these are shortcuts that will speed up the process
as far as the setup. But the big one that we're working with is the in clusters equals i. So we're gonna literally train our k-means eleven times. We're gonna do this process eleven times.
And if you're working with big data, you know the first thing you do is you run a small sample of the data so you can test all your stuff on it.
And you can already see the problem that if I'm gonna iterate through a terabyte of data eleven times, and then the k-means itself is iterating through the data multiple times,
that's a heck of a process.
So you've got to be a little careful with this.
A lot of times though, you can find your um elbow, using the elbow method, find your optimal number on a sample of data, especially if you're working with larger data sources.
So we want to go ahead and take our k-means and we're just going to fit it.
If you're looking at any of the sklearn very common you fit your model.
if you remember correctly, our variable we're using is the capital X.
And once we fit this value, we go back to the array we made, and we want to go and just depend that value on the end.
And it's not the actual fit we're pinning in there, it's when it generates it, it generates the value you're looking for is inertia.
So k means.
And
let's get a visual on this.
We'll do our plt plot, and what we're plotting here
is first the x-axis, which is range 011, so that will generate a nice little plot there, and the WCSS
for our y-axis.
It's always nice to give our plot a title.
And let's see, we'll just give it the elbow method for the title, and let's get some labels. So let's go ahead and do plt
x label.
And what we'll do, we'll do number of clusters for that, and plt y label.
And for that we can do oops, there we go.
WCSS, since that's what we're doing on the plot on there. And finally we want to go ahead and display our graph, which is simply plt.
show.
There we go. And because we have it set to inline, it'll appear inline.
Hopefully I didn't make a type error on there.
And you can see we get a very nice graph. You can see a very nice elbow joint there at two, and again, right around three and four, and then after that there's not very much.
Now, as a data scientist, if I was looking at this, I would do either three or four, and I'd actually try both of them to see what the
output looked like.
And they've already tried this in the back, so we're just going to use three as a setup on here.
And let's go ahead and see what that looks like when we actually use this to show the different kinds of cars.
And so let's go ahead and apply the k-means to the car's dataset.
And basically we're going to copy the code that we looped through up above, where k-means equals k-means number of clusters, and we're just going to set the number of clusters to three.
Since that's what we're going to look for.
And you can do three and four on this and graph them just to see how they come up differently.
But for this we're just going to set it to three.
Go ahead and create our own variable, yk means, for our answers.
And we're going to set that equal to whoops, double equal there.
To k means.
But we're not going to do a fit. We're going to do a fit predict is the setup you want to use.
And when you're using untrained models, you'll see a slightly different, because usually you see fit and then you see just the predict.
But we want to both fit and predict the k-means on this.
And that's fit underscore predict, and then our capital X is the data we're working with.
And before we plot this data, we're going to do a little pandas trick. We're going to take our X value and we're going to set X as matrix.
So we're converting this into a nice rows and columns kind of setup, but we want the we're going to have columns equals none, so it's just going to be a matrix of data in here.
And let's go ahead and run that.
A little warning.
You'll see this warnings pop up because things are always being updated.
So there's like minor changes in the versions and future versions.
Instead of matrix, now the it's more common to set it dot values instead of doing as matrix.
But mass matrix works just fine for right now.
and you'll want to update that later on. But let's go ahead and dive in and plot this and see what that looks like.
And before we dive into plotting this data, I always like to take a look and see what I am plotting.
So let's take a look at y k means. I'm just going to print that out down here.
And we see we have an array of answers. We have two, one, zero, two, one, two.
So it's clustering these different rows of data based on the three different spaces it thinks it's going to be.
And then let's go ahead and print X and see what we have for X.
And we'll see that X is an array, it's a matrix. So we have our different values in the array.
And what we're going to do, it's very hard to plot all the different values in the array. So we're only going to be looking at the first two, or position 0 and 1.
And if you were doing a full presentation in front of the board meeting, you might actually do a little different and dig a little deeper into the different aspects,
because this is all the different columns we looked at. But we'll only look at columns one and two for this to make it easy.
So let's go ahead and clear this data out of here and let's bring up our plot. And we're going to do a scatter plot here. So PLT, scatter.
And
this looks a little complicated, so let's explain what's going on with this.
We're going to take the x values
and we're only interested in y of k means equals zero, the first cluster.
Okay?
And then we're going to take value zero for the x-axis, and then we're going to do the same thing here.
We're only interested in k means equals zero, but we're going to take the second column. So we're only looking at the first two columns in our answer or in the data.
And then the guys in the back played with this a little bit to make it pretty.
And they discovered that it looks good with as a size equals 100. That's the size of the dots.
We're going to use red for this one. And when they were looking at the data and what came out, it was definitely the Toyota on this. We're just going to go ahead and label it Toyota.
Again, that's something you really have to explore in here as far as playing with those numbers and see what looks good.
We'll go ahead and hit enter in there.
And I'm just going to paste in the next two lines, which is the next two cars.
And this is our NISA and Honda.
And you'll see with our scatter plot we're now looking at where y underscore k means equals one.
And we want the zero column and y k means equals two. Again, we're looking at just the first two columns, zero and one, and each of these rows then corresponds to Nissan and Honda.
And I'll go ahead and hit enter on there.
And finally, let's take a look and put the centroids on there.
Again, we're going to do a scatter plot.
And on the centroids, you can just pull that from our k means, the model we created, dot cluster centers, and we're going to just do
All of them in the first number, and all of them in the second number, which is 0, 1, because you always start with 0 and 1.
And then they were playing with the size and everything to make it look good, we'll do a size of 300.
We're gonna go make the color yellow, and we'll label them so it's good to have some good labels, centroids.
And then we do want to do a title.
PLT title.
And pop up there.
PLT title, because you always want to make your graphs look pretty, and we'll call it clusters of car make.
And one of the features of the plot library is you can add a
legend.
It'll automatically bring in it since we've already labeled the different aspects of the legend with Toyota, Nissan, and Honda.
And finally we want to go ahead and show.
So we can actually see it. And remember it's in line.
so if you're using a different editor that's not the Jupyter Notebook, you'll get a pop-up of this.
And you should have a nice set of clusters here.
So we can look at this and we have uh clusters of Honda and green, Toyota and red, Nissan and purple, and you can see where they put the centroids to separate them.
Now, when we're looking at this, we can also plot a lot of other different data on here as far because we only looked at the first two columns.
This is just column one and two, or zero, one as as you label them in computer scripting.
But you can see here we have a nice clusters of car make, and we've been able to pull out the data, and you can see how just these two columns form very distinct clusters of data.
So if you were exploring new data, you might take a look and say, well, what makes these different?
Almost going in reverse, you start looking at the data and pulling apart the columns to find out why is the first group set up the way it is.
Maybe you're doing loans and you want to go, well, why is this group not defaulting on their loans, and why is the last group defaulting on their loans?
And why is the middle group 50% defaulting on their bank loans?
And you start finding ways to manipulate the data and pull out the answers you want.
So now that you've seen how to use k-mean for clustering, let's move on to the next topic.
Now let's look into logistic regression.
The logistic regression algorithm is the simplest classification algorithm used for binary or multi-classification problems.
And we can see we have our little girl from Canada who's into horror books is back.
That's actually really scary when you think about that with those big eyes.
In the previous tutorial, we learned about linear regression, dependent and independent variables.
So to brush up, y equals mx plus c, a very basic algebraic function of y and x.
The dependent variable is the target class variable we are going to predict.
The independent variables, x1 all the way up to xn, are the features or attributes we're going to use to predict the target class.
We know what a linear regression looks like, but using the graph we cannot divide the outcome into categories.
It's really hard to categorize 1.5, 3.6, 9.8.
for example, a linear regression graph can tell us that with increase in number of hours studied, the marks of a student will increase,
but it will not tell us whether the student will pass or not.
In such cases where we need the output as categorical value, we will use logistic regression.
And for that we're going to use the sigmoid function.
So you can see here we have our marks, 0 to 100, number of hours studied, that's going to be what they're comparing it to in this example.
And we usually form a line that says y equals mx plus c.
And when we use the sigmoid function, we have p equals one over one plus e to the minus y.
It generates a sigmoid curve.
And so you can see right here, when you take the ln, which is the natural logarithm, I always thought it should be n l, not ln, that's just the inverse of
e, or e to the minus y.
And so when we do this we get ln of p over one minus p equals m times x plus c.
That's the sigmoid curve function we're looking for.
And we can zoom in on the function, and you'll see that the function as it derives goes to one or to zero, depending on what your x value is.
And the probability if it's greater than 0.5, the value is automatically rounded off to one, indicating that the student will pass.
So if they're doing a certain amount of studying, they will probably pass.
Then you have a threshold value at the 0 five.
It automatically puts that right in the middle usually.
And your probability if it's less than 0.5, the value rounded off to 0, indicating the student will fail.
So if they're not studying very hard, they're probably going to fail.
This of course is ignoring the outliers of that one student who's just a natural genius and doesn't need any studying to memorize everything.
That's not me, unfortunately. I have to study hard to learn new stuff.
Problem statement to classify whether a tumor is malignant or benign.
And this is actually one of my favorite data sets to play with because it has so many features, and when you look at them, you really are hard to understand.
You can't just look at them and know the answer.
So it gives you a chance to kind of dive into what data looks like when you aren't able to understand the specific domain of the data.
But I also want you to remind you that in the domain of medicine, if I told you that my probability was really good at classified things at
say 90% or 95%, and I'm classifying whether you're going to have a malignant or a benign tumor, I'm guessing that you're going to go get it tested anyways.
So you've got to remember the domain we're working with.
So why would you want to do that if you know you're just going to go get a biopsy because you know it's that serious? This is like an all or nothing.
Just referencing the domain, it's important.
It might help the doctor know where to look just by understanding what kind of tumor it is.
So it might help them or aid them in something they missed from before.
So let's go ahead and dive into the code and I'll come back to the domain part of it in just a minute.
So use case, and we're going to do our normal imports here, we're importing numpy, Pandas, CBORN, the Matplot Library,
and we're going to do Matplotlibrary in line since I'm going to switch over to Anaconda.
So let's go ahead and flip over there and get this started.
So I've opened up a new window in my Anaconda Jupyter Notebook.
And by the way, Jupyter Notebook, you don't have to use Anaconda for the Jupyter Notebook.
I just love the interface and all the tools that Anaconda brings.
So we got our import numpy as in P for our NumPy number array. We have our pandas PD.
We're going to bring in Cborn to help us with our graphs as SNS.
So many really nice tools in both CBON and Matplotlibrary.
And we'll do our Matplotlibrary.pyplot as plt, and then of course we want to let it know to do it in line. let's go ahead and just run that so it's all set up.
And we're just going to call our data data. Not creative today, equals PD, and this happens to be in a csv file.
So we'll use a pd.read underscore csv, and I happen to name the file I renamed it data for p2.csv.
You can of course write in the comments below the YouTube and request for the dataset itself or go to the Simply Learn website, and we'll be happy to supply that for you.
And let's just open up the data before we go any further, and let's just see what it looks like in a spreadsheet.
So when I pop it open in a local spreadsheet, this is just a CSV file, comma separated variables, we have an ID.
So I guess the categorizes for reference or what ID which test was done, the diagnosis, M for malignant, B for B9. So there's two different options on there.
And that's what we're going to try to predict is the M and B and test it.
And then we have like the radius mean or average, the texture average, perimeter mean, area mean, smoothness.
I don't know about you, but unless you're a doctor in the field, most of the stuff, I mean you can guess what concave means just by the term concave.
But I really wouldn't know what that means in the measurements they're taking.
So they have all kinds of stuff like how smooth it is, the symmetry, and these are all float values. We can just page through them real quick.
And you'll see there's I believe 36 if I remember correctly in this one.
So there's a lot of different values they take, and all these measurements they take when they go in there and they take a look at the different growth, the tumorous growth.
So back in our data, and I put this in the same folder as a code. So I saved this code in that folder.
Obviously, if you have it in a different location, you want to put the full path in there.
And we'll just do um pandas
first five lines of data with the data.head.
And we run that, we can see that we have pretty much what we just looked at. We have an ID, we have a diagnosis.
If we go all the way across, you'll see all the different columns coming across displayed nicely for our data.
And while we're exploring the data, our uh C born, which we referenced as SNS, makes it very easy to go in here and do a joint plot.
You'll notice that it's very similar to because it is sitting on top of the plot library.
So the joint plot does a lot of work for us.
And we're just going to look at the first two columns that we're interested in, the radius mean and the texture mean.
We'll just look at those two columns.
And data equals data.
So that tells it which two columns we're plotting, and then we're going to use the data that we pulled in. Let's just run that.
And it generates a really nice graph on here.
And there's all kinds of cool things on this graph to look at. I mean we have the texture mean and the radius mean, obviously the axes.
You can also see
and one of the cool things on here is you can also see the histogram.
They show that for the radius mean.
Where is the most common radius mean come up and where the most common texture is?
So we're looking at the
on each growth its average texture and on each radius its average radius on there.
It's a little confusing because we're talking about the individual objects average, and then we can also look over here and see the histogram showing us the median
or how common each measurement is.
And that's only two columns, so let's dig a little deeper into C-borne.
They also have a heat map.
And if you're not familiar with heat maps, a heat map just means it's in color. That's all that means. Heat map.
I guess the original ones were plotting heat density on something, and so ever since then it's just called a heat map.
And we're gonna take our data and get our corresponding numbers to put that into the heat map, and that's simply data.corr for that.
That's a pandas expression.
remember we're working in a pandas data frame, so that's one of the cool tools in pandas for our data.
And let's just pull that information into a heat map and see what that looks like.
And you'll see that we're now looking at all the different features.
We have our ID, we have our texture, we have our area, our compactness, concave points.
And if you look down the middle of this chart, diagonal, going from the upper left to bottom right, it's all white.
That's because when you compare texture to texture, they're identical. So they're a hundred percent, or in this case a perfect one in their correspondence.
And you'll see that when you look at say area or right below it, it has almost a black on there when you compare it to texture.
So these have almost no corresponding data. They don't really form a linear graph or something that you can look at and say how connected they are, they're very scattered data.
This is really just a really nice graph to get a quick look at your data.
It doesn't so much change what you do, but it changes verifying.
So when you get an answer or something like that, or you start looking at some of these individual pieces, you might go, hey, that doesn't match.
According to showing our heat map, this should not correlate with each other. And if it is, you're gonna have to start asking, well, why? What's going on, what else is coming in there?
But it does show some really cool information on here.
we can see from the ID, there's no real one feature that just says, if you go across the top line, that lights up.
There's no one feature that says, hey, if the area is a certain size, then it's going to be benign or malignant.
It says there's some that sort of add up.
And that's a big hint in the data that we're trying to ID this, whether it's malignant or benign, that's a big hint to us as data scientists to go,
okay, we can't solve this with any one feature.
It's going to be something that includes all the features or many of the different features to come up with a solution for it.
And while we're exploring the data, let's explore one more area and let's look at data.isnull.
We want to check for null values in our data.
If you remember from earlier in this tutorial, we did it a little differently where we added stuff up and summed them up.
You can actually with pandas do it really quickly data.is null and summit and it's going to go across all the columns.
So when I run this,
you're going to see all the columns come up with no null data.
So we've just just to rehash these last few steps,
we've done a lot of exploration.
We have looked at the first two columns
and seen how they plot with the seaborne with a joint plot which shows both the histogram and the data plotted on the X and Y coordinates.
And obviously, you can do that more in detail
with different columns and see how they plot together.
And then we took and did the Cborne heat map, the SNS dot heat map of the data.
And you can see right here where it did a nice job showing us some bright spots where stuff correlates with each other and forms a very nice combination
or points of scattering points.
And you can also see areas that don't.
And then finally we went ahead and checked the data.
Is the data null value?
Do we have any missing data in there?
Very important step because it'll crash later on.
If you forget to do this step, it will remind you when you get that nice error code that says null values.
Okay. So not a big deal if you miss it, but it's no fun having to go back when you're you're in a huge process and you've missed this step,
and now you're ten steps later and you've got to go remember where you were pulling the data in.
So we need to go ahead and pull out our X and our Y.
So we just put that down here.
And we'll set the X equal to.
And there's a lot of different options here.
Certainly we could do X equals all the columns except for the first two.
Because if you remember the first two is the ID and the diagnosis.
So that certainly would be an option.
But what we're going to do is we're actually going to focus on the worst.
The worst radius, the worst texture, parameter, area, smoothness, compactness, and so on.
One of the reasons to start dividing your data up when you're looking at this information is sometimes the data will be the same data coming in.
So if I have two measurements coming into my model, it might overweigh them.
It might overpower the other measurements because it's basically taking that information in twice.
That's a little bit past the scope of this tutorial.
What I want you to take away from this though is that we are dividing the data up into pieces, and our team in the back went ahead and said, hey, let's just look at the worst.
So I'm going to create a an array, and you'll see this array radius worst, texture worst, perimeter worst.
We've just taken the worst of the worst, and I'm just going to put that in my X.
So this X is still a pandas data frame, but it's just those columns.
And our y, if you remember correctly, is going to be, oops, hold on one second.
It's not x, it's data.
There we go. So x equals data, and then it's a list of the different columns, the worst of the worst.
And if we're going to take that, then we have to have our answer for our y for the stuff we know.
And if you remember correctly, we're just going to be looking at
the diagnosis. That's all we care about is what is it diagnosed? Is it uh benign or malignant?
And since it's a single column, we can just do diagnosis. Oh, I forgot to put the brackets around the there we go.
Okay.
So it's just diagnosis on there, and we can also real quickly do like x dot head if you want to see what that looks like.
And y.head
and run this.
And you'll see it only does the last one, I forgot about that if you don't do print.
You can see that the the Y dot head is just mmm because the first ones are all malignant.
And if I run this, the x.head is just the first five values of radius worst, texture worst, parameter worst, area worst, and so on.
I'll go ahead and take that out.
So moving down to the next step, we've built our two data sets, our answer, and then the features we want to look at.
In data science, it's very important to test your model.
So we do that by splitting the data.
And from SK Learn Model Selection, we're going to import train test splits. We're going to split it into two groups.
There are so many ways to do this. I noticed in one of the more modern ways they actually split it into three groups, and then you model each group and test it against the other groups.
So you have all kinds of and there's reasons for that, which is past the scope of this, and for this particular example isn't necessary.
For this, we're just going to split it into two groups, one to train our data and one to test our data.
And the sklearn dot model selection, we have train test split.
You could write your own quick code to do this. We just randomly divide the data up into two groups, but they do it for us nicely.
And we actually can almost we can actually do it in one statement with this, where we're going to generate four variables capital X train, capital X
test.
So we have our training data we're going to use to fit the model, and then we need something to test it.
And then we have our Y train, so we're going to train the answer, and then we have our test. So this is the stuff we want to see how good it did on our model.
And we'll go ahead and take our train test split that we just imported.
And we're going to do X and our Y, our two different data that's going in for our split.
And then the guys in the back came up and wanted us to go ahead and use a test size equals 0.3.
That's test underscore size.
Random state, it's always nice to kind of switch a random state around, but not that important.
What this means is that the test size is we're going to take 30% of the data and we're going to put that into our test variables, our y test and our X test.
And we're going to do 70% into the X train and the Y train. So we're going to use 70% of the data to train our model and 30% to test it.
Let's go ahead and run that and load those up.
So now we have all our stuff split up and all our data ready to go.
And now we get to the actual logistics part. We're actually going to create our model.
So let's go ahead and bring that in from sklearn. We're going to bring in our linear model and we're going to import logistic regression. That's the actual model we're using.
And this we'll call it logmodel.
Oops, there we go. Model.
And let's just set this equal to our logistic regression that we just imported.
So now we have a variable log model set to that class for us to use.
And with most of the models in the sklearn, we just need to go ahead and fix it, fit, do a fit on there,
and we use our X train that we separated out with our Y train.
And let's go ahead and run this. So once we've run this, we'll have a model that fits this data, that 70% of our training data.
And of course it prints this out that tells us all the different variables that you can set on there. There's a lot of different choices you can make.
But for word, do we're just going to let all the defaults set.
We don't really need to mess with those on this particular example.
And there's nothing in here that really stands out as super important until you start fine-tuning it. But for what we're doing, the basics will work just fine.
And then let's we need to go ahead and test out our model. Is it working?
So let's create a variable y predict.
And this is going to be equal to our log model.
And we want to do a predict. Again, very standard format for the sklearn library is taking your model and doing a predict on it.
And we're going to test y predict against the y test. So we want to know what the model thinks it's going to be. That's what our y predict is.
And with that we want the capital X X test.
So we have our train set and our test set.
And now we're going to do our y predict.
And let's go ahead and run that.
And if we print
y predict, let me go ahead and run that.
You'll see it comes up and it
prints a nice array of B and M for B9 and Malignant
for all the different test data we put in there.
So it does pretty good. We're not sure exactly how good it does, but we can see that it actually works and is functional.
It was very easy to create.
You'll always discover with our data science that as you explore this, you spend a significant amount of time prepping your data
and making sure your data coming in is good.
There's a saying, good data in, good answers out, bad data in, bad answers out.
That's only half the thing.
That's only half of it.
Selecting your models becomes the next part as far as how good your models are.
And then of course fine tuning it depending on what model you're using.
So we come in here, we want to know how good this came out. So we have our y predict here, logmodel.predict x test.
So, for deciding how good our model is, we're going to go from the sklearn.metrics, we're going to import classification report.
And that just reports how good our model is doing.
And then we're going to feed it the model data. let's just print this out.
And we'll take our classification report
and we're going to put into there
test, our actual data.
So this is what we actually know is true.
And our prediction, what our model predicted for that data on the test side.
And let's run that and see what that does.
So we pull that up, you'll see that we have a precision for B9 and malignant, B and M.
And we have a precision of 93 and 91, a total of 92, so it's kind of the average between these two, of 92. There's all kinds of different information on here. Your F1 score,
your recall, your support coming through on this.
And for this, I'll go ahead and just flip back to our slides that they put together for describing it.
And so here we're going to look at the precision using the classification report. And you see this is the same printout I had up above.
Some of the numbers might be different because it does randomly pick out which data we're using.
So this model is able to predict the type of tumor with 91% accuracy.
So we look back here, you'll see where we have B9 am in England. It actually is 92 coming up here.
But we're looking at about a 92, 91% precision.
And remember I reminded you about domains. So when we're talking about the domain of a medical domain with a very catastrophic outcome, you know, at 91 or 92% precision,
you're still gonna go in there and have somebody do a biopsy on it.
Very different than if you're investing money and there's a 92% chance you're gonna earn 10%
and 8% chance you're gonna lose 8%, you're probably gonna bet the money.
Because at that odds it's pretty good that you'll make some money. And in the long run, if you do that enough, you definitely will make money.
And also with this domain, I've actually seen them use this to identify different forms of cancer.
That's one of the things that they're starting to use these models for.
Because then it helps the doctor know what to investigate.
So that wraps up this section.
We're finally we're going to go in there and let's discuss the answer to the quiz asked in Machine Learning Tutorial Part 1.
Can you tell what's happening in the following cases?
Grouping documents into different categories based on the topic and content of each document.
This is an example of clustering where k-means clustering can be used to group the documents by topics using bag of words approach.
So if you've gotten in there that you're looking for clustering, and hopefully you had at least one or two examples like k-means that are used for clustering different things,
then give yourself a two thumbs up.
b.
Identifying handwritten digits and images correctly.
This is an example of classification.
The traditional approach to solving this would be to extract digit-dependent features like curvature of different digits, etc., and then use a classifier like SVM to distinguish between images.
Again, if you got the fact that it's a classification example, give yourself a thumb up.
And if you're able to go, hey, let's use SVM or another model for this, give yourself those two thumbs up on it.
C.
Behavior of a website indicating that the site is not working as designed.
This is an example of anomaly detection.
In this case, the algorithm learns what is normal and what is not normal, usually by observing the logs of the website.
Give yourself a thumbs up if you got that one.
And just for a bonus, can you think of another example of anomaly detection?
One of the ones I use it for my own business is detecting anomalies in stock markets.
Stock markets are very fickle and they behave very erratic.
So finding those erratic areas and then finding ways to track down why they're erratic.
Was something released in social media, was something released you can see where knowing where that anomaly is can help you to figure out what the answer is to it in another area.
D.
Predicting salary of an individual based on his or her years of experience.
This is an example of regression.
This problem can be mathematically defined as a function between independent years of experience and dependent variables, salary of an individual.
And if you guess that this was a regression model, give yourself a thumbs up.
And if you're able to remember that it was between independent and dependent variables and that terms, give yourself two thumbs up.
Summary.
So to wrap it up, we went over what is k means.
and We went through also the chart of choosing your elbow method and assigning a random centroid to the clusters,
computing the distance, and then going in there and figuring out what the minimum centroids is and computing the distance and going through that loop until it gets the perfect centroid.
And we looked into the elbow method to choose for based on running our clusters across a number of variables and finding the best location for that.
We did a nice example of clustering cars with K means, even though we only looked at the first two columns to make it simple and easy to graph.
You can easily extrapolate that and look at all the different columns and see how they all fit together.
And we looked at what is logistic regression.
We discussed the sigmoid function, what is logistic regression, and then we went into an example of classifying tumors with logistics.
I hope you enjoyed part two of machine learning.
So in today's session, we will discuss what RNN model is, moving ahead.
We will see why should we use RNN.
After that, we will see how does RNN work, the current neural network.
After covering these topics, we will move forward and see types of RNN, recurrent neural network, and applications of RNN.
At the end, we will do a hands-off live demo of sentiment analysis using RNN.
So before starting, let us have a simple question to brush our knowledge. So, question is what are the application of RNN? Okay, NLP,
time series, image captioning, and all of the above.
Please answer in the comment section below and we will update the correct answer in the pinned comments or you can pause this video, give it a thought, and answer in the comment section.
Before we move on to the programming part, let's discuss what RNN is and proceed further for the same. So, what is RNN? Recurrent neural network.
So RNN work on the principle of saving output on a particular layer and feeding this back to the input in order to predict the output of the layer.
This is how can convert a feed neural network into a recurrent neural network, RNN.
The node in different layers of neural network are compressed to form a single layer of recurrent neural network.
A, B, and C are the parameters of neural network.
Now that you understand what RNN is, let's look at the way why RNN.
Okay. So why RNN?
RNN were created because there are few issues in the feed forward neural network. Cannot handle the sequential data, considers only the current input, cannot memorize previous input.
Okay, so the solution of these issues is RNN.
and RNN can handle sequential data accepting the current input data and previously received input data. So RNN can memorize previous input due to their internal memory.
So moving forward, let's see how does RNN networks work.
Okay, so the input layer X takes an input to the neural network and process it and passes it into the middle layer.
The middle layer H can consist of multiple hidden layers, each with its own activation function and weight and biases.
If you have a neural network where the various parameters of different hidden layer are not affected by the previous layer, that is the neural network
does not have the memory, then you can use RNN.
So the RNN will standardize the different activation function and weights and biases so that each hidden layer has the same parameter.
Then instead of creating multiple hidden layers, it will create one and loop over it as many times it has required. So moving forward, let's see types of RNN. So there are four types of RNN
one to one,
one to many, many to many, and many to one.
So let's see one to one RNN.
So this type of neural network is known as the vanilla neural network it is used for general machine learning problem which has a single input and a single output.
Now see
one to many RNN.
This type of neural network has a single input and multiple outputs.
An example of this is an image captioning.
Now let's see many to one RNN.
This RNN take a sequence of input and generates a single output.
Sentiment analysis is a good example of this kind of neural network where a given sentence can be classified as expressing positive or negative sentiment.
And the last one is many to many RNN.
This RNN takes a sequence of inputs and generates a sequence of output.
Machine translation is the one of the example.
So moving forward, let's see application of recurrent neural network.
First one is
image captioning.
RNNs are used to caption an image by analyzing the activities present.
The second one is time series prediction.
Any time series problem like predicting the prices of stocks in a particular month can be solved using RNN.
And the third one is natural language processing.
Text mining and sentiment analysis can be carried out using RNN for NLP, natural language processing.
The fourth one is machine translation.
Given an input in one language, RNNs can be used to translate the input into different language as output. So now let's move to the programming part.
First we will import some libraries, major libraries for the first we will import for the data frame.
So I will write import
panda
spt.
The second one is import
numpy as np.
So pandas is a software library written for the Python programming language for data manipulation and analysis.
In particular, it offers a data structure and operations for manipulating numerical tables and the time series.
And this numpy.
Numpy is a library for the Python programming language adding support to four large multi-dimensional array and matrices along with a large
collection of high-level mathematical function to operate on these arrays.
Okay So for plotting, we will import some libraries like C bond
as
This is nothing just a short form of we don't have to write again and again C bond, C bond. We can write SNS.
So then, another one: from
word _cloud,
import
word
_cloud.lib;
dot
pyplot
as plt.
Okay, so cbon is a library that uses matplotlib underneath to plot graphs.
It will be used to visualize random distribution.
And the word cloud is a visual representation
of words.
Cloud creators are used to highlight popular words and phrases based on frequency and relevance.
They provide you with quick and simple visual insights that can lead to more in-depth analysis.
And this matplotlib.
Matplotlib is a plotting library for the Python programming language and its numerical mathematical
extension number.
It provides an object-oriented API for embedding plots into application using general purpose UI.
Okay, like
Tinker, X Python, QT or GTK.
So let's import some
NLTK
natural Language Toolkit.
So
I will write import
NLTK.
From
NLTK
dot stem
import
corpus,
and
from
Ltget.
N Ltk.
The natural language toolkit, or more commonly, NLTK, is a suite of libraries and programs for symbolic and statical natural language processing for English
written in Python programming language.
And this is stop words.
Stop words are words that are so common they are basically ignored by typical tokenizers.
And this word tokenize is a function in Python that splits a given sentence into words using the analytical library.
Okay, so let's import some scikit learn
library.
So for that I will write from sklearn
dot model
collection
import
train
test.
Okay.
Then from
SKLarn
dot feature
extraction,
dot text import
vectorizer.
And then from
sk learn.matrices
matrix
import
confusion metric
classification.
Okay.
So scikit-learn is a free source software machine learning library for Python programming language.
It features various classification, regression, and clustering algorithms, including support vector machine learning, logistic regression, and many others, like
random forest classifier.
And this train test split method is used to split our data into train and test set.
First, we need to divide our data into features like X and Y labels.
And this TFID vectorizer converts a collection of raw documents into a matrix of TF or IDF features, the fast text
or what to vectorize or what embedding Python implementation.
And this confusion matrix. A confusion matrix is a table that is used to define the performance of a classification algorithm.
Okay,
then we'll import some libraries like from
SKL
dot
linear model,
importistic
regression
from
killed
and from
killer
symbol
random
forest classifier.
Okay.
Then from
ask learn today.
Okay.
So everything is correct.
You will see while running.
So logistic regression estimate the probability of an event occurring, such as voted or didn't vote, based on a given dataset of the independent variable.
Sorry, linear support vector machine SVC is an algorithm that attempts to find a hyperplane to maximize the distance
between classified samples.
And this random forest classifier creates a set of decision trees from a randomly selected subset of the training set.
And this Bernoulli and Vernolly name base is a part of the name base family. It is based on Bernoulli distribution and accept only binary values that is zero or one.
So let's import some tensor flow. So import
tensor flow,
compad, dot v2
and
import
tensor flow
datasets
as TFTS.
So TensorFlow is a free and open source library for machine learning and artificial intelligence across a range of tasks, but has a particular focus on training and inference of deep neural networks.
Okay, let's import
warnings.
So everything is basic, just let's see the pickle. Pickle is a Python is primarily used in serializing and deserializing a Python object structure.
Okay, let's run it.
Let's see how many other.
After that, we will load the data set and we will go through data visualization.
Okay, word cloud cannot import name word cloud. Okay, C is C will be capital here.
Okay,
it's still loading here.
Let's see.
Okay, so loading is done.
So now let's load the data set. So, we'll write: data equals to pd dot
data suite,
underscore, csv,
dataset name,
test.
So
you can find this data set on the description box below.
Perhaps you forget, come over
to the, okay? It's
fine.
Let me change this first
is using RNN.
So here, I will write data, person
data.sample
to one.
So let me like brief, uh, tell you that what we are going, okay?
Let me brief you like what we will do in this sentiment analysis using RN.
So in this demo, like you will see text processing on Twitter dataset, and after that we will perform different machine learning algorithms on the data such as logistic regression,
random forest classifier, SPC name base to classify positive and negative data.
After that, I will also build RNN recurrent neural network, which is the best fit for such textual sentiment analysis.
Okay, since it's a sequential data set, which is requirement for the RNN network.
So let's dive into.
So now
we will see the data, data visualization, data set details target like the polarity of the tweets, zero negative, okay, then the date,
like date of the tweet, and the polarity and the user that what tweeted, then the text.
Okay, so I will write print
data set
shape
data
comma shape.
Okay,
it let me first do like this, yeah.
So there are 20
or you can say two like rows and six number of columns.
Okay, so it is a huge data.
I will you can find this data set from the description box below.
So here let's see the data,
and why I use head, head is used for like
for showing
top ten rows of the dataset.
If you will use tail instead of head, it will show the last 10 rows of the dataset.
Okay, here polarity zero, zero means negative and four means positive.
Okay, like you can consider zero one.
This is ID, date, then query, then user, then the text.
Okay, so
that I will do data
polarity.
Okay,
these are the zero, four, okay. Uniqueness zero means negative and the four means positive.
Yeah, replacing the value four as one for the ease of understanding. What I said to you, you can consider as zero, one.
so data,
polarity,
data,
four to one.
data.
Now you can see zero one zero one zero one one zero.
Okay.
So if you will write only head, it will show the top five rows only.
So now let's use one Python function describe
data dot.
Right.
So as you can see here, count is two like,
and the mean of the particular row is this,
and the ID is this standard deviation, minimum value, the 25%, the 50%, and the 75%, and the maximum.
Okay.
So let's see the number of positive versus negative tag the sentence.
So here, I will write: Positives
was to data
polarity,
data. dot polarity
was equals. one.
then it is
data.
polarity.
Polarity
is equal to
zero. Shape.
now I will print
the total length, the negative, and the positives.
Okay, so number of
positive.
I will copy
this and paste it here.
And here I will do the changes for the negatives.
Okay, now let's see.
So here polarity is not defined.
So
you as you can see the total length of the data is two lakh, and the number of positive sentences is
like 146 number
of negatives okay.
The number of negative text sentences 99,954.
Okay, so now we have a brief data.
So now let's get a word count per of text.
So for this,
I will write
count
ten words,
length of
first dot split.
now let's plot a word count distribution for both positive and negative.
So I will create a bar plot. So for that, I will add it
but
data
text
dot apply
count.
Okay.
Then I will write P positive equals to data
count
data dot polarity
equals to one.
let me copy this only. I
will write 0
and
Okay, then
PLT figure
and figure size
cost to
twelve, comma six,
then P L T,
L T dot
forty five,
then P L T, dot X level,
word count,
PLT, dot, Y level,
and frequency
will write
G
alpha equals to zero. five
positive.
Okay, then let's make a legend also.
Location should be
right
walls.
Data word count priority goes to
... Okay, my bad.
So, as you can see, the positive and the negatives.
Okay.
So these are the like word count distribution for both positive and negative.
So now let's uh what we can do, we can do the get like get the common words in training dataset
for the training dataset.
So for that, I will do:
from
collections
import
Counter.
All
words
pursue
or
test
data
text
to line,
dot,
split
or word
and
words.
if length of
word
and
two
all
words.lower
(). Here, I can write counter.
all words,
dot most
common.
then I need twenty.
As you can see, these are the most common words used, like in every sentence, the and you for have that I am but just
like this out over all.
So
these are the most common words, like it used those used like 64,000 times and like this UR is used for a thousand
times,
doing like that.
So now we will do some data pro data processing.
Okay, now let's do the data processing.
So, map
live
and SNS dot
count plot
data,
polarity.
These are the negatives and this positives.
There is a slight change I guess
that is why it's not looking
so much of different, like there's a slight
46 different, so that is why it's looking almost same.
Okay,
so now removing the unnecessary columns like query, user word count
data. dot Drop
it,
very
what count.
Okay.
a
true.
here I will write data
what on this okay, my bad.
Here, I will write data. Dot drop
ID,
comma access,
pursue one,
then data. dot Head
the data.
See we have only the two the polarity and the text.
Okay.
let's see the null values.
So data
dot.
data
Okay.
So now converting Panda's object to a string type.
For that, we have to write
text,
pursuit, data,
text
type,
that,
yes, I.
So now, download the stop words. NLTK
download
words,
words
also said
stop words.
in English.
Stop words.
these are some, you know, stop words.
So moving forward, let's download
and I'll take a dot
download.
Okay.
So
the pre-processing steps taken are like lower casting. Each text is converted to lowercase, then remover of URLs will do this.
Okay. Links starting with HTTP or HTTPS or WW are replaced by like
commas and removing usernames, removing short words, removing stop words, like climatization is the process
will do of con for the converting a word to its base.
Okay.
So for that,
what I will do,
we'll just copy the whole code for you.
Will explain you one by one what I've done.
Okay.
So this is a course for the URL pattern for removing all the ww https and http type of thing,
and removing
them.
and I have used pattern for the lower casting removing all the URL.
Okay.
Then removing all the usernames like at the red and removing punctuations and stop words.
Okay, like this.
So now, what we have to do. data
processed
tweets
and data
text,
apply
lambda X
process
and tweets,
and print.
next
preprocessing
time.
Okay.
As you can see, the text put pre-processing is
done. So now let's check
data.
As
you can see, see the at the rate and this slices are gone.
Okay.
So now the text is pre-processed.
So now what we will do, we will analyze the data.
So now we are going to analyze the pre-processed data to get an understanding of it. We will plot word clouds for positive and negative tweets from our data set and see which words occurs the most.
Okay, first we will create for the negative words or negative tweets. You can see.
so.
I will add plt dot figure
and figure size.
Fifteen, comma, fifteen.
Okay.
Then word cloud cost to
bird
cloud
max words
equals to
two thousand, comma.
Right equals to
sixteen hundred,
comma
height cost to
eight hundred,
and rate
join the data.
dot polarity;
then
I will write here polarity.
Okay, what equals zero
now again
processed tweets.
Then, here
I have to write:
PLT show,
may show
W Cher
polation.
bilinear.
Perhaps you forget the comma here.
then comma bit
dot generate
what I can do.
Let me run now.
Let's see.
Hope this time it will work.
Okay, like today I am and work, don't wish, they need, much.
These are the most negative tweets.
Okay, words from negative tweets you can say.
Right?
So let's see the positive tweets.
Okay.
So the thing will be the same.
paste it here. So for this, I will do
one.
Take a little bit of time
to come.
Still loading.
Like as you can see, hate can't.
Okay.
Sorry,
these are the negative words.
Okay, still loading.
So let's wait for like a few seconds.
Now you can see the positive words like love, okay. Good,
lol,
and awesome, something like that.
Okay, so these are some
positive words.
So now let's do the vectorization and splitting the data, like storing into input variable process tweets to X and output variable polarity to Y.
Okay, we'll do that.
So, X equals to data
process
tweets,
values,
and y equals to
data
dot
values.
Okay.
Now I will write print
text dot shape
print by dot shape.
Okay, cool. So now what we will do, we will convert text to word frequency vectors.
Okay, t a tf to idf. So this is an acronym that stands for term frequency to inverse document frequency, which are the components of the resulting scores
assigned to each word.
Okay, so term frequency this summarizes how often a given in word appears within a document and inverse document frequency this downscales
word that appear a lot across documents.
Okay, so now here we will convert a collection of raw documents to a matrix of TF to IDF features.
Okay, then I will write,
enter
t IDF revisor
and sublinear
X, because
print
number of features,
comma, length
director,
names.
So number of feature words are like one seven zero three to one.
Okay, now we will do like
now let's rent the shape.
So the previous data is divided into two sets of data training data and the testing data.
So data set upon which the model would be trained on contains 80% data.
The test data is the data set upon which model would be tested again contains 20% of data.
So for that, I will write: extrain
test
train
test size
equals to 0.20.
Random
state
was one zero one.
So
what I will do, I will do the you know, print the shape of X train, Y train, X text, Y test. Like how many columns are there? Rows, not column exactly, the rows are there. Okay,
so I will paste there.
So see
X train, like this is a total was like two lakh.
Okay, so one lakh sixty thousand in training, as we discussed earlier, like 80% in training and 20%
in testing.
Okay,
so now let's do the model building,
okay.
Model evaluating functions.
So now let's make a model,
okay.
And first I will do I will write and then I will explain you the whole.
Okay.
So here what I did it this will tell you the accuracy of the model of training data and the testing data.
Okay, then we will predict the values for test data set and the evaluation for the data set, then we will compute and plot the confusion matrix,
okay. The both the categories negative positives, okay. Group name will be true, negative, and the false positive. Okay,
so
is nothing that's let's run it.
So now what we will do? We will do first for the logistic regression.
So here I will write LG goes to
logistic
regression.
Okay, then history
goes to Lg dot fit
X train,
comma
Y train,
then model
evaluate.
Let's see.
This is for the logistic regression.
Okay,
as you can see, the accuracy of the training data is 83%, percent the testing data is 77%.
so this is the concluding matrix, the predictive value, like these are the categories.
Now let's see for the linear SVM.
For that, I will write: SVM
equals two
linear
SVC,
and SVM
dot fit,
comma, white drain,
and model
evaluate
SVM.
Okay,
and after that we will do for random forest and the naive base.
Okay, then we will start with the RNN.
So as you can see, the accuracy of training data is very pretty good, 93% and logic is 83%,
and the testing is less than
regression model. Let's see
for the random forest. So, I will write here:
RF equals to
Random Forest
Classifier,
centimeters,
equals to 20,
criterion equals to
entropy.
More than max
depth equals to 50.
Then RF, dot weight,
strain,
comma,
y train,
and model
evaluate. okay
loading let's see the accuracy how it will come. T
After this we will do for the neighbors
and after that we will move on to the our main model RNN recurrent neural networks.
still loading.
it will take little bit of time.
So as you can see the confusion matrix
So training data accuracy is 75% very less. So now let's see the last model name base.
Okay.
So, NB equals to
knowly
NB dot fit
Spain,
comma
quite train.
Okay.
Then model
evaluate.
So nay base training eighty-six seventy-six.
So as far
linear SCC has the best
test training accuracy, you can say, and the best
testing accuracy is 7670 76.45.
See logistic variation.
So now let's move to the our main model RNN.
So what is RNN?
Recurrent neural network at the start,
are the state-of-the-art algorithm for sequential data and are used by Apple CD and Google search voice.
It is the first algorithm that remembers its input due to an internal memory, which make it perfectly suited for machine learning problems that involve sequential data.
And that is one more thing: embedding layer.
Embedding layer is one of the available layers in Keras.
This is mainly used in natural language processing related applications such as language modeling, but it can also be used with other tasks that involve neural networks.
While dealing with NLP problems, we can use pre-trained word embeddings such as Glow.
Alternatively, we can also train our own embeddings using Keras embedding layer.
LSTM layer, long short-term memory networks, usually called LSTMs.
I have made already many videos,
you can check it out, were introduced by SkyMender.
These have widely been used for speech recognition, language processing, sentiment analysis, and text prediction.
If you are going deep into LSTM, we should first understand the need of LSTM, which can be explained by the drawback of practical use of RNN.
So let's start with RNN.
Okay.
So here I will import some libraries.
So after that, I will write import
Keras
version
two point one one zero. Okay, fine.
so now let's
end.
Test
with
data dot polarity,
dot
values,
then
test
size
equals to zero. point two.
Test size zero two means
like 80 and 20 percent
thing,
82 training and then
twenty percent to
testing.
and let's
model evaluation.
Okay.
So I will these are relu sigmoid, all the you know the layers.
So now this epoch it will run till five thousand, like
count will go till five thousand.
Okay, see the five thousand and it will go to one to ten, so it will take time. So I will get back to you after this completing this okay.
Now, as you can see, the box
ran successfully.
Okay,
so what should I do?
But I will give some space here.
So now we will see the positive and negative outcome.
Okay, this is something like testing.
Okay, we will test, we will predict,
we will give one a sentence and then we will predict
it is coming right or wrong. The accuracy is giving a right or wrong.
Okay.
so here I will write:
sequence
equals to
tokenizer
.dot
(text
_sequences,
). then like this:
data science
article,
this
worst.
Okay.
So here I will write test equals to pad
sequences,
and here I will write sequence,
comma
max length
equals to
max length.
Then I will write here, "prediction equals to
". Write "model
". then we'll write "model. twelve
two dot predict
". then test.
Okay.
If prediction
is greater than zero five means fifty percent,
then
it should print
positive.
Okay.
Negative.
Okay, let me run this.
sequential object is no
okay spell.
Let's take
The negative because it is the word worst,
it is showing correct now. Check from the RNN model. So model equals to keras dot models
dot load
models.
Here we will load RNN model RNN underscore model
dot sg
f file.
It is pretend model.
Okay, pretend Rnn model.
So sequence
tokenizer
dot text
to sequences.
Then
I will write here this
ML
codes
is best.
Okay.
Sequence,
then prediction
equals to model
dot predict,
then test
prediction is greater than zero.
five
positive.
0.5 Means fifty percent, more than fifty percent.
Else
print negative 2
models
positive, because this ML course is best,
so there is no negative word.
Okay.
what we will do now, we will do model saving, loading and prediction.
so for that
I will write import
pickle,
by pursuit, open
vectorizer
and
w.
here I will write pickle
.dot, _dump
(dump
vector file vector.
Okay.
So like this, I have to write for nay base, logistic revision, SVM and random forest.
So
what I will do?
Okay, let's run this.
now what we have to do, we have to predict using saved model.
Okay.
What we will do here? We will load model first and we will predict.
So
first I will write the function name load
models
and we will load the vectorizer. So, file equals to
open
vectorizer,
dot pickle
rb
vectorizer
load
file;
that file dot close.
I am loading the logistic regression model.
So for that, we have to write open
pickle
file,
that file dot close,
then
LG.
Okay.
Yeah.
So now we will predict the sentiment. So, for that, I will write D F
predict
Riser.
So here, we will predict the sentiment. So, for that,
this is
text
equals to
process
underscore
sentiments
for
sentiment in
text
and
data
characterizer
dot
transformations,
understand,
then sentiment
to model
dot predict.
here I will make a list of text with sentiment. So for that I will add data equals to M DRA
then for
text
prediction
and zip
text comma sentiment
data.
Okay
and we will convert the list into Pantas data frame.
So for that, I will add: Tf equals to
Pd dot data.
frame
columns
pursue
text,
comma
sentiment.
Then D F equals to df dot,
replace
comma, one
negative
comma
positive.
So at last, I will write here F,
because two,
then here we will load in the model vectorizer,
comma, LG plus
load.
Here we text to classify like what should be in the list.
So
text question.
Here I will like I love machine.
Johnny
P, and so
here, DF equation
predict
retorizer
G, comma text,
then print
df, not
head.
I love machine learning positive. Bug is so active, positive. John I feel so good, negative.
Okay, there is
and
yeah, see now it's coming okay.
This is how you can do the sentiment analysis using RNN model. Here we have loaded RNN model, so it is showing right. So, let's do them
right here
at
boy
negative.
Okay.
RNN model is working so right.
Today we are going to explore K nearest neighbors or KNN, which is one of the most popular algorithms in data science.
Python is a powerful tool for data science, and KNN is great for classifying data by predicting the category of sample base on its closest neighbor.
This algorithm is used in many fields like healthcare, finance, and agriculture, helping us make decisions based on data.
The best part, it is really easy to use. You just need to pick a number for K and choose a distance function to compare data points.
However, KNN has its downsides. It doesn't work well with the large dataset and it requires proper scaling of the data to get accurate results.
In this video, we will show you how KNN works with real dataset.
The IRS dataset will walk you through simple Python code and demonstrate how to find the best key value to maximize your model's accuracy. So stay tuned to see KNN in action.
So welcome to the demo part. So I am here using Google Colab. So you can use any of your favorite ID like Jupyter Notebook, IntelliJ, Visual Code Studio, anything.
Okay, so let me rename this file as KNN classification.
Okay, cool. So let me tell you that KNN can be used for the classification regression predictive problems. So Knn falls in the supervised learning family of algorithms.
Okay, so we will measure the distance between the k neighbors, and the first step will be, we'll choose the number of k of neighbors. then
we'll take the k nearest neighbors of the new data point, according to your distance metric, and the step three will be our among these k
neighbors count the number of data points of each category.
okay. Step four, we will assign the new data points to the category where you counted the most neighbors.
Okay, so let's start first.
Let's import some library. Import
numpy
as
np, and let's import
pandas as pd. So everyone knows what is numpy and the pandas.
Okay, so numpy is a library for the python programming language, adding support for uh, you know, large multi-dimensional arrays.
okay. along with the large collection of what to say, high level mathematical functions, and various pandas is a software library written for the Python programming and is
for the data manipulation and analysis,
all the data frames and data structure it offers for the manipulating numerical tables.
okay, and the time series. you can see.
So, moving forward, uh we'll import our data set. So you can download the dataset from the description box below.
Okay, data set
equals to pd.read underscore csv.
The data name is iris.csv.
Okay, this is how you read your data in Python.
Okay, yeah, data set is loaded, so dataset dot shape
shape okay, yeah. So data set dot shape is used for how many numbers of rows and columns present in your dataset, okay. 150 rows and six columns.
So let me tell you brief about data set this iris dataset. So iris data set includes three iris species with 50 samples each, as well as some properties about each flower.
So one flower species is linearly separable from the other two, you can say, but the other two are not linearly separable from each other,
okay. And this shape I told you, we can get a quick idea of how many instances of rows and columns are present in our dataset.
So let's see our dataset dataset dot
head.
So head is used for uh you know by you can see top five rows of your dataset using head,
and if you will use tail you uh instead of head, you can see the last five rows of your dataset.
Cool, okay. So columns are ID, sepal length, sepal width, petal length, petal width, and the species.
Cool. Then moving forward, let's describe our data sets. So these are the basic function.
okay.
Of Python, you can say
so. Data set dot described. What describes do is it will give you count of all the rows, mean value, standard deviation value, minimum value.
What is the 25% okay of all the values in the particular row?
What is the 50%?
What is the 75%? What is the maximum? Maximum is 150. You can say okay, and 25% of 150 is 38.25.
This okay, of all the columns.
If it is normal, you know corrector, so it won't give you any data.
Okay, cool. Yeah, so moving forward, uh, let's now take a look at the number of instances row belong to each classes.
Okay, so we will write data set dot
group by
species dot
size, okay.
Uh species S is capital, that's why it's showing the error.
Yeah, so you can see iris satosa are 50, iris versical are 50, and virginica is 50.
Okay, and the data type type is integer.
Cool. So, as we can see, data set contains six columns like ID, sepal length, sepal width, and petal length, petal width, and species.
The actual features are described by columns one to four, the last columns labels or samples.
Okay, so firstly we need to split data into two arrays like x features and y labels.
So, how we will do is by writing code like feature underscore columns equals to
sample length, sample width, petal length, petal width.
Just remember you are writing correct name, okay. Then x equals to dataset
feature underscore
columns,
okay.
Dot
values,
then
y equals to
dataset
species.
Dot values.
Cool, And let me run it.
So, this is how we can split the data set okay into two areas x and the y.
Okay, in X there are feature columns, these four columns are there, and in y species column is there, okay. And what is the species column? This satosa, virginica and all this.
Cool.
Then now we will do label encoding.
So, as you can see, labels are categorical, uh, knamers classifier does not accept the string labels, so we need to use label encoder to transform them into numbers,
okay. Then iris satosa correspond to zero, iris voci color uh correspond to one, and iris virginica correspond to two.
Okay, zero, one, two.
Cool. So, how can I from
sklearn dot pre-processing
import
label
encoder?
Okay, so what we'll do label encoder transform them into numbers. Okay, so I will write Ali equals to
label encoder.
Okay, my bad.
Label encoder okay, then y equals to ally fit dot transform y.
Okay, so now I will run it, yeah, correct. So splitting data set into training set and the test set now.
Okay, so now we'll split data set into training set and test set to check later on whether or not a classifier work correctly or not.
Okay, so here I will write from sklearn dot
not cross.
I will write here sklearn dot model selection.
Import
import train test split.
So, what is train test split?
Train test split is a model validation procedure that reveals how your model performs on your new data.
Okay, and what is X train, XS, Y train, Y test in Python? Okay, let me first write it and then I will let you know. Okay, then I will write here
X train, comma, X test,
comma, Y train, comma, Y test.
Okay, question
train
test
split then X, comma Y,
comma test size 0.2 and the random system.
Okay, okay, some error came.
Okay, underscore model section.
Yeah, cool.
So what is X train, X test, Y train, Y test? Okay, so X train and Y train sets are used for training and fitting the model.
Okay, so the X test and the Y test are the set used for testing the model and it's predicting the right output level.
Okay, so here you can see test size is 0.2 means 80% is for testing.
Oh sorry, 80% is for training and 20% is for testing for the new data.
Cool, yeah.
So now we will see some let's do some data visualization.
Okay, so here I will write import matplotlib
pyplot
as plt,
then import
c bond as sns.
Then here I will write person matplotlib
So what is matplotlib?
Matplotlib is a plotting library for the python programming language and its numerical mathematic extension.
Okay, so numpy provides an object API for embedding plots into application using generating purpose GUI toolkits like Kinter
and Python Qt or GTK, okay, whereas Cbon Cbon is a library for making a statistical graph in Python;
it builds on the top of Matplotlib and integrates closely with Pandas data structure.
Okay, Cbon helps us to explore and understand the data.
Okay, so I will run it here. I will write: from pandas, dot plotting
import
parallel
coordinates,
then PLT dot
figure.
figure size should be
15, comma ten,
okay.
Then parallel coordinates,
okay, then dataset dot drop.
I don't need ID,
comma, X is one
okay, and comma species.
Then plt dot
title and let parallel
coordinates
plot.
Okay, and
you can give some font size equals to 20,
then font
weight
equals to,
okay, let's say bold, only bold.
Then plt dot x level
then
features
comma
font size plus to fifteen.
Then plt
dot y level then I'll write here features
values,
comma font size equals to 15.
Okay, then plt dot legend,
then loc equals to one,
comma
I will have frame on
equals to true, comma shadow equals to true, comma face color
equals to white
(should, be capital
), and comma edge color
equals to
plt dot show, okay. Some error is there: plt dot figure size okay.
Spelling mistake,
okay. One more error: plt dot legend okay face color okay. Some spelling mistake. So yeah, let me make it free output in full screen.
Yeah, so parallel coordinates is a plotting technique for plotting, you know, multivariate data, so it allows one to see clusters in the data
and to estimate other stand visually.
So, using parallel coordinate points, uh, you know, are represented as the connected line segments, as you can see.
Okay. And each vertical line represents one attribute, and one set of connected line segments represent one data point.
Okay.
And points that tend to cluster will appear closer together.
Okay. So this, uh, this color is iris satosa, and this is iris versicolor, and this one is iris
virginica as you can see in the legend.
Okay.
Cool.
So moving forward, let's create another graph.
Andrew curves. Okay. So here I will write from
pandas dot plotting import scatter.
No, it's uh plotting import.
Andrew curves,
okay. Then plt
dot figure it's AI based so it's giving me suggestions, suggestions, suggestions. Okay, so sometimes suggestions are good, but not always.
Yeah, let's carry on. Figure size is 15, comma 10,
then entry
Curves,
then I will add dataset dot drop id access species and plt and recurves plot. Okay, fine.
Okay,
let me add:
we don't need x label and all. Let me add legend;
plt dot legend
then same l oc equals to one,
then
the position size.
Then I will write here: size
is 15,
frame on equals to two,
comma shadow equals to true.
So this is truly based upon you if you want to add legend or not, or you can skip.
If you want to skip, you can skip.
Okay, face color equals to white, then edge color
equals to black.
Okay, then plt dot show
Yeah, so no error is there. So let me first view output in full screen.
Okay, so Andrew curves, these are the Android curves. Okay, the you can see the graph in the curve.
So Andrew curve allow one to plot multivariate data as a large number of curves, so that are created using the attributes of samples okay,
as coefficient for Fourier series. Okay, so by coloring these curves differently for each class, it is possible to visualize data clustering.
So curves belongs belonging to samples of the same class.
Will usually be closer together and they form large structure.
Okay, as you can see here, and this is the legend. Why we are setting the four color is should be white and yeah, and the edge color should be black.
Okay, and frame on shadow should be there as you can see the shadow.
Okay, like this. If you want to skip, you can skip this part, legend part, part legend part, okay.
But oh, like it's good to have, it's good practice to have this cool.
So let's create one small pair plot. Okay, so I will write here: plt, dot
figure.
Then I will write sns, dot pair plot.
then I will write dataset.
dot drop
will drop again. id. we don't need.
Um, x is is one.
Then I will write u equals to
species,
size equals to three,
then markers equals to
oh sd.
Yeah, cool. Then plt dot shoe it's running.
Yeah, so first let me make it to full screen.
Yeah, so here pairwise is useful when you want to visualize the distribution of the variable or the relationship between the multiple variable
separately within subsets of your data set.
Okay, so here.
This blue one is, uh, satosa versicolor and the virginica.
Okay, so these are some graph you can see. Or here, you can see sepal length.
Okay, so green one is virginica and versicolor are almost having same sepal length.
Okay, and here are the different types of graphs.
Okay, if you don't want to, uh, let's say, if you don't know how to read this graph, you can use this graph, or you can use
this graph, either you can use this graph.
Okay, that's the power of.
Pairwise plots you can say and the sepal, uh, width centimeter. Okay, setosa no. Okay, virginic and vertical again having almost same sample width.
Okay, and here as well.
Okay, this satusa is in different form.
Okay,
yeah, so we'll uh create one small uh pair of uh one small graph, then we'll move forward.
Okay, uh I will write here plt dot.
So now we are creating box plot figure.
Okay, then dataset dot drop,
then again id, comma, access should be one
dot box plot.
Okay, then figure size. I chose this. Yeah, let's run it.
Yeah, again, see this is the box plot petal and same petal width, sepal and sepal width.
Okay, according to width, it is showing like from this to this width, we have the versicolor and from this to this width,
this length. Sorry, sepal length. We have
that virginica lies here, iris virginica, and from here to here, iris satosa lies okay. The sepal length cool and like you can use 3D models, you can use different types of charts.
Okay, I did four and four are enough to read the data set, okay. So now we will do some KN classification. Okay, we will make prediction and we will see the accuracy of our dataset.
Okay, so now what I will do, I will write here from
SKlearn
dot
neighbors
import
k neighbors, okay.
Write from
sklearn dot
neighbors
import
k neighbor
classifier.
Okay,
then I will write here: from
sklearn dot
matrix
import,
confusion,
matrix, comma, accuracy, accuracy, score.
Okay, then I will write from
sklearn dot model
selection
import
cross
value score.
Okay,
so here what we I did we are fitting the classifier to the training set and the loading the libraries basically.
Okay, then we'll initiate a learning model k equals to through three.
Okay, so here I will write classifier.
Let me give one space classifier equals to
neighbors classifier
and
neighbors equals to three.
Okay, then fitting the model I will write here classifier dot
fit
x train,
comma, y train
okay. Then now we will predicting the test test set results. Okay, so y prediction equals to
classifier dot
predict
x test cool okay. From okay, spelling mistake.
Okay,
okay.
I guess fine now.
So now let's evaluate the prediction. So here I will uh build the confusion matrix.
Okay, so here I will add CM confusion matrix equals to confusion underscore matrix uh
Y test, comma, Y prediction.
Okay, then here I will add CM. Okay, so what is confusion matrix basically?
So I confusion matrix uh you know is a table that shows how well a model performs by comparing its prediction to the actual values,
okay. So what it shows a confusion uh dismatrics displays the number of correct and incorrect prediction of each class in models,
which either it can give you true positive, true negative, false positive, false negative, either it can give you zero or one.
Okay, so yeah, moving forward, let's calculate the model accuracy. This is the main part. If the model accuracy is low, it means uh your analysis of you know classification is not good.
Okay, so accuracy it should be more than 80 at least.
Accuracy.
Equals to
accuracy underscore score y test,
comma y prediction into 100, otherwise it will give me in points. So I will write print
canon model accuracy
is
oh I will write plus str
I will round it okay accuracy.
I will add the person. So why I wrote this accuracy to round so I don't want after points, I need only two numbers. Okay, I don't want like 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 10 like this.
Okay, I need only like 80.20, like this.
Cool.
Let's run it.
See uh KN model accuracy is 96.67. That's why I wrote two here, and the person should be
so 96, which is very, very, very good.
Okay, so this is how you can find the accuracy. So now let's find the optimal number of neighbors in k.
Okay, basically finding the best k.
So we will use using cross-validation parameter, okay. Tuning so first I will create the list of k for kn okay. So here I will write k underscore list
equals to list
range
one, comma 50 comma two.
Here I am I will create the list of C V score.
Okay, so here I will write C V
scores
okay, okay. I have to give the brackets, yeah.
So we'll here perform the tenfold cross validation.
I will explain you what is cross-validation, don't worry. First, let me write: 4k
nk list.
KNN equals to
k Neighbor classifier, and here I will write N neighbor
neighbors, equals to K.
then scores
equals to cross
value, score
KN, then x train,
comma, y train,
okay, comma. I will write here cross validation equals to 10 my scoring equals to I will write here
accuracy.
Okay,
and then here cv underscores course dot append
to scores dot mean
So now yeah, let me run it okay.
Sum error came okay. The error is the scoring parameter,
yeah.
Why because here accuracy you can see, and I did the spelling mistake.
Okay, so now what is cross-validation? Of course, Cross validation, you know determine the accuracy of your machine learning model by partioning the data into two different groups,
okay. Called training set and testing set. You can see trains test in the testing set, okay. Accent by so they the data is randomly separated into a certain number of groups or subsets called folds.
Okay, you can see the 10 folds we have wrote. Each fold contains about the same amount of okay, and there is one more thing validation.
So, validation is a technique for assessing the accuracy of the model on data set.
Okay, and this cross-validation we did on new dataset.
Cool.
So now let's find the best K.
Okay.
So here I will write best
K equals to K
list.
Okay, before that I will write one thing.
I will write here MSE was changing to misclassification error. Okay. So equals to one's X
for X in for X in
C V scores.
Okay. At least I will write MSE dot
index
minimum
MSE.
I will use this bracket, square bracket.
Okay. So then, I will write: "print.
the best
optimal
number
of
neighbors
is person T
person
best underscore K.
Okay, let's run it.
See the best optimal number of neighbors. Okay,
neighbors is nine. Okay, so in the K nearest neighbor Kn algorithms, okay. So K represent the number of neighbors that are considered when classifying a query point.
Okay, see the if we'll classify this particular point, you will get the six.
Okay, one, two, three, four, five, six.
Okay.
And uh let me show you if you will classify this portion only, so you will get one, two, three, four, five, six points, like this.
So the best optimal number of neighbor is nine.
What is Python?
Python is a high-level object-oriented programming language developed by Guido Van Rosum in 1989 and was first released in 1991.
Python is often called a batteries included language due to its comprehensive standard library.
A fun fact about Python is that the name Python was actually taken from the popular BBC comedy show of that time, Monty Python's Flying Circus.
Now, let's look at the top features of Python.
First, so Python has a simple structure and a clearly defined syntax.
This allows the learners to pick up the language quickly so it is easy to learn and use.
Python can run on different operating systems such as Windows, Linux, and Mac, making it a portable language.
It enables programmers to develop the software for several competing platforms by writing a program only once.
Third, Python is freely available at the official website.
Since it is open source, this means that source code is also available to the public.
Now Python uses an object-oriented approach that encapsulates code within objects.
Python provides a collection of libraries for various tasks such as machine learning, web development and data analysis.
And finally, in Python, you don't need to assign the data type of the variable.
When you assign some value to the variable, it automatically allocates the memory to the variable at runtime.
So,
Python programming language is used to develop desktop applications and build web applications too.
It is popularly used in the field of data science, machine learning, and artificial intelligence to analyze data, build predictive models, and make business decisions.
Python is also widely used in game development.
Now, let's see some of the popular Python frameworks and libraries.
Python can be used for web development using frameworks like Django, Flask, Pyramid, and CherryPy.
You can build graphical user interfaces using libraries and frameworks such as tkinter or justkinter.
You can also use PygtK, PyQt or PYJS or Python JavaScript.
Now Python is also used to perform machine learning tasks using libraries such as TensorFlow, PyTorch, scikit-learn, matplotlib and SciPy.
You can also perform mathematical computations using NumPy and Pandas.
Now let's look at the best IDEs that you can use to write programs in Python and perform specific tasks.
So we have Jupyter Notebook, which is part of the Anaconda distribution that is widely used these days.
Even for our demo in this video, we'll be using Jupyter Notebook. I'll show you in a while.
Then we have the visual code editor from Microsoft.
This is also one of the preferred
IDEs by learners and companies.
Then we also have the popular text editor called Sublime Text Editor.
Then we also have PyCharm followed by Python IDLE and Spider as our top IDEs.
Now let's look at the top companies that are using Python in our day-to-day work.
So we have Google, Quora, Facebook, even Netflix, Spotify, and Instagram.
Now there are other top product-based, service-based and startups that also use Python programming.
So what really is Python programming language?
Python is an object-oriented, high-level programming language that supports built-in data structures and dynamic semantics.
It supports multiple programming paradigms such as structured, object-oriented, and functional programming.
Python is often described as batteries-included language because it has a comprehensive collection of standard libraries.
Python supports different modules and packages, which allows program modularity and code reuse.
Python was developed by Guido Van Rosum and its implementation started in December 1989.
Python 1.0 version was released in the year 1994.
Python 2.0 came out in October 2000, while Python 3.0 was released in December 2008.
Now that you have got an understanding of the Python programming language, let's now look at the top 10 reasons why you should learn Python.
So at number 10, we have ease of use.
One of the most common reasons to like Python is that it is quite easy to learn and code.
It provides a simple syntax that improves readability and makes it easier to understand.
So developers can create any desktop or machine-based application using this language.
Python is very versatile and is instrumental in artificial intelligence and machine learning.
We will talk about this later in the session.
Compared to Java or C C, it has fewer lines of codes.
In the example here, we are printing a hello world program in Java.
As you can see,
if you have to write a program in Java, you first have to declare the class name along with its scope.
Next, using curly braces, you need to pass the main method along with its arguments.
And then using system.out.println method, you can print hello world.
That's quite a tedious task, isn't it?
The same task of printing hello world can be done using just one line of code in Python as shown here.
You can write the print function and pass whatever you want to display inside the brackets, and that will print the output.
It is so simple.
That is why Python is considered as a high-level language and it's open source.
You can just download it from the website and start using it.
At 9, we have Active Community.
You need a community to learn new technology, and friends are your best asset when it comes to learning a programming language.
Python has large community support.
It has an extensive and active community to assist engineers, developers, analysts, and data scientists with expert support in case of programming errors or issues with the software.
You can just go ahead and put your queries in the community forum.
The community members will address your queries in real quick time.
Communities like Stack Overflow also brings many Python experts together to help learners.
Python Enhancement Proposals or PEP is where the proposals and the improvements are announced.
Also, there are a set of recommendations or core values called the Zen of Python written by Tim Peters that represents the guiding principles for Python development.
Up next at 8, we have portable and extensible.
Multiple cross-language operations can be performed effectively because Python is portable and extensible in nature.
For example, if the users have a Python code written on Windows and they want to execute on a Mac operating system or Linux operating system or Solaris,
they can easily do it without any amendment.
They can also run this code on any platform flawlessly and without any interrupt.
Due to its extensibility feature, you can integrate other programming languages such as Java, .NET, C and C codes with Python.
The components of other programming languages can be used with Python and thus it can be used to make a cross-platform suitable application too.
So it is a really good feature that Python provides.
The next reason to learn Python is testing frameworks.
Python supports several built-in flawless testing tools and frameworks that help in debugging and speeding up workflows.
Some of the tools and frameworks supported by Python are PyTest, Selenium, and Splinter.
This is the reason for which every tester tries to use Python-based tools and frameworks to test any application or code or to validate it in an easier manner.
PyTest is the most recommended testing framework for functional, integrational, and unit testing.
You can run Selenium test scripts using Python programming language to automate various tasks, and Splinter is an open source tool for testing web applications using Python.
It lets you automate browser actions such as visiting URLs and interacting with their items.
At number six, we have libraries and packages.
Another reason why Python has become so popular in the industry these days is that it has a massive collection of libraries and packages that make your tasks
simple and easy.
It has a range of libraries, packages, frameworks, and modules for data manipulation, statistical calculation, web development, machine learning, and data science.
Python programmers have developed tons of free and open source libraries that you can use.
You can find many of them via Python package index, the repository of Python software.
Python provides the default package called PIP.
Anaconda is a third party Python ecosystem.
Other examples include NumPy, SciPy, and Django.
Then we have scripting and automation.
Python is not just a programming language.
It can also be used for writing scripts for automating tasks and workflows without human intervention.
The code can be written in the form of scripts and executed later.
Further, it is interpreted by the machine and checked for errors at runtime.
The machine is used to read and interpret the code.
Once the developer checks the code, it can further run or be used several times without any interruption.
This allows you to automate a set of certain tasks within a program or the same code can be used with other applications as well.
At number 4, we have web development.
Another reason to learn Python is that it makes the web development process so much easier.
It provides a wide collection of frameworks that make it easier for developers to develop web applications.
Some of the examples are Django, Flask, Pyramid, TurboGears, CherryPy, etc.
These frameworks are written in Python, which makes the code a lot faster and stable.
The task which used to take hours in PHP can be finished in minutes using Python.
Python is also used for web scraping.
Django offers many elements of intricate programs such as template design, management panel, signing in, signing up,
signing out, URL routing, etc.
Once the user establishes the framework, all these features become ready to use.
Flask is a microwave framework written in Python.
Of all the components that are part of this module, they are all ready to execute in the server context.
Pinterest and LinkedIn use Flask.
Pyramid offers more attributes than Flask.
It will assist users with URL routing and authentication support.
Turbo Gears is a highly recommended and scalable framework that supports features such as authentication, caching, identification,
management of sessions, and pluggable applications.
Up next at number three,
we have machine learning.
The growth of machine learning has been phenomenal in the last five years and it's rapidly changing the world around us.
Python is one of the most preferred programming languages for machine learning because of its simple syntax and support for several machine learning libraries.
Using different libraries and functions in Python, the system can learn and train itself from past data.
Once the system is trained, it can then learn to adjust itself to new inputs.
Finally, it can make predictions and perform human-like tasks automatically.
At number two, we have data science.
Machine learning and data science go hand in hand.
Python is robust, scalable, and provides extensible visualization and graphics options.
Hence, it is widely used in data science.
Python has libraries such as NumPy for numerical computation of data, pandas for operations to manipulate data on numerical tables and time series.
It also provides SymPy for symbolic computation and SciPy for technical and scientific computations.
It has another library called PyBrain, which is sought for Python-based reinforcement learning, artificial intelligence, and neural network library.
Scikit-learn is the machine learning library for creating classification regression and clustering algorithms.
And finally, it provides PyTorch and TensorFlow for deep learning.
Finally, coming to the most important and the top reason to learn Python, which is career opportunities and salary.
Python language provides a variety of job opportunities and promises a high growth graph with huge salary prospects.
It has been used by most of the tech giants.
Industry leaders using Python are Amazon, Google, Facebook, IBM, NASA, Netflix, and YouTube.
Next, you can see the Google Trends,
but I have considered three programming languages Python, Java, and C.
I have compared them for the past 12 months.
You can see it clearly on your screens that Python has become a frontrunner in terms of popularity and web search volume.
It means people are interested in Python, they want to learn it and use it in their work.
You can also check for the YouTube search.
There also you will find that Python Programming Language is the most searched language on YouTube.
Now on your screens, you can see the report of PYPL, which is popularity of programming language index.
It is created by analyzing how often language tutorials are searched on Google.
It is a leading indicator.
The raw data comes from Google Trends.
The bar graph depicts that Python is the most popular and widely used programming language across the globe, followed by Java, then JavaScript and C sharp.
The popularity of programming language index can help you decide which language to study or which one to use in a new software project.
The next graph shows the popularity of Python and Java over the years, starting from 2004 till the current period, which is 2020.
Worldwide, Python is the most popular language.
Python grew the most in the last 5 years by 19.4%, and Java lost the most by minus 7.2%.
Now let's talk about the different career opportunities and the job roles that you can get into if you learn Python language.
First, you can become a Python developer,
where you will be asked to write and test codes, debug programs, and integrate applications with third-party web services.
Second, you can become a web developer.
Here, you will be responsible for writing server-side web application logic.
Python web developers usually develop back-end components, connect the application with third-party services,
and support the front-end developers by integrating their work with the Python application.
You can also become a data analyst if you know Python.
As a data analyst, you have to gather data from multiple sources using scripts, analyze that data, develop and implement databases and data collection systems.
You can become a data scientist.
As a data scientist, you need to understand the challenges in business and come up with the best solutions using modern tools and techniques to analyze,
visualize, and build prediction models to make business decisions.
Lastly, you can be a machine learning engineer where you can develop intelligent machines that can learn from vast volumes of data and apply knowledge without human intervention.
So there's a lot of scopes if you learn Python.
But before we move on, let's understand first what is Jupyter Notebook.
So, guys, as you can see all over here, that Jupyter Notebook is a popular open source tool that basically allows you to create and share documents
which contains codes, equations, you can have visualizations also.
Basically, it is used for data analysis, machine learning, and scientific research, which makes it a very essential tools for developers like data scientists and researchers alike.
Now, before installing Jupyter Notebook, I request you that you have Python installed in your system.
So the requirement should be Python 3.6 or greater.
So now let us officially navigate to the Python's website.
So guys, as you can see all over here, so on python.org, if I click on download Python, so we are gonna see that all over here,
download Python 3.125.
So as I already told you that the requirement of Python should be greater than 3.6.
So just you can click all over here and you can see the download had started.
So, guys, as you can see all over here that we have installed the Python.
Now let us open the file.
So you can see the given software is going to install on this directory.
Okay.
So just click all over here.
So guys, as you can see all over here, the Python installation of 3.125 is in progress.
Let's wait for some time till it gets installed.
So as you can see, guys, all over here, that we have successfully installed our Python.
Now let us open our terminal and let us check whether Python is correctly installed.
So we are going to type
Python
slash version.
So as you can see all over here, we have successfully installed our Python.
So guys, that was our prerequisite.
Now there are two ways to install Jupyter Notebook.
The first one can be pip.
Okay, pip is a package manager or using Anaconda distribution.
let us see with PIP first.
So guys, pip is a package manager which is used to install and manage software packages, libraries written in Python.
So you can see all over here that the Python version greater than 3.6 have default pip installed in them.
Okay, so we can use pip command to install our Jupyter Notebook.
So guys, as you can see all over here, we have come to the official documentation of jupyter.org and it is saying that installing JupyterLab with pip command.
So what you can do, guys, you can just copy all over here.
You can go right all over here and click on this.
Now as you can see all over here, it has started downloading the Jupyter Lab.
So guys, we are going to install our Jupyter lab with the pip command.
So this is the official documentation of Jupyter Notebook.
Okay, and just all you have to do is copy this and type on your terminal.
So as you can see all over here, it has started downloading the packages which is required to download the Jupyter Notebook.
Let us wait for some time.
Okay, guys, so we have successfully completed this step.
Now let us move on to our next step.
So as you can see all over here,
so we have installed, okay.
Then what we have to do, then you can type this, you can launch the Jupyter lab with this command on the terminal.
Now let us wait.
So as you can see all over here, guys, we have successfully installed our Jupyter notebook.
So you can go all over here and just create a new notebook, and you can also choose your kernel and you can start working on your Jupyter notebook.
Suppose I'll show you one snippet.
So 3 plus 5, let us try to run this notebook.
So as you can see, it is giving us the 8 as answer.
So it is following the Python syntax, and in this way, we have successfully installed our Jupyter notebook using the pip command.
So now, as you can also see all over here, you can also install Jupyter Notebook with this command, pip install notebook, and then you can just open it.
This is also another alternative.
Similarly, you can install with Viala also.
Same command and just open the Viala.
Now, if you are using any other operating system like Mac OS or Linux, then you can install by Brew install JupyterLab.
So home brew will be the package manager for Mac OS and Linux.
So I hope so you are pretty clear with how to install Jupyter Notebook with the PEP command.
Now I have downloaded Anaconda from this official website.
So as you can see all over here, this is the official website of Anaconda.
Okay.
Now just type your email and you can just download it.
So similarly, as you can see, after installing, I'm going to launch my installer and let us click next.
Okay.
Let us click agree.
And let us install this on the given directory.
Let us wait for some time till the installation gets complete.
So guys, as you can see all over here, we have completed our installation of Anaconda.
So just click on finish and.
You can say we have successfully installed our Anaconda.
Now let us open our Anaconda navigator.
So just click on.
So as you can see all over here, just right-click on this and our Anucanda navigator will be opened.
So as you can see all over here, this is our Anucanda navigator and it is loading the packages.
And for us to install the Jupyter notebook, so as you can see all over here, just click on launch.
So guys, if you click on launch, it is going to open our Jupyter notebook.
So as you can see all over here, it is saying launching the Jupyter Notebook.
And it is hosted on localhost 8889.
So this is our hosted Jupyter Notebook.
And similarly, you can create a new notebook all over here.
And in this way, you can start working.
LLMs.
If you ever wondered how machine learning can now understand and generate human-like text, you are in the right place.
From chat boards like ChatGPT to AI assistant that power search engines.
LLMs are transforming how we interact with technology.
One of the most exciting advancements in this space is Google Gemini or OpenAI ChatGPT.
A cutting-edge large language model designed to push the boundaries of what AI can achieve.
In this video, we will explore what LLMs are, how they work, and why models like Gemini are critical for the future of AI.
Google Gemini is part of a new wave of AI models that are smarter, faster, and more efficient.
It is designed to understand context better, offer more accurate responses, and integrate deeply into service like Google Search and Google Assistant,
providing more human-like interactions.
So we will break down the science behind LLMs, including their massive training data set, transformer architecture, and how models like Gemini use deep learning innovation to change industries.
Plus, we will compare Google Gemini to other popular LLMs such as OpenAI Chat GPT models, showing how each of these technologies is used to power chatbots,
virtual assistants, and other AI-driven applications.
By end of this video, you will have a clear understanding of how large language models like Gemini work, their key features, and what they mean for their future AI.
Don't forget to like, subscribe, and hit the bell icon to never miss any update from Simply Learn. So, what are the large language models?
Large language models like ChatGPT 4, Generative Pre-Trained, Transformer 4, O, and Google Gemini are sophisticated AI system designed to comprehend and generate human-like text.
These models are built using deep learning techniques and are trained on vast datasets collected from the internet.
They leverage self-attention mechanisms to analyze the relationship between words or tokens allowing them to capture context and produce coherent relevant responses.
LLMs have significant applications, including powering virtual assistant, chat boards, content creation, language translation, and supporting research and decision making.
Their ability to generate fluent and contextually appropriate text has advanced natural language processing and improved human-computer interaction.
So now let's see what are large language models used for.
Large language models are utilized in scenarios with limited or no domain specific data available for training.
These scenarios include both few short and zero short training approaches, which rely on the model's strong inductive bias and its capability to derive meaningful
representation from a small amount of data.
Or even no data at all. So now let's see how our large language models are trained.
Large language models typically undergo pre-training on a board, all encompassing data set that shares statistical similarities with the dataset
specific to the target task. The objective of pre-training is to enable the model to require high level features that can later be applied during the fine-tuning phase for specific tasks.
So there are some training processes of LLM which involves several steps. The first one is text pre-processing.
The textual data is transformed into a numerical representation that the LLM model can effectively process.
This conversion may involve techniques like tokenization encoding, and creating input sequences. The second one is random parameter initialization.
The model's parameters are initialized randomly before the training process begins. The third one is input numerical data.
The numerical representation of the text data is fed into the model of processing.
The model's architecture, typically based on transformers, allows it to capture the conceptual relationship between the words or tokens in the next.
The fourth one is loss function calculation. A loss function calculation measures the discrepancy between the model's prediction and the actual next word or token in a syntax.
The LLM model aims to minimize this loss during training.
The fifth one is parameter optimization. The model's parameters are adjusted through optimization technique.
This involves calculating gradient and updating the parameters accordingly, gradually improving the model's performance. The last one is iterative training.
The training process is repeated over multiple iterations or epochs until the model's output achieves a satisfactory level of accuracy on that given task or dataset.
By following this training process, large language models learn to capture linguistic patterns, understand context, and generate coherent responses,
enabling them to excel at various language-related tasks.
The next topic is how do large language models work?
So, large language models leverage deep neural networks to generate output based on patterns learned from the training data.
Typically, a large language model adopts a transformer architecture which enables the model to identify relationship between words in a sentence irrespective of their position in the sequence.
In contrast to RNNs that rely on recurrence to capture token relationship, transform a neural network, employ self-attention as their primary mechanism.
Self-attention calculates attention scores that determine the importance of each token with respect to the other token in the text sequence,
facilitating the modeling of intricate relationships within the data.
Next, let's see application of large language models. Large language models have a wide range of applications across various domains.
So here are some notable applications. The first one is natural language processing NLP.
Large language models are used to improve natural language understanding tasks such as sentiment analysis, named entity recognition, text classification,
and language modeling.
The second one is chatbot and virtual assistant.
Large language models power conversational agents, chatbots, and virtual assistant, providing more interactive and human-like user interaction.
The third one is machine translation.
Large language models have been used for automatic language translation, enabling text translation between different languages with improved accuracy.
The fourth one is sentiment analysis.
LLMs can analyze and classify the sentiment or emotion expressed in a piece of text, which is valuable for market research, brand monitoring, and social media analysis.
The fifth one is content recommendation.
These models can be employed to provide personalized content recommendations, enhancing user experience and engagement on platforms such as news websites or streaming services.
So these applications highlight the potential impact of large language models in various domains for improving language understanding automation.
So hello guys, welcome to this demo part of this video.
So here what I will do, I will go to new Python Python 3.
Data
analysis.
Basically, we will so we have one
dataset file of
roller coaster basically.
So we will be using then, and you can download that file from the description box below from the below link driving.
Okay, so we will be doing some small basic function
using Python and later on we will make some good charts.
Okay, we will remove duplicates and all, we will do all that
thing.
We'll do data preparation, we'll do feature engineering, okay.
And uh we'll remove the duplicates, we'll check for the duplicates, we'll make charts like histogram,
kd plots, box plot, and like many more similar to that, like heat map. We'll make scatter plot group by comparison. Okay, we all do that, right?
So just stick with me and you can
write side along with me your discourse, okay.
Okay, so let's start with importing
pandas first.
I guess everyone know what is pandas and numpy.
Fine
as np, then I will import
numpy
as np.
Why this is np and pd?
Sorry, my bad pd is here because I don't want to write again and again this pandas, this numpy. So basically, I can write this a small version, okay.
Yeah, so if you guys don't know what is pandas. so panda is very popular library for working with data.
Okay, it's
goal is to be the most powerful and flexible open source tool.
Okay, so it has these that code.
So data frames are the center of pandas,
and what is data frame? A data frame is structured like a table or a spreadsheet, okay. The rows and the columns, okay. Whereas numpy numpy is an open source Python library again
that facilitates you know efficient numerical operation on large quantities of data.
Okay, so there are many functions in numpy as well.
Those we can use in the pandas data frame.
Got it?
So we'll import one more
dot pyplot.pylab
as
plt.
Okay, there is one more library matplotlib for plotting the graph, and
and there is one more import
c1
as SNS.
So, what is C1? Cbon is again the Python data visualization library based on matplotlib.
it provides a high level interface for drawing attractive and informative statical unographs.
Okay, then I will write here plt dot
style
use.
We'll write ggplot.
Got it ggplot.
Fine.
So yeah,
let me run it. So, what is ggplot? So, ggplot is an again this is an open source data visualization package for historical programming.
Okay, so yeah,
you can say or a general scheme for data visualization which breaks up graph into you know semantic components such as scales and layers.
Okay, maploadlib dot py.
Okay, it's pylab.
P okay, yeah.
So now
we will import our data set.
Df df means data frame. You can write any word of your choice, then pd again pandas.read underscore csv
use for readings CSV file.
Okay, Excel files.
Got it.
Then here I will write my
this
coaster.csv.
Okay, I'm not writing any path because my this uh
dataset is here itself.
Coaster coaster C coast.
This is coaster.csv okay.
If you have your data set in another location as in like in C drive, D drive or whatever, You can give that path.
Okay, let me run it.
Yeah, so now we will do some data understanding.
Okay, we'll see data frame shape, head and tail, data types, and describe like small small function we will use
df dot
shape.
so we have 1087 rows and 56 columns in our dataset.
Okay, then we will see df.hat
five.
So df.head means it will give me top five rows of my data set.
Okay, you can see one, two, three, four, five.
Okay, five rows and 56 columns here 56 columns, but we have one zero eight seven
rows. Okay, so we have cluster name, length, speed, location, status, opening, date, type, this, this, this, this.
we will do
uh you know, we'll make some graphs using this these columns,
And there is one more df.tail
again, last five rows. So df.tail gives you the last five rows.
See one zero eight six one zero eight five. Okay,
and if you want to see
full data, it is here,
okay. 021086, fine.
Yeah, so we have one more df.columns to check
all the columns.
See cluster name, land, speed, location, status, opening date, type, and these all are my columns names.
Fine.
So we have one more data types.
Actually, we have like many data types, but let me show you some important ones, or you can say some of the basics ones, okay.
So df dot d types, d types means data types, Question name is object type, length object, and inversion is float.
Okay,
we'll check inversion.
Where is the inversion?
Yeah, float type, okay.
Then everything is object, and year introduces int numeric one and latitude float.
Okay,
so basically we have three types float, int, and object.
then what do we do?
Let's just quickly check this.
Describe.
so what is the count of this inversion 932?
it won't include any, you know, what is it?
Empty cells.
it won't count empty cells, Mean of this particular table, then standard deviation, then mean, minimum value 25 percent, 70 percent,
75 percent, and max.
It will describe you all this,
okay.
And there is one more df.info to get the info.
See
question name 1087 value non-null object, then length 953 non null. Okay, like this.
Yeah, so now moving forward, what we will do? We will do data preparation.
Okay, what comes in data preparation, like dropping irrelevant columns and rows which we don't want, okay.
Then second thing is identifying duplicates, columns, and third is renaming columns.
Then we will do some feature creations,
right?
So if you want to drop a column,
okay, how you can drop?
So you have to write just df.drop.
First, I will give here stack data
reparation.
Okay, yeah.
So how you can drop a column?
Okay, df.drop,
then here
opening
date
comma access equals to one.
Okay.
Opening okay, access spelling is wrong.
Instead of this,
Maybe what is the opening date?
Okay, always capital here.
Instead of this, you can use double plus two.
Okay, access is not defined.
My bad.
So what you have to do, you have to give this here, and you have to put it here. Yeah,
again, access is not defined.
Yeah,
fine.
Okay,
so as you can see here,
first I will show you this question name, length, speed, location, status, and opening date is there.
Fine.
So if you will go here,
question name, length, speed, location, status, nothing opening date is there, right? So this is how you can drop a table.
Fine.
For a while, I'm making this as a comment, maybe in future or upcoming, you know, making graph.
I need this.
Okay, so yeah, so I will write here: df equals to
df
cluster name,
comma, location,
then comma,
status.
Then here I will write, manufacture
fine,
then again, comma.
then I will give here
ear
introduced.
then
latitude.
Wait, I will tell you why I'm doing this, then
longitude, latitude, longitude, then
type in
okay, then
date
clean
fine.
Then speed into
in meter per hour to slide
speed into hour,
and, comma what else?
Then
height
foot
inversion,
clean,
G force,
clean
copy, yeah.
So here I will write okay
type in
okay, one more mistake is here.
Now, what I will do?
I will write here: opening
date
clean equals to
Pd, two
dot date time
DF
opening
date,
clean find.
So what is does this pd.2 datetime do?
Okay, so it converts argument to data time date time.
Okay, so this function you know you can say converts a scalar array like or series or data frame dictionary like to a pandas
date time object okay.
So now let's rename the columns.
Okay.
Then, to, you know, for better things, df
equals to df .dot (rename
columns equals to
poster
name
). Then,
poster
name,
comma
here
introduced.
Then
here
introduced, okay.
Opening date clean to
open
date,
okay.
Then I will write a speed
in the interval r.
Then I will write it caps
speed and so
interval r,
got it.
Then
height
into foot,
I will write it as
catch.
So why I'm writing this?
Because this is a very good practice as a professional way.
Or no, as a data analyst or as a business analyst, whatever. You are working on machine learning projects or whatever the thing, this is a good practice.
Okay?
So inversions,
inversions
clean.
Then it should be like
"inversions
", then
"g force"
clean,
fine.
Let me run it.
Okay, now let's check the column.
Yeah, so now you can say our column is changed.
Fine,
so I will write this an a
dot.
So
what does this is?
na dot sum, do so is an a function returns, a boolean value of.
you know, true if the value is n an And the false otherwise, and the sum function return the sum of the two values, which equals to the number of n
n values in the column.
So here we have zero and n. Here same this status 213, here 217.
height foot is 916. Okay,
so now what we will do?
We will write here:
df
location,
duplicate.
I told you in starting,
we'll
duplicate it.
Okay,
so question name, location, status, manual.
Okay, duplicate it now.
Okay.
So now, what we will do? I will check duplicates for the question name. So you can write df dot co l o d, l o c.
then df
df dot
duplicate it.
and subset equals to
poster
name,
then dot hat,
Okay.
head of five.
Now everyone know right what do
what this hat does?
Okay,
yeah.
So here you can see so these are duplicate
okay of the question
name, right?
Why because you can just check the type in word
and all fine.
So now, checking with an example, duplicate. let's check df.query,
(question _name,
="crystal ". custom
_crystal
). and now you will get "beach
I took this crystal beach cyclone.
So now you can see 39 and 43 are the same.
Okay, everything is same.
So this one is duplicate.
So now what I will do? I will write here let me give some space here df.columns,
then I will write here df question df.
Then df.
Question, name,
location,
opening
date,
dot
dset
index,
then drop that.
So
now what we will do? We will do some feature understanding.
So now we will do some feature understanding.
So in this we will plot some feature distribution like histogram kd box plot.
Okay, for that I will write a df
er
introduced.
then
I will write value
counts.
So now what I will do?
Let's create
bar chart.
Okay.
Ax equals to DF
year
introduced dot
value
comes.
Okay, then dot
head ten max I need
then dot plot kind equals to any bar,
then title is topped.
I write what what what what should we give top ten
years
clusters introduced?
Okay,
then
I will write here ex
.dot
.set
x level,
then I will write here ears
introduced.
Okay,
then I will write here ax .dot
.set y level,
then
count.
Okay, let me run it. Okay, unexpected character after line continuation.
Okay,
we can remove this as we go;
unexpected, intended.
Now let me run it.
Yeah.
So this is our bar
plot.
So this is how you can create bar plot
using your data.
So
a bar plot is you know one of the most common types of graphics in this data visualization or EDU.
It shows the relationship between a numerical and the categorical variable.
Okay, so each entity of this category variable is represented as a bar.
Got it?
So now let's do some more.
So what
let's make a historogram class.
Okay,
histogram.
So for that, I will write
ax equals to df
speed
r.
then plot
kind
equals to
store gram,
then comma.
I will write bins here.
Okay, pins equals to 20,
title
equals to coaster
speed
and metapol.
then ax
dot set x
level
is
speed meter per hour.
forgot to give this
yeah.
So histogram displays numerical data by grouping data into bins of equal width.
So here each bin is plotted as a bar whose height correspond to how many data points are in that bin.
So bins you can say are also sometimes called the intervals or classes or buckets.
Basically,
it's the same.
So here for this, this much is the bin.
For this, this much is a bin.
So this is like that.
Okay.
So now let's create kd plot.
So for that, it's very simple: ax equals to df.
then I can write speed in meter power r.
then plot
kind
equals to kd,
comma, then title.
I can write anything coaster
speed
then ax.
Yeah.
So kd, what does kd mean?
A kernel density estimate.
This plot is a method of you know visualizing the distribution of observation in a data set analogs to a histogram.
So kd represent the data using a continuous probability density curve in one or more dimension,
okay?
In one or more dimension that curve.
Fine.
So now let's do some feature relationship.
So in this we will make scatter plot, heat map correlation, and pair plot, okay, or we can also do some group by comparison.
Fine.
So now let's first make
scatter plot.
Okay, so df. dot plot
kind
was to
scatter, comma,
x equals to
speed meter per hour.
comma, y equals to
height in foot,
fine.
Then comma, let's give the title equals to coaster speed
versus
uh height.
Fine then PLD dot show.
Okay, some error is there.
Speed meter bar.
Okay.
Okay, s should be capital and should be capital.
Yeah.
So this is scatter plot speed versus height.
This is the speed versus height.
Okay.
If the
I can see here height is directly proportional to speed, somewhat because if you can see the 350 is the speed is then
120 kilometer per hour. No, it's not like that.
Okay, fine.
So scatter plot identifies the possible relationship between change observed in two different sets of variables.
Here the variables are height and the speed.
Okay, it provides a visual and aesthetical uh you know means to test the strength of relationship between two variables.
Fine.
Now let's okay, now let's make one more to give you better idea.
Okay, with legend.
Now I will show you bit sns, dot
scatter
plot.
then x equals to
speed.
inter R,
comma. y equals to
height into foot
feet.
whatever you can say, then hue will be there.
then here
introduced.
okay.
then data equals to df.
then ax equals to set title,
set title, then
coaster,
speed. what is
height?
then plt dot show.
Yeah,
so now you can see.
So this color, you know the light color. I will let me zoom it.
Okay, so this color we have some here which are introduced in 90s, okay, and this color which are introduced in 1925, and these colors
which are introduced in 2000.
so you can see like this as well.
So now let's make pair plot,
okay.
It's look amazing.
So let me write sns dot
dot
pair plot.
then tf, comma
variable is equals to
I need year. introduce.
then
speed
meter per r,
comma,
as should be kept on height.
foot.
Just remember the spelling, okay?
It's case sensitive: inversion,
inversions, comma, g force,
okay, comma hue. I will put what what what what what okay I will put type
mean
find that PLT dots
okay let me run it.
Okay, some error is there
here introduced
why it will be carabitall
that's same here.
See, that's why I'm saying, just remember the proper spelling.
Again, some
error, sorry, my bad. Inversions,
inversions.
Let me run it.
Okay, again, some errors.
What? Inversions.
Okay, let me check here while renaming
inversions only.
Okay, fine.
Inversions there.
Paste input, nothing changes.
Let me check again.
Okay, some error is there
Wait,
so yeah, you can see it's running fine.
So after this, what I will do?
So, what is the pair plot? So, pair plot function allows the user to get you know then an access grid via which each numerical variable is stored in the data is shared across the x and the y
in the structured column.
So this is how we you know type in wood, other
and steel.
This red one is wood, other other
are the blue one and the purple are the other
steel one.
Okay,
the different different formats.
Okay, now let's create the last graph which is
a heat map.
Okay.
so let me write.
DF
correlation
here
introduced
speed,
foot
drawing.
So
this is correlation values of all the things, right?
So now let's write SNS dot
heat map and tf underscore,
comma, and not that will be true.
Okay.
Now let me run it.
Yeah.
So to create heat map in Python, so you can use this, okay. See born library for this heat map.
So this function takes a data frame, you know, as an input and generates a heat map
type of things as the output.
so this is how you can perform EDA using any data set, or you can show your data or insights with a beautiful representation
using graphs and all, like this.
Fine.
Web scraping is a powerful technique that allows you to automatically extract data from website.
turning the vast amount of information available online into something you can easily analyze and use, whether you are gathering data for research, building a data set for machine learning project
or just curious about how websites work behind the scenes.
Web scraping is an essential skill to have in your toolkit.
On the other hand, Python is one of the most popular programming languages for web scraping.
thanks to its simplicity and the wealth of libraries available. In this video, we will explore how to use Python to script data from websites.
And we will dive into practical examples using Python libraries like request and beautiful soap to fetch and parse web content.
But it's not just about the code.
Web scraping comes with its own set of challenges and ethical considerations.
We will talk about how to script responsibly, respecting the rules set by websites and ensuring that your scraping activity don't negatively impact the sites you are collecting data from.
So by the end of this video, you will have a solid understanding of how to start scraping data from the web using Python.
Whether you are new to programming or looking to add web scraping to your skill set, this video will give you the knowledge and tools you need to get started.
So let's jump in and see how Python can help you unlock the full potential of the web.
So without any further ado, let's get started.
So here I am using this Google Collab for the web scrapping.
Okay, you can use your own like Jupyter Notebook, Visual Code Studio, anything.
Okay, so here I'll write scrapping
using Python.
Okay, then here first, you have to install some libraries, like,
you know, uh, request,
and you have to install beautiful. so,
and you have to install that.
you know, on dust because we will create one data frame and we will save it.
Then we will check our data.
Okay.
And you can install some basic Python levels like NumPy and all that.
Okay. So here first I will import
request.
Okay.
Then I will write from PS4
import
beautiful
soap.
Okay.
Then I will write import
pandas
as PD.
Fine.
Then now what I will do. Okay, let's see what is this request and all the things. So request is an HTTP client library for the Python programming language.
So request is one of the most you know downloaded Python libraries.
Okay, It's like more like over 2000, not exactly 2000, sorry, 200 or 300 million monthly download.
Okay, so what it does is it maps the STP protocol onto Python's object-oriented semantics.
And here beautiful soup. So
beautiful soup is a Python package for you know parsing the HTML and XML documents, including those with you know malphone markup.
It creates a parse tree for documents that can be used to extract data STML from HTML, which is useful for web
scraping.
Let's be trying
here.
Our second step will be
define the URL and the headers.
Okay, URL and the
headers.
So URL.
Okay, from where you want to set your data.
So I will write here simply learn
then this.
Okay, let's open this PMP certification.
Okay, let's cut it.
Yeah, so here i'll write this
and headers
to
these are the headers, okay.
So like in which you know device or you're working on, which browser you are working on.
So these are for the headers.
So now what I will do, I will send a get request to the simplic page, okay, to this URL.
For that,
sending
get request.
Okay, here write response
request
dot
get
then you added
comma headers
to headers.
Okay, let me run it.
Okay, working fine.
So now
let's check if the request is successful or not for that. If
the sponsor dot status code was to equals to quote equals two hundred,
then
equals. so
it was so
okay.
Then
response
dot
content
comma
HTML
dot parser.
Okay.
Here
so here I will write codes
titles.
Why?
Because here I am you know initializing the list to store our
titles or whatever the things are, okay, basically the data.
Okay, why I'm writing course here? Because this is again course page.
That's right.
Nothing else.
Okay, here I will give the empty list.
So now we will find all course titles based on the actual HTML structure. What is HTML structure?
You have to go to the page, right click,
then inspect.
Okay, according to this HTML structure means
what is the class name, what is the you know this PMP certification is which heading H1 adding, H2 adding, which heading it is.
Okay, so let's see
which heading it is okay.
All it is PMP certification training H1 adding.
Okay, just remember H1 adding.
So here I will write for
course in so
dot
find
or
H one.
Okay.
Then title
costume course text
dot strip.
Okay.
Then here I'm write course
titles
dot
append
title.
Okay.
Now what I will do?
I will check
if any data was extracted before it not.
Okay, I will write if
course
titles.
Here I will create a data frame df also pd.data
frame.
In this I will write course title, it will be our
you know that
column name.
So for I will write it course zeta.
Okay,
then
course
titles
okay.
Then, here I will write df
dot to
then uh just create simply learn.csv.
Okay, so our data will be saving this simply learn.csv.
Okay, csv
fine.
Here, what I will do? I will write index equation, false
print
data, and data is saved in csv.
simply learn
dot csv
Fine.
so here I will write
else
print
web page.
Okay, let me write field
to
retrieve the
web page.
Okay, that's it.
Let me run it.
Okay, here
if response or is to
disconnect object has no attribute status code.
Okay,
outdate title.
Some minor spelling mistakes are there.
Okay, dear doctor.
Sorry, sorry, my bad.
Again.
Okay, sorry.
D will be kept alive.
Yeah.
So now you can see data is saved in simply learn.csv. So what I will do? I will write data equals to everyone know how to read csv in python.read read underscore csv.
What was a file name?
Simplylearn.csv.
Okay, let me copy paste, run it,
and find data.
Okay.
Pmp certification training.
Data is fetched.
Okay.
Here you can see H1 we give and that's why PMP certification training came.
Let's take what's in H2.
Okay, in H2, there is leading premier PMI partner. Something is there.
Okay, I will change here
H1 H2, then I will
fine.
See leading premier PMI. Okay, let me make it bigger.
Yeah.
So now you can see
course data we mentioned.
So
if you will see this H1 didn't come.
Why? Because we have mentioned H2.
That's why. So these all are the H2.
Okay.
So what is this? I don't know.
This is a time series graph. This is Google tool, I think.
Okay, so this is how you can literally retrieve your data from any website.
Okay, just remember that some websites don't give you access to their, you know, for the scrapping, just like Amazon don't give. So you have to use at that time API.
And this is not ethical also to use someone's data.
Okay?
Without asking whatever you guys. Welcome to the neural network tutorial.
My name is Richard Kirschner. I'm with the Simply Learn team.
What's in it for you?
Well, today we're going to cover what is a neural network.
What can neural networks do?
How does a neural network work?
Types of neural networks. And then we're going to jump into a use case to classify between the photos of dogs and cats.
And we'll do that on the Karas with the TensorFlow in the back. But it's a Python script, so that's always my favorite part is when we dive into the actual script.
So what is a neural network?
So hi guys. I heard you want to know what a neural network is. Here we have looks like he just went shopping at a red tag sale. My robot's back.
So, as a matter of fact, you have been using neural network on a daily basis. In today's world, it's just amazing how much we use our new technology. We're not even aware of it.
When you ask your mobile assistant to perform a search for you, you know, like saying your Google or Siri or whoever you use, Amazon Web, self-driving cars,
so that's the newest thing coming out. They're just now trying to make those legal in different states in the US and around the world.
Even in the UK, they now have uh self-driving cars going up and down the streets. It's pretty amazing. These are all neural network driven. Computer games use it.
a lot of computer games are driven by neural networks in the back end as part of the game system and how it adjusts to the players.
And it's also used in processing the map images on your phone.
So every time you do a navigation someplace and it opens it up, they now use neural networks to help you find the quickest way to get there.
Neural network.
A neural network is a system or hardware that is designed to operate like a human brain.
In today's development, this is so important to understand because we don't have anything else to compare it to.
I'm sure someday in the future the computer will redefine, or the neural network or the AI, artificial intelligence, will redefine what these mean.
But as far as we can today's world and today's commercial development, we have to compare it to what humans do.
So it's we want to compare how it operates to a human brain and how it solves problems like a human does.
What can a neural network do? And really, we're just gonna dive in deeper to what we just covered and look at other examples.
So what can a neural network do? Well, let's list out the things neural networks can do for you.
Translate text.
Boy, we got Google Translate and Microsoft has their own translate. They have some really cool they actually have an earpiece that's supposed to start translating as you talk.
What a cool technology, what a cool time to live. Identify faces. Can you imagine all the uses for facial identification?
In the case of our sample or our code that we're gonna look at later, we'll be identifying dogs and cats, so not quite as detailed as uh understanding whose face belongs to who.
I'm waiting for the Google Glasses to come out so I can see who's who and identify faces as I'm walking around, have a little name tag over them. Not out there yet, but boy, we are close.
We can identify the faces and they have all kinds of technologies to bring that information back to us. Recognize speech goes along with the translate text.
So now as you're talking into your assistant, it can use that to do commands, turn lights on. All kinds of things you can do with recognizing speech.
Read handwritten text. They're starting to translate all these old text documents that they've had in storage.
Instead of doing it individually where somebody's going through each text by themselves in a room, you can picture like an old Raiders of the Lost Ark theme where he's in the back, you know,
archaeologists studying the text. Now it's fed into a computer, they take a picture.
They even use neural networks to take a scroll that is so messed up that they can't undo the scroll and they x-ray it,
and then they use that x-ray to translate the text off of it without ever opening the scroll.
I mean, just way cool stuff they're starting to do with all this. And of course, control robots.
What would be a neural network without bringing in the robots? And we have our own favorite robot in the middle who goes to our red tag cell and goes shopping for us.
So, you know, these are just a few of the wonderful things that neural networks are being applied to. It's such an infant stage technology. What a wonderful time to jump in.
And there are a lot of other things it goes into. I mean, we could spend just forever talking about all the different applications from business to whatever you can even imagine.
They're now applying neural networks to help us understand.
So now that we talked a little bit about all the cool things you can do with a neural network, let's dive in and say how does a neural network work?
So now we've come far enough to understand how neural network works. Let's go ahead and walk through this in a nice graphical representation.
They usually describe a neural network as having different layers. And you'll see that we've identified a green layer, an orange layer, and a red layer.
The green layer is the input.
So you have your data coming in. It picks up the input signals and passes them to the next layer. The next layer does all kinds of calculations and feature extraction.
It's called the hidden layer.
A lot of times there's more than one hidden layer.
We're only showing one in this picture, but we'll show you how it looks like in a more detail in a little bit. And then finally we have an output layer.
This layer delivers the final result.
So the only two things we see is the input layer and the output layer.
Now let's make use of this neural network and see how it works. Wonder how traffic cameras identify vehicles registration plate on the road to detect speeding vehicles and those breaking the law?
They got me going through a red light the other day. Well, last month. That's like the horrible thing.
They send you this picture of you and all your information because they pulled it up off of your license plate and your picture. I shouldn't have gone through the red light.
So here we are, and we have an image of a car, and you can see the license plates on there. So let's consider the image of this vehicle and find out what's on the number plate.
The picture itself is 28 by 28 pixels. And the image is fed as an input to identify the registration plate.
Each neuron has a number called activation that represents the grayscale value of the corresponding pixel range. And we range it from zero to one, one for a white pixel and zero for a black pixel.
And you can see down here we have an example where one of the pixels is registered as like 0.82, meaning it's probably pretty dark. Each neuron is lit up when its activation is close to one.
So as we get closer to black on white, we can really start seeing the details in there. And you can see again the pixel shows this one up there. It's like part of the car. And so it lights up.
So pixels in the form of arrays are fed to the input layer.
And so we see here the pixel of a car image fed as an input. And you're going to see that the input layer, which is green, is one dimension, while our image is two dimension.
Now, when we look at our setup that we're programming in Python, it has a cool feature that automatically does the work for us.
If you're working with an older neural network pattern package, you then convert each one of those rows so it's all one array. So you'd have like row one and then just tack row two onto the end.
You can almost feed the image directly into some of these neural networks.
The key is though, is that if you're using a 28 by 28 and you get a picture of this 30 by 30, shrink the 30 by 30 down to fit the 28 by 28.
So you can't increase the number of input, in this case green dots. It's very important to remember when you work on neural networks. And let's name the inputs x1, x2, x3 respectively.
So each one of those represents one of the pixels coming in. And the input layer passes it to the hidden layer.
And you can see here we now have two hidden layers in this image, in the orange, and each one of those pixels connects to each one of those hidden layers.
And the interconnections are assigned weights at random. So they get these random weights that come through. If x1 lights up, then it's going to be x1 times this weight going into the hidden layer.
And we sum those weights. The weights are multiplied with the input signal, and a bias is added to all of them.
So as you can see here, we have x1 comes in and it actually goes to all the different hidden layer nodes, or in this case whatever you want to call them, network setup,
the orange dots.
And so you take the value of x1, you multiply it by the weight for the next hidden layer.
So x1 goes to hidden layer 1, x1 goes to hidden layer 2, x1 goes to hidden layer 1, node 2, hidden layer 1, node 3, and so on.
And the bias, a lot of times they just put the bias in as like another green dot or another orange dot.
And they give the bias a value 1, and then all the weights go in from the bias into the next node. So the bias can change. We always just remember that you need to have that bias in there.
There's things that can be done with it. Generally, most of the packages out there control that for you, so you don't have to worry about figuring out what the bias is.
But if you ever dive deep into neural networks, you've got to remember there's a bias, or the answer won't come out correctly.
The weighted sum of the input is fed as an input to the activation function to decide which nodes to fire, and for feature extraction.
As a signal flows within the hidden layers, the weighted sum of inputs is calculated and is fed to the activation function in each layer to decide which nodes to fire.
So here's our feature extraction of the number plate. And you can see these are still hidden nodes in the middle. And this becomes important.
We're going to take a little detour here and look at the activation function.
So we're going to dive just a little bit into the math. So you can start to understand where some of the games go on when you're playing with neural networks in your programming.
So let's look at the different activation functions.
Before we move ahead, here's our friendly red tag shopping robot. And so one is a sigmoid function.
And the sigmoid function, which is one over one plus e to the minus x, takes the x value and you can see where it generates almost a zero and almost a one
with a very small area in the middle where it crosses over. And we can use that value to feed into another function. So if it's really uncertain, it might have a 0 one or 0 two or 0 three.
But for the most part, it's going to be really close to one and really close to in this case zero, zero to one. The threshold function.
So if you don't want to worry about the uncertainty in the middle, you just say, oh, if x is greater than or equal to zero, if not, then x is zero. So it's either zero or one.
Really straightforward, there's no in between in the middle.
And then you have what they call the
relu function.
And you can see here where it puts out the value, but then it says, well, if it's over one, it's going to be one. And if it's less than zero, it's zero.
So it kind of just dead ends it on those two ends, but allows all the values in the middle. And again, this like the sigmoid function allows that information to go to the next level.
So it might be important to know if it's a 0 one or a minus 0 one.
The next hidden layer might pick that up and say, oh, this piece of information is uncertain, or this value has a very low certainty to it.
And then the hyperbolic tangent function. And you can see here it's a 1 minus e to the minus 2x over 1 plus e to the minus 2x.
And it's very much along the same theme. A little bit different in here in that it goes between minus 1 and 1.
So you'll see some of these they go 0 to 1, but this one goes minus 1 to 1.
And if it's less than 0, it's, you know, it doesn't fire. And if it's over 0, it fires. And it also still puts out a value.
So you still have a value you can get off of that, just like you can with the sigmoid function and the ReLU function. Very similar in use.
And I believe the original used to be everything was done in the sigmoid function. That was the most commonly used. And now they just kind of use more the ReLU function.
The reason is one, it processes faster, because you already have the value and you don't have to add another compute the one over one plus e to the minus x for each hidden node.
And the data coming off works pretty good as far as putting it into the next level if you want to know just how close it is to zero. How close is it not to functioning?
You know, is it minus 0.1, minus 0.2? Usually they're float values, you get like minus 0.00138 or something.
So, you know, important information. But the ReLU is most commonly used these days as far as the setup we're using. But you'll also see the sigmoid function very commonly used also.
Now that you know what an activation function is, let's get back to the neural network.
So finally the model would predict the outcome of applying a suitable activation function to the output layer.
So we go in here we look at this we have the optical character recognition, OCR, is used on the images to convert it into a text in order to identify what's written on the plate.
And as it comes out, you'll see the red node, and the red node might actually represent just a letter A. So there's usually a lot of outputs when you're doing text identification.
We're not going to show that on here. But you might have it even in the order, it might be what order the license plate's in.
So you might have A, B, C, D, E, F, G, you know, the alphabet plus the numbers, and you might have the one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten
places.
So it's a very large array that comes out. It's not a small amount of uh, you know, we show three dots coming in, eight hidden layer nodes, you know, two sets of four, we just show one red coming out.
A lot of times this is uh you know, twenty-eight times 28. If you did 30 times 30, that's 900 nodes. So 28 is a little bit less than that, just on the input.
And so you can imagine the hidden layer is just as big, each hidden layer is just as big if not bigger, and the output is going to be there's so many digits, you know,
it's a lot, there's it's a huge amount of input and output. But we're only showing you just you know, it's it'd be hard to show in one picture.
And so it comes up, and this is what it finally gets out on the output is it identifies a number on the plate. And in this case we have 08-d dash zero three eight five eight.
Error in the output is back propagated through the network, and weights are adjusted to minimize the error rate. This is calculated by a cost function.
When we're training our data, this is what's used. And we'll look at that in the code when we do the data training.
So we have stuff we know the answer to, and then we put the information through, and it says, yes, that was correct, or no, because remember we randomly set all the weights to begin with.
And if it's wrong, we take that error. How far off are you? You know, are you off by is it if it was like minus one, you're just a little bit off.
If it's like minus 300 was your output, remember when we're looking at those different options, you know, hyperbolic or whatever, and we're looking at the REL, the REL could
doesn't have a limit on top or bottom. It actually just generates a number. So if it's way off, you have to adjust those weights a lot.
But if it's pretty close, you might adjust the weights just a little bit.
And you keep adjusting the weights until they fit all the different training models you put in.
So you might have 500 training models, and those weights will adjust using the back propagation.
It sends the error backward.
The output is compared with the original result, and multiple iterations are done to get the maximum accuracy.
So not only does it look at each one, but it goes through it and just keeps cycling through these the data and making small changes in the network until it gets the right answers.
With every iteration, the weights at every interconnection are adjusted based on the error.
We're not going to dive into that math, because it is a differential equation, and it gets a little complicated.
But I will talk a little bit about some of the different options they have when we look at the code.
So we've explored a neural network.
Let's look at the different types of artificial neural networks. And this is like the biggest area growing is how these all come together. Let's see the different types of neural network.
And again, we're comparing this to human learning.
So here's a human brain. I feel sorry for that poor guy.
So we have a feed forward neural network.
Simplest form of a they call it an ANN, a neural network. Data travels only in one direction, input to output.
This is what we just looked at.
So as the data comes in, all the weights are added, it goes to the hidden layer, all the weights are added, it goes to the next hidden layer, all the weights are added, and it goes to the output.
The only time you use the reverse propagation is to train it.
So when you actually use it, it's very fast.
When you're training it, it takes a while because it has to iterate through all your training data. And you start getting into big data because you can train these with a huge amount of data.
The more data you put in, the better train they get.
The applications, vision and speech recognition, actually they're pretty much everything we talked about. A lot of almost all of them use this form of neural network at some level.
Radio basis function, neural network. This model classifies the data point based on its distance from a center point.
What that means is that you might not have training data, so you want to group things together and you create central points and it looks for all the things,
you know, some of these things are just like the other. If you've ever watched the Sesame Street as a kid, that dates me.
So it brings things together, and this is a great way if you don't have the right training model, you can start finding things that are connected you might not have noticed before.
Applications, power restoration systems.
They try to figure out what's connected, and then based on that, they can fix the problem if you have a huge power system.
Cahonan's self-organizing neural network. Vectors of random dimensions are input to discrete map comprised of neurons.
So they basically find a way to draw, and they call them, they say dimensions or vectors, or planes, because they actually chop the data in one dimension,
two dimension, three dimension, four, five, six. They keep adding dimensions and finding ways to separate the data and connect different data pieces together.
Applications used to recognize patterns in data, like in medical analysis.
The hidden layer saves its output to be used for future prediction. Recurrent neural networks. So the hidden layers remember its output from last time and that becomes part of its new input.
You might use that, especially in robotics or flying a drone.
You want to know what your last change was and how fast it was going to help predict what your next change you need to make is to get to where the drone wants to go.
Applications, text-to-speech, conversation model. So you know I talked about drones, but you know, just identifying on Lexus or Google Assistant or any of these, they're starting to add in.
I'd like to play a song on my Pandora, and I'd like it to be at volume 90%. So you now can add different things in there and it connects them together.
The input features are taken in batches, like a filter.
This allows a network to remember an image in parts.
Convolution, neural network.
Today's world in photo identification and taking apart photos and trying to, you know, have you ever seen that on Google where you have five people together?
This is the kind of thing that separates all those people so that it can do a face recognition on each person. Applications used in signal and image processing.
In this case, I used facial images or Google picture images as one of the options.
Modular neural network.
It has a collection of different neural networks working together to get the output. So wow, we just went through all these different types of neural networks.
And the final one is to put multiple neural networks together.
I mentioned that a little bit when we separated people in a larger photo and individuals in the photo and then do the facial recognition on each person.
So one network is used to separate them, and the next network is then used to figure out who they are and do the facial recognition. Applications still undergoing research. This is a cutting edge.
You hear the term pipeline, and there's actual in Python code and in almost all the different neural network setups out there, they now have a pipeline feature usually.
And it just means you take the data from one neural network and maybe another neural network, or you put it into the next neural network,
and then you take three or four other neural networks and feed them into another one. So how we connect the neural networks is really just cutting edge and it's so experimental.
I mean it's almost creative in its nature. There's not really a science to it because each specific domain has different things it's looking at.
So if you're in the banking domain, it's going to be different than the medical domain, then the automatic car domain.
And suddenly figuring out how those all fit together is just a lot of fun and really cool.
So we have our types of artificial neural network.
We have our feed forward neural network, we have a radial basis function neural network, we have our Kohenan self-organizing neural network, recurrent neural network,
convolution neural network, and modular neural network where it brings them all together.
And uh no, the colors on the brain do not match what your brain actually does, but they do bring it out that most of these were developed by understanding how humans learn.
And as we understand more and more of how humans learn, we can build something in the computer industry to mimic that, to reflect that.
And that's how these were developed.
So exciting part, use case, problem statement. So this is where we jump in. This is my favorite part. Let's use the system to identify between a cat and a dog.
If you remember correctly, I said we're going to do some Python code, and you can see over here my hair is kind of sticking up over the computer, a cup of coffee on one side, and
a little bit of old school, a pencil and a pen on the other side. Yeah, most people now take notes. I love the stickies on the computer, that's great.
that is my computer. I have sticky notes on my computer in different colors. So not too far from today's programmer.
So the problem is is we want to classify photos of cats and dogs using a neural network.
And you can see over here we have quite a variety of dogs in the pictures and cats, and you know, just sorting out it is a cat is pretty amazing.
And why would anybody want to even know the difference between a cat and a dog?
Okay, you know, why? Well, I have a cat door.
It'd be kind of fun that instead of it identifying, instead of having like a little collar with a magnet on it, which is what my cat has, the door would be able to see,
oh, that's the cat, that's our cat coming in. Oh, that's the dog. We have a dog too. That's the dog I want to let in. Maybe I don't want to let this other animal in because it's a raccoon.
So you can see where you could take this one step further and actually apply this. You could actually start a little startup company idea, a self-identifying door.
So this use case will be implemented on Python. I am actually in Python 3.6.
It's always nice to tell people the version of Python because that does affect sometimes which modules you load and everything. And we're going to start by importing the required packages.
I told you we're going to do this in Karas. So we're going to import from Karas models a sequential from the Karas Layers, Conversion 2D or C O N V 2D, Max Pooling 2D,
Flatten, and dense.
And we'll talk about what each one of these do in just a second. But before we do that, let's talk a little bit about the environment we're going to work in.
And uh, you know, in fact, let me go ahead and open the website, Karas' website, so we can learn a little bit more about Karas.
So here we are on the Karas website, and it's K E R A S dot Io.
That's the official website for Karas. And the first thing you'll notice is that Carras runs on top of either TensorFlow, CNTK, and I think it's pronounced Thano or Theano.
What's important on here is that TensorFlow, and the same is true for all these, but TensorFlow is probably one of the most widely used currently packages out there with the Carras.
And of course, you know, tomorrow this is all going to change. It's all going to disappear and they'll have something new out there.
So make sure when you're learning this code that you understand what's going on. And also know the code. I mean, when you look at the code, it's not as complicated once you understand what's going on.
The code itself is pretty straightforward.
And the reason we like Caras, and the reason that people are jumping on it right now, and it's such a big deal, is if we come down here, let me just scroll down a little bit.
They talk about user friendliness, modularity, easy extensibility, work with Python.
Python's a big one, because a lot of people in data science now use Python, although you can actually access Caras other ways. If we continue down here is layers.
And this is where it gets really cool.
When we're working with Caras, you just add layers on. Remember those hidden layers we were talking about? And we talked about the RELU activation.
You can see right here, let me just up that a little bit in size. There we go. That's big. I can add in an RELU layer, and then I can add in a softmax layer, in the next instance.
We didn't talk about softmax. So you can do each layer separate. Now, if I'm working in some of the other kits I use, I take that and I have one setup and then I feed the output into the next one.
This one I can just add hidden layer after hidden layer with the different information in it, which makes it very powerful and very fast to spin up and try different setups
and see how they work with the data you're working on. And we'll dig a little bit deeper in here. And a lot of this is very much the same, so when we get to that part, I'll point that out to you also.
Now, just a quick side note, I'm using Anaconda with Python in it, and I went ahead and created my own package, and I called it the Karas Python 3.6
because I'm in Python 3.6. Anaconda is cool that way. You can create different environments real easily.
If you're doing a lot of different experimenting with these different packages, you probably want to create your own environment in there.
And the first thing is you can see right here, there's a lot of dependencies. A lot of these you should recognize by now if you've done any of these videos.
If not, kudos for you for jumping in today.
Pip install numpy, scipy, the sci kit learn.
Pillow and h5py are both needed for the TensorFlow and then putting the caras on there. And then you'll see here, and pip is just a standard installer that you use with Python.
You'll see here that we did pip install tensorflow. Since we're going to do caras on top of TensorFlow.
And then pip install, and I went ahead and used the GitHub. So Git plus Git. And you'll see here GitHub.com.
This is one of their releases, one of the most current release on there that goes on top of TensorFlow. And you can look up these instructions pretty much anywhere. This is for doing it on Anaconda.
Certainly you'd want to install these if you're doing it in Ubuntu server setup.
You'd you'd want to get, I don't think you need the H5PY in Ubuntu, but you do need the rest in there because they are dependencies in there. And it's pretty straightforward.
And that's actually in some of the instructions they have on their website. So you don't have to necessarily go through this. Just remember their website on there.
And then when I'm under my Anaconda navigator, which I like, you'll see where I have environments, and on the bottom I created a new environment and I called it CrossPython 36.
Just to separate everything. You can say I have Python 3.5 and Python 3.6. I used to have a bunch of other ones, but I kind of cleaned house recently.
And of course, once I go in here, I can launch my Jupyter notebook, making sure I'm using the right environment that I just set up.
This of course opens up my in this case I'm using Google Chrome.
And in here I could go and just create a new document in here. And this is all in your browser window when you use the Anaconda. Do you have to use Anaconda in Jupyter Notebook?
No.
You can use any kind of Python editor, whatever setup you're comfortable with and whatever you're doing in there.
So let's go ahead and go in here and paste the code in.
And we're importing a number of different settings in here. We have import sequential, that's under the models, because that's the model we're going to use as far as our neural network.
And then we have layers and we have conversion 2D, max pooling 2D, flatten, dense. And you can actually just kind of guess at what these do. We're talking, we're working in a 2D photograph.
And if you remember correctly, I talked about how the actual input layer is a single array. It's not in two dimensions, it's one dimension.
All these do is these are tools to help flatten the image. So it takes a two-dimensional image and then it creates its own proper setup. You don't have to worry about any of that.
You don't have to do anything special with the photograph. You let the Karas do it.
We're going to run this, and you'll see right here they have some stuff that is going to be depreciated and changed because that's what it does. Everything's being changed as we go.
You don't have to worry about that too much. If you have warnings, if you run it a second time, the warning will disappear.
And this has just imported these packages for us to use. Jupiter's nice about this that you can do each thing step by step. And I'll go ahead and also zoom in there. A little control plus.
That's one of the nice things about being in a browser environment.
So here we are back, another sip of coffee. If you're familiar with my other videos, you notice I'm always sipping coffee. I always have a in my case latte next to me, an espresso.
So the next step is to go ahead and initialize, we're going to call it the CNN or Classifier Neural Network.
And the reason we call it a classifier is because it's going to classify it between two things. It's going to be cat or dog. So when you're doing classification, you're picking specific objects.
it's a true or false. Yes, no. It is something or it's not.
So first thing we're going to create our classifier and it's going to equal sequential.
So their sequential setup is the classifier. That's the actual model we're using. That's the neural network. So we call it a classifier. And the next step is to add in our convolution.
And let me just do a uh let me shrink that down inside so you can see the whole line.
And let's talk a little bit about what's going on here.
I have my classifier and I add something. What am I adding? Well, I'm adding my first layer.
This first layer we're adding in is probably the one that takes the most work to make sure you have it set correct.
And the reason I say that this is your actual input. And we're going to jump here to the part that says input shape equals 64 by 64 by 3.
What does that mean? Well, that means that our picture's coming in, and there's these pictures, remember we had like the picture of the car was 128 by 128 pixels?
Well, this one is 64 by 64 pixels, and each pixel has three values.
That's where these numbers come from.
And it is so important that this matches. I mentioned a little bit that if you have like a larger picture, you have to reformat it to fit this shape.
If it comes in as something larger, there's no input notes. There's no input neural network there that will handle that extra space. So you have to reshape your data to fit in here.
Now, the first layer is the most important because after that, Karas knows what your shape is coming in here and it knows what's coming out.
And so that really sets the stage. Most important thing is that input shape matches your data coming in. And you'll get a lot of errors if it doesn't.
You'll go through there and picture number 55 doesn't match it correctly. And guess what it does? It usually gives you an error.
And then the activation, if you remember we talked about the different activations on here, we're using the RELU model.
Like I said, that is the most commonly used now because one, it's fast, doesn't have the added calculations in it. It just says here's the value coming out based on the weights and the value going in.
And from there, you know, it's uh it's if it's over one, then it's good, or over zero, it's good. If it's under zero, then it's considered not active. And then we have this conversion 2D.
What the heck is conversion 2D?
I'm not going to go into too much detail in this, because this has a couple of things it's doing in here, a little bit more in-depth than we're ready to cover in this tutorial,
but this is used to convert from the photo, because we have 64 by 64 by three, and we're just converting it to two-dimensional kind of setup.
So it's very aware that this is a photograph and that different pieces are next to each other.
And then we're going to add in a second convolutional layer. That's what the C O N V stands for, 2D.
So these are hidden layers. So we have our input layer and our two hidden layers, and they are two dimensional, because we're doing with a two dimensional photograph.
And you'll see down here that on the last one we add a max pooling 2D.
And we put a pool size equals two, two. And so what this is, is that as you get to the end of these layers, one of the things you always want to think of is what they call mapping and then reducing.
Wonderful terminology from the big data. We're mapping this data through all these layers, and now we want to reduce it to only two sets.
In this case, it's already in two sets because it's a 2D photograph. But we had, you know, two dimensions by we actually have 64 by 64 by 3. So now we're just getting it down to a two by two.
just the two dimension two dimensional, instead of having the third dimension of colors. And we'll go ahead and run these.
We're not really seeing anything on our run script because we're just setting up. This is all set up.
And this is where you start playing, because maybe you'll add a different layer in here to do something else to see how it works and see what your output is.
That's what makes Karas so nice, is I can with just a couple flips of code put in a whole new layer that does a whole new processing and see whether that improves my run or makes it worse.
And finally, we're going to do the final setup, which is to flatten.
Classifier add a flatten setup. And then we're going to also add a layer, a dense layer, and then we're going to add in another dense layer, and then we're going to build it.
We're going to compile this whole thing together.
So let's flip over and see what that looks like. And we've even numbered them for you, so we're going to do the flattening. And flatten is exactly what it sounds like.
We've been working in a two-dimensional array of picture, which actually is in three dimensions because of the pixels. The pixels have a whole other dimension to it of three different values.
And we've kind of resized those down to two by two, but now we're just going to flatten it.
I don't want to have multiple dimensions being worked on by tensor and by karas. I want just a single array so it's flattened out.
And then step four, full connection. So we add in our final two layers. And you could actually do all kinds of things with this.
You could actually leave out this some of these layers and play with them. You do need to flatten it.
That's very important.
Then we want to use the dents. Again, we're taking this and we're taking whatever came into it.
So once we take all those different the two dimensions or three dimensions as they are, and we flatten it to one dimension, we want to take that and we're going to pull it into units of 128.
They got that. You're going to say, where did they get 128 from? You could actually play with that number and get all kinds of weird results. But in this case, we took the 64 plus 64 is 128.
You could probably even do this with 64 or 32. Usually you want to keep it in the same multiple, whatever the data shape you're already using is in.
And we're using the activation, the R-E-L-U, just like we did before. And then we finally filter all that into a single output.
And it has how many units? One. Why? Because we want to know whether true or false. It's either a dog or a cat.
You could say one is dog, zero is cat, or maybe you're a cat lover and it's one is cat and zero is dog. And if you love both dogs and cats, you're going to have to choose.
And then we use the sigmoid activation. If you remember from before, we had the R E L U, and there's also the Sigmoid. The sigmoid just makes it clear it's yes or no.
We don't want any kind of in-between number coming out. And we'll go ahead and run this, and you'll see it's still all in setup. And then finally we want to go ahead and compile.
And let's put the compiling our classifier neural network.
And we're going to use the optimizer atom. And I hinted at this just a little bit before. Where does Atom come in? Where does an optimizer come in?
Well, the optimizer is the reverse propagation. When we're training it, it goes all the way through and says error, and then how does it readjust those weights? There are a number of them.
Atom is the most commonly used and it works best on large data.
Most people stick with the atom.
Because when they're testing on smaller data, see if their model is going to go through and get all their errors out before they run it on larger data sets.
They're going to run it on atom anyway, so they just leave it on atom, most commonly used. But there are some other ones out there.
You should be aware of that that you might try them if you're stuck in a bind or you might blur that in the future. But usually atom is just fine on there. And then you have two more settings.
You have loss and metrics.
We're not going to dig too much into loss or metrics. These are things you really have to explore corros because there are so many choices. This is how it computes the error.
There's so many different ways to on your back propagation and your training. So we're using the Atom model, but you can compute the error by standard deviation, standard deviation squared.
They use binary cross-entropy. I'd have to look that up to even know what that is. There's so many of these.
A lot of times you just start with the ones that look correct, that are most commonly used, and then you have to go read the Caras
site and actually see what these different losses and metrics and what different options they have.
So we're not going to get too much into them other than to reference you over to the Caras website to explore them deeper. But we are going to go ahead and run them.
And now we've set up our classifier. So we have an object classifier. And if you go back up here, you'll see that we've added in step one, we added in our layer for the input.
We added a layer that comes in there and uses the RELU for activation. And then it pulls the data.
So this is, even though these are two layers, the actual neural network layer is up here, and then it uses this to pull the data into a two by two.
So into a two-dimensional array from a three-dimensional array with the colors.
Then we flatten it. So there's our adder flatten. And then we add another dense, what they call dense layer. This dense layer goes in there and it downsizes it to 128. It reduces it.
So you can look at this as we're mapping all this data down the two-dimensional setup, and then we flatten it.
So we map it to a flattened map, and then we take it and reduce it down to 128, and we use the R E L U again.
And then finally we reduce that down to just a single output.
And we use the sigmoid to do that, to figure out whether it's yes, no, true, false, in this case cat or dog.
And then finally, once we put all these layers together, we compile them.
That's what we've done here.
And we've compiled them as far as how it trains to use these settings for the training, back propagation.
So if you remember, we talked about training our setup.
And when we go into this, you'll see that we have two data sets. We have one called the training set and the testing set.
And that's very standard in any data processing, is you need to have that's pretty common in any data processing is you need to have a certain amount of data to train it,
and then you gotta know whether it works or not. Is it any good?
And that's why you have a separate set of data for testing it.
Where you already know the answer, but you don't want to use that as part of the training set.
So in here we jump into part two, fitting the classifier neural network to the images.
And then from Carras, and let me just zoom in there. I always love that about working with Jupyter Notebooks you can really see.
We're going to come in here, we do the cross pre-processing an image, and we import image data generator.
It's so nice of Carras, it's such a high-end product right now going out, and since images are so common, they already have all this stuff to help us process the data,
which is great. And so we come in here, we do train data gen, and we're going to create our object for helping us train it for reshaping the data so that it's gonna work with our setup.
And we use an image data generator, and we're gonna rescale it.
And you'll see here we have one point, which tells us it's a float value on the rescale over 255.
Where does 255 come from? Well, that's the scale in the colors of the pictures we're using.
their value from zero to 255.
So we want to divide it by 255 and it'll generate a number between zero and one.
They have shear range and zoom range, horizontal flip equals true. And this of course has to do with if the photos are different shapes and sizes. Like I said, it's a wonderful package.
You really need to dig in deep to see all the different options you have for setting up your images. For right now, though, we're gonna just stick with some basic stuff here.
And let me go ahead and run this code. And again, it doesn't really do anything because we're still setting up the pre processing. Let's take a look at this next set of code.
And this one is just huge. We're creating the training set.
So the training set is going to go in here and it's going to use our train data gen we just created.flow from directory. It's gonna access, in this case, the path data set training set.
That's a folder.
So it's going to pull all the images out of that folder.
Now I'm actually running this in the folder that the data sets in.
So if you're doing the same setup and you load your data in there and you're doing this, make sure wherever your Jupyter Notebook is saving things to
that you create this path, or you can do the complete path if you need to, you know, Clash, etc.
And the target size, the batch size, and class mode is binary.
So the classes we're switching everything to a binary value.
Batch size, what the heck is batch size? Well that's how many pictures we're going to batch through the training each time.
And the target size, 64 by 64.
A little confusing, but you can see right here that this is just a general training, and you can go in there and look at all the different settings for your training set.
And of course with different data, we're doing pictures, there's all kinds of different settings depending on what you're working with.
Let's go ahead and run that and see what happens.
And you'll see that it found 800 images belonging to one classes.
So we have 800 images in the training set.
And if we're gonna do this with the training set, we also have to format the pictures in the test set.
Now we're not actually doing any predictions, we're not actually programming the model yet.
All we're doing is preparing the data. So we're gonna prepare a training set and the test set. So any changes we make to the training set at this point also have to be made to the test set.
So we've done this thing, we've done a train data generator, we've done our training set, and then we also have, remember our test set of data. So I'm going to do the same thing with that.
I'm going to create a test data gen, and we're going to do this image data generator. We're going to rescale one over 255.
We don't need the other settings, just the single setting for the test data gen. And we're going to create our test set.
We're going to do the same thing we did with the test set, except that we're pulling it from the test set folder.
And we'll run that.
And you'll see in our test set we found 2,000 images.
That's about right. We're using 20% of the images as test and 80% to train it. And then finally we've set up all our data.
We've set up all our layers, which is where all the work is, is cleaning up that data and making sure it's going in there correctly, and we are actually going to fit it.
We're going to train our data set.
And let's see what that looks like.
And here we go, let's put the information in here, and let's just take a quick look at what we're looking at with our fit generator.
We have our classifier dot fit generator.
That's our back propagation.
So the information goes through forward with a picture, and it says, oh, you're either right or you're wrong, and then the error goes backward and reprograms all those weights.
So we're training our neural network.
And of course we're using the training set. Remember we created the training set up here, and then we're going steps per epoch.
So it's eight thousand steps. Epic means that that's how many times we go through all the pictures.
So we're going to rerun each of the pictures and we're going to go through the whole data set 25 times. But we're going to look at each picture during each epoch 8,000 times.
So we're really programming the heck out of this and going back over it.
And then they have validation data equals test set. So we have our training set, and then we're gonna have our test set to validate it.
So we're gonna do this all in one shot, and we're gonna look at that and they're gonna do 200 steps for each validation.
And we'll see what that looks like in just a minute.
Let's go ahead and run our training here.
And we're gonna fit our data.
And as it goes, this says Epic 1 of 25, you start realizing that this is gonna take a while.
On my older computer, it takes about 45 minutes. I have a dual processor. we're processing uh 10,000 photos. That's not a small amount of photographs to process.
So if you're on your laptop, you know which I am, it's gonna take a while. So let's go ahead and uh go get our cup of coffee and a sip and come back and see what this looks like.
So I'm back.
You didn't know I was gone. I was actually a lengthy pause there. I made a couple changes, and let's discuss those changes real quick and why I made them.
So the first thing I'm gonna do is I'm gonna go up here and insert a cell above, and let's paste the original code back in there.
And you'll see that the original thing was steps per epic eight,000, 25 epics, and validation steps two thousand.
And I changed these to four thousand epics or four thousand steps per epic.
10 epics and just ten validation steps. And this will cause problems if you're doing this as a commercial release. But for demo purposes this should work.
And if you remember, our steps per epic, that's how many photos we're going to process. In fact, let me go ahead and get my drawing pen out.
And uh let's just highlight that right here. Well we have 8,000 pictures we're going through.
So for each epic, I'm gonna change this to 4,000. I'm gonna cut that in half. So it's gonna randomly pick 4,000 pictures each time it goes through an epic. And the epic is how many processes.
So this is 25, and I'm just gonna cut that to 10.
So instead of doing 25 runs through 8,000 photos each, which you can do the math of 25 times 8,000, I'm only gonna do 10 through 4,000.
So I'm going to run this 40,000 times through the processes.
And the next thing
you'll want to notice is that I also changed the validation step. And this would cause some major problems in releasing, because I dropped it all the way down to 10.
What the validation step does is it says we have 2,000 photos in our trainings or in our testing set, and we're going to use that for validation.
Well, I'm only going to use a random ten of those to validate. So not really the best settings, but let me show you why we did that.
Let's scroll down here just a little bit, and let's look at the output here and see what that what's going on there.
So I've got my drawing tool back on, and you'll see here it lists a run.
So each time it goes through an epic, it's going to do 4,000 steps. And this is where the 4,000 comes in. So that's where we have. We have epic one of ten, four thousand steps.
it's randomly picking half the pictures in the file and going through them. And then we're gonna look at this number right here.
That is for the whole epic, and that's two thousand four hundred and eleven seconds. And if you remember correctly, you divide that by 60 you get minutes. If you divide that by 60 you get hours.
Or you can just divide the whole thing by 60 times 60 which is thirty-six hundred. If thirty six hundred is an hour, this is roughly 45 minutes right here.
And that's 45 minutes to process half the pictures. So if I was doing all the pictures, we're talking an hour and a half per epic times 36. Or no, 25. They had 25 up above.
25. So that's roughly a couple days.
A couple days of processing. Well, for this demo, we don't want to do that. I don't want to come back the next day. Plus, my computer did a reboot in the middle of the night.
So we look at this and we say, okay, let's we're just testing this out. My computer that I'm running this on is a dual core processor, uh runs 0.9 gigahertz per second.
For a laptop, you know, it was good about four years ago, but for running something like this it's probably a little slow. So we cut the times down, and the last one was validation.
We're only validating it on a random ten photos. And this comes into effect because you're going to see down here where we have accuracy, value loss, value accuracy, and loss.
Those are very important numbers to look at.
So the 10 means I'm only validating across 10 pictures.
That is where here we have value. This is ACC is for accuracy, value loss, we're not going to worry about that too much, and accuracy.
Now accuracy is while it's running, it's putting these two numbers together. That's what accuracy is.
And value accuracy is at the end of the epic. What's our accuracy at the end of the epic? What is it looking at?
In this tutorial, we're not going to go so deep, but these numbers are really important when you start talking about these two numbers reflect bias.
That is really important. Let me just put that up there. And bias is a little bit beyond this tutorial, but the short of it is if this accuracy, which is being our validation per step, is going
down and the value accuracy continues to go up, that means there's a bias.
That means I'm memorizing the photos I'm looking at.
I'm not actually looking for what makes a dog a dog, what makes a cat a cat.
I'm just memorizing them. And so the more this discrepancy grows, the bigger the bias is. And that is really the beauty of the Karas.
Neural network. It is a lot of built-in features like this that make that really easy to track. So let's go ahead and take a look at the next set of code.
So here we are into part three. We're going to make a new prediction. And so we're going to bring in a couple tools for that.
And then we have to process the image coming in and find out whether it's an actual dog or cat. We can actually use this to identify it.
And of course, the final step of part three is to print prediction. We'll go ahead and combine these. And of course you can see me there adding more sticky notes to my computer screen.
Hidden behind the screen. And you know, last one was don't forget to feed the cat and the dog.
So let's go ahead and take a look at that and see what that looks like in code and put that in our Jupyter notebook. All right. And let's paste that in here.
And we'll start by importing NumPy as NP. NumPy is a very common package. I pretty much import it on any Python project I'm working on. Another one I use regularly is pandas.
They're just ways of organizing the data. And then np is usually the standard in most machine learning tools as a return for the data array.
Although you know you can use a standard data array from Python. And we have cross, pre-processing, import image.
This should all look familiar because we're going to take a test image and we're going to set that equal to, in this case, cat or dog one, as you can see over here.
And you know what? Let me get my drawing tool back on.
So let's take a look at this. We have our test image we're loading.
And in here we have test image one. And this one hasn't data hasn't seen this one at all. So this is all new.
Oh, let me shrink the screen down. Let me start that over.
So here we have my test image. And we went ahead and the cross processing has this nice image setup. So we're going to load the image and we're going to alter it to a 64 by 64 print.
So right off the bat we're gonna cross this nice that way it automatically sets it up for us so we don't have to redo all our images and find a way to reset those.
And then we use also to set the image to an array. So again, we're all in pre-processing the data, just like we pre-processed before with our test information and our training data.
And then we use the numpy.
Here's our numpy that's from our right up here, important numpy as in p. Expand the dimensions test image axes equal zero. So puts it into a single array.
And then finally, all that work, all that pre-processing, and all we do is we run the result.
We click on here we go result equals classifier, predict test image, and then we find out well what is the test image? And let's just take a quick look and just see what that is.
And you can see when I ran it, it comes up dog, and if we look at those images, there it is, cat or dog, image number one.
That looks like a nice floppy-eared lab.
Friendly with his tongue hanging out. It's either that or a very floppy-eared cat. I'm not sure which. But according to our software, it says it's a dog.
And we have a second picture over here. Let's just see what happens we run the second picture.
We can go up here and change this from dog image one to two.
We'll run that, and it comes down here and says cat. You can see me highlighting it down there as cat. So our process works. We are able to label a dog a dog and a cat a cat just from the pictures.
There we go, cleared my drawing tool. And the last thing I want you to notice, when we come back up here to when I ran it, you'll see it has an accuracy of one and the value accuracy of one.
Well, the value accuracy is the important one, because the value accuracy is what it actually runs on the test data. Remember I'm only testing it on I'm only validating it on a random ten photos.
And those ten photos just happened to come up one. Now, when they ran this on the server, it actually came up about 86%. This is why cutting these numbers down so far for a commercial release is bad.
So you want to make sure you're a little careful of that when you're testing your stuff that you change these numbers back when you run it on a more enterprise computer
other than your old laptop that you're just practicing on or messing with. And we come down here and again, you know, we had the validation of cat.
And so we have successfully built a neural network that could distinguish between photos of a cat and a dog. Imagine all the other things you could distinguish.
Imagine all the different industries you could dive into with that, just being able to understand those two difference of pictures. What about mosquitoes?
Could you find the mosquitoes that bite versus the mosquitoes that are friendly?
It turns out the mosquitoes that bite us are only four percent of the mosquito population, if even that, maybe two There's all kinds of industries that use this,
and there's so many industries that are just now realizing how powerful these tools are. Just in the photos alone, there is a myriad of industries sprouting up.
And I said it before, I'll say it again. What an exciting time to live in with these tools that we get to play with. So, key takeaways. Well, we covered what is a neural network.
We use all kinds of processing, the map images on your phone. We talked about things that a neural network can do.
Translate text, identify faces, all the way to control robots, you know, lots of exciting things. How does a neural network work?
So we discussed that with the different layers, going from the picture to the input layer, to the hidden layers and their weights to the final output layer.
We also talked about how it does the math and computing the output as yes or no, categorically true-false.
We discussed types of artificial neural networks. A lot of vocabulary there from the feed forward neural network, which is the most commonly used.
That's the one the neural network we used is a feed forward neural network that does backward propagation to train. And there's all a lot of other ones out there.
There's the radial biases, the Kohinen self-organizing, recurrent neural network, convolution neural network, modular neural network.
The big one was modular because it incorporates pieces of all the other ones, so that whatever you're working on now is a huge conglomerate of multiple networks. Just all cutting edge.
All of it's new. People even working on it don't even know where it's going. Again, very exciting times. And finally, we dug through my favorite part.
You can see with my latte on one side, my old school pens and pencil, and all my sticky notes working away. That's not actually me, by the way. You probably guessed that.
And we walked through and actually did a cat and dog photo, a simple cat and dog photo, and you could see where some of the problems are in processing large amounts of photographs and data,
where that starts to become going from a single machine on my laptop with its lower amount of resources all the way to big data.
How if you're processing hundreds and thousands of these photos, this now needs to be set up on an enterprise machine or even on a cluster of computers. Again, significantly past the scope of this.
The neat part about it though is once you write this code, MOSA's code, they now have tools that you can almost take the same ideas, if not the actual code,
and push it right on to a cluster computation.
So really cool times for this. Python. My name is Richard Kirschner with the Simply Learn team. That's www.simplylearn.com. Get certified, get ahead.
Although deep learning has been around for a while, it is just in its infant stages of development as far as exploding on the market.
I mean it is. Right now they're building robots with it. Deep learning is used to train robots to perform human tasks. Music composition.
Deep neural nets can be used to produce music by making computers learn the patterns involved in composing music.
Image colorization. Neural network recognizes objects and uses information from the images to color them. Machine translation.
Given a word phrase or a sentence in one language, neural networks automatically translate them into another language. Google Translate is one such popular machine translator you may have come across.
And you'll notice in here we didn't show any examples of straight numbers, like projective cells in a business, tracking your favorite stock.
You can certainly do those with machine languages, but this is the next level.
Uh save that for your regression models, your linear regression where you're actually processing and crunching just straight numbers.
With machine learning and deep learning, we're going to a whole new level as far as what we can figure out on the computer.
What's in it for you?
We're going to cover what is deep learning. and take a look at the biological versus artificial intelligence. What is neural network? Activation function in your neural network and the cost function.
And how do neural networks work?
How do neural networks learn? So there's a little, you'll see a switch right there. We just went from how are they working in the math in the background to exactly how are they learning.
We'll be implementing the neural network, we'll do gradient descent, deep learning platforms, and we'll give an introduction to TensorFlow and implementation in TensorFlow.
That's Google's platform that they open sourced recently, and it's probably one of the most cutting edges in deep learning.
And even it is still in the infant stage, which is one of the reasons they released it to open source. What is deep learning?
Deep learning is a subfield of machine learning that deals with algorithms inspired by the structure and function of the brain. And you can see we have a nice picture here.
We have artificial intelligence, which is kind of the big bubble that encompasses all these different things we're talking about. This is the ability of machine to imitate intelligent human behavior.
And in there we have machine learning, application of AI that allows a system to automatically learn and improve from experience.
And if you looked at any of our other videos, you'll know that machine learning covers a lot. So deep learning is a subcategory of that.
But don't forget, machine learning has all kinds of other tools that people use to do very basic descriptive and predictive and postscriptive
analytics. And then you have deep learning, application of machine learning that uses complex algorithms and deep neural nets to train a model.
Let's take a look at the biological neuron versus the artificial neuron. Now remember in the human brain, and this is true for most animals, there are a lot of different neurons going on.
So this is a very basic one.
I mean, there's hundreds of different cells involved. So when we talk about neural networks, this is why I say it's in a very infant stage, they're really basing it on
just the most basic thing that we're able to figure out going on in the neural networks.
And you can see right here we have dendrites fetch information from an adjacent neuron and pass them on as inputs. So you have your data coming in and your data going out.
Any computer model should be looking at that. What's coming in, what's going out. The data is fed as an input to the neuron.
So when we look at the artificial neuron, you can see we have our inputs, they come in, each one is specially weighted into the neuron, and then the neuron has an output.
The cell nucleus processes the information received from the dendrites, and the neuron processes the information provided as inputs.
Axons are the cables over which the information is transmitted, and the information is transferred over weighted channels.
So you can look at that, I mentioned weights briefly, but to alter the data coming in.
So those weights are what causes different information coming in to be weighted differently and processed differently.
And the synapses receive the information from the axons and transmit it to the adjacent neurons. That's in your biological model.
And then when we look at the artificial neuron, the output is a final value predicted by the artificial neuron.
So as we dig deeper into looking at the theory behind the neural network, and we kind of flip back and forth between these because there's two huge aspects of it.
One is from the outside, what are you seeing, and what's going on from the inside, so you can find to do what you need to do and give the best results you can. And we start off with what do we feed?
We feed an unlabeled image to a machine which identifies it without any human intervention. And so you can see here we have a circle that comes in at 784 pixels, and it comes in by 28 by 28.
And you can see how it colors in the circle on there. And we put a triangle in, the triangle in also comes in as 28 by 28, and it has 784 pixels.
So you'll see between these two, both of them are 784 pixels. This machine is intelligent enough to differentiate between the various shapes.
So that's what we want to use our neural network to do is to say, hey, this is a circle, this is a triangle. That's more of a categorical.
You can also do a regression model where you're actually putting out a float value or a numerical value.
We'll be looking at the truefalse or the categorical model mostly because that's where you usually start at.
The difference there is no real difference when you As far as the way the internal functioning goes, when you start flipping between them, other than well, we'll talk about that in just a minute.
So you can actually go between the two quite easily. And the neural network provides this capability. So we're going to use this capability to look between those two.
One of the things I want you to note in here is that we're looking at 784 pixels. We're looking at 784 inputs. That's very different than stock with a high low or last year's cells based on date.
we're looking at just a couple of numbers and they're very clear their numbers, they're very clear what they are, which is something you'd put into a machine learning linear regression model.
This is a step up from that in that we're looking at complex patterns and how do you figure those complex patterns out.
So a neural network is a system modeled on the human brain.
And we looked at that comparing the two, let's go ahead and look deeper into the neural network itself. We have our inputs coming in.
So the inputs are fed to a neuron that processes the data and gives us an output.
Input and output. This is the most basic structure of a neural network known as a perceptron.
So if you see the term perceptron, that's what we're talking about. We're talking about this single node that has inputs and an output.
However, neural networks are usually much more complex. Let's start with visualizing a neural network as a black box.
And I always love that symbol. It's a black box. It's kind of magical. We have our inputs coming in and we want certain outputs. The box takes inputs, processes them, and gives an output.
Let's have a look at what happens within this box.
you can see me there in my secret agent getup. I got my hidden hood and everything. I guess I'm part of the black skull or something like that group.
so let's take a look at what happens within this magic box.
And remember we're skipping back and forth between the theory of what's going on in the box, which you have to know how to fine-tune and how to build, versus looking at it from the outside.
We're programming this box and we have an input and an output to the box as a whole. Within the box exists a network that is a core of deep learning.
And you can see here we're showing one layer, and we have our grid coming in.
The network consists of layers of neurons.
Each neuron is associated with a number called the bias. And you can think of the bias if you overly simplify this and we're doing a linear regression model.
This is your y-intercept in your Euclidean geometry. You have to have something that offsets it, and so you always have a bias in these cells.
Neurons of each layer transmit information to neurons of the next layer over channels. And so you can see each of our layers going through from left to right.
These channels are associated with numbers called weights.
These weights, along with the biases, determine the information that is passed over from the neuron to neuron.
So just like the bias is your y-intercept in Euclidean geometry, you could look at the one weight. Remember this is very complicated, so we're not looking at just one weight.
You can look at the weight as your slope of the line. Or if you're doing x equals uh my plus c, it would be the m value. Neurons of each layer transmit information to neurons of the next layer.
And you can see here as they light up going across into the final layer, and then to the output.
And in this case, the output is going to be either a square in this one, or it might light up the other one, which is a circle. The output layer emits a predicted output.
So in this case we're looking at a classification, uh true false. Is it a circle? Is it a triangle? Is it a square?
Let's now go deeper what happens within the neuron.
So we're going to dig deeper and start getting a little bit closer to some of the math. Don't worry, you don't have to be a calculus expert or know your differential equations.
Even though this is one giant differential equation, you don't need to understand those to understand what's going on.
Within each neuron, the following operations are performed.
The product of each input and the weight of the channel it's passed over is found. This is simply addition.
We're going to sum up the weight times the output from the previous channel, and plus the bias. Some of the weighted products is computed. This is called the weighted sum.
Bias unique to the neuron is added to the weighted sum. The final sum is then subjected to the particular function. And we'll discuss that particular function.
That part is really important because those functions have a huge impact on how well your model performs under different conditions. The final sum is then subjected to a particular function.
This is the activation function. So if you ever hear the term activation function, that's what we're talking about. What activates this cell and what doesn't?
As we dig deeper into activation function, an activation function takes the weighted sum of the input as its input, adds a bias, and provides an output.
And a lot of times you'll actually see one formula for the sum of the weight the weighted sum and the bias. You'll just see that as a single line of everything added together.
And here we've broken it apart because it makes it clear that this bias is not computed the same as the weighted sums.
Here are the most popular types of activation function. And I always find these interesting because at one point I was sitting at a table with a gentleman who was finishing his PhD.
He was in his last year, and he said he went through all this stuff and he ended up just trying the four different activation functions on this particular problem he was working on.
So knowing the math behind it doesn't necessarily mean you're going to know it right away.
So even somebody who might have a PhD and be doing the calculations on this comes back out of it and ends up just trying the different activation functions to see what's going to make a difference.
And a lot of times that's a final step.
That's the kind of thing where you built your whole model, you've come back, and you're like, wait a minute, can I do a better deal with a sigmoid function or the threshold or the rectifier?
Knowing what they're doing is important, so you can explain it to somebody else. And again, you probably do this on a small set of data.
If you're working with big data, you don't want to take down the full server farm just to test out your three different series.
You take a small portion of that data, test it, and then you put it through to the big data.
So let's take a look at this. We have the sigmoid function, and it's used for models where we have to predict the probability as an output. It exists between zero and one.
And you'll see that's true of all of our activation functions we're working with. Either the cell's on or off, it's true or false.
And there might be a little variation in there, which as an output could be used to compute uncertainty in your solution.
So if you're getting a 0.7 with this activation function, it might be, well, I'm not sure if that's really a square, or I'm not sure that's really a triangle.
And that might be a flag for it to be looked at by a human observer, at least in today's models where we're at right now.
And you can see here where we have the formula simply equals 1 over 1 plus e to the minus x, where x is your value coming in,
and it's going to give you a result that looks very similar to the graph on there, which is somewhere between 0 and 1.
and right in the middle, you can see that there's a huge kind of you can go through all the different values and uncertainties involved.
So the sigmoid function is probably the default on most of them.
the next one is the threshold function. It is a threshold-based activation function. If x value is greater than a certain value, the function is activated and fired, else not. Pretty straightforward.
Yes, no, true, false. I don't want to test for improbabilities, I just want a straight answer.
I don't want to know if there's a partial value on there. It either is true or it's false.
And the rectifier function, it is the most widely used activation function. I would debate that.
rectifier is a pretty common one, although I see that the sigmoid function is used to be the basic one, but it's up there.
The rectifier function is very commonly used It gives the output of x if x is positive and zero otherwise, and you can see here again, just like
it's either kind of get a value going up there. So max of x of zero. So it's you it's again, it's like the threshold function. Yes, no, true, false.
it's either zero or it's some kind of progressive value. And then we have the rectifier function.
I would argue with this, because the sigmoid function used to be the most common one.
But with the rectifier function, it now says it is the most commonly used or widely used activation function and gives an output of x if x is positive and zero otherwise.
This is kind of nice because it now says absolutely not, or it gives you a value of probability. Now, when I say a value of probability, be very careful there.
I'm not saying that it's gonna tell you this is a 75% chance of being a circle.
I'm gonna tell you that it says, hey, if this says point one, it probably needs to be looked at, or point two, or point three. It's gonna depend on your data as to what that value means.
In general, that just means it's flagging it that if it's not a one, then chances are it needs to be looked at by a person and reevaluated. And there's a hyperbolic tangent function.
This function is similar to sigmoid function, is bound to a range of minus one to one. So you can see there's our one minus e to the minus two x and one plus over one plus e to the minus two x.
Again, it's very similar to the sigmoid function. The bonus of the hyperbolic function is you have that variable coming through the middle.
So again, you can look at it and you have a little bit more weight as far as you can process that down the line.
That's a little bit more advanced than what we're looking at right now, and a lot of times it's not even necessary in a lot of our different uses for these activation functions.
Now we looked at activation functions, and I kind of said those are a little bit like a black box, because even if you know all the math,
a lot of times you end up just playing with them to find out what works.
and it also depends on what model you're working with, whether you need a flat yes, no, true, false, or you need to have something in the middle that says, "Hey.
this isn't quite a one .". you might need to process this with the human intervention. And you can look at that one example would be self-driving cars.
You don't want a car to be yes, no, I'm going to go through the light. You want it to be like, okay, if it's almost yes, maybe we stop and have human intervention so we don't get an accident.
Cost function is something you can really see and measure and is very important.
The cost value is the difference between the neural net's predicted output and the actual output from a set of labeled training data.
So we have our group of data that's a square circle, and since we're looking at geometrical shapes, we've had somebody already labeled that data.
They've already said this is a triangle, this is a square.
And so if this is coming up and it's giving us and saying a square is a triangle, and it's saying a triangle is a circle, the output is wrong.
And so that output can then be measured in the versus the actual output, and that's the cost. you might also hear this as error, because that's the error value being returned. How far off is it?
And what we're looking for is the least cost or the least error value, and it's obtained by making adjustments to the weights and biases iteratively throughout the training process.
And this is called back propagation. And we're going to look in that a little deeper as we look into an example.
It's really hard to see when you're just looking at arrows without actual numbers and where that flow is coming from.
But you can look at this as here's our inputs, they put out a prediction, the prediction comes out and says,
hey, we've already labeled this data because we're in training mode and the training data is off. This is the cost. Can we send that error or that cost back and adjust those weights?
And we do it in very small increments across large amounts of data so that those weights minimize that cost or that error. But what happens within these neurons?
So let's look at a little example of this. Kind of helps if you have some kind of visual. Let's build a neural network that predicts bike prices based on a few of its features.
And we'll see here we have our CC, our mileage, and our ABS, and these are our three input layers. And then we have the bike price and the output layer.
Now, it doesn't do us very good to just pump it in from the beginning and pump it out.
And to be honest, I would use a machine learning linear regression model on this, since these are just straight numbers.
But because we want a simple example, we're gonna put this through and show you as a neural network what that looks like. And we gotta put a hidden layer in there.
The hidden layer helps in improving the output accuracy. And you could look at this as a bunch of ores.
So it might say, hey, when we compare these three values on the first hidden layer neuron, we're looking at one set of features. And then we might weight them in the second one.
So these are a bunch of different ores, kind of how the math comes out in behind the scenes. And then they go out, of course, to the bike price or the output layer.
And each of the connections have a weight assigned with it. And you'll see here we have a mileage CC with the weight one and weight two going into our first neuron.
And you'd also have your ABS going in there. And so X1 times weight one plus X2 times weight two plus the bias of one. And step two is our activation, the activation function coming in there.
When does this fire? And the neuron takes a subset of the inputs and processes it.
And then we go through, we do that with the second hidden layer neuron and the third one and so on. So you process each layer in order going forward.
Now, what I told you is in its infant stage, they now have neurons that fire into the same layer or back a layer,
so that you now have a time series, and there's all kinds of wild things that they're experimenting with on these layers. This basic setup has been around since the mid-90s.
It's only now because of our technology that it's open to almost everybody to play with it. And that's why I say this is in an infant stage in development.
Is this basic math is here, but what we can do with it is amazing, and what they're actually doing with all these different things is amazing.
And so we're just at the beginning of how to use all these different tools in our deep learning and our neural networks.
And so once we have our hidden layer computed, the information reaching the neurons in the hidden layer is subjected to the respective activation function.
And so each one of these fires an activation output, and then those are each weighted to the final output layer.
So the processed information is now sent to the output layer, once again over weighted channels.
And you could look at this as each one of these is I always look at this as like a group of people.
They're all looking at the bulletin board, and the first person says, this is what I project sells for the company, and the second person and the third, and so on,
and then their perspectives are weighted based on their expertise.
So your accountant might have a very high weight where the um maybe your janitor has a very low weight because their expertise is not in accounting. And then that goes into the output layer.
And once in the output layer, it goes the output, which is the predicted value, is compared against the original value.
So now we have our output layer, and since we have like already a list of bikes with their the different setups and what their value is, we can now generate an error from this.
The cost function determines the error in prediction and reports it back to the neural network.
So this is the cost, this is how far off it is, this is your error coming back. And as you can see, this is uh back propagation going on.
So now our error is going in reverse because we know we're not completely correct on this particular channel.
The weights are adjusted in order to reduce the error. So each time we go back, we are changing those weights to reduce that error, and we change them in small increments.
You don't want to fit one input. Remember, you might have a data pool with a terabyte of data.
You don't want to solve for the first set of data that comes in and that be the main solution, because everything else will be off. This is going to confuse you.
That's also called a bias.
So we have the bias in the cell where we're adding a value, kind of like the y-intercept, and we have a bias of the whole neural network, which means that it's weighted towards one set of answers.
So we want to make small changes in these weights so we don't create a bias. And the weights are adjusted in order to reduce the error or the cost. The network is now trained using the new weights.
Once again, the cost is determined and backpropagation is continued until the cost cannot be reduced any further. So let's go ahead and plug in values and see how our neural network works.
So here we come in here, and initially our channels are assigned with random weights.
This is important because if you assign them all with the same weight, you might be able to reproduce it, but it turns out that if I put all my weights as one or all my weights as zero,
it takes longer to train. Where if you have random weights, they already have like a little bit of adjustment and ores built in, and that will give us a better answer and train faster.
Our first neuron takes a value of mileage and CC as inputs. So here comes our computation, whatever those inputs are, and we do that again with the second neuron with those values coming in.
You can see here we have weight three and so on, and then our third neuron coming down, and of course our fourth neuron. So we're adding all these different values coming in here in our hidden layer.
The process value from each neuron is sent to the output layer over weighted channels. So again, here's our weights coming in.
And we have N1, N2, N3, and N4. Once again, the values are subjected to the activation function, and a single value is emitted as the output.
On comparing the predicted value to the actual value, we clearly see that our network requires training.
So here we have it that our bike price we put out, we thought it was worth 2,000 on our random weights, and the bike actually was 4,000 on there.
Guessing that's not US dollars, because that'd be a very expensive bike, but maybe it is. There's some $2,000, $4,000 bikes out there. The cost function is calculated and back propagation takes place.
this is pretty simple. You can look at that as our um we're subtracting one value from the other, we square it, and then we take half of that.
And that is propagated back up, and each layer generates its own errors. Let's go back one, because you have your predicted y and your actual y.
That goes back to the first layer. And then based on the value of the cost function, certain weights are changed.
So when we look at the next layer, that error is not the original 4,000 minus 2000 squared divided by two. This error is based on the error of each cell generated.
How far off is that cell as far as its weights? We're not going to show you, it's actually a very complicated differential equation, and you can probably write it out if you wanted to.
You just write out each formula, that goes into the next level, and you add them all together, and you can write it out all the way through. Computers make it so you don't have to.
And our neural network is considered trained when the value for the cost function is minimum. So when we get our error way down as low as we can, that's when our neural network is trained.
And there, I mean, just recently they've come up with all kinds of different means for measuring that particular value.
A little bit beyond the scope of today's neural network, but you can actually you can actually see it how far do you do this until the neural network doesn't need to be trained anymore?
And you can overtrain a neural network. Now the tools that we're looking at automatically let you know when to stop, which is really nice.
And that is just like I said, we're at the beginning stages in neural networks, and it's just really cool what they can do now,
and how much of it's automated and how much of it is experimental right now.
Let's take a look at gradient descent. But what approach do we take to minimize the cost function?
So here we have a nice error thing coming in. This is our cost or our error. let's start with plotting the cost function against the predicted value.
And so you can see they've fed in multiple y's, and these are the errors coming in and the cost of each of these inputs and changes going on.
Note we start at a random point on the curve.
So usually you put in, you know, you pick up your data and you randomly pick where to start in your data.
A lot of times you just run it from the beginning, because you're going through so much data it's not that big of a deal, but you start with one point going in.
So your forward propagation goes through, you're going to go ahead and find your cost or your error. It points out on the curve, and you can see how we're plotting it right here.
Since the gradient at this point is positive, we may move right. So we're going to move a little bit to the right on here. And this time the gradient is negative, we move a little bit to the left.
Eventually we try out the point where the gradient is zero. This is the least value of cost function.
You have to be a little careful with this because this particular, I mean they make it look nice and simple in this graph.
Sometimes these curves look like stair steps, and so there is global minimums, and then there is local. There might be a local point where the gradient is zero, but it's not the global one.
so it might be way off to the left where it just happens to step down a little bit, and you think you're in the right gradient.
And with that we have all the right weights, and we can say our network is trained.
So here we have um just some major, these are some of the big names out there right now in development for deep learning platforms. TensorFlow, which we'll actually do an example in in a minute.
Deep Learning4j, which is in the Java platform.
Uh so if you're a Java programmer, by the way, as TensorFlow is accessed, most people are using Python to access it, but it is a system that's kind of separate from a lot of the programming languages,
which makes it a lot more flexible as far as used. Deep Learning4j is Java based. And then Cross is just exploding right now. And this is interesting, Cross is working with TensorFlow.
It actually can sit on top of TensorFlow and it can also do its own thing.
so if you're studying deep learning or getting into it, you'll want to know the basics of TensorFlow, but you also are going to want to know the upper level of Karas sitting on top of TensorFlow.
We're just looking at TensorFlow today, though, in our example. And there's also Torch on there. There's a bunch more that we didn't.
list on here. even sklearn or the uh side package in Python has a neural network you can program, a very basic one.
And it is the same basic one that you could do in TensorFlow if you stripped everything out of it. And then TensorFlow has a lot of tools they've added in and so has Karas.
But we're going to be looking specifically at TensorFlow in our example. And TensorFlow is an open source tool used to define and run computations on what they call tensors. Very common language now.
So more and more we see the term tensor as being a standard in the deep learning language. And this was originally developed by Google. So let's take a little bit big in there. What are tensors?
Tensors are just another name for arrays. So a tensor of dimension five you can see here we have A B k M Q whatever.
So it's an array coming in and the tensor of dimension 54 more like a picture very common to see that in a picture.
You can also see a tensor even more detailed in a picture as we go to the next one tensor of dimension 333.
This is 3D space you might have a picture that also has colors that might be the third dimension.
You might have four dimensions because you have both your grid and your different color channels and your Z plot you can see where you can now process a very high
level set of data coming in whether as an image or features. They could be features that have nothing to do with images. So there's a lot of stuff you can do now with the tensors coming in.
This is where the term TensorFlow comes from so we have right now that TensorFlow is the most popular library in deep learning and I did mention Karas
now works with TensorFlow so there's a lot of stuff you can do between the two. It's an open source software library developed by Google.
So they hit a roadblock and they realized hey this is an infant stage technology.
You know we thought it was going to be the next greatest thing and we were going to have a hold on it but it's really infant as far as how it's applied and what we can do with it.
Let's open source it so everybody can work on it. Let's take it to the next level and that's really what open source does to a lot of these packages when they release them.
And you can run on either a CPU or a GPU.
So when we look at the details if you have your graphic processing units what's nice about those is they run a lot faster.
The downside is you have to play with them a little bit to get them up and running and it's a hardware upgrade.
When we run it I'll be running it in the CPU mode. I have played with it in my GPU on my personal computer.
You know it does increase the processing but I did run into some version problems with my Python and stuff like that and when I did finally work it out
I went back to the CPU because it didn't increase my speed enough for what I was working on.
But in a larger group you might be able to put that on if you're working with a larger stack of computers you might want to run it in the GPU.
You can create a data flow graphs that have nodes and edges.
So there's our edges coming in we didn't talk about edges but that's a very up and coming way of looking at your analytical data is how do different nodes connect.
What do those edges look like in between them? And it's used for machine learning applications such as neural networks.
It is mostly a neural network but they have all kinds of tools which sit on top of our basic neural network. They have new stuff evolving into the TensorFlow library so it's very much just exploding.
Great time to jump into TensorFlow because there's all kinds of cool things we're doing with it and all kinds of cool applications you can now use TensorFlow for.
So let's take a look at implementation in TensorFlow and we're going to build a neural network to identify handwritten digits using the MNIST
database or the MNIST database. And that stands for Modified National Institute of Standards and Technology database.
It has a collection of 70,000 handwritten digits and the digit labels identify each of the digits from zero to nine.
This is a cool example because it's simple enough that you could actually run this through some basic machine learning categorizing algorithms and train them,
and you'll get about the same answer because again it's it's simple grid.
The digits on the grid don't have a huge amount of variation like you would say an automated driving car looking at the environment.
So you can still do this with a lot of your different linear models and stuff like that. You can solve this, and you'll get about the same answer.
When I ran a comparison between TensorFlow and between some basic regression models or category models in machine learning, they came up pretty even as far as their output.
so this is kind of where we start to see the complexity of something coming in, uh, in this case a tensor, or a grid of information, where the deep learning model does as good as the regular models.
And when you get past this kind of complexity and features, suddenly the neural networks come up with better answers, better solutions, and a better build.
And that's why there's such a move into neural networks, is we live in a complicated world, and it's just really cool we can do with this.
So the handwritten digits from the NIST database, they come in, the data set is used to train the machine, a new image of a digit is fed,
and the digit is identified. Um if you've looked at any of our other machine learning tools where we're doing training uh where we train our model to fit and then you test it out,
this will look pretty familiar. Uh and there is some tools out there for say untrained categorizing, where it's just looking for features that fit together.
So there are tools that don't need that training. But this is where when we talk about neural networks, we do need to train them, and this is what we're looking at.
So for this, I'm going to use the Anaconda Navigator just because it's a very nice visual tool.
You might be in PyCharm or one of your other IDEs for editing Python, because we are looking at Python TensorFlow.
And under Anaconda, we have the notebook, which is something we use pretty regularly, and they have the Jupyter Lab. The Jupyter Lab is the Jupyter Notebook, but with tabs and a few new features.
So we'll be using the Jupyter Lab today. And under the environment, you'll want to go ahead and if you haven't yet, you'll see that I have a number of different setups in here.
Right now I have the Python version 3.6 and the TensorFlow. In this case I have TensorFlow 1.12. If we scroll down, you can see that. here we go, TensorFlow and it's version 1.12.
And in here, if you haven't yet, you'll need to install those and go in and just open our terminal.
And if you've never used the Anaconda or if you're in your other thing, you might have something simple like pip.conda is what I use for my install, and you can simply do conda
install tensorflow. that should bring in the most current version.
Now, when I installed this a few months ago, Python version, I'm not going to run this because I already have installed on here, Python version 3.7,
the newest one out, still had a couple glitches with the TensorFlow. I believe they fixed it as of writing of this, but I'm gonna stick with 3.6 just so I don't get any surprises on there.
So this is Python version 3.6 with TensorFlow 1.12 on here.
And if you haven't installed it yet, you also want to install Numpy for this example, that's NumbersPython or N-U-M-P-Y. you can just simply run install on there.
Keep in mind if you're in Anaconda and you've created one of these environments specific to this, keep with conda if you're gonna use conda. If you're gonna use pip, keep with pip.
Don't install one package with pip and one under conda because that's how they track those version numbers and how they fit together, and you can end up with a problem.
They don't pip doesn't see conda and vice versa. so just keep that in mind when you're running your installs. We'll go ahead and open up JupyterLab and we're going to launch that.
So here's my Jupyter Lab. One of the really cool features of JupyterLab is you have tabs now, so you can open up multiple notebooks.
this is nice because I have my notes I'm working on and then our actual window we're looking in.
And we'll go ahead and zoom in a little bit here. There we go. So you have a nice, hopefully easy to see fonts. And then we'll go ahead and do a simple or get our imports out of the way.
and so we're going to import our TensorFlow as TF. that's pretty much a standard for TensorFlow. NumPy our numbers Python as py. And we'll import our matplot library as plt.
Again, these are very common. So if you see tf or py or plt, this is a standard that most people use.
Do you have to? No.
You could just do import numpy instead of doing as py. And then from tensorflow.examples.tutorials, this is always nice because they actually include
data set we're going to play with. So we're going to import input data. So those are data coming in. That's all we're doing is telling it this is where it's coming from.
And if we're going to tell where it's coming from, we need to go ahead and create a variable with that information in it. And we'll just call this uh MNIST NIST or minst.
You know, I don't really know how they pronounce that. I should probably look that up. It's a very common data set to use. And there's our input data, and we're going to read data sets.
And this is if you look at this, we imported input data from our TensorFlow, and so this is a TensorFlow read statement for their tutorials.
So this isn't like some special Python setup, this is just their setup. makes it easy to pull it in. So once we get into their data sets, we need to go ahead and tell it what kind of data set.
And again, this is what we brought in, but it's going to be the NINS data. And this part is very important. One hot
equals true.
This means that instead of importing a value from zero to nine, we evaluate the data set, it's going to bring it in as one
hot. Whenever you see one hot encoder, we're flattening that out and we have true false for zero, true false for one, true false for two.
So our output, if you remember from our output from the slide we did earlier, in this case I grabbed the one for bike price, doesn't really matter which one we use.
This has one output, so we have our bike price. On this, we're going to have instead of one output, we're going to have ten outputs representing each of the digits in there.
And this code really isn't going to show us anything. It's good to see what we're actually looking at. So let's go ahead and do a figure ax equals, go into our plot library, subplots, ten, comma
ten.
And that is, if you remember we talked about tensor, tensor being data coming in. This is a 10 by 10 grid or 100 pixels on there.
And if we're going to display it, let's go do k0 for i in range ten, just a simple loop through on the data. Let's do what is it, for j and range 10. So I actually misquoted that.
10 by 10 is not the actual size of the pixels. the actual pixels are going to be when we look at the shapes, we'll get into that in just a second here. We'll take a quick look at the shape on there.
Uh turns out
They are, I believe 28 by 28.
so let's take a look at that. And we're just going to plot these.
What are we looking at? What are we working with?
As a data scientist, you should always be looking back at your data and seeing what it looks like You can get that human perspective because you just never know.
You know, the the computer might put something out that makes no sense, and at that point you want to go back and reevaluate what you did. so we're going to go ahead and plot.
We're gonna plot ten digit, you know, ten of the digits by ten of the digits, and here's our ax. We'll create the IJ on our subplots, and we're going to do an image show.
We're going to look at the training image for images of K.
And then we want to reshape this. We're going to reshape this. And we're going to reshape this 28 by 28.
That's how I knew I had it wrong, is because I looked down my notes and it's like, oh no, that says 28, it's not 10 by 10.
And I should know that already because I've done enough messing with this data set that I should remember. But it's 28 by 28. And the aspect we're going to do is auto.
And this is all, if you look at this, here's our variable NIST. The NIST is coming from data set. So this is all part of the TF TensorFlow learning or examples tutorial in there.
And then we'll go ahead and do K plus equals one. So we just keep paging through our different images. And let's see what that looks like. Let's go ahead and do a plot show.
And we'll go ahead and run this so we take a look and see what we have here.
And so we have a nice plot here, and you can just see that we have some random numbers showing up in each one of these little subplots.
If you're wanting a copy of this code, put a note down in the YouTube video and let us know, or come visit us at www.simplylearn.com and we'll send you out a copy of what we're working on.
and get a copy of that for your own setup. so now we've taken a look, we can just see we have our here's our pictures that are coming on.
We've plotted them so we have an idea of what we're looking at. Let's go ahead and print, let's look at the shape of the features.
so when we have this, we have our uh NIST train images, and we'll do the shape on there. Let's take a look and just see what we're looking at as far as our count and everything.
And so you can see here we have 55,000. That's basically how many images we have, and this by 784.
And in this data set, there's also our labels. So let's take a look at that. We have our NIST train labels shape. Let's take a look and see what that looks like.
and there we have 10 because there's 10 digits. So we brought in that's our output we're looking at.
And so we have there we go, 55,000, they match, they should match, because you should have equal numbers in both of those. You know, here's our data in and here's our answer.
If you remember, this is a bunch of zeros and with one each each one will be zero, zero, zero, one would be what, letter four or something like that.
So let's take a look at what our one hot encoding did for the first observation. And this is when we're exploring data, you really want to dig in there and just see what the heck am I looking at.
So we're going to look at the labels, and this would be the first label that comes up. And we'll go ahead and run this. And we look at that, you can see this is what I'm talking about.
Zero, zero, our one is zero, two is zero, three is zero, four is zero, five is zero, six is zero, seven equals one.
So our very first label is a seven, but our very first label comes up that it's a seven.
And so we don't have like zero through nine, we have a bunch of zeros and just the one to mark it as a seven on here.
So now we've kind of liked a quick look at the data, and in here you might ask some questions like what is 784? 24 times 24. Remember that's the size of our grid on there, or our tensor coming in.
So 784 is a setup on there. And we've gone through all this viewing the data. We'll go ahead and start looking at our tensor flow. So let's take our X variable. This is going to be our training set.
We'll do a placeholder, and then we're going to have these come in as float.
Now, if I remember correctly, they're actually, you know, zero or one for the values, because they're either uh but we have them coming in as a float value,
and we have a little bit of a shape coming in here, and there's our 784. so we let it know that this is what's what our input is for our tensor flow. And this is our training set.
So we'll just put a label on there to help us track that train set, and then w.
And with W we'll go ahead and do TF variables, and we'll do this as zeros. Variables, to have zeros, and we'll set this as 784 by 10, 10 being the output, 784 being our number of
variables in, and this is our weights. Remember we have a bias in there too. And I'll go back over this in just a second as we see how that fits together in our tensor flow.
And we'll do this one with our variables. Again, we have 10, so we're going to do the bias. We do it the same kind of format and setup on here, and so we'll do that as TF0s of ten.
So just create an array of 10 there, and this is our bias. So with these three lines, and there's actually they're coming out with the eager execution, which would bypass some of what we're doing.
But this is important to understand is the first thing you have to do with TensorFlow is we have to allocate a space for the variables.
And our TF placeholder and our TF variable with our weights and our biases, this actually hasn't done anything yet. So all it is is placeholders, that's why it's okay to use zeros.
You could have just as easily used ones or anything else, and it wouldn't matter. The next stage is to go ahead and set up some of the functions going on.
But before we do that, just note that this hasn't done anything. Even if I execute it, all it's done is created placeholders until we do the final initialization.
And so we need to go ahead and set up we'll do y equals tf.nn.softmax. And the code for this is tf.matmole xw plus b. And this is our sum.
Let's just put a note here so we can keep track of what's going on. We're finding weighted sum of inputs plus the bias. so there's our plus b the bias.
And then we need to go ahead, keep um, let's do y underscore, and again another placeholder. And this one we'll set um, it's actually we'll put in as tf placeholder on here.
Tf placeholder float none 10. There's our one hot encoder going on there. So our 10 values coming out. And we'll do a cross entropy on here, and this is going to be minus tf reduce sum.
And we'll do y. Here's our y underscore, which is remember we have your y output and your actual output. so this will be our y underscore times the tf log of y.
And then finally, before we do the actual initialization of all our variables, we'll set up our train step. This equals our gradient descent optimizer. Very important.
Remember we looked at that chart on our slides, and so we've set up all these formulas, and here's our gradient descent optimizer, and as it keeps looking, it keeps looking for that zero value.
That's what we're doing with that particular formula.
So let's take a look and see what we're doing here. We just put together all of our pieces for tensor flow.
And you know, the devil's in the details. We have here our training set coming in.
We have to put a placeholder on there, we have our variables with their weights, we have our biases coming out, and then we put in our uh the weighted
sum.
So here's uh summising our summation here. Then we have our y variable output, so there's our y how it works, and then of course the actual output on there.
And then we have our cross entropy coming in, and that's our minus tf.reduce sum, the y times the tf log of y.
And then the training step, gradient descent optimizer.
we're using a 0.01 in this, and we're gonna minimize cross entropy. So we're gonna let it do all the work.
So once we've set up all of these different layers, we've allocated for them, we need to go ahead and initialize them. So we're gonna do an init tf initialize, and it's gonna be all variables.
one of the cool things is they're in the process of doing away with this. So all these steps would be bundled into one instead of having to have placeholders.
You initialize them in the same process going on. And then finally, everything in TensorFlow is based on your session. Now, this is changing that there's other options to be able to run this.
But we want to go ahead and do session. There's our TF, which is a TF session, and then we want to go ahead and do session run. And what are we going to run?
Well, we did initialization of all our variables.
so this is what we're running. And this is where actually, once we do this, we actually create our TensorFlow object. So this whole piece of code right here is our TensorFlow object.
We have our input coming in with our weighted variables coming in, our softmax for our metmal going out. How does it add it together for our y value?
Uh and then we have the actual float value coming out, checking on our all the way down. So you can see all the different stages going through that we're setting up.
and this is one of the reasons that a lot of people like TensorFlow is because you can designate all these different pieces one step at a time.
This is also one of the reasons people don't like TensorFlow, is because you have to designate all the different layers coming down.
And there's a lot of steps being made right now to minimize this, to make it either easier to automate it or to allow you to do more complicated things.
And all those steps are still at play, so it's worth looking into the more advanced version of what's going on with Karas on top of TensorFlow.
It's also important to understand what's going on in these individual levels if you're gonna play with them.
It's important to understand, hey, what's going on with the um uh finding the weighted sum of the inputs plus the bias, because there's other ways to do that.
There's all kinds of other tools in there now. But this is the basic setup that you want to do on a TensorFlow coming in. And we want to go ahead and just run and init our TensorFlow.
So let's go ahead and do that. Let's run this. We do get a warning here because there's a move to use global variables. This is one of the changes they're making.
But as far as this example, it's not going to make a difference because we're doing once we initialize it.
This is initializing our variables, and again, these are only placeholders up here until we initialize them.
And I would highly suggest put a note down there or go over to simply learn.com and let them know and have them email you a copy of the code so you can actually play with this code right here.
Because this is the body of what's going on in TensorFlow. This is the build in neural networks.
And then once we've done that, now comes kind of the fun part is we need to go ahead and train it. so we've created our TensorFlow.
We've created our network. And now we need to go ahead and train it.
so let's put together that training code and let's just do for i in range uh 1000, 0 to 1000.
So we're just gonna look at the first 1000 in our training. And the way we pull that data from our mints train, next batch of 100.
so you look at this, we're gonna be doing groups of 100, and then there's gonna go through a thousand of them.
This is very important that TensorFlow builds this in. This is one of the downsides of doing sklearn or one of the older packages, is they don't let you batch groups in.
they wanted to have it all up front, and then you have to build your own batch programs right now. this lets us go ahead and do that, and you can see here we have batch x of s, batch y of s.
So there's our x and our y. You can look at this as our training of x and our train of y or the data in and the answer in. Uh and then we simply do our session run.
so here's our session that we've created. We're going to run it, and we want to do the train step.
where we initialized our train step up here in our TF, and so there's our train step feed, it's a dictionary. Dictionary coming in, which we're going to create right here.
is X is our batch, X of our sample, comma and our Y underscore is going to be our batch of our Y
sample. and so this goes through and we've now hit the run button and we've trained our session. We've trained this setup on here.
And once we've trained it, then we need to go ahead and find out how good our accuracy was and actually start running some predictions through there. so we'll go ahead and create a correct prediction.
And this is where our tf.equal, we'll use our argmax y of one and tf argmax of y of underscore of one to help us get the correct predictions on there.
And then we want to use that to feed into an accuracy.
And so our accuracy is going to be tf reduce mean. And we'll take that and we'll do a cast. And this is the correct prediction that we're sending in there. And it is a float value. Keep it simple.
And Let's go ahead and print this out so we can see what we're looking at. So what are we printing out? we need to do a session run. This session around is going to be on the accuracy.
Where did accuracy comes from? This is our we're casting our TF on there with the correct predictions on that. So here's our accuracy. Feed in, so it needs a dictionary for the data coming in.
We're going to create our dictionary, and x is going to be our NIST test images. and y underscore There is going to be our NIST dot test labels.
Let me just double check and make sure I have that typed in there correctly. There we go. And let's go ahead and run that and see what comes up. And we end up with a 0.9165
for our accuracy. Which means our trained neural network does a pretty good job letting us know what these different symbols are.
I'm guessing that a seven and a three and a four, something that as humans. We kind of take for granted. I even have trouble reading this.
So I don't know if I would be able to, like the first one, I would sit there for a long time figuring out that's a seven versus a two. That could have easily been a two to me.
We can now create this nice neural network that does all kinds of cool things.
Do you know, friends, that according to the lending statistics, the demand for AI and ML specialist is projected to surge by 40% between 2023 to
2027?
And on an average, an ML engineer is expected to earn around $133 and $336 dollars per year.
So if you are an aspiring ML engineer and thinking about what innovative projects you can show in your portfolio, then your wait is over.
Because in this video, I'll be covering eight amazing ML projects that you can showcase in your resume.
So guys, let's start first with a Bigner level project.
And the first project that we are going to encounter that is home value prediction.
So, guys, this project aims to develop a predictive model to estimate the value of residential properties.
The model will analyze various features such as location, square, footage, number of bedrooms and bathrooms, age of the property,
and other relevant factors.
By leveraging historical property data, the model will be able to provide accurate home value predictions, which can be useful for real estate agents,
buyers, and sellers.
So, guys, the programming language that we are going to use all over here will be Python, and machine learning libraries that we will be using will be ScikitLearn, TensorFlow,
keras and for data handling libraries we have Pandas, NumPy, and for visualization, we have to use matplotlib and CBON.
Now, what will be the approach for this one, guys?
So, guys, the first one that we have a data collection.
So, here, what is going to happen, guys? So, first you have to collect the historical property data from the sources like Zillow Retailer.com.
You can also get database from the public real estate databases like Kaggle datasets where you have Zillow home value prediction.
Ensure that the dataset includes features like location, where you have latitude-longitude, square footage, number of rooms, ear build, property type, and previous sales.
The next step that comes is data cleaning.
You have to handle the missing values by using imputation techniques or removing incomplete records, removing outliers that may skew the model's prediction,
normalize or standardize the data to ensure consistency.
The third one that we have is feature engineering.
You have to create new features such as proximity to schools, crime rates, and access to the public transportation.
Encode categorical variables, example property type, location using techniques like one-hot encoding. Generate interaction features that capture relationship between existing features.
The fourth one that we have is model selection.
Use regression models like linear regression, random forest, gradient boosting, neural networks.
Experiment with different models to identify the best performing one.
Now, in the next phase, all you have to do, guys, is model training and evaluation.
Split the data set into training and test sets.
Train the model on the training set and evaluate their performance on the testing set using metrics like RSME, which means root mean squared error.
You can use cross-validation to ensure the model's robustness and avoid overfitting.
The sixth one that we have always hyperparameter tuning.
You can optimize the model's hyperparameter using techniques such as grid search or random search to improve accuracy.
And if you're looking forward to deploy your model, then you can develop a web interface using Flask or Django to allow users to input property features and get predictions.
You can deploy the model on the cloud platform like AWS for scalability.
Now, if we talk about the complexity level of this, we all know that it is a beginner level project.
Now let us move on to the one more set that is music genre classification and generation.
So, guys, this is also one of the most beginner level project.
This project aims to develop a system that can classify music tracks into different genres and generate new music composition within specified genre.
The goal is to build a model that analyzes audio features to categorize music and uses deep learning techniques to create new music.
This project introduces advanced concepts of audio processing, deep learning, and generative models.
So, guys, what will be used in this? So we'll have programming language that will be Python.
For audio processing, we'll be using Librosa.
For machine learning libraries, we'll be using TensorFlow, Kiras, PyTorch.
For data handling libraries, we'll be using Pandas, NumPy.
For visualization, we'll be using Matplotlib, Seaborn.
For a dataset, guys, you can use GDZAN Music Genre dataset or you can get it from Free Music Archive.
So guys, in the first phase, we are going to have data collection.
You can update datasets containing music tracks and their corresponding genre from the sources, from GDZAN Music Genre dataset and the free music
archive.
Ensure that a dataset includes diverse genre and substantial number of tracks per genre.
Next, we'll go for data pre-processing.
Use library Librosa to load and pre-process audio files, including feature extractions such as mill frequency, septical coefficients,
chroma features, and spectral contrast.
You can normalize the extracted features to ensure consistent input for the given models.
Now, if we talk about feature engineering guys, you can extract additional features from the audio files such as tempo, beat, zero crossing rate, etc.
Create a feature matrix that represents the extracted audio features.
Then go for the model selection.
Use conventional neural network or recurrent neural networks for the music genre classification. Split the dataset into training and testing dataset.
Now, if we talk about model training and evaluation, guys, then you can train the selected classification model on the training set.
Evaluate the model's performance on the testing set using metrics like accuracy, precision, recall, and F1 score.
Use confusion matrices to understand the classification performance across different genres.
Now, if we talk about model selection and training for the music generation, what you will do, guys, you can use the generative adversarial networks or recurrent neural networks such as LSTM,
long short-term memory for music generation. Train the generative model on the dataset to create new music sequences.
Next, we have model training and evaluation.
You can train the generative model on sequences of audio features, you can evaluate the generated music by listening tests and by objective metrics like inception score or frichet audio distance.
If I talk about hyperparameter tuning guys, you can optimize the model. You can use the hyperparameters using techniques like grid search or random search to improve performance.
If I talk about deployment, guys, you can deploy these models on cloud platforms like AWS.
Now let us move on to our next project.
So, guys, the complexity of this project is at the beginner level.
Now let us move to the intermediate level projects.
Next project that we have all over here is sentiment analysis of Twitter data.
This project aims to develop a sentiment analysis model that can classify tweets as positive, negative, or neutral.
The goal is to analyze public sentiment on various topics or events using natural language techniques.
So, guys, what will be used all over here? So in this, we will have programming language like Python, okay, NLP libraries, NLTK Spacey.
For machine learning libraries, you can use ScikitLearn, TensorFlow, Kiras for data handling libraries, we have Pandas, NumPy.
For visualization, we have Matplotlib, Cbon, and we can use the API Twitter for data collection.
Now, how are you going to work on it, guys?
So, guys, if I talk about the data collection, use a Twitter API to collect tweets based on specific hashtags like keywords or topics.
Extract relevant fields like tweet text, user information, timestamp, etc.
Then if I talk about data preprocessing guys, clean the tweet text by removing special characters, links, mentions, hashtags, and stop words.
Tokenize the text and perform lemization or stemming to reduce the words to their base form.
Next, if we talk about feature engineering guys, you convert the clean text data into numerical representation using TFIDF, bag of words, or word
embedding.
Now if I talk about model selection, guys, you can choose a classification algorithm such as logistic regression, nape bias, or LSTM.
Split the dataset into training and testing dataset.
Now, if I talk about model training and evaluation, then you can train the selected model on the training set.
Evaluate the model's performance on the testing set using metrics like accuracy, precision, recall, and FN score. Use cross-validation to ensure the model's robustness.
If I talk about hyperparameter tuning, guys, you can optimize the model's hyperparameters using grid search or random search to improve the performance.
For deployment, which can be optional, you can deploy your model on AWS for real-time sentiment analysis.
So if I talk about the complexity level, guys, its complexity is intermediate.
So guys, our next project is customer segmentation using K-Means clustering.
This project aims to segment customers into distinct groups based on their purchasing behavior and demographic information.
The objective is to understand customer segments and tailor marketing strategies accordingly.
So guys, what programming languages will be using?
So basically, we'll be using Python.
For machine learning libraries, we'll have ScikitLearn.
For data handling libraries, we'll have Pandas, NumPy. For visualization libraries, we'll have Matplotlab, CBON, and the dataset source will be e-commerce transaction data.
How are we going to work on this one?
For data collection, we can obtain a data set of e-commerce transactions that include customer demographics, purchase history, and product information.
Next, we'll have data pre-processing.
For data pre-processing, we are going to do the cleaning of the data by handling the missing values and outliers.
Then for feature engineering, we are going to create features like total purchase amount, purchase frequency, and recency of the purchases.
Then we are going to proceed for the model selection.
We can use k-means clustering to segment the customers into distinct groups.
You can determine the optimal number of clusters using methods like elbow methods or Silhout score.
Now, if I talk about model training and evaluation, you can train the K-means model on the process dataset.
You can evaluate the quality of clusters by analyzing intra-cluster and intercluster distances.
Next, we have the evaluation. You can visualize the clusters using techniques like PCA, principal component analysis, TSNE, etc.
Next, we have the hyperparameter tuning.
Now you can tune this model and interpret the characteristic of each segment.
You can develop a target marketing strategies for each segment based on unique behavior and preferences.
Now deployment is optional. You can develop a dashboard using Flask or Django to visualize customer segments and track marketing campaigns.
So, guys, if I talk about the complexity of this project, so this is an intermediate level project.
So, guys, for dataset, you can use the Kaggles customer segmentation dataset, which is available at the Kaggles platform.
Now, the third intermediate level project that we have all over here is building a chatbot with Rasa.
This project aims to build an intelligent chatbot using RASA framework.
The chatbot will be capable of understanding user queries and providing appropriate responses, making it useful for customer support, personal assistance, or information retrieval.
What languages we are going to use? So it will be Python based.
We will have the NLP libraries like Rasa, NLTKs, PIC.
For machine learning libraries, we are going to have ScikitLearn, TensorFlow, Kira's, etc.
For data handling libraries, we are going to use Pandas, NumPy.
So guys, this was what we are going to do it.
And how you can work on this one? By collecting the data, collect the conversation data and FAQs from the target domain.
Annotate the data to create training examples for the chatbot.
Next comes is data pre-processing.
Clean the text data by removing special characters and normalizing the text.
You can tokenize and limitize the text to prepare for a training.
The third one we have the models training.
You can use Rasa's NLU's component to train a model for intent recognition and entity extraction.
You can define the dialog management policies to handle different conversation flows.
Next, guys, you can perform the feature engineering and integration.
You can integrate the Rasa's NLU and core components to build complete chatbot.
You can connect the chatbot to messaging platform like Facebook, Messenger, etc.
For model selection and testing, what you can do, guys, you can test this chatbot with various inputs to ensure that it handles the scenarios appropriately.
And you can also select the right model using this.
Now, if I talk about model training, guys, what do you have to do? You have to collect the user feedback and conversational logs to continuously work on training the model.
Next, similarly, you have to retrain the model periodically with the new data to see how it is working. So that will be your evaluation.
Now for the hyperparameter tuning, what are you going to do, guys?
You have to check in those scenarios where it is able to tune up with those scenarios where it can handle the input appropriately.
And next is deployment. So guys, for deploying it, you can use AWS.
So guys, for a dataset, you can use RASAS open source.
So that's a very good dataset for you to proceed.
So guys, if you talk about difficulty of this project, this is an intermediate level project.
Now let us move on to the advanced level projects.
For advanced level projects, the first one that comes up to my mind is movie similarity from plot summaries.
Now, this project aims to develop a system that can find out recommended movies similar to a given movie based on their plot summaries.
By analyzing the textual content of the movie, plot summaries, the model will identify similarities and suggests movies with similar themes, storylines, or genres.
This project introduces beginners to natural language processing, text similarly measures, and recommendation systems.
What languages we are going to use, guys? We'll be using Python, NLP libraries like NLTK, Spacey, Machine Learning Libraries like ScikitLearn, data handling libraries like Pandas,
NumPy, Visualization, we can use NumPy, and dataset source will be IMDB or Kegel.
So guys, this process is also involving the data collection.
Then you have to go for data cleaning, then feature engineering, next, model selection.
So similar process as I have discussed in other projects. So you have to also go through the same one.
Next, what do you have to do, guys?
Similarly, what do you have to do? You have to train the model, then evaluate the model, then hypertune it, and finally proceed for the deployment.
So this is overall process of this project.
Try to research on the website a lot, like how you can extract it.
So, guys, you can use Kegel or Towards Data Science to research more about this project.
Now, guys, if I talk about the difficulty of this project, and this is an advanced level project.
Now, let us move on to the next one that we have all over here.
That is image segmentation project for brain tumor prognosis. This is a very, very amazing project, and definitely you can put up on your portfolio.
Basically, guys, this project aims to develop an image segmentation model to identify and de-alienate brain tumors from MLI scans.
The goal is to accurately segment the tumor regions which can aid in prognosis, treatment, planning, surgical interventions.
This project introduces intermediate level concepts of computer visions, deep learning, and medical image analysis.
So, guys, what we'll be using all over here?
For programming languages, we can use Python. For deep learning libraries, we can use TensorFlow, Keras, PyTorch. For image processing libraries, we can use OpenCV, Scikit Image.
For data handling libraries, we can use Pandas, NumPy.
For visualization, we can use Matplotlab CBON.
Now, if I talk about what is the process of developing this project, the first step will be the same data collection.
So next step, you have to go for data pre-processing.
Third step, you have to do the model selection where you can use CNN models for image segmentation tasks.
Then you go for model selection.
Moving ahead, you're going to have the model training and evaluation.
You have to split the dataset into training and validation and testing datasets.
Next, proceed for the evaluation phase.
Okay. Evaluate the model with certain metrics. So here I can give you certain idea like you can use dice coefficient, intersection over union, or accuracy.
Then go for hyperparameter tuning where you have to optimize the model's hyperparameters.
You can use grid search or random search as we have discussed, and finally, you can deploy this model on AWS.
Now, guys, we have come to the final project.
This is also very amazing project, guys.
So, guys, the complexity level of this project is advanced level.
Now, let us move on to our final project, that is the impact of climate change on birds.
This is a very, very amazing project, and definitely you can add it on your resume.
This project aims to analyze the impact of climate change on the bird population and migration patterns.
By examining various climatic factors and their correlation with bird species data, the project seeks to predict how climate change might affect bird behavior and distribution.
This project will introduce you some advanced level concepts like time series analysis, environmental data modeling, etc.
So, guys, what programming languages we'll be using? For data analysis, you can see we'll have pandas, numpy. For machine learning libraries, we are going to have scikit-learn, tensor flow.
For visualization, we are going to have matplotlib, Plotly.
For geospatial, we are going to have GeoPandas, Folium.
For radar service, we're going to have public data sets on bird observation and climate data sources from eBird.
Now, what will the process flow for this one, guys?
First, you have to proceed for data collection, gather bird observation from the data like eBird, which provides extensive record of bird sightings.
Okay. And for climate data, you can collect it from NOAA, including temperature, precipitation, and other relevant climatic factors over the time.
And similar next process will be the data pre-processing, then you have to proceed for feature engineering, then you have to go for model selection.
Okay.
Moving ahead, you have to go for model training, then evaluation, then hypoparameter tuning, and finally, you have to deploy the model.
So research about this project, see what models you're going to use. Suppose I can give you a hint about this. You can use time series analysis models like Arima or ML models.
You can also use random forest or gradient boosting for predicting impact on the bird population.
So, guys, use Google exhaustively to research about this project.
This is also a very amazing project, and it's going to give you a lot of idea.
Now, if I talk about the complexity level of this, it is an advanced level project.
Welcome to Deep Learning Interview Questions.
My name is Richard Kirschner with the Simply Learn team. That's www.simplylearn.com.
Get certified, get ahead.
Today we're going to help you prepare for interview questions dealing with deep learning.
And we're going to go from the very basics of neural networks and deep learning into some of the more commonly used models
so that you can have an understanding of what kind of questions are going to come up and what you need to know in interview questions.
We'll start with a very general concept of what is deep learning.
This is where we take large volumes of data, in this case on cats and dogs or whatever. A lot of times you use a training setup to train your model.
Remember it's kind of like a magic black box going on there. Then we use that to extract features or extract information, and in this case, classify the image of a cat and a dog.
So the primary takeaway we're talking about deep learning is it learns from large volumes of structured and even unstructured data and uses complex algorithms to train neural network.
It also performs complex operations to extract hidden patterns and features.
And if we're going to discuss deep learning in this very simplified overview, then we also have to go over what is a neural network.
This is a common image you'll see of a drawing of a forward propagation neural network. And it's it's a human brain inspired system which replicate the way humans learn.
So this is inspired how our own neurons and our brain fire, but at a much simplified level.
Obviously, it's not ready to take over the human population and be our leader yet, not for many years. It's very much in its infant stage. But it's inspired by how our brains work.
And they use a lot of other inspirations. You can study brains of moths and other animals that they've used to figure out how to improve these neural networks.
The most common one consists of three layers of network, and this is generally how you view these networks, is you have an input, you have a hidden layer, and an output.
And the neural network is broken up into many pieces, but when we focus just on the neural network, it's always on the hidden layers that we're making all the adjustments
and figuring out how to best set up those hidden layers for their functions to both train faster and to function better. When we look at this, of course, we have our input, hidden, and output.
Each layer contains neurons called as nodes that perform various operations.
And you can see here we have the list of the nodes, we have both our input nodes and our output nodes, and then our hidden layer nodes.
And it's used in deep learning algorithm like CNN, RNN, JN, etc.
We'll address some of these models a little closer, at least the most common models, as we go down the list and we study the deep learning and the neural network framework.
Let's start with what is a multi-layer percepitron, or MLP, a lot of time is referred to. And you'll see these abbreviations.
I'll be honest, I have to write them down on a piece of paper and go through them because I never remember what they all mean, even though I play with them all the time.
What is a multilayer percipitron? Well, if you look at the image on the right, it's very similar to what we just looked at. You have your input layer, your hidden layer, and your output layer.
And that's exactly what this is. It has the same structure of a single layer perceptron with one or more hidden layers, except the input layer.
Each node in the other layers uses a nonlinear activation function.
What that means is your input layer is your data coming in, and then your activation function is based upon all those nodes and weights being added together, and then it has the output.
MLP uses supervised learning method called backpropagation for training the model.
Very key word there is backpropagation. Single layer perceptron can classify only linear separable classes with binary output, zero, one, but the MLP can classify nonlinear classes.
So let's break this down just a little bit the multi-layer percipitron with an input layer and a hidden layer and an output layer.
As you see that it comes in there, it adds up all the numbers and weights, depending on how your setup is, that then goes to the next layer,
that then goes to the next hidden layer if you have multiple hidden layers, and finally to the output layer.
The back propagation takes the error that it sees. So whatever the output is, it says, hey, this has an error to it, it's wrong. And it sends that error backwards from where it came from.
And there's a lot of different functions used to train this based on that error and how that error goes backwards in the nodes.
So forward is you get your answers, backward is for training.
You see this every day. Even my Google Pixel phone has this. They train the neural network, which takes a lot more data to train than it does to use.
And then they load up that neural network into, in this case, I have a Pixel 2, which actually has a built-in neural network for processing pictures.
And so it's just the forward propagation I use when it processes my photos. But when they were training it, it used the back propagation to train it with the errors they had.
We'll be coming back to different models that are used.
For right now, though, multi-layer Perceptron MLP.
Put that down as your vocabulary word. And of course, backpropagation.
What is data normalization and why do we need it? This is so important. We spend so much time in normalizing our data and getting our data clean and setting it up.
So we talk about data, there's a pre-processing step to standardize the data.
So whatever we have coming in, we don't want it to be a one gigabyte file here, a two gigabyte picture here, and a three-kilobyte text there.
Even as a human, I can't process those all in the same group. I have to reformat them in some way that loops them together so that the standardized format.
We use this data normalization in pre-processing to reduce it and eliminate data redundancy.
A lot of times the data comes in and you end up with two of the same images or the same information in different formats.
Then we want to rescale values to fit into a particular range for achieving better convergence. What this means is with most neural networks they form a bias.
We've seen this in recently in attacks on neural networks where they light up one pixel or one piece of the view and it skews the whole answer.
So suddenly because one pixel is really bright, it doesn't know what to do.
Well, when we start rescaling it, we put all the values between say minus one and one, and we change them and refit them to those values, it helps get rid of that bias,
helps fix for some of those problems. And then finally we restructure the data and improve the integrity. We want to make sure that we're not missing values or we don't have partial data coming in.
One way to look at this is bad data in, bad data out. So we want clean data in and you want good answers coming out.
One of the most basic models used is a Boltzmann machine. So let's address what is a Boltzmann machine. And if you know, we just did the MLP multi-layer perceptron.
So now we're going to come into almost a simplified version of that.
And in this we have our visible input layer and we have our hidden layer. The Boltzmann machines are almost always shallow.
They're usually just two-layer neural nets that make stochastic decisions whether a neuron should be on or off. True, false. Yes, no.
First layer is the visible layer, and second layer is the hidden layer.
Nodes are connected to each other across layers, but no two nodes of the same layer are connected. Hence it is also known as restricted Boltzmann machine.
Now that we've covered a basic MLP or multi layer perceptron, and we've gone over the Boltzmann machine, also known as the restricted Boltzmann machine,
let's talk a little bit about activation formulas.
And this is a huge topic that can get really complicated, but it also is automated, so it's very simple. So you have both a complicated and a simple at the same time.
So what is the role of activation functions in a neural network? Activation function decides whether a neuron should be fired or not.
That's the most basic one. And that actually changes a little bit because it's either whether it's fired or not, in this case activation function, or what value should come out when it's fired.
But in these models we're looking at just the Boltzmann restricted layers.
So this is what causes them to fire. Either they don't or they do. It's a yes or no, true, false, all or nothing.
It accepts the weighted sum of the inputs, the bias as input to any activation function.
So whatever activation function is, it needs to have the sum of the weights times the input. So each input, if you remember on that model, and let's just go back to that model real quick.
And then you always have to add a bias.
And you can look at the bias if you remember from your Euclidean geometry, you draw a straight line.
The formula for that line has a y coordinate at the end.
It's always cx plus m or something like that, where m is where it crosses the y coordinates if you're doing a straight line.
With these weights, it's very similar, but a lot of times we just add it in as its own weight.
We take it as a node of a one value coming in, and then we compute its new weight, and that's how we compute that bias, just like we compute all the other weights coming in.
The node which gets fired depends on the y value, and then we have a step function. And the step function, this is where, remember I said it's going to get complicated and simple all at the same time.
We have a lot of different step functions. We have the sigmoid function, we have just a standard step function, we have the ReLU, it's pronounced like Ray, the ray from the sun
and lu, like a name. So ReLU function, and we have the tangent h function. And if you look at these, they all have something similar. They all either force it to be one value or the other.
They force it to be in the case of the first three a zero or one, and in the last one, it's either a minus one or a one. And you can easily convert that to a zero, one, yes, no, true, false.
And on this, one of the most common ones is the step function itself, because there is no middle value, there is no discrepancy that says,
well, I'm not quite sure. But as you get into different models, probably the most commonly used used to be the sigmoid was most commonly used, but I see the ReLU used more often.
Really, depending on what you're doing, you just have to play with these and find out which one works best, depending on the data and your output.
The reason to have a non-zero one answer or something kind of in the middle is when you're looking at this and it's coming out, you can actually process that
middle ground as part of the answer into another neural network. So it might be that the ReLU function says, hey, this is only a 0.6, not a 1.
And even though the one is what's going into the next neural network or the next hidden layer as an input, the 0.6
value might also be going in there to let you know, hey, this is not a straight up one or a straight up zero, it's someplace in the middle. This is a little uncertain what's coming out here.
So it's a very powerful tool. But in the basic neural network, you usually just use the step function. It's yes or no.
Let's take a big step back and take a uh kind of an overview. The next function is what is a cost function that we're going to cover.
This is so important because this is your end result that you're going to do over and over again and use to decide whether the model is working or not,
whether you need to try a different step function, whether you need to try a different activation, whether you need to try a fully different model used.
so what is the cost function?
Cost function is the measure to evaluate how good your model's performance is.
It is also referred to as loss or error used to compute the error of the output layer during backpropagation. There's our backpropagation where we're training our model. That's one of our key words.
Mean squared error is an example of a popular cost function. And so here we have the cost function c equals half of y minus y predicted. and then you square that.
So the first thing is you know, real quick, if you haven't done statistics, this is not a percentage. It's not a percentage of how accurate it is, it's just a measurement of the error.
And we take that error for training it, and we push that error backwards through the neural network, and we use that through the different training functions, depending on what model you're using,
to train the neural network. So when you deploy the network, you're usually done training it, because it takes a lot of computational force to train it. Um this is a very simple model.
And so you deploy the trained one, but we want to know how your error is. And so how do we do that? Well, you split your data.
Part of your data is for training and part of your data is for testing, and then we can also test the error on there. So that's very important. And then we're going to go one more step on this.
We gotta look at both the local and the global setup. It might work great to test your data on what you have on your computer, but that's different than in the field.
So when we're talking about all these different tests in the error test as far as your loss, you don't you want to make sure that you're in a closed environment when you do initial testing,
but you also want to open that up and make sure you follow up with the testing on the larger scale of data because it will change. It might not fit the larger scale.
There might be something in there in the way you brought the data in specifically, or the data group you used, or any of those could cause an error.
So it's very important to remember that we're looking at both the local and the global context of our error.
And just one other side note on a lot of the newer models of neural networks, by comparing the error we get on the data, our training data,
with a portion of the test data, we can actually figure out how good the model is, whether it's overfitted or not. We'll go into that a little bit more as we go into some of the different models.
So we have our output, we're able to figure out the error on it based on the square means usually, although there's other functions used. So we want to talk about what is gradient descent.
Another vocabulary word. Gradient descent is an optimization algorithm to minimize the cost function or to minimize the error.
Aim is to find the local or global minima of a function.
Determine the direction the model should take to reduce the error. So as we're looking at this, we have our squared error that we just figured out, based on the cost function.
It says how bad is my model fitting the data I just put through it. And then we want to reduce that error.
So how do you figure out what direction to do that in? Well, it could be that you're looking at just that line of that line of data coming in, so that would be a local minima.
We want to know the error of that particular setup coming in. And then you have your global, your global minima. We want to minimize it based on the overall data we're putting through it.
And with this, we can figure out the global minimum cost. We want to take all those local minimum costs of each piece of data coming in and figure out the global one.
How are we going to adjust this model to fit all the data?
We don't want it to be biased just on three or four lines of data coming in. We want it to kind of extrapolate a general answer for all the data coming in.
This, of course, we mentioned it briefly about backpropagation. This is where it really comes in handy is training our model. Neural network technique to minimize the cost function.
helps to improve the performance of the network, backpropagates the error, and updates the weights to reduce the error.
So as you can see here is a very nice depiction of a backpropagation. We have our predicted Y coming out, and then we have, since it's a training set, we already know the answer.
And the answer comes back and based on case of the square means was one of the functions we looked at. One of the activation functions based on cost function.
That cost function then, depending on what you choose for your backpropagation method, and there's a number of them, will change the weights.
It will change the weight going to each of the one of those nodes in the hidden layer.
And then based upon the error that's still being carried back, it'll change the weights going to the next hidden layer. And then it computes an error level on that and sends that back up.
And you're going to say, well, if it computes the error into the first hidden layer and fixes it, why would it stop there?
Well, remember, we don't want to create a biased neural network. So we only make small adjustments on these weights. We don't make a big adjustment that changes everything right off the bat.
So no matter how far back you go, you're always going to have a small amount of error, and that's still going to continue to go all the way back up the hidden layers.
For right now, focus on the back propagation is taking that error and moving it backwards on the neural network to change the weights and help program it so that it'll have the correct answers.
So far, we've been talking about forward propagation neural networks. Everything goes forwards, goes left to right.
But let's take a little detour and let's see what is the difference between a feed forward neural network and a recurrent neural network.
Now this is in the function, not when we're training it using the back propagation.
So you've got new information coming in and you want to get the answer, and there's a couple different networks out there,
and we want to know we have a feed forward neural network and we have a new vocabulary term, recurrent neural network.
A feedforward neural network, signals travel in one direction from input to output. No feedback loops, considers only the current input, cannot memorize previous inputs.
One example of one of these feedforward neural networks, and we've covered a number of them, but one of the ones that has a big highlight nowadays is the CNN,
a convolutional neural network. TensorFlow, the one put out by Google, is probably most known for their CNN.
where the information goes forward: it first takes a picture, splits it apart, goes through the individual pixels on the picture, so it picks up a different reading,
then calculates based on that, goes into a regular feedforward neural network, and then gives your categorization on there.
Now we're not covering the CNN today, but we do have a video out that you can look up on YouTube, put out by Simply Learn, the convolutional neural network. Wonderful tutorial.
Check that out and learn a lot more about the convolutional neural network.
But you do need to know that the CNN is a forward propagation neural network only.
So it's only moving in one direction. So we will look at a recurrent neural network. Signals travel in both directions, making it a looped network.
Considers the current input along with the previous received inputs for generating the output of a layer, has the ability to memorize past data due to its internal memory.
And you can see they have a nice image here. We have our input, and for some reason they always do the recurrent neural network in reverse from bottom up in the images.
Kind of a standard, although I'm not sure why. Your X goes into your hidden layer, and your hidden layer, the answer for part of the answer from that it generates, feeds back into the hidden layer.
So now you have an input of both X and part of the hidden layer, and then that feeds into your output.
Now, if we go back to the forward, let me just go back a slide, and we're looking at our forward propagation network.
One of the tricks you can do to use just a forward propagation network is if you're in what they call a time sequence, that's a good term to remember,
or a time series. Meaning that it's sequential data. Each term comes after the other. You can trick this by creating your input nodes with the history.
So if you know that you have values one, five, and seven going in, and you know what the output is from one what those outputs are, you can expand the input to include the history input.
That's one of the ways to trick a forward propagation network into looking at that. But when you do it with a recurrent neural network, you let the hidden layer do that for you.
It sends that data and reprocesses it back into itself.
What are some of the applications of recurrent neural network?
The RNN can be used for sentiment analysis and text mining.
Getting up early in the morning is good for health.
And it's a positive sentiment.
One of the catches you really want to look at this when you're looking at the language is that I could switch this around and totally negate the meaning of what I'm doing,
so it would no longer be positive. So when you're looking at a sentence, knowing the order of the words is as important as the meaning of the words.
You can't just count how many good words there are versus bad words to get a positive sentiment. You now have to know what they're addressing.
And there's lots of other different uses. kids are playing football or soccer as we call it in the US. RN can help you capture an image.
So based on previous information coming in, it refeeds that back in and you have an image setter.
And then time series problems like predicting the prices of stocks in a month or quarter or sell a product can be solved using an RNN. And this is a really good example.
You have whatever your stocks were doing earlier this month will have a huge effect on what they're doing today if you're investing.
So having an RNN model, a recurrent neural network feeding into itself what was happening previously allows it to take that model and program in that whole series without having to put in the whole
a month at a time of data.
You only put in one day at a time, but if you keep them in order, it will look back and say, oh, this because of what happened yesterday, I need some information from that,
and I'm going to use that to help predict today's and so on and so on.
We're going to go back to our activation functions. Remember I told you ReLU was one of the most common functions used? so let's talk a little bit more about ReLU and also Softmax.
Softmax is an activation function that generates the output between 0 and 1.
It divides each output such that the total sum of the outputs is equal to 1. It is often used in the output layers. Softmax L of the n equals e to L of the N over the absolute value of E to the L.
So what does this function mean? I mean, what is actually going on here? So we have our output nodes, and our output nodes are giving us let's say they gave us 1.2, 0.9, and 0.4.
As a human being, I look at that and I say, well, the greatest value is 1.2.
So whatever category that is, if you have three different categories, maybe you're not just doing if it's a cat or it's a dog or let's say it's a cow. We had cats and dogs earlier.
Why the cats and dogs are hanging out with a cow, I don't know. But we have a value, and it might say 1.2 is a cat, 0.9 is a dog, and 0.4 is a cow.
for some reason it thinks that there's a chance of it being any one of these three items, and that's how it comes out of the output layer.
Well, as a human, I can look at 1.2 and say this is definitely what it is. It's definitely a cat or whatever it is.
Maybe it's looking at different kinds of cars, might be a better whether it's a car, truck, or a motorcycle.
Maybe that'd be a better example.
Well, from a computer standpoint, that might be a little confusing because they're just numbers waving at us. And so with the softmax, we want all those numbers to always add up to one.
So when I add three numbers together, I want the final output to be one on there.
And so it goes through this formula, changes each of these numbers, in this case it changes them to 0.46, 0.34, and 0.20. They all add up to one.
And that's a lot easier to register because it's very set. It's a set output. It's never going to be more than one, it's never going to be less than zero.
And so you can see here that there's probably a pretty high chance that it's the first one. So you're a human being, we have no problem knowing that.
But this output can then also go into say another input. So it might be an automated car that's picking up images, and it says that image in front of us is probably a big truck.
We should deal with it like it's a big truck. It's probably not a motorcycle, or whatever those categories are.
That's the softmax part of it. But now we have the RELU. Well, what's where's the RELU coming from? Well, the RELU is what's generating the 1.2 and the 0.9 and the 0.4.
And so if you remember, our RELU stands for rectified linear unit and is the most widely used activation function.
We looked at a number of different activation functions, including tangent H, the step function.
remember I said the step function is really used if that's what your actual output is, because then you know it's a zero or one.
But the ReLU, if you have that as your output, you now have a discrepancy in there. And if that's going into another neural network or another process, having that discrepancy is really important.
And it gives an output of x if x is positive and zero otherwise. So it says my x value is going to be somewhere between zero or one.
And then usually unless it's really uncertain, the output is usually a one or zero.
And then you have that little piece of uncertainty there that you can send forward to another network or you can look at to know that there's uncertainty involved.
And is often used in the hidden layers. This is what's coming out of the hidden layers into the output layer usually.
Or as we reference the uh convolution uh neural network, the CNN, which you'd have to go to another video to review. The ReLU is the most common used for convolutional part of that network.
It has a bunch of little pieces that are very simplified looking at all the different images or different sections of the map, and the ReLU works really good for that.
Like I said, there's other formulas used, but this is the most common one, and you'll see that in the hidden layers going maybe between one layer and the next layer.
So just a quick recap, we have our soft max, which means that if you have numerous categories, only one of them is going to be picked,
but you also want to have some value attached to it, how well it picked it. And you put that between zero and one, so it's very standardized. So we have our softmax.
We looked at that, let's go back one. We looked at that here where it transforms the numbers.
And then we have our ReLU function, which takes the information and the summation and puts it between a zero and a one, where it's either clearly a zero
or depending on how confident our model is, it'll go between the zero and one value. What are hyperparameters? Wow, this is a great interview question. Hyperparameters.
When you are doing neural networks, this is what you're playing with most of the time once you've gotten the data formatted correctly.
A hyperparameter is a parameter whose value is set before the learning process begins, determines how a network is trained and the structure of the network.
This includes things like the number of hidden units, how many hidden layers are you going to have, and how many nodes in each layer? Learning rate.
Learning rate is usually multiplied once you've figured out the error and how much you want to change the weights.
We talked about, or I mentioned it early, just briefly, you don't want to just make a huge change, otherwise you're going to have a biased model.
So you only take some little incremental changes, and that's what the learning rate is, is those small incremental changes.
Epics, how many times are you going to go through all the data in your training set? So one epic is one trip through all the data.
And there's a lot of other things depending on which model you're working with and which programming script you're working with.
Like the Python SKLearn package will have it slightly different than say Google's TensorFlow package, which will be a little bit different than the Spark machine learning package.
So these are just some examples of the hyperparameters.
And so you see in here we have a nice image of our data coming in and we train our model, then we do a comparison to see how good our model is, and then we go back and we say,
hey, this this model is pretty good, but it's biased.
So then we send it back and we change our hyperparameters to see if we can get an unbiased model, or we can have a better prediction on it that matches our data closer.
What will happen if learning rate is set too low or too high? We have a nice couple graphs here.
We have one over here that says a learning rate set too low, you can see that it slowly works its way down the curve. And on the right, you can see a learning rate set too high.
It's just bouncing back and forth.
When your learning rate is too low, as we studied it two slides over this, what the learning rate was.
Training of the model will progress very slowly as we are making very tiny updates to the weights. We'll take many updates before reaching the minimum point.
So I just mentioned epic going through all the data. You might have to go through all the data a thousand times instead of 500 times for it to train.
Learning rate too high causes undesirable divergent behavior to the loss function due to drastic updates and weights. At times it may fail to converge or even diverge.
So if you have your learning rate set too high and it's training too quickly, maybe you'll get lucky and it trains after one epic run,
but a lot of times it might never be able to train because the weights are changing too fast. They flip back and forth too easy.
And you see down here we've introduced two new terms, converge and diverge.
Uh converge means that our model has reached a point where it's able to give a fairly good answer for all the data we put in. All those weights have adjusted and it's minimized the error.
Diverge means that the data is so chaotic that it can never manage to train to that data. The data is just too chaotic for it to train.
So we have two new words there, converge and diverge are important to know also. What is dropout and batch normalization?
Dropout is a technique of dropping out hidden and visible units of a network randomly to prevent overfitting of data.
It doubles the number of iterations needed to converge the network. So here we have our standard neural network, and then after applying dropout. Now it doesn't mean we actually delete the node.
The node is still there, and we're still going to use that node. What it means is that we're only going to work with a few of the nodes.
A lot of times, I think the most common one right now used is 20%.
Uh so you'll drop out 20% of the nodes when you do your training, you reverse propagate your data, and then you'll randomly pick another 20 nodes the next time you go through an epic data training.
So each time you go through one epic, you will randomly pick 20 of those nodes not to mess with. And this allows for less overfitting of the data.
So by randomly doing this, you create some, I guess it just kind of pulls some nodes off to the sides and says we're going to handle the data later on so we don't overfit.
Batch normalization is the technique to improve the performance and stability of neural network.
The idea is to normalize the inputs in every layer so that they have mean output and activation of zero and standard deviation of one. This question covers a lot of different things, which is great.
It's a great interview question because it pulls in that you have to understand what the mean value is. So a mean output activation of zero, that means our average activation is zero.
So when you normalize it, remember usually we're going between minus one and one on a lot of these.
It's a very standard setup, so you have to be very aware that this is your mean output activation of zero. And then we have our standard deviation of one.
So we want to keep our error down to just a one value. The benefits of this doing a batch normalization is it provides regularization, it trains faster, higher learning rates,
and weights are easier to initialize. What is the difference between batch gradient descent and stochastic gradient descent?
Batch gradient descent. Batch gradient computes the gradient using the entire data set. It takes time to converge because the volume of data is huge and weights update slowly.
So you can look at the batches. A lot of times if you're using big data, batch the data in, but you still go through a full epic. You still go through all the data on there.
So batch gradient descent means you're going to use it to fit all the data and look for a convergence there. Stochastic gradient descent.
Stochastic gradient computes the gradient using a single sample. It converges much faster than batch gradient because it updates weight more frequently.
Explain overfitting and underfitting and how to combat them.
Overfitting happens when a model learns the details and noise in the training data to the degree that it adversely impacts the execution of the model on the new
information. It is more likely to occur with nonlinear models that have more flexibility when learning a target function.
An example of this would be if you're looking at, say, cars and trucks and motorcycles, it might only recognize trucks that have a certain box-like shape.
It might not be able to notice a flatbed truck unless it's only a specific kind of flatbed truck or only Ford trucks, because that's what it saw on the training set.
This means that your model performs great on your train data and great on maybe a small test amount of data, but when you go to use it in the real world, it leaves out a lot and
is not very functional outside of your small area, your small laboratory data coming in.
Underfitting, doing the opposite when you underfit your data, underfitting alludes to a model that is neither well trained on training data nor can generalize to new information.
Usually happens when there is less and improper data to train a model. Has a burr of performance and accuracy.
So if you're using underfitted data and you generate a model and you distribute that in a commercial zone,
you'll have a lot of people unhappy with you because it's not going to give them very good answers.
So we've explained overfitting and underfitting, so now we want to ask how to combat them. Combating overfitting and underfitting.
Resampling the data to estimate the model accuracy, K-fold cross-validation.
Having a validation data set to evaluate the model.
So when we do the resampling, we're randomly going to be picking out data, and we'll run it a few times to see how that works, depending on our random data and how we
sample the data to generate our model.
And then we want to go ahead and validate the data set by having our training data and then keeping some data on the side, testing data to validate it.
How are weights initialized in a network?
Initializing all weights to zero. All the weights are set to zero. This makes your model similar to a linear model.
So if you have linear data coming in, doing a basic setup like that might work. All the neurons in every layer perform the same operation given the same output and making the deep net useless.
Right there is a key word. It's going to be useless if you initialize everything to zero.
At that point, be looking into some other machine learning tools. Initializing all weights randomly. Here the weights are assigned randomly by initializing them very close to zero.
It gives better accuracy to the model since every neuron performs different computations. And here we have the weights are set randomly.
We have our input layer, the hidden layers, and the output layer. And W equals NP random, random n. Layer size L layer size L minus one.
This is the most commonly used is to randomly generate your weights. What are the different layers in CNN? Convolutional neural network.
First is the convolutional layer that performs a convolutional operation.
We have our other video out if you want to explore that more so and go into detail exactly how the C the convolutional layer works in the CNN as far as creating a number of smaller
picture windows that go over the data.
The second step is as a RELU layer. ReLU brings nonlinearity to the network and converts all the negative pixels to zero.
Output is rectified feature map.
So it goes into a mapping feature there. Pooling layer. Pooling is a downsampling operation that reduces the dimensionality of the feature map.
So we have all our ReLU layer, which is pulling all these little maps out of our convolutional layer.
It's taking that picture and creating little tiny neural networks to look at different parts of the picture.
Then we need to pull it together, and then finally the fully connected layer.
So we flatten our pooling layer out, and we have a fully connected layer recognizes and classifies the objects in the image.
And that's actually your forward propagation, reverse propagation training model, usually. I mean there's a number of different models out there, of course.
What is pooling in CNN and how does it work?
Pooling used to reduce the spatial dimensions of a CNN performs down sampling operation to reduce the dimensionality, creates a pooled feature map by sliding a filter matrix over the input matrix.
I mentioned that briefly on the previous slide. It's important to know that you have, if you see here they have a rectified feature map.
And so each one of those colors, like the yellow color, that might be one of the smaller little neural network using the Relu.
You'll look at, it'll just kind of go over the main picture and look at all the different areas on the main picture.
So you might step one, two, three, four spaces. And then you have another one that's also looking at features. And it has a two, seven, eight, five. Each one of those is a map.
So it might be the first one, might be a map looking for cat ears, the second one looking for human eyes.
When it does this, you then have this rectified feature map looking at these different features.
And the max pooling with a two by two filters and a stride of two. Stride means instead of skipping every pixel, you're going to go every two pixels. You take the maximum values.
And you can see over here, we look at a pooled feature map.
One of the features says, hey, I had a max value of eight. So somewhere in here we saw a human eye labeled as eight. Pretty high label.
And maybe seven was a human hand, and maybe four was cat whiskers, or something that we thought might be cat whiskers. Four is kind of a low number in this particular case compared to the other ones.
So you have your full pooled feature map. You can see the process here is we have our stepping.
We look for the max value, and then we create a pooled feature map of the maxed values. How does a LSTM network work? That's long short-term memory.
So the first thing to know is that an LSTMS are a special kind of recurrent neural network capable of learning long-term dependencies.
Remembering information for long periods of time is their default behavior.
We did look at the RNN briefly, talked about how the hidden layer feeds back into itself with the LSTM it has a much more complicated feedback.
And you can see here we have the hidden layer of T minus one and the hidden layer, that's what the H stands for, hidden layer of T and the formula is going in.
As we can see here, we have the hidden layers.
We have T minus one and then H of T, where T stands for time. So this is a series. Remember working with series and we want to remember the past.
And you can see you have your X your input of T, and that might be a frame in a video.
As the frame comes in, they usually use in this one the tangent h activation formula, but you also see that it goes through a couple other formulas,
the omega formula.
And so when it combines these, that then goes into the next layer, your next hidden layer.
That then goes into the data that's submitted to the next input. So you have your x of t plus one.
So when you have that coming in, then you have your h value that's coming forward from the last process.
And depending on how many of these omega structures you put in there, depends on how long term the memory gets. So it's important to remember this is more for your long-term recurrent neural networks.
The three steps in an LSTM. Step one decides what to forget and what to remember.
Step two, selectively update cell state values. So based on what we want to remember and forget, we want to update those cell values.
And then decides what part of the current state make it to the output. So now we have to also have an output on there.
What are vanishing and exploding gradients? This is a great question that affects all our neural networks.
While training an RNN, your slope can become either too small or too large, and this makes the training difficult. When the slope is too small, the problem is known as vanishing gradient.
So our slope, we have our change in X and our change in Y. When the slope decreases gradually to a very small value, sometimes negative, and makes training difficult.
When the slope tends to grow exponentially instead of decaying, this problem is called exploding gradient. The slope grows exponentially. You can see a nice graph of that here.
Issues in gradient problem, long training time, poor performance, and low accuracy. What is the difference between epic, batch, and iteration in deep learning?
Epic.
An epic represents one iteration over the entire data set.
So that's everything you're going to go ahead and put into that training model.
Batch.
We cannot pass the entire data set into the neural network at once. So we divide the data set into a number of batches. And then iteration.
If we have 10,000 images as data and a batch size of 200, then the epic should run 10,000 times over 200. So that means we have our total number over the 200 equals 50 iterations.
So in each epic, we're running over all the data set, we're going to have 50 iterations. And each of those iterations includes a batch of 200 images in this case.
Why TensorFlow is the most preferred library in deep learning? Well, first, TensorFlow provides both C and Python APIs that makes it easier to work on.
Has a faster compilation time than other deep learning libraries like Karas and Torch.
TensorFlow supports both CPU's and GPUs computing devices.
So right now, TensorFlow is at the top of the market because it's so easy to use for both programmer side and for hardware side and for the speed of getting something up and running.
What do you mean by tensor in TensorFlow?
Tensor is a mathematical object represented as arrays of higher dimensions. These arrays of data with different dimensions and ranks that are fed as input to the neural network are called tensors.
You can see here we have a tensor of dimensions 5, 4. So it's a two-dimensional tensor coming in.
You can look at an image like this that each one of those pixels is a different value if it's a black and white. So it might be zero and ones, and then each one represents a black and white image.
In a color photo, you might either find a different value system or you might have a tensor value that has the xy coordinates as we see here, plus the colors.
So you might have three more different dimensions for the three different images, the red, the blue, and the yellow coming in.
And even as you go from one layer or one tensor to the next, these layers might change. We might flatten them, might bring in numerous.
In the case of the convergence neural network, we have all those smaller different mappings of features that come in.
So each one of those layers coming through is a tensor if it has multiple dimensions coming in and weights attached to it. What are the programming elements in TensorFlow? Well we have our constants.
Constants are parameters whose value does not change. To define a constant, we use tf.constant command. Example a equals tf.constant 2.0, tf float32. So it's a tensor float value of 32.
B equals tf constant 3.0, print ab.
If we did a print of a b we'd have tf.constant and then of course b is that instance of it.
Variables. Variables allow us to add new trainable parameters to graph.
To divine a variable, we use tf.variable command and initialize them before running the graph in session.
Example, w equals tf variable point three d type tf float32, or b equals a tf variable minus three, comma d type float32. Placeholders.
Placeholders allow us to feed data to a tensor flow model from outside a model.
It permits a value to be assigned later. To define a placeholder, we use tf placeholder command. Example, a equals tf placeholder, b equals a times two.
With the tf session as S E S S result equals session run b, comma feed, dictionary equals a three.0 print result.
So we have a nice example there of a placeholder.
Session. A session is run to evaluate the nodes. This is called as the TensorFlow runtime.
So for example you have A equals TF constant 2.0, B equals TF constant 4.0, C equals A plus B.
And at this point you'd go ahead and create a session equals TF session, and then you could evaluate the tensor C print session run C.
That would input C as an input into your session.
What do you understand by a computational graph? Everything in TensorFlow is based on creating a computational graph.
It has a network of nodes where each node performs an operation. Nodes represent mathematical operation and edges represent tensors.
Since data flows in a form of a graph, it is also called a data flow graph. And we have a nice visual of this graph or graphic image of a computational graph.
And you can see here we have our input nodes, our add multiply nodes, and our multiply node at the end, and then we have the edges where the data flows. So we have from A going to C, A going to D.
You can see we have a two flowing, a four flowing. Explain generative adversarial network along with an example.
Suppose there is a wine shop that purchases wine from dealers, which they will resell later. So we have our dealer going to the wine, our shop owner that then sells it for a profit.
But there are some malefactor dealers who sell fake wine. In this case, the shop owner should be able to distinguish between fake and authentic wine.
The forger will try to different techniques to sell fake wine and make sure certain techniques go past the shop owner's check. So here's our forger, fake wine, shop owner.
The shop owner would probably get some feedback from the wine experts that some of the wine is not original. The owner would have to improve how he determines whether a wine is fake or authentic.
Goal of forger, to create wines that are indistinguishable from the authentic ones. Goal of shop owner, to accurately tell if the wine is real or not.
There are two main components of generative adversarial network.
And we'll refer to as a noise vector coming in, we have our forger who's going to generate fake wine, and then we have our real authentic wine,
and of course our shop owner who has to figure out whether it's real or fake.
The generator is a CNN that keeps producing images that are closer in appearance to the real images, while the discriminator tries to determine the difference between real and fake images.
The ultimate aim is to make the discriminator learn to identify real and fake images. What is an autoencoder?
The network is trained to reconstruct its inputs.
It is a neural network that has three layers. Here the input neurons are equal to the output neuron.
The network's target outside is same as the input.
It uses dimensionality reduction to restructure the input.
Input image comes in, we have our Latin space representation, and then it goes back out reconstructing the image.
It works by compressing the input to a Latin space representation and then reconstructing the output from this representation. What is bagging and boosting?
Bagging and boosting are ensemble techniques where the idea is to train multiple models using the same learning algorithm and then take a call.
So we have in here where we're bagging, we take a data set and we split it. We're gonna have our training data and our test data. Very standard thing to do.
Then we're going to randomly select data into the bags and train your models separately. So we might have bag one, model one, bag two, model two, bag three, model three, and so on.
In boosting, the emphasis is to select the data points which give wrong output in order to improve the accuracy. So in boosting, we have our data set.
Again, we split it to test data and train data, and we'll take a bag one and we'll train the model. Data points with wrong predictions then go into bag two, and we then train that model and repeat.
Now, without further delay, let's get started with our Python exploratory data analysis.
But before getting started with the demonstration, let's have a brief understanding of exactly what is exploratory analysis.
Is this anything different from regular data analysis?
Yeah, that's exactly what we're going to discuss.
Now, types of data analysis.
So basically there are two different types of data analysis: initial data analysis and exploratory data analysis.
Now what is initial data analysis and what is exploratory data analysis?
Let's understand a little briefing about these both.
First, let's get started with initial data analysis.
So what exactly do you mean by initial data analysis?
So data can be in any form.
It can be an Excel file, it can be a SQL file, it can be a PDF, it can be an XML, it can be even a website.
Whatever it is, it is data. If you have some information in this which can be used to extract some valuable information, then it is data.
So initial data analysis is a process of inspecting the data and screening the data that takes place after data collection and before statistical analysis.
So before you conduct any statistical formulas and analysis on the data and squeeze the data to extract some valuable insights,
the process which you perform is called as initial data analysis, like taking the data from the source, cleaning the data, transforming the data into a readable format,
and using that readable data to build some basic charts. What exactly is happening with this particular company, brand, or anything.
Let's say I give you some data from the company, then you get some insights of it, how many number of traffic you receive, how many number of orders you receive,
what's the sale that you made in a specific month, specific quarter, or specific year, and what was the profit.
So basic information which you convert from the data and create a dashboard, right?
That is called as initial data analysis.
So a step beyond initial data analysis is known as the exploratory data analysis.
This is where you perform some statistics and probability and predict the future, right?
So let's dive deep and learn what exactly is exploratory data analysis.
So a simple definition for exploratory data analysis is as follows.
Exploratory data analysis is a key step in data analysis process that helps you identify patterns, outliners, and relationships between variables
before making assumptions.
It is not like you just create a dashboard out of the initial data analysis and you can predict the future.
No, it's not like that.
You might have to last, you might have to go through some permutations and combinations, you might have to check the seasons, you might have to check the possibilities,
right?
During some particular seasons in the year, let's say it's Christmas, then you can expect some good sales.
Let's say it's some festival, it's some special occasion, you can expect some good sales on the product, right?
And maybe a part of the year, maybe a part of 10 years, a decade, right? In a certain period of time, there might be some reason due to which the sales of a certain product were high.
So to make sure that your assumptions, to make sure that your projection of the sales is 100% accurate or at least 90 to 95%
accurate, then you might have to go through the exploratory data analysis where you make use of statistics in your data analysis.
Now, there are certain steps that you might have to follow while going through exploratory data analysis.
So, following are the steps.
So a first few steps might be slightly relevant to initial data analysis, like connecting data, cleaning it, transforming it, and loading it.
After that, you will import certain libraries from Python.
And after that, you read the data. What exactly you have in your data, the number of columns, the number of rows, and if there are any null values, if there are any entries which are invalid,
you might have to check that, read that, and you might have to check for duplicate entries.
It is possible that one entry might have been entered by two different people, right?
There might be a duplication, so you might have to.
Eliminate those duplications. You might have to check for some missing values.
You might have to calculate the total number of missing values from the dataset and try to eliminate them from the calculation during your exploratory data analysis.
Followed by that, you have to do some model engineering.
Followed by that, you might have to do some feature engineering, creating features, and then you will get started with exploratory data analysis.
and at the end, you will generate a projection or a prediction or give you an assumption that this might happen in the future.
and you might have to take action to avoid it, or you might have to take action to improvise it.
Right?
So, this is how the steps in exploratory data analysis take part.
Now let's proceed and start with our demo on Python's exploratory data analysis, and in this session, we will be using the use case that we discussed before,
which happens to be the student's performance dataset.
So in this particular dataset, we will be having some columns based on physical activity.
the distance from home, parental education, the subjects, the marks they have scored in the previous exam, the marks that they have scored in the previous exam.
and if they have any disabilities, if they are having any resources that they require to write the exams, right?
So a few parameters, the important parameters that we will be discussing in this session.
And followed by that, we will project the future that how they will you know improve in their exams, and if there is a
problem and if there is a solution to it, then we can implement that solution and help students to gain better marks in their exam.
So that's the overall use case for this demonstration. Now let's get started with a Jupyter notebook.
Now we are on a Jupyter notebook.
Now let's get started. So I would like to have a title for my notebook.
So I'll write an HTML code for that.
So HTML code,
and I have
three apostrophes,
and here I would like to write something in H1, so I want my title to be in H1.
So
style will be
background color.
color name will be dark blue.
So we'll let's proceed with the simply dance background which will be dark blue usually.
And I also want to have the font, let's let me give the font size as 30.
And in the next line I'd like to have border
radius, I can get the border radius as 20 pixels
and padding to be 16 pixels.
Text Alignment I'd like to keep it center.
There you go.
Let's code the let's close the h1
now. Let's code the background color or border color.
So
B style.
So what we can do is we can basically have this code here, and what we will do is we will reuse this particular code segment
because we will be having multiple HTML codes in this particular workbook, which will explain the results of the
analysis that we are doing.
So the way we just run the code, and after that, we will be getting some visualizations, and I will be writing some textual content in XT in
HTML page so that it will be easier for the people to understand what exactly is happening here, right?
So the color will be light blue, and now comes the text.
We will close this, and here we will write the text as
"Python,
Exploratory
Data Analysis
,". and we will
break here.
the student performance.
And here we will close the
H1.
And lastly, we will display this in HTML code. So basically, we missed this library.
So we will be importing from iPython display import HTML to display this particular code.
So without this particular library, we cannot display any HTML codes in our notebook.
So we will quickly run that and we have a title over here.
Now let's proceed with the next part.
Now we will use some libraries like catboost and light bgm.
So for that we might have to install these libraries.
So we will be using pip install here.
Pip, install, cat boost
and control, enter to run this particular code segment. or you can also use run, and it's installed.
and after that, we will also install
light. bgm,
sorry, not bgm.
So it's already installed.
Now we will start importing the libraries that we need.
So we will be needing NumPy, Panda, Cbon, MapLotlib, and we will also import another special library which is for ignoring warnings.
So we will import warnings and after that from we will be importing that warnings from iPython display import clear output.
And after that, we will tell the Jupyter Notebook to import if there are any warnings. So that code will be warning dot filter warnings, and in the brackets we will write ignore.
So the basic libraries which we will be needing are as follows import
numpy
as np.
Let's quickly copy this and proceed.
Enter.
And now we will be needing pandas as pd.
And now we will be needing c born
as sns,
and we will also use
matplotlib.pyplot
as plt.
And after that, we will import warnings
from ipython
display,
import
clear
output
dot filter warnings,
ignore.
Now we'll just quickly run this query.
Run.
And now we will proceed with feature engineering.
So you can use a hashtag to ignore that particular line from execution for Jupyter Notebook.
And here, we will be importing import RE
from
sklearn .dot .impute, import
simple impute
from sklearn .dot .model.
_selection,
import
k _fold.
There you go.
Now let's quickly run this query.
Now we will proceed with modeling and model evaluation.
Once we are done with this, then we will directly import the data into our notebook.
So for modeling the data, we will again use a hash code so that this particular line will not execute
and import some libraries: L, I, G, T, GBM.
As LGB from Lite GBM library.
Import
LGBM regressor
from cat boost import
cat boost regressor.
There you go. Let's quickly run this command.
There you go.
Now lastly, we have one more task before importing the data that is model evaluation. Once that is done, we can proceed with importing the data.
There you go, let's quickly run it.
And now so far, so good. We have done the basic library imports and feature engineering is done, modeling is done, and model evaluation is also done.
Now we can begin with importing the data.
So we let's also add
the HTML code where we have done this importing.
So here I will try to add another segment and I will import the HTML code here, which displays a similar HTML format which explains what exactly is happening here.
Just a moment.
I have the code ready. I'll just paste it here.
There you go. Let's quickly run this so that we have a HTML code here, page here, which explains what exactly is happening here.
So we are importing libraries and also student data.
Now let's import the student data.
So that let's write the query.
So we are importing the data as data frame, and after that, we will write pandas readcsv.
Right.
And here we will add the location of the file, right?
So the file is located in my downloads section.
So let's quickly copy that location and paste it here.
So this is the location of my file. Let's quickly run it.
So there might be some error.
It's okay, we can resolve it.
So in such scenarios, you don't have to worry. Either you can add an R, but even if that doesn't work, you might have to change.
in this case it worked, but in case if it doesn't work, what you can do is you can eliminate the R and you can just change this from
forward slash to backslash.
This will also help. So this could be worth it.
So this can also work. So these are the situations where you can use this now. Let's proceed with some more interesting facts. Let's try to understand what's going on with our uh dataset, right?
So what you can do is now the data is stored in df variable as a data frame.
So what you can do is read this particular data df.shape so that you can understand what's the uh what's happening with this data,
right? So it can tell you that there are uh 600 and sorry, 6607 rows and 20 columns.
Now let's add another query part, and here you can try to see the head right what head means basically head means uh the column headers.
So what you can do is just write df dot head
and run.
Now you have the column headers and couple of sample columns.
sorry, couple of sample rows.
Now let's proceed with checking the duplicates and identifying the total number of duplicate entries in this particular dataset.
So you can write down df.duplicated
sum
and you will get the number of duplicates present in this particular file.
So we have zero duplicate entries.
Now let's see if there are any null elements in this particular data frame.
So df..isNull
sum.
So these are all functions control enter.
There you go.
So in the column teacher quality, there are 78 null entries, and in parental educational level, there are 90 null entries,
and distance from home there are 67 null entries.
Now, what we can do is uh from the okay, so from DF shape, we can add a new cell here and we can write a HTML code so that the viewer
can understand that we are trying to understand our data.
So let's write a quick code for that.
So let's not waste much time in just writing the HTML code. So I've got that HTML code written in a notepad already.
So I'll just paste it over here and let's quickly run it so that we have a HTML visibility here.
So this was supposed to be the result, so we will add it here.
So, what we will do is quickly edit this particular content. We'll just quickly copy this code and paste it over here.
Change the
content from importing libraries to
reading
student data, and we will cut this code from here, and we will paste it in here,
so that it gives you —give us. some information.
Let's also run this particular code segment so that we have reading student data. There you go.
Now the next part of this session will be about creating a target variable.
So overall target of this particular data analysis is about exam score, right?
So we can name our target variable as exam score and let's understand the distribution of this particular exam score with
the variables we have.
Now let's write down plot dot figure.
Figure size should be around 15 comma nine
equals to let's add a bracket here 15 comma 9
or let's keep it as 6, 9 would be a little bigger.
Now enter.
Now we will use seaborn library here sns.count plot
x is equals to data frame clean the target.
Okay, uh before clean the target, we might have to run a few more.
Okay, we did not perform data cleaning so far, right?
So let's proceed with data cleaning so far. So we found some empty entries, right? Null entries, and we also found some. So here we have 299 rows which have missing value.
So we will have to remove that.
For that, we might have to create a new column which has to be named as not
assigned, right? df data frame not assigned, which is equals to df dot drop na.
So we will be dropping the null values here, it's a function, and here let's print the values print df
dot df underscore hype underscore n a dot shape.
So how many number of rows and columns we have, right?
And after that, let's also try to eliminate the null values as well.
is null, so we don't have basically we don't have null values, but we have some illegal entries maybe.
Some there you go. Now let's quickly run this query.
So there you go. So the new data is about 678, 20.
So there is some okay. We did some mistake here.
So we are supposed to add it as null n unl nul.
Now quickly run this so we should not get any errors this time.
There you go, no errors so far so good.
Now let's describe the new dataset dfna
describe.
So these are the new columns and rows that we have, and we have mean standard variation, standard deviation,
minimum, maximum.
So the scores are split into 25%, 50%, and 75%, which could be based on hours studied, which could be based on attendance,
sleep hours, previous course, tutoring sessions, everything.
So uh minimum sleep hours, maximum sleep hours, 25% of that, 50% of that, 75% of that.
So that is supposed to be the uh described.
Now, what we will do is we have a target variable which is exam score, right?
Now we will do some changes to it.
We already know in an exam there will be a threshold value.
It can be 25 marks per exam, it can be 50 marks per exam, and it can be 100 marks per exam.
In our situation, let's consider the threshold value is 100 marks.
If there is a situation where marks is entered in a wrong way,
if they wanted to add 11, but by mistake, if they added another one, right? Triple one, it's not a right entry, right?
So we will try to eliminate those kind of data.
So we will create a new data frame here, which is data frame cleaned is equals to data frame underscore
not null. So we have eliminated the null values df underscore na.
Now we will add our target variable which is exam score,
should be so let's come out of this, and here we will add it as should be less than or equal to 100,
but not more than 100.
Let's use square brackets
here. We also the format is square brackets actually.
Now enter and
we will describe this particular
data set.
Instead of TFNA we will copy paste this here.
Now let's run this.
Okay, exam score is not identified.
Let's quickly check the error and resolve it.
Yeah, so we missed out to add colons here.
It's okay, not a problem.
So this was supposed to be how it is. Now let's run this and we will have the answer over here. So we have the output.
Now let's check the head of this particular cleaner dataset. So we can make use of the same code here and paste it right here, and instead of describe, let's write head so that we have the header of
this particular dataset. So we have our study and everything normal, and we will categorize the data, right?
So we will make use of three columns: our study, attendance, and previous course.
And after that, we will also make use of other columns in this particular dataset, which happens to be the parental involvement, access to resources,
sleep hours, tutoring sessions, etc.
And now, our target will be the exam score that we created over here.
This exam score will be our target, and using this particular exam score target, we will categorize the data.
We will categorize the data in terms of, uh, let's say, first class, second class, and
pass or something like that.
So, if a student is scoring below 64, and that is a separate category;
if the score student is scoring equals to or above 65, that is a different category;
and if the student is scoring beyond 70, that's a different category.
And before we proceed with that, let's try to add a HTML code before this particular data set so that we have
an understanding of what exactly happened here.
So I'll let's uh let's I'll just quickly copy paste this particular code here.
So we will run it, and now next we will describe check the data type column separate and everything, and we will create data type category variables.
Right and now so far so good.
Now we will create the categories.
So num call
equals to
hours study
comma
attendance.
So let's quickly add the data,
previous exam scores.
Just a minute, let's quickly add the columns. Let me take a while.
There you go, I have added the columns. So we are considering three different columns our study attendance and previous course for num call and for cat call.
We are considering the other columns apart from the first three, and our target value is
exam score. Let's quickly run this. There you go, and now we will try to build some visualizations, and before that, let's try to add
some data from in HTML.
Let's try to create a okay. What we can do is simply copy this particular HTML file here.
We can take this
and add it here so that we will understand what exactly is happening next.
And in place of reading student data, we will write data visualization for student data.
And we will keep the colors same dark blue background, and the color for data visualization will be light blue and student data will be orange.
Let's quickly run and there we have it.
Now our target variable is exam score, Now we will compare this particular target variable with three other parameters.
So our parameters will be the following as we discussed creating the segregation in dataset, right?
So, first will be distribution of target variable with other parameters.
So we will create another HTML file for that right here.
Just a minute while I paste the code for HTML.
Quickly run this.
There you go.
So distribution of target variable exam score against some parameters.
Now we will write the plot for that
plot.figure.
So we are going to consider the size equals to 15 comma six
big size.
Is equals to 15 comma 6, the same one that we considered before, and we will be using c1 sns dot
countplot
open bracket.
This is a function x is equals to df
clean. Okay, uh what we can do is just quickly take the column name so that we don't create any mistakes here, and we will paste it over
here
and strip tf.
There you go, of target.
So our target is exam score.
comma and we will use the palette as green,
and the plot title will be distribution of target variable exam score.
We can copy this, okay. Just a minute before that PLD dot title
should be let's use double quotes now. Copy this
and paste it here.
I think semicolons went off. Okay, not a problem.
It's right here.
Let's add a dot as a full stop and the next line.
If you need, you can add the full stop. If not, you can eat, not
plt grid true,
which
equals to major
comma
axis is equals to y
comma line style equals to.
so I want lines to be hyphen -hyphen in this way. I want the lines
and comma line width uh let's say 0.5 or 0.7. Let's go with 0.7
line width
equals to 0.9 mm.
There you go. Now let's quickly run this query.
There you go, done.
And we have the first visualization.
So here you can see, there are some students which are scoring 58, 59, and you can see maximum number of students are already scoring good marks,
which is under 65, and uh sorry, which is under 70 and above 65.
and there is a good number of students which are also scoring above 65 as well. right?
So sorry, 70 70 as well. So we have it now less than or equal to 70, 71, and highest scorer in some situations there is also 100.
If we can see there is slight growth here, there are a few students, stoppers maybe, which have already scored 100 as well.
Now we have the list here.
Now what we need to do is we need to segregate that is part one, which is less than or equal to 64, which falls under 65, and another category which falls in between 65 to 70
and above 70. So we need to categorize these three datas and segregate them as bottom 65, top, which is above 70, and mid between 70 to 65.
Right now, before that, if you want to add an HTML document sorry, segment here which explains about the distribution of target,
you can also do that.
It's already added here now.
Let's continue.
But in case if you want to add some data which explains that we are trying to segregate, you can also do that.
I would like to do that.
Let's quickly add that HTML code here.
So, what this particular code will do is it will tell the percentage of students which are scoring less than 65, number of students to uh percentage of students
scoring in between 65 and 70, and the percent of students which are scoring beyond 70.
Right, let's run this, and here we have the result bottom 21.81% scores under 64, while 24% scores over 70 and 50 percent are in between 65 to 69.
Right now, let's continue with the segregation part of the data.
So for segregation, we will create three different variables a, b, c.
So, first a is equals to length of df cleaned. So let's copy the
column name, sorry, data frame name, length of
df cleaned inside the square brackets. We'll again add df cleaned of target variable which is exam score.
Let's also add single quotes here.
Who are scoring in between or less than? Let's start with less than or equal to 64.
We will not consider 65, we'll consider 64 divided by len of df cleaned target variable
exam score single quotes into 100.
Which will give us the percentage.
Now similarly, let's just copy and paste this three more times for B and C.
So here instead of minus, we're supposed to add equals to,
and another one.
So here equals to, and instead of A, I will write B and the last one is C.
And instead of 64, we will add 70 here for top, and here we will make some changes.
It should be greater than or equal to
65. So this is the third category a, b, c, and
then we will proceed with printing the files.
So print
the bottom
for the first one, which is f of
a,
is to dot 2f.
and we will add the percentage symbol over here are under
64.
Now we can copy paste the same here and we can change the variables.
So here we will be adding the under over 70,
lastly in between the ones in between
65 and 70.
There you go.
Here we will change the values from A to B and here A to C.
There you go, and we can quickly run this query.
So it's not 70, it was supposed to be 69.
There you go.
So we forgot to mention this particular one.
Now let's run this.
There you go. So we have 21%
of people who are scoring under 64, 24% over 70, and 53% are in between average.
So I think the school is focusing on improving this particular percentage, reducing this particular percentage, and increasing this particular percentage,
and try to eliminate if possible this particular one which are under 64.
So that is the overall motto, I guess.
Now, so far so good.
Let's now try to remove infinite values from HTML.
Right? So before that, let's add this particular HTML code here, so which explains what we are trying to do.
So we will first implement the code that prevents warning about infinite values during data visualization.
And now let's add the code which will try to eliminate the infinite values. Let's copy this particular data frame cleaned
data frame name here.
Now dfcleaned dot replace
square brackets
np dot
info
comma
minus np
dot info out of these square brackets. dot np dot na
non n values, we are trying to eliminate n a values.
In place of those values, you can write true.
And after that, we will try to eliminate the null.
So if it is null
dot sum, give me the total number of null values after this, right?
So let's try to execute that.
There you go.
So all the null entries have been removed here.
Now let's see the distribution of numerical values here.
So before that, let's add the HTML code for that.
So let's quickly run this.
So distribution of numerical values.
So we will be considering these three parameters.
So if you go back
here, you can see our studied attendance and previous course.
So we will be considering these three values or these three columns and check the distribution of these variables against
the exam score.
So is it making any um you know kind of variation if the attendance is high?
if the attendance is high, is the exam score high?
And apart from that, we have if our studies is high, is the mark score is high, and if the previous scores are high,
is there a chance to get better scores in this particular exam?
So, what we are trying to do is we are trying to see if there is any direct involvement of number of study hours and number of days attended and number of
or the number of marks they received in the previous course, and we'll try to build a visualization on that front.
So let's go and build that.
So we'll try the try to write the code here
figure axis
equals to plt
dot
subplots. So we will be having three different plots here since we are considering three different categories,
and the fixed size should be
equal to 12, 4.
There you go.
Now,
is equals to access _dot _variable
for idx,
comma call
in enumerate,
and we will try to import the c _bound library. here.
We will try to create histoplots here, histograms here,
histoplot.
So line style we will be selecting this one
and comma.
Line width will be 0.7.
There you go.
Next will be access
IDX.
dot set
title So for this we will be setting the title as distribution of columns.
So the columns will be the three uh ones attendance hours studied, and what was the third one that we considered
previous course, right?
So instead of mentioning them specifically, what we can do is we can just write columns here, C O L and close.
There you go.
And lastly,
PLT.ite
and show the plot.
There you go. Let's quickly run this query.
Run and now we will be having the visualizations here.
So you can directly see the involvement of these three parameters here.
If they are trying to help, if the number of hours are increased, then you can see if there is a better improvement in scores, if the attendance is increased, if there is a better
moment in scores, or if the previous scores are helping, then you can find it out how it is.
There you go.
Now we can write a result here in the form of HTML page, and if we run this, it will give you the result.
The breaks or gaps in the our study variable may be due to the respondents answering appropriately.
The variables attendance and previous scores which exhibit a uniform distribution have a normal impact on exam scores variable, which is a target variable.
Now let's proceed with another part of this session, which will be about the relationship between the numerical values and the target variables.
Now we will copy-paste the same code and make some minute changes to it.
So the only change that we did to it is we are trying to build a scatter plot.
So we will be getting a scatter plot here, but before that, let's try to add another column here and try to add an HTML code which explains why we are doing it.
There you go.
A scatter plot. So basically, these two are one and the same.
Here we use some column graphs. So here we did the same using the scatter plot, which will help for a better understanding.
Now we will try to build some correlations.
So basically, a list is called correlation is created containing the names of the columns for which you want to calculate the correlation.
So here in our situation it is the df.corr which is a data frame, and it is created by selecting only these columns for DFclean
data frame, effectively created a new data frame containing only the specified columns.
Now the second one, which is the C ORR, which is a calculate correlation.
So this method computes the correlation matrix for selected columns, which is in DFCORR.
The 1 indicates perfect positive correlation, minus 1 indicates the perfect negative correlation, and 0 indicates no correlation.
And lastly, the setup of plot.
This line sets up the figure size of the plot.
In this particular situation, we are choosing 5 and 4.
Right now, let's quickly try to execute this query and see the answer.
And we will also add the HTML code for this so that we have a better understanding for this.
So we will be adding that HTML
box here, which will explain what exactly happened here.
So this is our plot and this is the correlation.
Now let's try to add that HTML code right here.
The result of this particular data visualization will be maintained here.
So the hour study and attendance shows a positive correlation with the target variable, which is exam sour.
However, previous course appears to have no or little relationship with the target variable.
Right now, let's continue with our next part of this session.
So now we will try to identify the relationship between studies,
hours, and attendance and extracurricular scores.
So we have other
columns to consider, which is extracurricular activities.
So there is a belief that extracurricular activities will also help students to study better.
So we will find if there is a relation between the target variable and these extracurricular activities, attendance and study hours.
Now let's quickly add the code here.
Now let's quickly execute the code.
Now we have the visualization which explains the relationship between the number of hours studied, extracurricular activities, etc.
So here it is.
And now let's add an HTML code which explains about this result.
In this particular code was supposed to be added here.
So this is the resultant column here.
Now here it explains about the influences that it performs.
So the extra collectible activities, parental income, and extra things that influence the scores.
And there you go.
Now let us also consider other columns, right?
The other parameters like resources are available or not, parental education and other things which also might have influenced the exam scores of students.
So for that, let's add an HTML code so that we have an HTML page here which explains what is the next procedure that we are following, right?
Now let's add the query here.
So here we are considering the other parameters like family income, peer influence, motivation level, gender, parental involvement, parental educational level, and extracurricular activities.
And we are considering them against the target variable which is exam score.
And now let's execute this query.
There you go. Now we have generated a graph which explains about this particular parameters against the target variable.
And now let's add the HTML page here which explains about these results.
Let's quickly run it.
And there you go.
So when certain factors affect Q1 and Q2, but not Q2, it can be understood that individual has overcome challenges through personal effort, right?
So if government policies and corporate social contributors are focused on addressing these aspects, it seems that we could create a dynamic country
with greater social mobility and open opportunities for all, right?
So if extracurricular activities can outweigh the influence of other variables in academic performance, then we should foster that kind of an environment, right?
So this is how you can get extract some statistical analysis on this particular dataset.
Now let's quickly rename this
Python
EDA
students
performance.
And you can quickly rename them and save it.
Hello everyone.
In this session, we will cover all the important supervised and unsupervised learning algorithms that are widely used with hands-on demonstrations in Python.
Our instructors with rich experience in machine learning will take us through this course.
But before we begin, make sure to subscribe to the Simply Learn channel and hit the bell icon to never miss an update.
So we will start by understanding the basics of machine learning from a short animated video, followed by the difference between supervised and unsupervised learning.
We will then jump into learning the various algorithms from scratch.
So we will understand linear regression, logistic regression, decision tree, and random forest.
We'll then look at support vector machines and k-nearest neighbor algorithm with a hands-on demonstration in Python.
Finally, we'll get an idea about unsupervised learning algorithms such as k-means clustering and principal component analysis.
We will conclude this session with regularization in machine learning.
So let's get started.
We know humans learn from their past experiences and machines follow instructions given by humans.
But what if humans can train the machines to learn from their past data and do what humans can do and much faster? Well, that's called machine learning.
But it's a lot more than just learning, it's also about understanding and reasoning. So today we will learn about the basics of machine learning. So that's Paul. He loves listening to new songs.
He either likes them or dislikes them. Paul decides this on the basis of the song's tempo, genre, intensity, and the gender of voice. For simplicity, let's just use tempo and intensity for now.
So here, tempo is on the x-axis ranging from relaxed to fast, whereas intensity is on the y axis ranging from light to soaring.
We see that Paul likes the song with fast tempo and soaring intensity, while he dislikes the song with relaxed tempo
and light intensity. So now we know Paul's choices. Let's say Paul listens to a new song. Let's name it as song A. Song A has fast tempo and a soaring intensity. So it lies somewhere here.
Looking at the data, can you guess whether Paul will like the song or not? Correct. So Paul likes this song.
By looking at Paul's past choices, we were able to classify the unknown song very easily, right? Let's say now Paul listens to a new song. Let's label it as song B.
So song B lies somewhere here with medium tempo and medium intensity. Neither relaxed nor fast, neither light nor soaring. Now can you guess whether Paul likes it or not?
Not able to guess whether Paul will like it or dislike it? Are the choices unclear? Correct. We could easily classify song A.
But when the choice became complicated, as in the case of song B, yes, and that's where machine learning comes in. Let's see how.
In the same example for song B, if we draw a circle around the song B, we see that there are four votes for like, whereas one vote for dislike.
If we go for the majority votes, we can say that Paul will definitely like the song. That's all. This was a basic machine learning algorithm also. It's called K nearest neighbours.
So this is just a small example in one of the many machine learning algorithms. Quite easy, right? Believe me, it is. But what happens when the choices become complicated? As in the case of song B.
That's when machine learning comes in. It learns the data, builds the prediction model, and when the new data point comes in, it can easily predict for it.
More the data, better the model, higher will be the accuracy. There are many ways in which the machine learns. It could be either supervised learning, unsupervised learning, or reinforcement learning.
Let's first quickly understand supervised learning. Suppose your friend gives you 1 million coins of three different currencies, say 1 rupee, 1 euro, and 1 dirham. Each coin has different weights.
For example, a coin of 1 rupee weighs 3 grams, 1 euro weighs 7 grams, and 1 dirham weighs 4 grams. Your model will predict the currency of the coin.
Here, your weight becomes the feature of coins, while currency becomes their label. When you feed this data to the machine learning model, it learns which feature is associated with which label.
For example, it will learn that if a coin is of 3 grams, it will be a 1 rupee coin. Let's give a new coin to the machine.
On the basis of the weight of the new coin, your model will predict the currency. Hence, supervised learning uses labeled data to train the model.
Here the machine knew the features of the object and also the labels associated with those features. On this note, let's move to unsupervised learning and see the difference.
Suppose you have cricket dataset of various players with their respective scores and the wickets taken.
When we feed this data set to the machine, the machine identifies the pattern of player performance. So it plots this data with the respective wickets on the x-axis while runs on the y-axis.
While looking at the data, you will clearly see that there are two clusters.
The one cluster are the players who scored high runs and took less wickets, while the other cluster is of the players who scored less runs but took many wickets.
So here we interpret these two clusters as batsmen and bowlers. The important point to note here is that there were no labels of batsmen and bowlers.
Hence, the learning with unlabeled data is unsupervised learning. So we saw supervised learning where the data was labeled and the unsupervised learning where the data was unlabeled.
And then there is reinforcement learning, which is reward-based learning. Or we can say that it works on the principle of feedback.
Here, let's say you provide the system with an image of a dog and ask it to identify it. The system identifies it as a cat.
So you give a negative feedback to the machine saying that it's a dog's image.
The machine will learn from the feedback and finally, if it comes across any other image of a dog, it will be able to classify it correctly. That is reinforcement learning.
To generalize machine learning model, let's see a flowchart. Input is given to a machine learning model, which then gives the output according to the algorithm applied.
If it's right, we take the output as a final result. Else, we provide feedback to the training model and ask it to predict until it learns.
I hope you've understood supervised and unsupervised learning. So let's have a quick quiz. You have to determine whether the given scenarios uses supervised or unsupervised learning. Simple, right?
Scenario 1. Facebook recognizes your friend in a picture from an album of tagged photographs. Scenario 2. Netflix recommends new movies based on someone's past movie choices. Scenario 3.
Analyzing bank data for suspicious transactions and flagging the fraud transactions. Think wisely and comment below your answers.
Moving on, don't you sometimes wonder how is machine learning possible in today's era? Well, that's because today we have humongous data available.
Everybody is online, either making a transaction or just surfing the internet. And that's generating a huge amount of data every minute. And that data, my friend, is the key to analysis.
Also, the memory handling capabilities of computers have largely increased, which helps them to process such a huge amount of data at hand without any delay.
And yes, computers now have great computational powers. So there are a lot of applications of machine learning out there.
To name a few, machine learning is used in healthcare where diagnostics are predicted for doctor's review.
The sentiment analysis that the tech giants are doing on social media is another interesting application of machine learning,
fraud detection in the finance sector, and also to predict customer churn in the e-commerce sector.
While booking a gap, you must have encountered search pricing often where it says the fare of your trip has been updated. Continue booking. Yes please, I'm getting late for office.
Well, that's an interesting machine learning model which is used by global taxi giant Uber and others, where they have differential pricing in real time based on demand,
the number of cars available, bad weather, rush hour, etc. So they use the search pricing model to ensure that those who need a cab can get one.
Also, it uses predictive modeling to predict where the demand will be high, with the goal that drivers can take care of the demand and search pricing can be minimized. Great.
Hey Siri, can you remind me to book a cab at 6 pm today? Okay, I'll remind you. Thanks. No problem.
Comment below some interesting everyday examples around you, where machines are learning and doing amazing jobs.
Hi guys, this is a picture from Simply Learn, and we are going to talk about the two types of machine learning, supervised and unsupervised learning.
Their types and applications.
But before we talk about them, let's quickly understand what is machine learning.
These days applications use artificial intelligence in machine learning to optimize speech recognition.
I usually ask Siri things I want to know, like hey Siri, how far is the nearest subway?
So whenever we ask something to Siri, a powerful speech recognition kicks off and converts the audio into its corresponding textual form,
which is then sent to the Apple servers for further processing.
Then neural language processing algorithms are run to understand the user's intent.
And then finally, Siri tells you the answer.
Well, this is what machine learning is all about.
Making the machines learn and act like humans by feeding them with data and information without being explicitly programmed.
As we saw in the previous example, when the data comes in, machines immediately starts analyzing the data and eventually gets trained on it and learns it.
Now, when a new data point comes in, machine accurately makes predictions and decisions based on the past data.
Now that you know what is machine learning, let's talk about supervised and unsupervised learning.
Supervised learning, as the name suggests, works under supervision, that is, it's a learning in which machine is trained with data which is well labeled, and then
predicts with the help of the labeled dataset.
But what is a labeled dataset?
Data for which you already know the target answer is called a labeled data.
Like I show you an image and tell you that it's a dog, then it's a label data.
While if I show you an image without telling you what exactly it is, then it's an unlabeled data.
Now let's say we have images which are labeled as spoon or knife.
We then feed it to the machine, which analyzes and learns the association of these images with its labels based on its features such as shape,
size, sharpness, etc.
Now, when a new image is fed to the machine without any label.
with the help of the past data, the machine is able to predict accurately and tell that it's a spoon.
Hence in supervised machine learning, the algorithm teaches the model to learn from the labeled example that we provide.
So supervised learning can be further divided into classification and regression.
It is a classification problem when the output variable is categoric, such as red or blue, disease or no disease, male or female.
Whereas it's a regression problem when the output variable is a real or continuous value.
For example, salary based on work experience, weight based on height. So it creates a predictive model showing trends and data.
So now if I say will I get a salary raise or not, that's classification.
But if I say how much salary raise will I get, that is regression.
Now let's understand classification with the help of an example.
In order to predict whether an email is a spam or not, first we need to teach our machine what a spam mail looks like.
This is done based on a lot of spam filters, like firstly reviewing the content of the email, then review the email header and search if it contains any falsified information.
This is done based on some keywords like free, lottery, price claim, etc.
Then, general blacklist filters to stop emails that come from already blacklisted, known spammers and etc.
So. all these filters scores the email, which is known as spam score.
The lower the total spam score of the email, it is more likely that the email will land in subscribers inboxes.
So based on the content, labels and spam score of the new incoming mail, the algorithm decides whether it should land in
inbox or the spam folder.
Now let's quickly understand regression.
So let's say we have two variables, that is temperature and humidity, where temperature is the independent variable and humidity is the dependent variable,
such that as the temperature increases, humidity decreases.
Hence, they are correlated.
When we feed this data to a regression model, it will understand the relationship between these two variables and how one variable depends on the other.
After the machine is trained, it can easily predict the humidity based on the given temperature.
Well, that was about regression.
Now let's see some real life applications where supervised learning is used.
So supervised learning is used in risk assessment to assess risk in financial services or in insurance domain to minimize the risk portfolio of the companies.
Image classification.
Facebook recognizes your friend in a picture from an album of TAG photos.
So image classification is one of the key use cases of demonstrating supervised machine learning algorithms.
Obviously, a lot more goes into all these, like convolutional neural networks, etc.
Fraud detection, whether the transactions made by the user are authentic or not.
And visual recognition, the ability of a machine learning model to identify objects, places, people, and actions in images.
Now let's quickly talk about unsupervised learning.
In unsupervised learning, there is no supervision.
That is, no training will be given to the machine allowing it to act on the data which is not labeled.
Hence, machine tries to identify patterns and gives the response.
Let's take a similar example as before.
But this time we do not tell the machine whether it's a spoon or a knife.
The machine identifies patterns from the given set and groups them based on their patterns, similarities, etc.
Again, unsupervised learning can be further grouped into clustering and association.
Clustering is basically where the machine forms groups based on the behavior of the data.
Secondly, association.
It is a rule-based machine learning to discover interesting relation between variables in large datasets.
For example, which customer made similar product purchases is clustering, whereas association is which products were purchased together.
Now, let's understand clustering with the help of an example.
To reduce their churn rate, a telecom company studies the behavior of the customers based on average call duration and internet usage and observes that while some customers'
call duration is quite high, others have heavy internet usage.
The customers are grouped based on their observed behavior and a strategy is adopted to minimize churn rate and maximize profit via suitable promotions and campaigns.
As you can see in the chart on the right hand side, customers in group A use more data and also have high call duration.
Group B customers are heavy internet users, while group C customers have high call duration.
So Group B will be given more data benefit plans, while group C will be given cheaper call rates to buy their loyalty.
So this was the example of clustering.
Now let's understand association with another example.
Let's say customer 1 goes to a supermarket and buys these products, say bread, milk, fruits, wheat.
Then customer 2 goes and buys bread, milk, rice and butter.
Now, when customer 3 goes and buys bread, it is highly likely that he will also buy milk.
Hence, relationship is established based on customer behavior and recommendations are made.
Now let's look at some real life applications of unsupervised learning.
Market basket analysis is a machine learning model based on the algorithm that if you buy a certain group of items, you are less or more likely to buy another group of items.
Semantic clustering.
Semantically similar words share similar context.
People post their queries on websites in their own ways.
Semantic clustering groups all responses in a cluster with same meaning to ensure that the customer finds the information they want quickly and easily.
It plays an important role in information retrieval, good browsing experience and comprehension.
Delivery store optimization.
Machine learning models are used to predict the demand and keep up with the supply.
Also, to open stores where demand is more and optimizing routes for more efficient deliveries according to past data and behavior.
We can also use unsupervised machine learning models to identify accident prone areas based on the intensity of those accidents and the area in order to introduce safety measures.
By now I hope you've understood supervised and unsupervised learning.
For a quick recap, let's see a few differences between the two.
The most fundamental difference is that supervised learning uses known and labeled data and unsupervised learning uses unlabeled data as their input.
Secondly, supervised learning follows a feedback mechanism, while unsupervised learning does not.
Also, the most commonly used algorithms in supervised learning are decision tree, logistic regression, support vector machine, etc.
And in unsupervised learning, there are k-means clustering, hierarchical clustering, a priori algorithm, and many more. Welcome to linear regression.
My name is Richard Kirschner. I'm with Simply Learn.
Let's look at an example of a common use for linear regression.
Profit estimation of a company.
If I was going to invest in a company, I would like to know how much money I could expect to make.
So we'll take a look at a venture capitalist firm and try to understand which companies they should invest in.
So we'll take the idea that we need to decide the companies to invest in.
We need to predict the profit the company makes, and we're going to do it based on the company's expenses, and even just a specific expense.
In this case, we have our company, we have the different expenses, so we have our RD, which is your research and development, we have our marketing,
we might have the location, we might have what kind of administration it's going through. Based on all this different information, we would like to calculate the profit.
Now in actuality, there's usually about 23 to 27 different markers that they look at if they're a heavy-duty investor.
We're only going to take a look at one basic one.
We're going to come in and for simplicity, let's consider a single variable RD and find out which companies to invest in based on that.
So we take our R&D, we're plotting the profit based on the RD expenditure, how much money they put into the research and development, and then we look at the profit that goes with that.
We can predict a line to estimate the profit. So we draw a line right through the data.
when you look at that, you can see how much they invest in the R&D is a good marker as to how much profit they're going to have. We can also note that companies spending more on RD make good profit.
So let's invest in the ones that spend a higher rate in their RD. What's in it for you?
First, we'll have an introduction to machine learning, followed by machine learning algorithms. These will be specific to linear regression and where it fits into the larger model.
Then we'll take a look at applications of linear regression, understanding linear regression, and multiple linear regression.
Finally, we'll roll up our sleeves and do a little programming in use case profit estimation of companies.
Let's go ahead and jump in.
Let's start with our introduction to machine learning, along with some machine learning algorithms and where that fits in with linear regression.
Let's look at another example of machine learning.
Based on the amount of rainfall, how much would be the crop yield? So here we have our crops, we have our rainfall, and we want to know how much we're going to get from our crops this year.
So we're going to introduce two variables, independent and dependent.
The independent variable is a variable whose value does not change by the effect of other variables and is used to manipulate the dependent variable.
It is often denoted as x. In our example, rainfall is the independent variable.
This is a wonderful example because you can easily see that we can't control the rain, but the rain does control the crop.
So we talk about the independent variable controlling a dependent variable, let's define dependent variable as a variable whose value change when there
is any manipulation in the values of the independent variables.
It is often denoted as y. And you can see here our crop yield is dependent variable, and it is dependent on the amount of rainfall received.
Now that we've taken a look at a real life example, let's go a little bit into the theory and some definitions on machine learning and see how that fits together with linear regression.
Numerical and categorical values.
Let's take our data coming in, this is kind of random data from any kind of project.
We want to divide it up into numerical and categorical.
So numerical is numbers, age, salary, height, where categorical would be a description, the color,
a dog's breed, gender.
Categorical is limited to very specific items where numerical is a range of information.
Now that you've seen the difference between numerical and categorical data, let's take a look at some different machine learning definitions.
When we look at our different machine learning algorithms, we can divide them into three areas supervised, unsupervised, reinforcement.
We're only going to look at supervised today.
Unsupervised means we don't have the answers we're just grouping things.
Reinforcement is where we give positive and negative feedback to our algorithm to program it, and it doesn't have the information until after the fact.
But today we're just looking at supervised because that's where linear regression fits in.
In supervised data, we have our data already there and our answers for a group, and then we use that to program our model and come up with an answer.
The two most common uses for that is through the regression and classification.
Now we're doing linear regression, so we're just going to focus on the regression side.
And in the regression, we have simple linear regression, we have multiple linear regression, and we have polynomial linear regression.
Now on these three, simple linear regression is the examples we've looked at so far where we have a lot of data and we draw a straight line through it.
Multiple linear regression means we have multiple variables.
Remember where we had the rainfall and the crops?
We might add additional variables in there like how much food do we give our crops?
When do we harvest them?
Those would be additional information add into our model. And that's why it'd be multiple linear regression.
And finally we have polynomial linear regression. That is, instead of drawing a line, we can draw a curved line through it.
Now that you see where regression model fits into the machine learning algorithms, and we're specifically looking at linear regression,
let's go ahead and take a look at applications for linear regression.
Let's look at a few applications of linear regression.
Economic growth, used to determine the economic growth of a country or a state in the coming quarter, can also be used to predict the GDP of a country.
Product price can be used to predict what would be the price of a product in the future.
We can guess whether it's going to go up or down or should I buy today.
Housing sales to estimate the number of houses a builder would sell and what price in the coming months.
Score predictions. Cricket fever to predict the number of runs a player would score in the coming matches based on the previous performance.
I'm sure you can figure out other applications you could use linear regression for. So let's jump in and let's understand linear regression and dig into the theory.
Understanding linear regression.
Linear regression is the statistical model used to predict the relationship between independent and dependent variables by examining two factors.
The first important one is which variables in particular are significant predictors of the outcome variable.
And the second one that we need to look at closely is how significant is the regression line to make predictions with the highest possible accuracy.
If it's inaccurate, we can't use it.
So it's very important we find out the most accurate line we can get.
Since linear regression is based on drawing a line through data, We're going to jump back and take a look at some Euclidean geometry.
The simplest form of a simple linear regression equation with one dependent and one independent variable is represented by y equals m
times x plus c.
And if you look at our model here, we plotted two points on here, x1 and y1, x2 and y2.
y being the dependent variable, remember that from before, and x being the independent variable.
So y depends on whatever x is.
m in this case is the slope of the line where m equals the difference in the y2 minus y1 and x2
minus x1.
And finally we have c which is the coefficient of the line, or where it happens to cross the zero axes.
Let's go back and look at an example we used earlier of linear regression.
We're going to go back to plotting the amount of crop yield based on the amount of rainfall.
And here we have our rainfall.
Remember we cannot change rainfall, and we have our crop yield, which is dependent on the rainfall.
So we have our independent and our dependent variables.
We're going to take this and draw a line through it as best we can through the middle of the data.
And then we look at that, we put the red point on the y-axis is the amount of crop yield you can expect for the amount of rainfall represented by the green dot.
So if we have an idea what the rainfall is for this year and what's going on, then we can guess how good our crops are going to be.
And we've created a nice line right through the middle to give us a nice mathematical formula.
Let's take a look and see what the math looks like behind this.
Let's look at the intuition behind the regression line.
Now, before we dive into the math and the formulas that go behind this and what's going on behind the scenes,
I want you to note that when we get into the case study and we actually apply some Python script, that this math that you're going to see here is already done automatically for you.
You don't have to have it memorized.
It is, however, good to have an idea what's going on, so if people reference the different terms, you'll know what they're talking about.
Let's consider a sample data set with five rows and find out how to draw the regression line.
We're only going to do five rows because if we did like the rainfall with hundreds of points of data, that would be very hard to see what's going on with the mathematics.
So we'll go ahead and create our own two sets of data.
And we have our independent variable x and our dependent variable y.
And when x was one, we got y equals two.
When x was two, y was four, and so on and so on.
If we go ahead and plot this data on a graph, we can see how it forms a nice line through the middle.
You can see where it's kind of grouped going upwards to the right.
The next thing we want to know is what the means is of each of the data coming in, the x and the y.
The means doesn't mean anything other than the average.
So we add up all the numbers and divide by the total. So one plus two plus three plus four plus five over five equals three.
And the same for y, we get four.
If we go ahead and plot the means on the graph, we'll see we get three, four, which draws a nice line down the middle.
A good estimate.
Here we're gonna dig deeper into the math behind the regression line.
Now remember before I said you don't have to have all these formulas memorized or fully understand them, even though we're gonna go into a little more detail of how it works.
And if you're not a math whiz and you don't know if you've never seen the sigma character before, which looks a little bit like an e that's opened up,
that just means summation.
That's all that is.
So when you see the sigma character, it just means we're adding everything in that row.
And for computers this is great, because as a programmer, you can easily iterate through each of the xy points and create all the information you need.
So in the top half you can see where we've broken that down into pieces, and as it goes through the first two points, it computes the squared value of x, the squared value of y,
and x times y.
And then it takes all of x and adds them up, all of y adds them up, all of x squared adds them up, and so on and so on, and you can see we have the sum of equal to 15,
the sum is equal to 20, all the way up to x times y where the sum equals 66.
This all comes from our formula for calculating a straight line where y equals the slope times x plus the coefficient c.
So we go down below and we're going to compute more like the averages of these, and we're going to explain exactly what that is in just a minute and where that information comes from
is called the square means error.
But we'll go into that in detail in a few minutes. All you need to do is look at the formula and see how we've gone about computing it line by line instead of trying to have a huge.
set of numbers pushed into it.
And down here you'll see where the slope m equals, and in the top part if you read through the brackets, you have the number of data points times the sum
of x times y, which we computed one line at a time there, and that's just the 66.
And take all that and you subtract it from the sum of x times the sum of y.
And those have both been computed. So you have 15 times 20.
And on the bottom we have the number of lines times the sum of x squared, easily computed as 86 for the sum, minus,
I'll take all that and subtract, the sum of x squared.
And we end up, as we come across with our formula, you can plug in all those numbers, which is very easy to do on the computer.
You don't have to do the math on a piece of paper or calculator, and you'll get a slope of 0.6.
And you'll get your c coefficient.
If you continue to follow through that formula, you'll see it comes out as equal to 2.2.
Continuing deeper into what's going behind the scenes, let's find out the predicted values of y for corresponding values of x using the linear equation where m equals 0.6
and c equals 2.2.
We're going to take these values and we're going to go ahead and plot them.
We're going to predict them so y equals 0.6 times where x equals 1 plus 2 two equals 2 eight, so on and so on.
And here the blue points represent the actual y values and the brown points represent the predicted y values based on the model we created.
The distance between the actual and predicted values is known as residuals or errors.
The best fit line should have the least sum of squares of these errors, also known as e square.
If we put these into a nice chart where you can see x and you can see y, where the actual values were you can see y predicted.
you can easily see where we take y minus y predicted and we get an answer. What is the difference between those two?
And if we square that, y minus y prediction squared, we can then sum those squared values.
That's where we get the 0.64 plus the 0.36 plus 1 all the way down until we have a summation equals 2.4.
So the sum of squared errors for this regression line is 2.4.
We check this error for each line and conclude the best fit line having the least e square value.
In a nice graphical representation we can see here where we keep moving this line through the data points to make sure the best fit line has the least squared distance between the data points
and the regression line.
Now we only looked at the most commonly used formula for minimizing the distance.
There are lots of ways to minimize the distance between the line and the data points. like sum of squared errors, sum of absolute errors, root mean square error, etc.
What you want to take away from this is: whatever formula is being used.
you can easily using a computer programming and iterating through the data calculate the different parts of it.
That way these complicated formulas you see with the different summations and absolute values are easily computed one piece at a time.
Up until this point we've only been looking at two values x and y. Well in the real world it's very rare that you only have two values when you're figuring out a solution.
So let's move on to the next topic multiple linear regression. Let's take a brief look at what happens when you have multiple inputs.
So in multiple linear regression we have well we'll start with the simple linear regression where we had y equals m plus x plus c and we're trying to find the value of y.
Now with multiple linear regression we have multiple variables coming in.
So instead of having just x we have x1 x2 x3 and instead of having just one slope each variable has its own slope attached to it.
As you can see here we have m1 m2 m3 and we still just have the single coefficient.
So when you're dealing with multiple linear regression you basically take your single linear regression and you spread it out.
So you have y equals m1 times x1 plus m2 times x2 so on all the way to m to the nth x to the nth
and then you add your coefficient on there. Implementation of linear regression. Now we get into my favorite part.
Let's understand how multiple linear regression works by implementing it in Python.
If you remember before we were looking at a company and just based on its RD trying to figure out its profit we're going to start looking at the expenditure of the company
we're going to go back to that and we're going to predict its profit.
But instead of predicting it just on the RD we're going to look at other factors like administration costs, marketing costs, and so on.
And from there we're going to see if we can figure out what the profit of that company is going to be.
To start our coding we're going to begin by importing some basic libraries.
And we're going to be looking through the data before we do any kind of linear regression.
We're going to take a look at the data to see what we're playing with Then we'll go ahead and format the data to the format we need to be able to run it in the linear regression model.
And then from there we'll go ahead and solve it and just see how valid our solution is.
So let's start with importing the basic libraries.
Now I'm going to be doing this in Anaconda Jupyter Notebook, a very popular IDE.
I enjoy it because it's such a visual to look at and so easy to use.
Just any IDE for Python will work just fine for this.
So break out your favorite Python IDE.
So here we are in our Jupyter Notebook.
Let me go ahead and paste our first piece of code in there.
And let's walk through what libraries we're importing. First, we're going to import NUMPy as NP, and then I want you to skip one line and look at import pandas as PD.
These are very common tools that you need with most of your linear regression.
The NUMPY, which stands for number python, is usually denoted as np, and you have to almost have that for your SK Learn Toolbox. you always import that right off the beginning.
Pandas, although you don't have to have it for your sklearn libraries, it does such a wonderful job of importing data, setting it up into a data frame so we can manipulate it rather easily.
And it has a lot of tools also in addition to that.
So we usually like to use the pandas when we can, and I'll show you what that looks like.
The other three lines are for us to get a visual of this data and take a look at it.
So we're going to import matplotlibrary.pyplot as plt and then cborn as sns.
cborn works with the mapplot library.
So you have to always import mapplot library and then cborn sits on top of it.
And we'll take a look at what that looks like.
You could use any of your own plotting libraries you want. There's all kinds of ways to look at the data.
These are just very common ones, and the cborne is so easy to use that it just looks beautiful. It's a nice representation that you can actually take and show somebody.
And the final line is the Ambersigned Mapplot Library inline.
That is only because I'm doing an inline IDE.
My interface in the Anaconda Jupyter Notebook requires I put that in there, or you're not going to see the graph when it comes up.
Let's go ahead and run this. It's not going to be that interesting, so we're just setting up variables.
In fact, it's not going to do anything that we can see, but it is importing these different libraries and setup.
The next step is load the data set and extract independent and dependent variables.
Now, here in the slide you'll see companies equals pd.readcsv and it has a long line there with the file at the end, 1000 companies.csv.
You're going to have to change this to fit whatever setup you have.
And the file itself you can request.
Just go down to the commentary below this video and put a note in there, and Simply Learn will try to get in contact with you and supply you with that file so you can try this coding yourself.
So we're going to add this code in here, and we're going to see that I have companies equals pd dot reader underscore csv.
And I've changed this path to match my computer, c colon slash simply learn slash 1000 underscore companies dot csv.
And then below there we're going to set the X equals to companies under the ILocation.
And because this is companies is a PD dataset, I can use this nice notation that says take every row, that's what the colon, the first colon is,
comma, except for the last column.
That's what the second part is, where we have a colon minus one, and we want the values set into there.
So x is no longer a data set, a pandas data set. But we can easily extract the data from our pandas dataset with this notation.
And then y we're going to set equal to the last row.
Well, the question is going to be what are we actually looking at?
So let's go ahead and take a look at that.
And we're going to look at the companies.head, which lists the first five rows of data.
And I'll open up the file in just a second so you can see where that's coming from.
But let's look at the data in here as far as the way the pandas sees it. When I hit run, you'll see it breaks it out into a nice setup.
This is what pandas, one of the things pandas is really good about, is it looks just like an Excel spreadsheet.
You have your rows. And remember, when we're programming, we always start with zero. We don't start with one.
So it shows the first five rows.
01234 and then it shows your different columns R D spend, administration, marketing spend, state,
profit.
It even notes that the top are column names.
It was never told that, but Pandas is able to recognize a lot of things that they're not the same as the data rows.
Why don't we go ahead and open this file up in a CSV so you can actually see the raw data?
So here I've opened it up as a text editor, and you can see at the top we have R&D spend, comma, administration, comma, marketing, spend comma,
state, comma, profit, carriage return.
I don't know about you, but I'd go crazy trying to read files like this.
That's why we use the pandas.
You could also open this up in an Excel and it would separate it since it is a comma separated variable file.
But we don't want to look at this one, we want to look at something we can read rather easily. So let's flip back and take a look at that top part, the first five rows.
Now, as nice as this format is where I can see the data, to me it doesn't mean a whole lot.
Maybe you're an expert in business and investments and you understand what $165,349.20
compared to the administration cost of $136,897.80, so on so on, helps to create the profit of $192,261.83.
That makes no sense to me whatsoever, no pun intended.
So let's flip back here and take a look at our next set of code where we're going to graph it so we can get a better understanding of our data and what it means.
So at this point, we're going to use a single line of code to get a lot of information so we can see where we're going with this.
Let's go ahead and paste that into our notebook and see what we got going.
And so we have the visualization, and again we're using SNS, which is pandas.
As you can see, we imported the mapplot library.py plot as plt, which then the cborne uses.
And we imported the cborne as SNS.
And then that final line of code helps us show this in our inline coding.
Without this, it wouldn't display, and you could display it to a file and other means.
And that's the mapplot library inline with the amber sign at the beginning.
So here we come down to the single line of code.
Cborne is great because it actually recognizes the panda data frame.
So I can just take the companies.core for coordinates, and I can put that right into the Cborne.
And when we run this, we get this beautiful plot.
And let's just take a look at what this plot means.
If you look at this plot on mine, the colors are probably a little bit more purplish and blue than the original one.
we have the columns and the rows. We have R and D spending, we have administration, we have marketing spending and profit.
And if you cross-index any two of these, since we're interested in profit, if you cross-index profit with profit, it's going to show up, if you look at the scale on the right,
way up in the dark.
Why? Because those are the same data, they have an exact correspondence.
So RD spending is going to be the same as R&D spending, and the same thing with administration costs.
So right down the middle, you get this dark row or dark diagonal row that shows that this is the highest corresponding data
that's exactly the same.
And as it becomes lighter, there's less connections between the data.
So we can see with profit, obviously profit is the same as profit, and next it has a very high correlation with RD spending, which we looked at earlier,
and it has a slightly less connection to marketing spending, and even less to how much money we put into the administration.
So now that we have a nice look at the data, let's go ahead and dig in and create some actual useful linear regression models so that we can predict values and have a better profit.
Now that we've taken a look at the visualization of this data, we're going to move on to the next step.
Instead of just having a pretty picture, we need to generate some hard data, some hard values.
So let's see what that looks like.
We're going to set up our linear regression model in two steps.
The first one is we need to prepare some of our data so it fits correctly.
let's go ahead and paste this code into our Jupyter Notebook.
And what we're bringing in is we're going to bring in the SKLearn pre-processing where we're going to import the label encoder and the one hot encoder.
To use the label encoder, we're going to create a variable called label encoder and set it equal to capital L label, capital E encoder.
This creates a class that we can reuse for transferring the labels back and forth.
Now about now you should ask what labels are we talking about?
Let's go take a look at the data we processed before and see what I'm talking about here.
If you remember when we did the companies.
We have column zero, which is RD spending, column one, which is administration.
Column two, which is marketing spending, and column three is state, and you'll see under state we have New York, California, Florida.
Now, to do a linear regression model, it doesn't know how to process New York, it knows how to process a number.
So the first thing we're going to do is we're going to change that New York, California, and Florida, and we're going to change those to numbers. That's what this line of code does here.
X equals, and then it has the colon, comma three in brackets.
The first part, the colon, comma, means that we're going to look at all the different rows. So we're going to keep them all together. But the only row we're going to edit is the third row.
And in there we're going to take the label coder and we're going to fit and transform the X, also the third row. So we're going to take that third row, we're going to set it equal to a transformation.
And that transformation basically tells it that instead of having a New York, it has a zero or a one or a two.
And then finally we need to do a one hot encoder, which equals one hot encoder categorical features equals three.
And then we take the X and we go ahead and do that equal to one hot encoder fit transform X to array.
This final transformation preps our data for us so it's completely set the way we need it as just a row of numbers.
Even though it's not in here, let's go ahead and print x and just take a look what this data is doing.
You'll see you have an array of arrays, and then each array is a row of numbers.
And if I go ahead and just do row zero, you'll see I have a nice organized row of numbers that the computer now understands.
We'll go ahead and take this out there because it doesn't mean a whole lot to us, it's just a row of numbers.
Next, on setting up our data, we have avoiding dummy variable trap.
This is very important.
Why?
Because the computer has automatically transformed our header into the setup, and it's automatically transformed all these different variables.
So when we did the encoder, the encoder created two columns. And what we need to do is just have the one because it has both the variable and the name.
That's what this piece of code does here.
Let's go ahead and paste this in here, and we have x equals x colon, comma, one colon.
All this is doing is removing that one extra column we put in there when we did our one hot encoder and our label encoding.
Let's go ahead and run that.
And now we get to create our linear regression model.
And let's see what that looks like here. And we're going to do that in two steps.
The first step is going to be in splitting the data.
Now, whenever we create a predictive model of data, we always want to split it up so we have a training set and we have a testing set.
That's very important. Otherwise, we'd be very unethical without testing it to see how good our fit is.
And then we'll go ahead and create our multiple linear regression model and train it and set it up.
Let's go ahead and paste this next piece of code in here. And I'll go ahead and shrink it down a size or two so it all fits on one line.
So from the sklearn module selection, we're going to import train test split.
And you'll see that we've created four completely different variables. We have capital X train, capital X test, smaller case y train, smaller case y test.
That is the standard way that they usually reference these when we're doing different models.
Usually see that a capital X, and you see the train and the test and the lowercase y.
What this is, is X is our data going in.
That's our R D spin, our administration, our marketing.
And then Y, which we're training, is the answer. That's the profit. Because we want to know the profit of an unknown entity. So that's what we're going to shoot for in this tutorial.
The next part, train test split.
We take X and we take Y.
We've already created those. X has the columns with the data in it, and Y has a column with profit in it. And then we're going to set the test size equals 0.2.
That basically means 20%. So 20% of the rows are going to be tested. We're going to put them off to the side.
So since we're using a thousand lines of data, that means that 200 of those lines we're going to hold off to the side to test for later.
And then the random state equals zero. We're going to randomize which ones it picks to hold off to the side.
We'll go ahead and run this.
It's not overly exciting because it's setting up our variables.
But the next step is, the next step we actually create our linear regression model.
Now that we got to the linear regression model, we get that next piece of the puzzle.
Let's go ahead and put that code in there and walk through it.
So here we go. We're going to paste it in there.
And let's go ahead and since this is a shorter line of code, let's zoom up there so we can get a good look.
And we have from the sklearn.linear underscore model, we're going to import linear regression.
Now I don't know if you recall from earlier when we were doing all the math. Let's go ahead and flip back there and take a look at that.
Do you remember this where we had this long formula on the bottom and we were doing all this summization?
And then we also looked at setting it up with the different lines, and then we also looked all the way down to multiple linear regression where we're adding all those formulas together.
All of that is wrapped up in this one section.
So what's going on here is I'm going to create a variable called regressor.
And the regressor equals the linear regression. That's a linear regression model that has all that math built in.
So we don't have to have it all memorized or have to compute it individually.
And then we do the regressor.fit.
In this case, we do X train and Y train because we're using the training data, X being the data in and Y being profit, what we're looking at.
And this does all that math for us.
So within one click and one line, we've created the whole linear regression model.
And we fit the data to the linear regression model.
And you can see that when I run the regressor, it gives an output linear regression, it says copy x equals true, fit intercept equals true, in jobs equal one,
normalize equals false.
It's just giving you some general information on what's going on with that regressor model.
Now that we've created our linear regression model, let's go ahead and use it.
And if you remember, we kept a bunch of data aside.
So we're going to do a y predict variable and we're going to put in the x test. And let's see what that looks like.
Scroll up a little bit, paste that in here.
Predicting the test set results.
So here we have ypredict equals Regressor predict
xtest going in, and this gives us y predict.
Now because I'm in Jupyter inline, I can just put the variable up there.
And when I hit the run button, it'll print that array out.
I could have just as easily done printy predict.
So if you're in a different IDE that's not an inline setup like the Jupyter Notebook, you can do it this way, print y predict.
And you'll see that for the 200 different test variables we kept off to the side, it's going to produce 200 answers.
This is what it says the profit are for those 200 predictions. But let's don't stop there. Let's keep going and take a couple look.
We're going to take just a short detail here and calculating the coefficients and the intercepts.
This gives us a quick flash at what's going on behind the line.
We're going to take a short detour here and we're going to be calculating the coefficient and intercepts.
So you can see what those look like.
What's really nice about our regressor we created is it already has the coefficients for us. we can simply just print regressor.coefficient underscore.
When I run this, you'll see our coefficients here.
And if we can do the regressor coefficient, we can also do the regressor intercept.
let's run that and take a look at that.
This all came from the multiple regression model.
we'll flip over so you can remember where this is going into and where it's coming from.
You can see the formula down here where y equals m1 times x1 plus m2 times x2 and so on and so on plus c the coefficient.
So these variables fit right into this formula.
y equals slope 1 times column 1 variable plus slope 2 times column 2 variable all the way to the m to the n and x to the n plus c the coefficient.
Or in this case you have minus 8.89 to the power of 2, et cetera, et cetera, times the first column and the second column and the third column.
And then our intercept is the minus 103009 point.
Boy, it gets kind of complicated when you look at it.
This is why we don't do this by hand anymore. This is why we have the computer to make these calculations easy to understand and calculate.
Now I told you that was a short detour, and we're coming towards the end of our script.
As you remember from the beginning, I said if we're going to divide this information, we have to make sure it's a valid model, that this model works and understand how good it works.
So calculating the R squared value.
That's what we're going to use to predict how good our prediction is. And let's take a look at what that looks like in code.
And so we're going to use this from sklearn.metrics. We're going to import R2 score.
That's the R squared value.
We're looking at the error. So in the R2 score, we take our y test versus our y predict.
Y test is the actual values we're testing. That was the one that was given to us that we know are true.
The y predict of those 200 values is what we think it was true.
And when we go ahead and run this, we see we get a 0.9352. That's the R2 score.
Now, it's not exactly a straight percentage.
So it's not saying it's 93% correct.
But you do want that in the upper 90s, oh and higher, shows that this is a very valid prediction based on the R2 score.
And if R squared value of 0.91, or 92 as we got on our model, remember it does have a random generation involved, this proves the model is a good model.
Which means success!
Yay!
We successfully trained our model with certain predictors and estimated the profit of the companies using linear regression.
What is logistic regression? Let's say we have to build a predictive model or a machine learning model to predict whether the passengers of the Titanic ship have survived or not, the shipwreck.
So how do we do that?
So we use logistic regression to build a model for this.
How do we use logistic regression?
So we have the information about the passengers, their ID, whether they have survived or not, their class and name, and so on and so forth.
And we use this information where we already know whether the person has survived or not.
That is the labeled information, and we help the system to train based on this information based on this labeled data. This is known as labeled data.
And during the process of building the model, we probably will remove some of the non-essential parameters or attributes here.
We only take those attributes which are really required to make these predictions.
And once we train the model, we run new data through it whereby the model will predict whether the passenger has survived or not. Alright, what is logistic regression?
As I mentioned earlier, logistic regression is an algorithm for performing binary classification.
So let's take an example and see how this works.
Let's say your car has not been serviced for quite a few years, and now you want to find out if it is going to break down in the near future.
So this is like a classification problem, find out whether your car will break down or not.
So, how are we going to perform this classification?
So here's how it looks.
If we plot the information along the X and Y axis, X is the number of years since the last service was performed, and Y
is the probability of your car breaking down.
And let's say this information was this data rather was collected from several car users.
It's not just your car but several car users. So that is our labeled data.
So the data has been collected and f for for the number of years and when the car broke down and what was the probability. And that has been plotted along X and Y axis.
So this provides an idea, from this graph, we can find out whether your car will break down or not. We'll see how.
So first of all, the probability can go from 0 to 1. As you're aware, probability can be between 0 and 1.
And as we can imagine, it is intuitive as well, as the number of years are on the lower side, maybe 1 year,
2 years, or 3 years till after the service, the chances of your car breaking down are very limited, right?
So for example, chances of your car breaking down the probability of your car breaking down within two years of your last service are 0.1
probability. Similarly, 3 years is maybe 0.3 and so on. But as the number of years increases, let's say if it was six or seven years, there is almost a certainty that your car is going to break down.
That is what this graph shows.
So this is an example of a application of the classification algorithm.
And we will see in little details how exactly logistic regression is applied here.
One more thing needs to be added here is that the dependent variables outcome is discrete.
So if we are talking about whether the car is going to break down or not, so that is a discrete value, the y that we are talking about, the dependent variable that we are talking about.
What we are looking at is whether the car is going to break down or not, yes or no.
That is what we are talking about.
So here the outcome is discrete and not a continuous value. So this is how the logistic regression curve looks.
Let me explain a little bit what exactly and how exactly we are going to determine the class at the outcome, rather.
So for a logistic regression curve, a threshold has to be set saying that because this is a probability calculation.
Remember, this is a probability calculation, and the probability itself will not be zero or one.
But based on the probability, we need to decide what the outcome should be.
So there has to be a threshold. Like for example, 0.5 can be the threshold, let's say in this case.
So any value of the probability below 0.5 is considered to be 0, and any value above 0.5 is considered to be 1.
So an output of let's say 0.8 will mean that the car will break down. So that is considered as an output of 1.
And let's say an output of 0.29 is considered as 0, which means that the car will not break down.
So that's the way logistic regression works.
Now let's do a quick comparison between logistic regression and linear regression because they both have the term regression in them,
so it can cause confusion.
So let's try to remove that confusion.
So what is linear regression? Linear regression is a process, is once again an algorithm for supervised learning.
However, here you're going to find a continuous value, you're going to determine a continuous value.
It could be the price of a real estate property, it could be your hike, how much hike you're going to get, or it could be a stock price.
These are all continuous values, these are not discrete compared to a yes or a no kind of a response that we are looking for in logistic regression. So this is one example of a linear regression.
Let's say the HR team of a company tries to find out what should be the salary hike of an employee.
So they collect all the details of their existing employees, their ratings, and their salary hikes, what has been given, and that is the labeled information that is available,
and the system learns from this.
It is trained and it learns from this labeled information so that when a new employee's information is fed based on the rating, it will determine what should be the high.
So this is a linear regression problem and a linear regression example. Now, salary is a continuous value.
You can get 5000, 5500, 5600.
It is not discrete like a cat or a dog.
Or an apple or a banana, these are discrete, or a yes or a no, these are discrete values, right?
So this where you are trying to find continuous values is where we use linear regression.
So let's say just to extend on this scenario, we now want to find out whether this employee is going to get a promotion or not.
So we want to find out that is a discrete problem, right?
A yes or no kind of a problem.
In this case, we actually cannot use linear regression, even though we may have labeled data. So this is the label data.
So based on the employee rating, these are the ratings, and then some people got the promotion, and this is the ratings for which people did not get promotion.
That is a no, and this is the rating for which people got promotion.
We just plotted the data about whether a person has got an employee has got promotion or not, yes, no, right?
So there is nothing in between, and what is the employee's rating?
Okay, and ratings can be continuous, that is not an issue. But the output is discrete in this case, whether employee got promotion, yes, no.
Okay, so if we try to plot that and we try to find a straight line, this is how it would look, and as you can see, doesn't look very right
because looks like there will be a lot of errors.
Thus, root mean square error, if you remember for linear regression, would be very, very high, and also the the values cannot go beyond zero or beyond one.
So the graph should probably look somewhat like this, clipped at zero and one, but still the straight line doesn't look
right.
Therefore, instead of using a linear equation, we need to come up with something different, and therefore, the logistic regression model
looks somewhat like this.
So we calculate the probability, and if we plot that probability not in the form of a straight line, but we need to use some other equation, we will see very soon what that equation is,
then it is a gradual process, right?
So you see here people with some of these ratings are not getting any promotions, and then slowly at certain rating they get promotion, so that is a gradual process,
and this is how the math behind logistic regression looks.
So we are trying to find the odds for a particular event happening, and this is the formula for finding the odds.
So the probability of an event happening divided by the probability of the event not happening, so p if it is the probability of the event happening,
probability of the person getting a promotion and divided by the probability of the person not getting a promotion, that is one minus p.
So this is how you measure the odds.
Now the values of the odds range from 0 to infinity. So when this probability is 0, then the odds will the value of the odds is equal to 0.
And when the probability becomes 1, then the value of the odds is 1 by 0, that will be infinity. But the probability itself remains between 0 and 1.
Now, this is how an equation of a straight line looks.
So y is equal to beta 0 plus beta 1x where beta 0 is the y-intercept and beta 1 is the slope of the line.
If we take the odds equation and take a log of both sides, then this would look somewhat like this.
And the term logistic is actually derived from the fact that we are doing this. We take a log of px by 1 minus px.
This is an extension of the calculation of odds that we have seen, right?
And that is equal to beta 0 plus beta 1x, which is the equation of the straight line.
And now from here, if you want to find out the value of px, you will see we can take the exponential on both sides.
and then if we solve that equation, we will get the equation of px, like this.
px is equal to 1 by 1 plus e to the power of minus beta 0. plus beta 1x.
And recall this is nothing but the equation of the line which is equal to y. Y is equal to beta 0 plus beta 1x.
So that this is the equation also known as the sigmoid function, and this is the equation of the logistic regression algorithm.
Alright, and if this is plotted, this is how the sigmoid curve is obtained.
So let's compare linear and logistic regression, how they are different from each other. Let's go back.
So linear regression is solved or used to solve regression problems, and logistic regression is used to solve classification problems.
So both are called regression, but linear regression is used for solving regression problems where we predict continuous values,
whereas logistic regression is used for solving classification problems where we have have to predict discrete values.
The response variables in case of linear regression are continuous in nature, whereas here they are categorical or discrete in nature.
And linear regression helps to estimate the dependent variable when there is a change in the independent variable.
Whereas here, in case of logistic regression, it helps to calculate the probability or the possibility of a particular event happening.
And linear regression, as the name suggests, is a straight line, that's why it's called linear regression.
Whereas logistic regression is a sigmoid function and the curve is the shape of the curve is S.
It's an S-shaped curve. This is another example of application of logistic regression in weather prediction, whether it's going to rain or not rain.
Now keep in mind both are used in weather prediction.
If we want to find the discrete values like whether it's going to rain or not rain, that is a classification problem. We use logistic regression.
But if we want to determine what is going to be the temperature tomorrow, then we use linear regression.
So just keep in mind that in weather prediction we actually use both. But these are some examples of logistic regression.
So we want to find out whether it's going to be rain or not, whether it's going to be sunny or not, whether it's going to snow or not. These are all logistic regression examples.
A few more examples.
Classification of objects.
This is a again another example of logistic regression. Now, here of course, one distinction is that these are multi-class classification.
So logistic regression is not used in its original form, but it is used in a slightly different form.
So we say whether it is a dog or not a dog. I hope you understand.
So instead of saying is it a dog or a cat or an elephant, we convert this into saying so because we need to keep it to binary classification.
So we say is it a dog or not a dog?
Is it a cat or not a cat? So that's the way logistic regression can be used for classifying objects. Otherwise, there are other techniques which can be used for performing multiclass classification.
In healthcare, logistic regression is used to find the survival rate of a patient.
So they take multiple parameters like trauma score and age and so on and so forth, and they try to predict the rate of survival.
All right. now finally, let's take an example and see how we can apply logistic regression to predict the number that is shown in the image.
So this is actually a live demo.
I will take you into Jupyter Notebook and show the code. But before that, let me take you through a couple of slides to explain what we are trying to do.
So let's say you have an eight by eight image and there the image has a number 1, 2, 3, 4, and you need to train your model to predict what this number is. So how do we do this?
So the first thing is obviously in any machine learning process you train your model.
So in this case, we are using logistic regression, so and then we provide a training set to train the model and then we test.
How accurate our model is with the test data, which means that like any machine learning process, we split our initial data into two parts
training set and test set. With the training set, we train our model, and then with the test set, we we test the model till we get good accuracy and then we use it for
inference, right?
So that is typical methodology of
training, testing, and then deploying of machine learning models.
So let's take a look at the code and see what we are doing. So I'll not go line by line but just take you through some of the blocks.
So, first thing we do is import all the libraries, and then we basically take a look at the images and see what is the total number of images
we can display using matplotlib. Some of the images or a sample of these images, and then we split the data into training and test as I mentioned earlier, and we can do some exploratory analysis,
and then we build our model. We train our model with the training set, and then we test it with our test set and find out how accurate our model is using the confusion
matrix, the heat map, and use heat map for visualizing this.
And I will show you in the code what exactly is the confusion matrix and how it can be used for finding the accuracy.
In our example, we got we get an accuracy of about 0.94, which is pretty good, or 94%, which is pretty good. All right, so what is the confusion matrix?
This is an example of a confusion matrix, and this is used for identifying the accuracy of a classification model
or like a logistic regression model.
So the most important part in a confusion matrix is that first of all, this as you can see, this is a matrix, and the size of the matrix depends on how many outputs we are expecting,
right?
So the most important part here is that the model will be most accurate when we have the maximum numbers in its diagonal,
like in this case.
That's why it has almost 93-94 %, because the diagonals should have the maximum numbers, and the others other than diagonals, the cells other than the diagonal should have very few numbers.
So here that's what is happening. So there is a 2 here, there are there's a one here, but most of them are along the diagonal. This what does this mean?
This means that the number that has been fed is zero and the number that has been detected is also zero. So the predicted value and the actual value are the same.
So along the diagonals, that is true, which means that let's let's take this diagonal, right?
If if the maximum number is here, that means that like here in this case it is 34, which means that 34 of the images that have been fed, or rather, actually, there are two misclassifications in there.
So 36 images have been fed, which have number 4, and out of which 34 have been predicted correctly as number 4,
and one has been predicted as number 8, and another one has been predicted as number 9. So these are two misclassifications, okay.
So that is the meaning of saying that the maximum number should be in the diagonal.
So if you have all of them, so for an ideal model which has let's say 100% accuracy, everything will be only in the diagonal. There will be no numbers other than zero in all other cells.
So that is like a hundred percent accurate model, okay.
So that's uh just of how to use this matrix, uh, how to use this confusion matrix.
I know the name uh is is a little funny sounding confusion matrix, but actually it is not very confusing, it's very straightforward.
So you are just plotting what has been predicted and what is the labeled information or what is the actual data that's also known as the ground truth sometimes.
Okay, these are some fancy terms that are used.
So predicted label and the actual label, that's all it is.
Okay, yeah, so we are showing a little bit more information here. So 38 have been predicted, and here you will see that all of them have been predicted correctly.
There have been 38 zeros, and the the predicted value and actual value is exactly the same. Whereas in this case, for right, it has there are I think 37 plus 5.
Yeah, 42 have been fed the images, 42 images are of digit 3, and the accuracy is
only 37 of them have been accurately predicted.
Three of them have been predicted as number seven, and two of them have been predicted as number eight, and so on and so forth. Okay, all right.
So, with that let's go into Jupyter notebook and see how the code looks.
So this is the code.
In in Jupyter notebook for logistic regression.
In this particular demo, what we are going to do is train our model to recognize digits, which are the images
which have digits from, let's say, 0 to 5 or 0 to 9, and um. and then we will see how well it is trained and whether it is able to predict these numbers correctly or not.
So let's get started. So the first part is as usual, we are importing some libraries that are required, and then the last line in this block is to load the digits.
So let's go ahead and run this code.
Then here we will visualize the shape of these digits. So we can see here if we take a look, this is how the shape is 1797 by 64.
These are like 8 by 8 images, so that's that's what is reflected in this shape.
Now from here onwards, we are basically once again importing some of the libraries that are required, like numpy and mapplot, and we will take a look at
some of the sample images that we have loaded. So this one, for example, creates a figure, and then we go ahead and take a few sample images to see how they look.
So let me run this code and so that it becomes easy to understand. So these are about five images, sample images that we are looking at 0, 1, 2, 3, 4.
So this is how the images, this is how the data is okay. And based on this, we will actually train our logistic regression model and then we will test it and see how well it is able to recognize.
So the way it works is the pixel information. So as you can see here, this is an 8 by 8 pixel kind of uh image, and
each pixel whether it is activated or not activated, that is the information available for each pixel.
Now, based on the pattern of this activation and non-activation of the various pixels, this will be identified as a zero, for example, right?
Similarly, as you can see, so overall each of these numbers actually has a different pattern of the pixel activation, and that's pretty much that our model
needs to learn for which number what is the pattern of the activation of the pixels, right? So that is what we are going to train our model.
Okay, so the first thing we need to do is to split our data into training and test data set, right?
So whenever we perform any training, we split the data into training and test so that the training data set is used to train the system.
So we pass this probably multiple times and then we test it with the test data set.
And the split is usually in the form of there, and there are various ways in which you can split this data, it is up to the individual preferences.
In our case, here we are splitting in the form of 23 and 77. So when we say test size as 0.23 that means 23% of the entire data is
used for testing, and the remaining 77% is used for training. So there is a readily available function which is called train test split.
So we don't have to write any special code for the splitting, it will automatically split the data based on the proportion that we give here, which is test size.
So we just give the test size automatically training size will be determined, and we pass the data that we want to split.
And the the results will be stored in X underscore train and y underscore train for the training data set. And what is X underscore train? These are these are the features, right?
Which is like the independent variable and y underscore train is the label, right?
So in this case, what happens is we have the input value, which is or the features value, which is in x underscore train, and since this is a labeled data
for each of them, each of the observations, we already have the label information saying whether this digit is a zero or a one
or a two. So that this is what will be used for comparison to find out whether the the system is able to recognize it correctly or there is an error. For each observation, it will compare with this.
Right, so this is the label.
So the same way x underscore train, y underscore train is for the training data set, x underscore test, y underscore test is for the test data set.
Okay, so let me go ahead and execute this code as well, and then we can go and check quickly what is the how many entries are there and in each of
this. So x underscore train the shape is 1383 by 64 and y underscore train has 1383 because there is
nothing like the second part is not required here, and then x underscore test shape we see is 414. So actually there are 414 observations in test and 1383 observations in train.
So that's basically what these four lines of code are saying. Okay.
Then we import the logistic regression library, and which is a part of scikit learn, so we don't have to implement the logistic regression process itself; we just call these the function.
And let me go ahead and execute that, so that we have the logistic regression library imported. Now we create an instance of logistic regression, right?
So logistic REGR is uh is an instance of logistic regression, and then we use that for training our model. So let me first execute this code. So these two lines.
So the first line basically creates an instance of logistic regression model, and then the second line way is where we are passing our data,
the training data set, and? This is our the predictors and this is our target. We are passing this data set to train our model, all right.
So once we do this, in this case the data is not large, but by and large, the training is what takes usually a lot of time.
So we spend in machine learning activities in machine learning projects, we spend a lot of time for the training part of it.
Okay, so here the data set is relatively small, so it was pretty quick. So, alright, so now our model has been trained using the training data set, and we want to see how accurate this is.
So, what we'll do is we will test it out in probably faces. So, let me first try out how well this is working for one image.
Okay, I will just try it out with one image, my the first entry in my test data set and see whether it is correctly predicting or not.
So and in order to test it, so for training purpose, we use the fit method. There is a method called fit which is for training the model.
And once the training is done, if you want to test for a particular value new input, you use the predict method.
Okay, so let's run the predict method and we pass this particular image and we see that the
shape is or the prediction is four. So let's try a few more.
Let me see for the next 10.
seems to be fine. So let me just go ahead and test the entire data set. Okay, that's basically what we will do.
So now we want to find out how accurately this has performed. So we use the score method to find what is the percentage of accuracy, and we see here that it has performed up to 94%
accurate. Okay, so that's on this part. Now, what we can also do is we can also see this accuracy using what is known as a confusion matrix.
So let us go ahead and try that as well so that we can also visualize how well this model has done.
So let me execute this piece of code which will basically import some of the libraries that are required, and
we basically create a confusion matrix, an instance of confusion matrix by running confusion matrix and passing these
values.
So we have so this confusion underscore matrix method takes two parameters one is the y underscore test
and the other is the prediction. So, what is the y underscore test?
These are the labeled values which we already know for the test data set, and predictions are what the system has predicted for the test data set.
Okay, so this is known to us.
And this is what the system has the model has generated. So we kind of create the confusion matrix and we will print it.
And this is how the confusion matrix looks, as the name suggests, it is a matrix.
And the key point out here is that the accuracy of the model is determined by how many numbers are there in the diagonal. The more the numbers in the diagonal, the better the accuracy is.
Okay. And first of all, the total sum of all the numbers in this whole matrix is equal to the number of observations in the test data set. That is the first thing, right?
So if you add up all these numbers, that will be equal to the number of observations in the test data set. And then out of that, the maximum number of them should be in the diagonal.
That means the accuracy is pretty good. If the the numbers in the diagonal are less and in all other places there are a lot of numbers, which means the accuracy is very low.
The diagonal indicates a correct prediction. This means that the actual value is same as the predicted value. Here again, actual value same as the predicted value and so on, right?
So the moment you see a number here, that means the actual value is something and the predicted value is something else.
Right? Similarly, here the actual value is something and the predicted value is something else.
So that is basically how we read the confusion matrix. Now, how do we find the accuracy? You can actually add up the total values in the diagonal.
So it's like 38 plus 44 plus 43 and so on, and divide that by the total number of test observations that will give you the percentage accuracy using a
confusion matrix.
Now let us visualize this confusion matrix in a slightly more sophisticated way using a heat map.
So we will create a heat map with some we'll add some colors as well. It's uh it's like a more visually visually more appealing. So that's the whole idea.
So if we let me run this piece of code and this is how the heat map looks, and as you can see here, the diagonals again
are all the values are here, most of the values, so which means reasonably this seems to be reasonably accurate, and yeah, basically the accuracy score is 94%.
This is calculated as I mentioned by adding all these numbers divided by the total test value so the total number of observations in
test data set.
Okay, so this is the confusion matrix for logistic regression.
Alright, so now that we have seen the confusion matrix, let's take a quick sample and see how well the system has
classified, and we will take a few examples of the data.
So if we see here we picked up randomly a few of them, so this is number four, which is the actual value, and also the predicted value, both are four.
This is an image of zero, so the predicted value is also zero, actual values of course zero, then this is the image of nine,
so this has also been predicted correctly. Nine and actual value is nine, and this is the image of one, and again this has been predicted correctly as like the actual value.
Okay, so this was a quick demo of logistic regression, how to use logistic regression to identify images.
What is a decision tree?
Let's go through a very simple example before we dig in deep.
Decision tree is a tree-shaped diagram used to determine a course of action.
Each branch of the tree represents a possible decision or occurrence or reaction. Let's start with a simple question. How do I identify a random vegetable from a shopping bag?
So we have this group of vegetables in here, and we can start off by asking a simple question is it red? And if it's not, then it's going to be the purple fruit to the left, probably an eggplant.
If it's true, it's going to be one of the red fruits. Is the diameter greater than two? If false, it's going to be a what looks to be a red chili.
And if it's true, it's going to be a bell pepper from the capsicum family. So it's a capsicum.
Problems that decision tree can solve.
So let's look at the two different categories the decision tree can be used on.
It can be used on the classification, the true false, yes, no, and it can be used on regression, where we figure out what the next value is in a series of numbers or a group of data.
In classification, the classification tree will determine a set of logical if-then conditions to classify problems.
For example, discriminating between three types of flowers based on certain features.
In regression, a regression tree is used when the target variable is numerical or continuous in nature. We fit the regression model to the target variable using each of the independent variables.
Each split is made based on the sum of squared error.
Before we dig deeper into the mechanics of the decision tree, let's take a look at the advantages of using a decision tree. And we'll also take a glimpse at the disadvantages.
The first thing you'll notice is that it's simple to understand, interpret, and visualize. It really shines here because you can see exactly what's going on in a decision tree.
Little effort is required for data preparation, so you don't have to do special scaling. There's a lot of things you don't have to worry about when using a decision tree.
It can handle both numerical and categorical data, as we discovered earlier, and nonlinear parameters don't affect its performance.
So even if the data doesn't fit an easy curved graph, you can still use it to create an effective decision or prediction.
If we're going to look at the advantages of a decision tree, we also need to understand the disadvantages of a decision tree.
The first disadvantage is overfitting. Overfitting occurs when the algorithm captures noise in the data.
That means you're solving for one specific instance instead of a general solution for all the data. High variance. The model can get unstable due to small variation in data.
Low bias tree, a highly complicated decision tree, tends to have a low bias, which makes it difficult for the model to work with new data.
Decision tree important terms. Before we dive in further, we need to look at some basic terms.
We need to have some definitions to go with our decision tree and the different parts we're going to be using. We'll start with entropy.
Entropy is a measure of randomness or unpredictability in the data set.
For example, we have a group of animals in this picture. There's four different kinds of animals, and this data set is considered to have a high entropy.
You really can't pick out what kind of animal it is based on looking at just the four animals as a big clump of entities.
So as we start splitting it into subgroups, we come up with our second definition, which is information gain. Information gain. It is a measure of decrease in entropy after the data set is split.
So in this case, based on the color yellow, we've split one group of animals on one side as true and those who aren't yellow as false.
As we continue down the yellow side, we split based on the height, true or false equals 10. And on the other side, height is less than 10, true or false.
And as you see, as we split it, the entropy continues to be less and less and less. And so our information gain is simply the entropy, E1 from the top, and how it's changed to E2 in the bottom.
And we'll look at the deeper math, although you really don't need to know a huge amount of math when you actually do the programming in Python, because it'll do it for you.
But we'll look on the actual math at how they compute entropy. Finally, we went into the different parts of our tree, and they call the leaf node.
Leaf node carries the classification or the decision, so it's the final end at the bottom.
The decision node has two or more branches. This is where we're breaking the group up into different parts. And finally, you have the root node. The topmost decision node is known as the root node.
How does a decision tree work? Wonder what kind of animals I'll get in the jungle today. Maybe you're the hunter with the gun, or if you're more into photography, you're a photographer with a camera.
So let's look at this group of animals and let's try to classify different types of animals based on their features using a decision tree.
So the problem statement is to classify the different types of animals based on their features using a decision tree. The data set is looking quite messy and the entropy is high in this case.
So let's look at a training set or a training data set.
And we're looking at color, we're looking at height, and then we have our different animals. We have our elephants, our giraffes, our monkeys, and our tigers.
And they're of different colors and shapes. Let's see what that looks like. And how do we split the data?
We have to frame the conditions that split the data in such a way that the information gain is the highest. Note gain is the measure of decrease in entropy after splitting.
So the formula for entropy is the sum, that's what this symbol looks like, that looks like kind of like a funky E of K, where I
equals 1 to K. K would represent the number of animals, the different animals in there, where value or P value of I would be the percentage of that animal
times the log base 2 of the same, the percentage of that animal. Let's try to calculate the entropy for the current data set and take a look at what that looks like.
And don't be afraid of the math. You don't really have to memorize this math. Just be aware that it's there and this is what's going on in the background.
And so we have three giraffes, two tigers, one monkey, two elephants, a total of eight animals gathered. And if we plug that into the formula, we get an entropy that equals three over eight.
So we have three giraffes, a total of eight, times the log. Usually they use base two on the log.
So log base two of three over eight, plus, in this case let's say it's the elephants, two over eight, two elephants over total of eight, times log base two,
two over eight, plus one monkey over total of eight, log base two, one over eight, and plus two over eight of the tigers, log base
two over eight.
And if we plug that into our computer or calculator, I obviously can't do logs in my head, we get an entropy equal to 0.571.
The program will actually calculate the entropy of the data set similarly after every split to calculate the gain.
Now we're not going to go through each set one at a time to see what those numbers are. We just want you to be aware that this is a formula or the mathematics behind it.
Gain can be calculated by finding the difference of the subsequent entropy values after a split. Now we will try to choose a condition that gives us the highest gain.
We will do that by splitting the data using each condition and checking that the gain we get out of them. The condition that gives us the highest gain will be used to make the first split.
Can you guess what that first split will be just by looking at this image? As a human, it's probably pretty easy to split it.
Let's see if you're right.
If you guessed the color yellow, you're correct. Let's say the condition that gives us the maximum gain is yellow. So we will split the data based on the color yellow.
If it's true, that group of animals goes to the left. If it's false, it goes to the right. The entropy after the splitting has decreased considerably.
However, we still need some splitting at both the branches to attain an entropy value equal to zero. So we decide to split both the nodes using height as a condition.
Since every branch now contains single label type, we can say that entropy in this case has reached the least value.
And here you see we have the giraffes, the tigers, the monkey, and the elephants all separated into their own groups.
This tree can now predict all the classes of animals present in the dataset with 100% accuracy. That was easy.
Use case loan repayment prediction. Let's get into my favorite part and open up some Python and see what the programming code and the scripting looks like.
In here, we're going to want to do a prediction.
And we start with this individual here who's requesting to find out how good his customers are going to be, whether they're going to repay their loan or not for his bank.
And from that, we want to generate a problem statement to predict if a customer will repay loan amount or not. And then we're going to be using the decision tree algorithm in Python.
Let's see what that looks like and let's dive into the code. In our first few steps of implementation, we're going to start by importing the necessary packages that we need from Python.
And we're going to load up our data and take a look at what the data looks like. So the first thing I need is I need something to edit my Python and run it in. So let's flip on over.
And here I'm using the Anaconda Jupyter Notebook.
Now you can use any Python IDE you like to run it in, but I find the Jupyter Notebooks really nice for doing things on the fly. And let's go ahead and just paste that code in the beginning.
And before we start, let's talk a little bit about what we're bringing in. And then we're going to do a couple things in here.
We have to make a couple changes as we go through this first part of the import. The first thing we bring in is NumPy as NP.
That's very standard. When we're dealing with mathematics, especially with very complicated machine learning tools, you almost always see the NUMPy come in for your numbers.
It's called number Python, it has your mathematics in there. In this case, we actually could take it out, but generally you'll need it for most of your different things you work with.
And then we're going to use pandas as PD.
That's also a standard. The pandas is a data frame setup, and you can liken this to taking your basic data and storing it in a way that looks like an Excel spreadsheet.
So as we come back to this, when you see NP or PD, those are very standard uses, you'll know that that's the pandas. And I'll show you a little bit more when we explore the data in just a minute.
Then we're going to need to split the data. So I'm going to bring in our train test and split. And this is coming from the SK Learn package cross-validation.
In just a minute, we're going to change that and we'll go over that too. And then there's also the SK.tree import decision tree classifier. That's the actual tool we're using.
Remember, I told you don't be afraid of the mathematics, it's going to be done for you.
Well, the decision tree classifier has all that mathematics in there for you, so you don't have to figure it back out again. And then we have sklearn.metrics for accuracy score.
We need to score our setup. That's the whole reason we're splitting it between the training and testing data. And finally, we still need the sklearn import tree.
And that's just the basic tree function that's needed for the decision tree classifier. And finally, we're going to load our data down here.
And I'm going to run this and we're going to get two things on here. One, we're going to get an error, and two, we're going to get a warning. Let's see what that looks like.
So the first thing we had is we have an error.
Why is this error here? Well, it's looking at this and says I need to read a file.
And when this was written, the person who wrote it, this is their path where they stored the file.
So let's go ahead and fix that.
And I'm going to put in here my file path. I'm just going to call it full file name.
And you'll see it's on my C drive and there's this very lengthy setup on here where I stored the data2.csv file.
Don't worry too much about the full path because on your computer it'll be different.
The data.2csv file was generated by Simply Learn.
If you want a copy of that, you can comment down below and request it here in the YouTube.
And then if I'm going to give it a name, full file name,
I'm going to go ahead and change it here
to full
file name.
So let's go ahead and run it now and see what happens.
And we get a warning.
When you're coding, understanding these different warnings and these different errors that come up is probably the hardest lesson to learn.
So let's just go ahead and take a look at this and use this as an opportunity to understand what's going on here.
If you read the warning, it says the cross-validation is depreciated. So it's a warning on it's being removed.
And it's going to be moved in favor of the model selection.
So if we go up here, we have sklearn.crossvalidation. And if you research this and go to the sklearn site, you'll find out that you can actually just swap it right in there with model selection.
And so when I come in here and I run it again,
that removes a warning.
What they've done is they've had two different developers develop it in two different branches.
And then they decided to keep one of those and eventually get rid of the other one.
That's all that is.
And very easy and quick to fix.
Before we go any further, I went ahead and opened up the data from this file. Remember the data file we just loaded on here, the data underscore two.csv.
Let's talk a little bit more about that and see what that looks like both as a text file, because it's a comma-separated variable file, and in a spreadsheet.
This is what it looks like as a basic text file. You can see at the top they've created a header and it's got one, two, three, four, five columns, and each column has data in it.
And let me flip this over because we're also going to look at this in an actual spreadsheet so you can see what that looks like.
And here I've opened it up in the OpenOffice Calc, which is pretty much the same as Excel, and zoomed in, and you can see we've got our columns and our rows of data. A little easier to read in here.
We have a result, yes, yes, no. We have initial payment, last payment, credit score, house number.
If we scroll way down,
we'll see that this occupies
one,001 lines of code or lines of data,
with the first one being a column and then one thousand lines of data.
Now, as a programmer,
if you're looking at a small amount of data, I usually start by pulling it up in different sources so I can see what I'm working with.
But in larger data, you won't have that option.
It'll just be too large. So you need to either bring in a small amount that you can look at it like we're doing right now, or we can start looking at it through the Python code.
So let's go ahead and move on and take the next couple steps to explore the data using Python. Let's go ahead and see what it looks like in Python to print the length and the shape of the data.
So let's start by printing the length of the database. We can use a simple line function from Python.
And when I run this, you'll see that it's a thousand long. And that's what we expected. There's a thousand lines of data in there if you subtract the column head.
This is one of the nice things when we did the balance data from the panda read CSV, you'll see that the header is row zero,
so it automatically removes the row
and then shows the data separate. It does a good job sorting that data out for us.
And then we can use a different function, and let's take a look at that.
And again, we're going to utilize the tools in panda,
and since the balance underscore data was loaded as a panda data frame,
we can do a shape on it.
And let's go ahead and run the shape and see what that looks like.
What's nice about the shape is not only does it give me the length of the data, we have a thousand lines, it also tells me there's five columns.
So we were looking at the data, we had five columns of data. And then let's take one more step to explore the data using Python.
And now that we've taken a look at the length and the shape, let's go ahead and use the pandas module for head. Another beautiful thing in the dataset that we can utilize.
So let's put that on our sheet here, and we have print dataset and balance data dot head.
And this is a pandas print statement of its own. So it has its own print feature in there.
And then we went ahead and gave a label for a print job here of data set, just a simple print statement.
And we run that, and let's just take a closer look at that. Let me zoom in here.
There we go.
Pandas does such a wonderful job of making this a very clean, readable data set.
So you can look at the data, you can look at the column headers, you can have it when you put it as the head, it prints the first five lines of the data.
And we always start with zero. So we have five lines, we have zero, one, two, three, four instead of one, two, three, four, five.
That's a standard scripting and programming set, is you want to start with the zero position.
And that is what the data head does. It pulls the first five rows of data, puts it in a nice format that you can look at and view. Very powerful tool to view the data.
So instead of having to flip and open up an Excel spreadsheet or open office calc or trying to look at a Word doc where it's all scrunched together and hard to read,
you can now get a nice open view of what you're working with.
We're working with a shape of a thousand long, five wide, so we have five columns, and we do the full data head, you can actually see what this data looks like.
The initial payment, last payment, credit scores, house number.
So let's take this now that we've explored the data and let's start digging into the decision tree. So in our next step, we're going to train and build our data tree.
And to do that, we need to first separate the data out.
We're going to separate into two groups so that we have something to actually train the data with, and then we have some data on the side to test it, to see how good our model is.
Remember, with any of the machine learning, you always want to have some kind of test set to weigh it against so you know how good your model is when you distribute it.
Let's go ahead and break this code down and look at it in pieces.
So first we have our X and Y.
Where do X and Y come from?
Well, X is going to be our data, and Y is going to be the answer or the target. You can look at it source and target.
In this case, we're using X and Y to denote the data in and the data that we're actually trying to guess what the answer is going to be.
And so to separate it, we can simply put in X equals the balance of the data dot values. The first brackets means that we're going to select all the lines in the database. So it's all the data.
And the second one says we're only going to look at columns one through five. Remember we always start with zero.
Zero is a yes or no, and that's whether the loan went default or not. So we want to start with one. If we go back up here, that's the initial payment, and it goes all the way through the house number.
Well, if we want to look at one through five, we can do the same thing for y, which is the answers, and we're going to set that just equal to the zero row.
So it's just the zero row, and then it's all rows going in there. So now we've divided this into two different data sets, one of them with the
data going in, and one with the answers.
Next, we need to split the data.
And here you'll see that we have it split into four different parts.
The first one is your X training, your X test, your Y train, your Y test.
Simply put, we have X going in where we're going to train it, and we have to know the answer to train it with.
And then we have X test where we're going to test that data.
And we have to know in the end what the Y was supposed to be.
And that's where this train test split comes in that we loaded earlier in the modules.
This does it all for us. And you can see they set the test size equal to 0.3, so that's roughly 30% will be used in the test.
And then we use a random state, so it's completely random which rows it takes out of there.
And then finally we get to actually build our decision tree.
And they've called it here CLF underscore entropy.
That's the actual decision tree or decision tree classifier.
And in here they've added a couple variables, which we'll explore in just a minute.
And then finally, we need to fit the data to that.
So we take our CLF entropy that we created and we fit the X train. And since we know the answers for X train are the Y train, we go ahead and put those in.
And let's go ahead and run this.
And what most of these SKLearn modules do is when you set up the variable, in this case, when we set the CLF entropy equal decision tree classifier,
it automatically prints out what's in that decision tree.
There's a lot of variables you can play with in here, and it's quite beyond the scope of this tutorial to go through all of these and how they work.
But we're working on entropy, that's one of the options.
We've added that it's completely a random state of 100, so 100%. And we have a max depth of three.
Now the max depth, if you remember above when we were doing the different graphs of animals, means it's only going to go down three layers before it stops.
And then we have minimal samples of leaves is five. So it's going to have at least five leaves at the end. So I'll have at least three splits.
We'll have no more than three layers and at least five end leaves with the final result at the bottom.
Now that we've created our decision tree classifier, not only created it but trained it.
Let's go ahead and apply it and see what that looks like.
So let's go ahead and make a prediction and see what that looks like.
We're going to paste our predict code in here.
And before we run it, let's just take a quick look at what it's doing here.
We have a variable yPredict that we're going to do.
And we're going to use our variable CLF entropy that we created.
And then you'll see dot predict.
And it's very common in the SKLearn modules that their different tools have the predict when you're actually running a prediction.
In this case, we're going to put our X test data in here.
Now, if you delivered this for use and actual commercial use and distributed it, this would be the new loans you're putting in here to guess
whether the person is going to pay them back or not.
In this case, though, we need to test out the data and just see how good our sample is, how good of our tree does at predicting the loan payments.
And finally, since Anaconda Jupyter Notebook works as a command line for Python, we can simply put the Y predictE in to print it.
I could just as easily have put the print
and put brackets around Y predict E in to print it out.
We'll go ahead and do that. It doesn't matter which way you do it.
And you'll see right here that it runs a prediction.
This is roughly 300 in here. Remember it's 30% of a thousand, so you should have about 300 answers in here.
And this tells you which each one of those lines of our test went in there, and this is what our y predict came out.
So let's move on to the next step. We're going to take this data and try to figure out just how good a model we have.
So here we go, since sklearn does all the heavy lifting for you and all the math, we have a simple line of code to let us know what the accuracy is.
And let's go ahead and go through that and see what that means and what that looks like. Let's go ahead and paste this in and let me zoom in a little bit.
There we go.
So you have a nice full picture.
And we'll see here we're just going to do a print accuracy is.
And then we do the accuracy score.
And this was something we imported earlier, if you remember at the very beginning. Let me just scroll up there real quick so you can see where that's coming from.
That's coming from here down here from sklearn.metrics import accuracy score.
And you could probably run a script, make your own script to do this very easily.
How accurate is it? How many out of 300 do we get right?
And so we put in our y test, that's the one we ran the predict on, and then we put in our y predict en that's the answers we got,
and we're just going to multiply that by a hundred, because this is just going to give us an answer as a decimal, and we want to see it as a percentage.
let's run that and see what it looks like. And
if you see here, we got an accuracy of 93.66667.
So when we look at the number of loans and we look at how good our model fit, we can tell people it has about a 93.6 fitting to it.
So just a quick recap on that.
We now have accuracy set up on here.
And so we have created a model that uses the decision tree algorithm to predict whether a customer will repay the loan or not.
The accuracy of the model is about 94.6%.
The bank can now use this model to decide whether it should approve the loan request from a particular customer or not. And so this information is really powerful.
We may not be able to, as individuals, understand all these numbers because they have thousands of numbers that come in.
But you can see that this is a smart decision for the bank to use a tool like this to help them to predict how good their
profits are going to be off of the loan balances and how many are going to default or not. We're going to be looking at random forest, one of the many powerful tools in the machine learning library.
Before we dive into the topic, let's start by looking at a few of the uses for random forest.
Currently, today it's used in remote sensing.
For example, they're used in the ETM devices. If you're a space buff, that's the enhanced thermatic mapper they use on satellites, which see far outside the human spectrum for looking at land masses.
And they acquire images of the Earth's surface.
The accuracy is higher, and training time is less than many other machine learning tools out there.
Also, object detection, multi-class object detection is done using random forest algorithms.
A good example is traffic where you're trying to sort out the different cars, buses, and things.
And it provides a better detection in complicated environments. It's very complicated up there.
And then we have another example, Connect.
And let's take a little closer look at Connect. Connect, they use a random forest as part of the game console.
And what it does is it tracks the body movements and it recreates it in the game.
And let's see what that looks like.
We have a user who performs a step. In this case, it looks like Elvis Presley going there.
That is then recorded so that Connect registers the movement and then it marks the user based on accuracy. And it looks like we have uh prints going on this one from Elvis Presley to Prince.
It's great.
so it marks user based on the accuracy. If we look at that a little closer, we have a training set to identify body parts. Where are the hands, where are the feet, what's going on with the body.
That then goes into a random forest classifier that learns from it.
Once we've trained the classifier, it then identifies the body parts while the person's dancing, it's able to represent that in a computer format, and then based on that
it scores the game and how accurate you are as being Elvis Presley or Prince in your dancing.
So why random forest? It's always important to understand why we use this tool over the other ones.
What are the benefits here? And so with the random forest, the first one is there's no overfitting.
If you use of multiple trees, reduce the risk of overfitting.
Training time is less.
Overfitting means that we have fit the data so close to what we have as our sample that we pick up on all the weird parts.
And instead of predicting the overall data, you're predicting the weird stuff, which you don't want.
High accuracy runs efficiently in large database.
For large data, it produces highly accurate predictions. In today's world of big data, this is really important.
And this is probably where it really shines. This is where why random forest really comes in.
It estimates missing data.
Data in today's world is very messy. So when you have a random forest, it can maintain the accuracy when a large proportion of the data is missing.
What that means is: if you have data that comes in from five or six different areas, and maybe they took one set of statistics in one area,
and they took a slightly different set of statistics in the other. so they have some of the same shared data. but one is missing like the number of children in the house.
if you're doing something over demographics, and the other one is missing the size of the house.
It will look at both of those separately and build two different trees, and then it can do a very good job of guessing which one fits better, even though it's missing that data.
Let us dig deep into the theory of exactly how it works.
And let's look at what is random forests.
Random forests or random decision forest is a method that operates by constructing multiple decision trees.
The decision of the majority of the trees is chosen by the random forest as the final decision.
And let's uh we have some nice graphics here. We have a decision tree, and they actually use a real tree to denote the decision tree, which I love.
And given a random some kind of picture of a fruit, this decision tree decides that the output is it's an apple.
And we have a decision tree two where we have that picture of the fruit goes in, and this one decides that it's a lemon.
And the decision three tree gets another image and it decides it's an apple, and then this all comes together in what they call the random forest.
And this random forest then looks at it and says, okay, I got two votes for apple, one vote for lemon. The majority is apples, so the final decision is apples.
To understand how the random forest works, we first need to dig a little deeper and take a look at the random forest and the actual decision tree and how it builds that decision tree.
In looking closer at how the individual decision trees work, we'll go ahead and continue to use the fruit example, since we're talking about trees and forests.
A decision tree is a tree-shaped diagram used to determine a course of action.
Each branch of the tree represents a possible decision, occurrence, or reaction.
So in here we have a bowl of fruit, and if you look at that, it looks like they switch from lemons to oranges. We have oranges, cherries, and apples.
And the first decision of the decision tree might be is a diameter greater than or equal to three? And if it says false, it knows that they're cherries because everything else is bigger than that.
So all the cherries fall into that decision.
So we have all that data we're training.
We can look at that, we know that that's what's going to come up.
Is the color orange?
Well it goes, hmm, orange or red. Well, if it's true, then it comes out as the orange, and if it's false, that leaves apples.
So in this example, it sorts out the fruit in the bowl or the images of the fruit.
A decision tree, these are very important terms to know, because these are very central to understanding the decision tree when working with them. The first is entropy.
Everything on the decision tree and how it makes those decisions is based on entropy. Entropy is a measure of randomness or unpredictability in the data set.
Then they also have information gain, the leaf node, the decision node, and the root node.
We'll cover these other four terms as we go down the tree, but let's start with entropy.
So starting with entropy, we have here a high amount of randomness.
What that means is that whatever's coming out of this decision, if it was going to guess based on this data, it wouldn't be able to tell you whether it's a lemon or an apple.
It would just say it's a fruit.
So the first thing we want to do is we want to split this apart. And we take the initial data set, we're going to create a data set one and a data set two. We just split it in two.
And if you look at these new data sets after splitting them, the entropy of each of those sets is much less.
So for the first one, whatever comes in there, it's going to sort that data and it's going to say, okay, if this data goes this direction, it's probably an apple.
And if it goes into the other direction, it's probably a lemon.
So that brings us up to information gain.
It is the measure of decrease in the entropy after the data set is split.
What that means in here is that we've gone from one set, which has a very high entropy, to two lower sets of entropy.
And we've added in the values of E1 for the first one and E2 for the second two, which are much lower.
And so that information gain is increased greatly in this example.
And so you can find that the information grain simply equals decision E1 minus E2.
As we're going down our list of definitions, we'll look at the leaf node.
And the leaf node carries the classification or the decision.
So we look down here to the leaf node, we finally get to our set one or our set two.
When it comes down there and it says, okay, this object's gone into set one.
If it's gone into set one, it's going to be split by some means and we'll either end up with apples on the leaf node or a lemon on the leaf node, and on the right it'll either be an apple or lemons.
Those leaf nodes or those final decisions or classifications, that's the definition of leaf node in here.
If we're going to have a final leaf where we make the decision, we should have a name for the nodes above it, and they call those decision nodes.
A decision node, decision node has two or more branches.
And you can see here where we have the five apples and one lemon, and in the other case the five lemons and one apple, they have to make a choice of which tree it goes down
based on some kind of measurement or information given to the tree.
And that brings us to our last definition.
The root node, the topmost decision node, is known as the root node. And this is where you have all of your data and you have your first decision it has to make or the first split in information.
So far, we've looked at a very general image with the fruit being split. Let's look and see exactly what that means to split the data and how do we make those decisions on there.
Let's go in there and find out how does a decision tree work.
So let's try to understand this and let's use a simple example, and we'll stay with the fruit.
We have a bowl of fruit.
And so let's create a problem statement. And the problem is we want to classify the different types of fruits in the bowl based on different features.
The data set in the bowl is looking quite messy and the entropy is high in this case.
So if this bowl was our decision maker, it wouldn't know what choice to make. It has so many choices.
Which one do you pick? Apple, grapes, or lemons. And so we look in here, we're going to start with a training set.
So this is our data that we're training our data with. And we have a number of options here. We have the color, and under the color we have red, yellow, purple.
We have a diameter, uh 331, 331, and we have a label, apple, lemon, grapes, apple, lemon grapes.
And how do we split the data?
We have to frame the conditions to split the data in such a way that the information gain is the highest.
It's very key to note that we're looking for the best gain.
We don't want to just start sorting out the smallest piece in there.
We want to split it the biggest way we can. And so we measure this decrease in entropy, that's what they call it entropy, there's our entropy, after splitting.
And now we'll try to choose a condition that gives us the highest gain. We will do that by splitting the data using each condition and checking the gain that we get out of them.
The conditions that give us the highest gain will be used to make the first split.
So let's take a look at these different conditions. We have color, we have diameter, and if we look underneath that, we have a couple different values.
We have diameter equals three, color equals yellow, red, diameter equals one. And when we look at that, you'll see over here we have one, two, three, four threes. That's a pretty hard selection.
So let's say the condition gives us the maximum gain of three.
So we have the most pieces fall into that range.
So our first split from our decision node is we split the data based on the diameter. Is it greater than or equal to three?
If it's not, that's false, it goes into the grape bowl.
And if it's true, it goes into a bowl full of lemon and apples.
The entropy after splitting has decreased considerably.
So now we can make two decisions. If you look at they're very much less chaos going on there.
This node has already attained an entropy value of zero as you can see. There's only one kind of label left for this branch.
So no further splitting is required for this node.
However, this node on the right still requires a split to decrease the entropy further.
So we split the right node further based on color.
If you look at this, if I split it on color, that pretty much cuts it right down the middle, and it's the only thing we have left in our choices of color and diameter, too.
And if the color is yellow, it's going to go to the right bowl, and if it's false, it's going to go to the left bowl.
So the entropy in this case is now zero. So now we have three bowls with zero entropy. There's only one type of data in each one of those bowls.
So we can predict a lemon with a hundred percent accuracy.
And we can predict the apple also with a hundred percent accuracy, along with our grapes up there.
So we've looked at kind of a basic tree in our forest.
But what we really want to know is how does a random forest work as a whole?
So to begin our random forest classifier, let's say we already have built three trees. And we're going to start with the first tree that looks like this.
Just like we did in the example, this tree looks at the diameter. If it's greater than or equal to three, it's true, otherwise it's false.
So one side goes to the smaller diameter, one side goes to larger diameter. And if the color is orange, it's going to go to the right, true. We're using oranges now instead of lemons.
And if it's red, it's going to go to the left, false.
We build a second tree, very similar, but split differently.
Instead of the first one being split by a diameter, this one, when they created it, if you look at that first bowl, it has a lot of red objects. So it says, is the color red?
Because that's going to bring our entropy down the fastest.
And so of course if it's true, it goes to the left. If it's false, it goes to the right.
And then it looks at the shape, false or true, and so on and so on.
And tree three, is the diameter equal to one?
And it came up with this because there's a lot of cherries in this bowl.
So that would be the biggest split on there is is the diameter equal to one? That's going to drop the entropy the quickest.
And as you can see, it splits it into true. If it goes false, and they've added another category, does it grow in the summer?
And if it's false, it goes off to the left. If it's true, it goes off to the right.
Let's go ahead and bring these three trees. So you can see them all in one image. So this would be three completely different trees categorizing a fruit.
And let's take a fruit.
Now let's try this.
And this fruit, if you look at it, we've blackened it out.
You can't see the color on it. So it's missing data. Remember one of the things we talked about earlier is that a random forest works really good if you're missing data, if you're missing pieces.
So this fruit has an image, but maybe the person had a black and white camera when they took the picture. And we're going to take a look at this, and it's going to have they put the color in there.
So ignore the color down there. But the diameter equals three.
We find out it grows in the summer equals yes, and the shape is a circle.
And if you go to the right, you can look at what one of the decision trees did. This is the third one.
Is the diameter greater than or equal to three? Is the color orange? Well, it doesn't really know on this one, but if you look at the value, it'd say true and it go to the right.
Tree two classifies it as cherries. Is the color equal red?
Is the shape a circle?
True, it is a circle.
So this would look at it and say, oh, that's a cherry.
And then we go to the other classifier and it says, is the diameter equal one?
Well that's false. Does it grow in the summer?
True.
So it goes down and looks at as oranges.
So how does this random forest work? The first one says it's an orange.
The second one said it was a cherry. And the third one says, it's an orange.
And you can guess if you have two oranges and one says it's a cherry, when you add that all together, the majority of the vote says orange.
So the answer is it's classified as an orange, even though we didn't know the color and we're missing data on it. I don't know about you, but I'm getting tired of fruit.
So let's switch, and I did promise you we'd start looking at a case example and get into some Python coding.
Today we're going to use the case, the iris flower analysis.
Oh this is the exciting part as we roll up our sleeves and actually look at some Python coding.
Before we start the Python coding, we need to go ahead and create a problem statement.
Wonder what species of iris do these flowers belong to? Let's try to predict the species of the flowers using machine learning in Python. Let's see how it can be done.
So here we begin to go ahead and implement our Python code. And you'll find that the first half of our implementation is all about organizing and exploring the data coming in.
Let's go ahead and take this first step, which is loading the different modules into Python. And let's go ahead and put that in our favorite editor, whatever your favorite editor is.
In this case, I'm going to be using the Anaconda Jupyter Notebook, which is one of my favorites. Certainly there's Notepad
and Eclipse and dozens of others, or just even using the Python terminal window. Any of those will work just fine to go ahead and explore this Python coding. So here we go.
Let's go ahead and flip over to our Jupyter Notebook. And I've already opened up a new page for Python 3 code. And I'm just going to paste this right in there.
And let's take a look and see what we're bringing into our Python. The first thing we're going to do is from the sklearn.datasets, import load iris.
Now this isn't the actual data, this is just the module that allows us to bring in the data, the load iris.
And the iris is so popular, it's been around since 1936 when Ronald Fisher published a paper on it. And they're measuring the different parts of the flower.
And based on those measurements, predicting what kind of flower it is.
And then if we're going to do a random forest classifier, we need to go ahead and import a random forest classifier from the sklearn module. So sklearn.ensemble, import random forest classifier.
And then we want to bring in two more modules. and these are probably the most commonly used modules in Python and data science with any of the other modules that we bring in.
And one is going to be pandas. We're going to import pandas as pd. PD is a common term used for pandas.
And pandas is basically creates a data format for us where when you create a pandas data frame, it looks like an Xscale spreadsheet.
And you'll see that in a minute when we start digging deeper into the code. Pandas just wonderful because it plays nice with all the other modules in there.
And then we have NumPy, which is our numbers python. And the numbers python allows us to do different mathematical sets on here.
We'll see right off the bat, we're going to take our np and we're going to go ahead and seed the randomness with it with zero. So np.random.seed is seeding that is zero.
This code doesn't actually show anything. We're going to go ahead and run it because I need to make sure I have all those loaded. And then let's take a look at the next module on here.
The next six slides, including this one, are all about exploring the data. Remember, I told you half of this is about looking at the data and getting it all set.
So let's go ahead and take this code right here, the script, and let's get that over into our Jupyter notebook. And here we go. We've gone ahead and run the imports.
And I'm going to paste the code down here.
And let's take a look and see what's going on. The first thing we're doing is we're actually loading the iris data.
And if you remember up here, we loaded the module that tells it how to get the iris data. Now we're actually assigning that data to the variable iris.
And then we're going to go ahead and use the DF to define data frame.
And that's going to equal PD. And if you remember that's pandas as pd, so that's our pandas.
And panda data frame. And then we're looking at iris data and columns equals iris feature names.
And we're going to do the DF head. And let's run this so you can understand what's going on here.
The first thing you want to notice is that our DF has created what looks like an Excel spreadsheet.
And in this Excel spreadsheet, we have set the columns.
So up on the top you can see the four different columns, and then we have the data, iris.data down below. It's a little confusing without knowing where this data is coming from.
So let's look at the bigger picture, and I'm gonna go print. I'm just gonna change this for a moment.
And we're gonna print all of iris and see what that looks like.
So when I print all of iris, I get this long list of information.
And you can scroll through here and see all the different titles on there.
What's important to notice is that first off there's a brackets at the beginning. So this is a Python dictionary.
And in a Python dictionary, you'll have a key or a label, and this label pulls up whatever information comes after it.
So feature names, which we actually used over here under columns, is equal to an array of sepal length, sepal width, pedal length,
pedal width. These are the different names they have for the four different columns. And if you scroll down far enough, you'll also see data down here. Oh goodness, it came up right towards the top.
And data is equal to the different data we're looking at.
Now there's a lot of other things in here like target, we're going to be pulling that up in a minute, and there's also the names,
the target names, which is further down, and we'll show you that also in a minute.
Let's go ahead and set that back
to the head.
And this is one of the neat features of pandas and panda data frames.
Is when you do df.head or the pandadata frame.head, it'll print the first five lines of the data set in there,
along with the headers if you have it. In this case we have the column headers set to iris features.
And in here you'll see that we have 01234. In Python, most arrays always start at zero. So when you look at the first five, it's going to be zero one two three four, not one, two, three, four, five.
So now we've got our iris data imported into a data frame. Let's take a look at the next piece of code in here.
And so in this section here of the code, we're going to take a look at the target.
And let's go ahead and get this into our notebook, this piece of code, so we can discuss it a little bit more in detail.
So here we are in our Jupyter notebook. I'm going to put the code in here.
And before I run it, I want to look at a couple things going on. So we have uh df species, and this is interesting because right here you'll see where I have df species in brackets,
which is the key code for creating another column. And here we have iris.target. Now these are both in the pandas setup on here. So in pandas we can do either one.
I could have just as easily done iris and then in brackets target, depending on what I'm working on. Both are acceptable.
Let's go ahead and run this code and see how this changes. And what we've done is we've added the target from the iris data set as another column on the end.
Now, what species is, this is what we're trying to predict.
So we have our data, which tells us the answer for all these different pieces, and then we've added a column with the answer.
That way, when we do our final setup, we'll have the ability to program our neural network to look for these this different data and know what a Setosa
is, or a Vera color, which we'll see in just a minute, or Virginica. Those are the three that are in there. And now we're going to add one more column.
I know we're organizing all this data over and over again. It's kind of fun. There's a lot of ways to organize it.
What's nice about putting everything onto one data frame is I can then do a printout and it shows me exactly what I'm looking at.
And I'll show you where you can where that's different, where you can alter that and do it slightly differently. But let's go ahead and put this into our script up to depth.
And here we go, we're going to put that down here.
And we're going to run that.
And let's talk a little bit about what we're doing. Now we're exploring data, and one of the challenges is knowing how good your model is. Did your model work?
And to do this, we need to split the data. And we split it into two different parts. They usually call it the training and the testing.
And so in here, we're going to go ahead and put that in our database so you can see it clearly.
And we've set it df, and remember you can put brackets, this is creating another column, is train, so we're going to use part of it for training, and this equals np,
remember that stands for numpy, dot random dot uniform. So we're generating a random number between zero and one, and we're going to do it for each of the rows. That's where the length df comes from.
So each row gets a generated number, and if it's less than 0.75, it's true, and if it's greater than 0.75, it's false.
This means we're going to take 75% of the data, roughly, because there's a randomness involved, and we're going to use that to train it, and then the other 25%
we're going to hold off to the side and use that to test it later on. So let's flip back on over and see what the next step is.
So now that we've labeled our database for which is training and which is testing, let's go ahead and sort that into two different variables,
train and test. And let's take this code and let's bring it into our project. And here we go, let's paste it on down here. And before I run this, let's just take a quick look of what's going on here.
Is we have up above, we created, remember there's our def.head, which prints the first five rows, and we've added a column is train at the end.
And so we're going to take that, we're going to create two variables.
We're going to create two new data frames. One's called train, one's called test, 75% in train, 25% in test,
and then to sort that out.
We're going to do that by doing DF, our main original data frame with the iris data in it. And if DF is train equals true, that's going to go in the train.
And if df is train equals false, it goes in the test.
And so when I run this, we're going to print out the number in each one. Let's see what that looks like.
And you'll see that it puts 118 in the training module and it puts 32 in the testing module, which lets us know that there was 150 lines of data in here.
So if you went and looked at the original data, you could see that there's 150 lines. And that's roughly 75% in one and 25% for us to test our model on afterward.
So let's jump back to our code and see where this goes. In the next two steps, we want to do one more thing with our data, and that's make it readable to humans.
I don't know about you, but I hate looking at zeros and ones. So let's start with the features, and let's go ahead and take those and make those readable to humans, and let's put that in our code.
Let's see, here we go, paste it in. And you'll see here we've done a couple very basic things. We know that the columns in our data frame, again, this is a panda thing, the DF columns.
And we know the first four of them, 0, 1, 2, 3, that'd be the first four, are going to be the features or the titles of those columns. And so when I run this,
you'll see down here that it creates an index, sepa length, sepa width, petal length, and petal width.
And this should be familiar, because if you look up here, here's our column titles going across, and here's the first four.
One thing I want you to notice here is that when you're in a command line, whether it's Jupyter Notebook or you're running command line in the terminal window,
if you just put the name of it, it'll print it out. This is the same as doing print
features.
And the shorthand is you just put features in here.
If you're actually writing a code and saving the script and running it by remote, you really need to put the print in there.
But for this, when I run it, you'll see it gives me the same thing.
But for this, we want to go ahead and we'll just leave it as features, because it doesn't really matter.
And this is one of the fun thing about Jupyter Notebooks is I'm just building the code as we go. And then we need to go ahead and create the labels for the other part.
So let's take a look and see what that.
For our final step in prepping our data, before we actually start running the training and the testing, is we're going to go ahead and convert the species
on here into something the computer understands. So let's put this code into our script and see where that takes us.
Alright, here we go. We've set y equal to pd.factorize, train species of zero. So let's break this down just a little bit. We have our pandas right here, pd, factorize.
What's factorize doing? I'm going to come back to that in just a second.
Let's look at what train species is and why we're looking at the group zero on there.
And let's go up here and here is our species.
Remember this? We created this whole column here for species.
And then it has setosa, setosa, setosa, setosa, and if you scroll down enough, you'd also see Virginica and Vera color.
We need to convert that into something the computer understands, zeros and ones.
So the train species of zero, because this is in the format of an array of arrays, so you have to have the zero on the end. And then species is just that column.
Factorize goes in there and looks at the fact that there's only three of them.
So when I run this, you'll see that y generates an array that's equal to, in this case, it's the training set, and it's zeros,
ones, and twos representing the three different kinds of flowers we have.
So now we have something the computer understands and we have a nice table that we can read and understand. And now finally we get to actually start doing the predicting. So here we go.
We have two lines of code. Oh my goodness, that was a lot of work to get to two lines of code. But there is a lot in these two lines of code.
So let's take a look and see what's going on here and put this into our full script that we're running.
And let's paste this in here. And let's take a look and see what this is. We have we're creating a variable CLF and we're going to set this equal to the random forest classifier.
And we're passing two variables in here, and there's a lot of variables you can play with. As far as these two are concerned, they're very standard.
in jobs, all that does is to prioritize it. Not something to really worry about. Usually when you're doing this on your own computer, you do n jobs equals two.
If you're working in a larger or big data and you need to prioritize it differently, this is what that number does is it changes your priorities and how it's going to run across the system
and things like that. And then the random state is just how it starts.
Zero is fine for here.
But let's go ahead and run this.
We also have clf.fit train features, comma y. And before we run it, let's talk about this a little bit more. CLF.fit. So we're fitting, we're training it.
We are actually creating our random forest classifier right here. This is the code that does everything. And we're going to take our training set. Remember, we kept our test off to the side.
And we're going to take our training set with the features. And then we're going to go ahead and put that in. And here's our target, the Y. So the Y is 0, 1, and 2 that we just created.
And the features is the actual data going in that we put into the training set. And let's go ahead and run that.
And this is kind of an interesting thing because it printed out the random forest classifier
and everything around it.
And so when you're running this in your terminal window or in a script like this, this automatically treats this like just like when we were up here
and I typed in Y and it printed out Y instead of print y.
This does the same thing.
It treats this as a variable and prints it out. But if you're actually running your code, that wouldn't be the case. And what is printed out is it shows us all the different variables we can change.
And if we go down here, you can actually see in jobs equals two.
You can see the random state equals zero. Those are the two that we sent in there. You would really have to dig deep to find out all these different meanings of all these different settings on here.
Some of them are self-explanatory if you kind of think about it a little bit, like max features is auto.
So all the features that we're putting in there is just going to automatically take all four of them. Whatever we send it, it'll take.
Some of them might have so many features because you're processing words.
There might be like 1.4 million features in there because you're doing legal documents and that's how many different words are in there.
At that point, you probably want to limit the maximum features that you're going to process.
And leaf nodes, that's the end nodes. Remember, we had the fruit and we're talking about the leaf nodes. Like I said, there's a lot in this. We're looking at a lot of stuff here.
So you might have in this case, there's probably only think three leaf nodes, maybe four.
You might have thousands of leaf nodes, at which point you do need to put a cap on that and say, okay, you can only go so far, and then we're going to use all of our resources on processing this.
And that really is what most of these are about is limiting the process and making sure we don't overwhelm a system. And there's some other settings in here.
Again, we're not going to go over all of them. Warm start equals false. Warm start is if you're programming it one piece at a time externally.
Since we're not, we're not going to have like we're not going to continually to train this particular learning tree.
And again, like I said, there's a lot of things in here that you'll want to look up more detail from the SK learn. And if you're digging in deep and running a major project on here.
For today, though, all we need to do is fit or train our features and our target Y. So now we have our training model.
What's next? If we're going to create a model,
we now need to test it. Remember we set aside the test feature, test group, 25% of the data. So let's go ahead and take this code and let's put it into our script and see what that looks like.
Okay, here we go.
And we're going to run this.
And it's going to come out with a bunch of zeros, ones, and twos, which represents the three type of flowers the Setosa, the Virginica, and the versicolor.
And what we're putting into our predict is the test features.
And I always kind of like to know what it is I am looking at. So, real quick, we're going to do test
features.
And remember, features is an array
of sepal length, sepal width, pedal length, pedal width. So when we put it in this way, it actually loads all these different columns that we loaded into features.
So if we did just features, let me just do features in here so you can see what features looks like. This is just playing with Panda's data frames. You'll see that it's an index.
So when you put an index in like this
into test features, into test, it then takes those columns and creates a panda data frames from those columns. And in this case,
we're going to go ahead and put those into our predict.
So we're going to put each one of these lines of data, the 5.0, 3.4, 1.5, 0.2, and we're going to put those in and we're going to predict what
our new forest classifier is going to come up with. And this is what it predicts. It predicts 0001211222. And
again, this is the flower type, Satosha, Virginica, and VersaColor. So now that we've taken our test features, let's explore that. Let's see exactly what that data means to us.
So the first thing we can do with our predicts is we can actually generate a different prediction model.
When I say different, we're going to view it differently.
It's not that the data itself is different. So let's take this next piece of code and put it into our script.
So we're pasting it in here, and you'll see that we're doing predict and we've added underscore proba for probability.
So there's our clf.predict probability. So we're running it just like we ran it up here, but this time with this, we're going to get a slightly different result.
And we're only going to look at the first ten.
So you'll see down here, instead of looking at all of them, which was what 27, you'll see right down here that this generates a much larger field on the probability.
And let's take a look and see what that looks like and what that means.
So when we do the predict underscore proba for probability, it generates three numbers. So we had three leaf nodes at the end. And if you remember from all the theory we did, this is the predictors.
The first one is predicting a one for Setosa, it predicts a zero for Virginica, and it predicts a zero for Versicolor,
and so on and so on and so on. And let's you know what, I'm going to change this just a little bit.
Let's look at ten
to 20 just because we can.
And we start to get a little different of data, and you'll see right down here, it gets to this one, this line right here.
And this line has zero, zero five, zero five.
And so if we're going to vote, and we have two equal votes, it's going to go with the first one.
So it says uh Setosa gets zero votes, Virginica gets 0.5 votes, VersaColor gets 0.5 votes, but let's just go with the Virginica since these two are equal,
and so on and so on down the list. You can see how they vary on here.
So now we've looked at both how to do a basic predict of the features, and we've looked at the predict probability. Let's see what's next on here.
So now we want to go ahead and start mapping names for the plants.
We want to attach names so that it makes a little more sense for us. And that's what we're going to do in these next two steps.
We're going to start by setting up our predictions and mapping them to the names. So let's see what that looks like.
And let's go ahead and paste that code in here and run it.
And this goes along with the next piece of code. So we'll skip through this quickly and then come back to it a little bit. So here's iris.target names.
And uh if you remember correctly, this was the the names that we've been talking about this whole time the Satosha, Virginica, VersaColor. And then we're gonna go ahead and do the prediction again.
We've run it, we could have just set a variable equal to this instead of rerunning it each time. But we're going ahead and run it again, clf.predict test features.
Remember that returns the zeros, the ones, and the twos.
And then we're going to set that equal to predictions. So this time we're actually putting it in a variable, and when I run this,
it distributes and it comes out as an array, and the array is setosa, setosa, setosa, setosa, setosa. We're only looking at the first five.
We could actually do, let's do the first 25 just so we can see a little bit more on there.
And you'll see that it starts mapping it to all the different flower types, the Versicolor and the Virginica in there. And let's see how this goes with the next one.
So let's take a look at the top part of our species in here, and we'll take this code and put it in our script.
And let's put that down here and paste it. There we go, and we'll go ahead and run it.
And let's talk about both these sections of code here and how they go together. The first one is our predictions. And I went ahead and did predictions through 25, let's just do five.
And so we have setosa, setosa, setosa, setosa. That's what we're predicting from our test model.
And then we come down here and we look at test species. And remember I could have just done test.species head, and you'll see it says setosa, setosa, setosa, setosa, and they match.
So the first one is what our forest is doing, and the second one is what the actual data is. Now, we need to combine these so that we can understand what that means.
We need to know how good our forest is, how good it is at predicting the features. So that's where we come up to the next step, which is lots of fun.
We're going to use a single line of code to combine our predictions and our actuals so we have a nice chart to look at. And let's go ahead and put that in our script in our Jupyter notebook here.
Let's see, let's go ahead and paste that in. And then I'm gonna because I'm on the Jupyter Notebook, I can do a control minus so you can see the whole line there.
There we go, resize it.
And let's take a look and see what's going on here.
We're going to create in pandas, remember PD stands for pandas, and we're doing a cross tab. This function takes two sets of data and creates a chart out of them.
So when I run it, you'll get a nice chart down here, and we have the predicted species.
So across the top you'll see the Setosa versicolor virginica and the actual species, Setosa versicolor virginica.
And so the way to read this chart, and let's go ahead and take a look on how to read this chart here.
When you read this chart, you have Setosa where they meet, you have Versicolor where they meet, and you have Virginica where they meet. And they're meeting where the actual and the predicted agree.
So this is the number of accurate predictions. So in this case it equals 30. If you add 13 plus 5 plus 12, you get 30.
And then we notice here where it says Virginica, but it was supposed to be versicolor. This is inaccurate.
So now we have two, two inaccurate predictions and 30 accurate predictions.
So we'll say that the model accuracy is 93.
That's just 30 divided by 32. And if we multiply it by 100, we can say that it is 93% accurate. So we have a 93% accuracy with our model.
I did want to add one more quick thing in here on our scripting before we wrap it up. So let's flip back on over to my script.
In here, we're going to take this line of code from up above.
I don't know if you remember it, but predicts equals the iris.target underscore names.
So we're going to map it to the names, and we're going to run the prediction, and we read it on test features.
But you know, we're not just testing it, we want to actually deploy it. So at this point, I would go ahead and change this, and this is an array of arrays.
This is really important when you're running these to know that.
So you need the double brackets, and I could actually create data, maybe let's let's just do two flowers. So maybe I'm processing more data coming in, and we'll put two flowers in here.
And then I actually want to see what the answer is.
So let's go ahead and type in preds and print that out. And when I run this, you'll see that I've now predicted two flowers that maybe I measured in my front yard as versicolor and versicolor.
Not surprising since I put the same data in for each one.
This would be the actual end product going out to be used on data that you don't know the answer for.
So that's going to conclude our scripting part of this. Introducing Naive Bayes Classifier.
Have you ever wondered how your mail provider implements spam filtering, or how online news channels perform news text classification,
or how companies perform sentimental analysis of their audience on social media. All of this and more is done through a machine learning algorithm called Naive Bayes Classifier.
Welcome to Naive Bayes Tutorial. My name is Richard Kirshner.
I'm with the Simply Learn team. That's www.simplylearn.com. Get certified, get ahead.
What's in it for you? We'll start with what is Naive Bayes, a basic overview of how it works.
We'll get into Naive Bayes and machine learning, where it fits in with our other machine learning tools, why do we need naive Bayes?
And understanding Naive Bayes classifier, a much more in-depth of how the math works in the background.
Finally, we'll get into the advantages of the naive Bayes classifier in the machine learning setup.
And then we'll roll up our sleeves and do my favorite part.
We'll actually do some Python coding and do some text classification using the Naive Bayes.
What is Naive Bayes?
Let's start with a basic introduction to the Bayes theorem, named after Thomas Bayes from the 1700s, who first coined this in the Western literature.
Naive Bayes classifier works on the principle of conditional probability as given by the Bayes theorem.
Before we move ahead, let us go through some of the simple concepts in the probability that we will be using.
Let us consider the following example of tossing two coins.
Here we have two quarters, and if we look at all the different possibilities of what they can come up as, we get that they can come up as head heads, they can come up as head tell,
tell head, and tell tell. When doing the math on probability, we usually denote probability as a P, a capital P.
So the probability of getting two heads equals one fourth. You can see on our data set we have two heads, and this occurs once out of the four possibilities.
And then the probability of at least one tell occurs three quarters of the time.
You'll see on three of the coin tosses we have tells in them.
And out of four, that's three fourths. And then the probability of the second coin being a head given the first coin is tell, is one half.
And the probability of getting two heads given the first coin is a head is one half. We'll demonstrate that in just a minute and show you how that math works.
Now when we're doing it with two coins, it's easy to see. But when you have something more complex, you can see where these pro these formulas really come in and work.
So the Bayes theorem gives us the conditional probability of an event A given another event B has occurred.
In this case, the first coin toss will be B and the second coin toss A.
This can be confusing because we've actually reversed the order of them and go from B to A instead of A to B. You'll see this a lot when you work in probabilities.
The reason is we're looking for event A. We want to know what that is, so we're going to label that A since that's our focus. And then given another event B has occurred.
In the Bayes theorem, as you can see on the left, the probability of A occurring given B has occurred equals the probability of B occurring given A has occurred
times the probability of A over the probability of B. This simple formula can be moved around just like any algebra formula.
And we could do the probability of A after a given B times probability of B equals the probability of B given A times probability of A.
You can easily move that around and multiply it and divide it out.
Let us apply Bayes' theorem to our example.
Here we have our two quarters, and we'll notice that the first two probabilities of getting two heads and at least one tail we compute directly off the data.
So you can easily see that we have one example, H H out of four, one fourth, and we have three with tels in them, giving us three quarters, or three fourths,
75%.
The second condition, the second set, three and four, we're going to explore a little bit more in detail.
Now we stick to a simple example with two coins because you can easily understand the math. The probability of throwing a tell doesn't matter what comes before it, and the same with the head.
So it's still going to be 50% or one half. But when that probability gets more complicated, let's say you have a D6 dice or some other instance, then this formula really comes in handy.
But let's stick to the simple example for now. In this sample space, let A be the event that the second coin is head and b be the event that the first coin is tells.
Again, we reversed it because we want to know what the second event is going to be. So we're going to be focusing on A. And we write that out as the probability of A given B.
And we know this from our formula that that equals the probability of B given A times the probability of A over the probability of B.
And when we plug that in, we plug in the probability of the first coin being tells given the second coin is heads,
and the probability of the second coin being heads given the first coin being over the probability of the first coin being tells.
When we plug that data in, and we have the probability of the first coin being tells given the second coin is heads, times the probability of the second coin being heads
over the probability of the first coin being tails. You can see it's a simple formula to calculate.
We have one half times one half over one half, or one half equals 0.5, or one fourth.
So the Bayes theorem basically calculates the conditional probability of the occurrence of an event based on prior knowledge of conditions that might be related to the event.
We will explore this in detail when we take up an example of online shopping further in this tutorial. Understanding naive Bayes and machine learning.
Like with any of our other machine learning tools, it's important to understand where the naive Bayes fits in the hierarchy.
So under the machine learning, we have supervised learning, and there is other things like unsupervised learning. There's also a reward system.
This falls under the supervised learning.
And then under the supervised learning, there's classification. There's also regression, but we're going to be in the classification side.
And then under classification is your naive Bayes.
Let's go ahead and glance into where is Naive Bayes used. Let's look at some of the use scenarios for it.
As a classifier, we use it in face recognition.
Is this Cindy or is it not Cindy or whoever? Or it might be used to identify parts of the face that they then feed into another part of the face recognition program.
This is the eye, this is the nose, this is the mouth.
Weather prediction, is it going to be rainy or sunny? Medical recognition.
News prediction.
It's also used in medical diagnosis. We might diagnose somebody as either as high risk or not as high risk for cancer or heart disease or other ailments.
And news classification.
You look at the Google News and it says, well, is this political or is this world news? Or a lot of that's all done with a naive Bayes.
Understanding naive Bayes classifier.
Now we already went through a basic understanding with the coins and the two heads and two tails and head tail, tailheads, etc.
We're going to do just a quick review on that and remind you that the naive Bayes classifier is based on the Bayes theorem, which gives a conditional probability of
event A given event B.
And that's where the probability of A given B equals the probability of B given A times probability of A over probability of B.
Remember this is an algebraic function, so we can move these different entities around.
We can multiply by the probability of B, so it goes to the left hand side, and then we could divide by the probability of A given B,
and just as easily come up with a new formula for the probability of B.
To me, staring at these algebraic functions kind of gives me a slight headache. It's a lot better to see if we can actually understand how this data fits together in a table.
And let's go ahead and start applying it to some actual data so you can see what that looks like.
So we're going to start with the shopping demo.
Problem statement. And remember, we're going to solve this first in table form so you can see what the math looks like. And then we're going to solve it in Python.
And in here, we want to predict whether the person will purchase a product. Are they going to buy or don't buy?
Very important if you're running a business, you want to know how to maximize your profits or at least maximize the purchase of the people coming into your store.
And we're going to look at a specific combination of different variables. In this case, we're going to look at the day, the discount, and the free delivery.
And you can see here under the day we want to know whether it's on the weekday.
You know, somebody's working, they come in after work, or maybe they don't work.
Weekend, you can see the bright colors coming down there, celebrating not being in work, or holiday.
And did we offer a discount that day? Yes or no. Did we offer free delivery that day? Yes or no.
And from this, we want to know whether the person's going to buy based on these traits so we can maximize them and find out the best system for getting somebody to come in and
purchase our goods and products from our store.
Now, having a nice visual is great, but we do need to dig into the data.
So let's go ahead and take a look at the data set. We have a small sample data set of 30 rows.
We're showing you the first 15 of those rows for this demo.
Now, the actual data file you can request, just type in below under the comments on the YouTube video, and we'll send you some more information and send you that file.
As you can see here, the file is very simple columns and rows. We have the day, the discount, the free delivery, and did the person purchase or not.
And then we have under the day, whether it was a weekday, a holiday, was it the weekend?
This is a pretty simple set of data, and long before computers, people used to look at this data and calculate this all by hand.
So let's go ahead and walk through this and see what that looks like when we put that into tables.
Also note in today's world, we're not usually looking at three different variables in 30 rows.
Nowadays, because we're able to collect data so much, we're usually looking at 27, 30 variables across hundreds of rows.
The first thing we want to do is we're going to take this data and based on the data set containing our three inputs, day, discount, and free delivery,
we're going to go ahead and populate that to frequency tables for each attribute.
So we want to know if they had a discount, how many people buy and did not buy.
Did they have a discount? Yes or no.
Do we have a free delivery? Yes or no. On those days, how many people made a purchase and how many people didn't? And the same with the three days of the week. Was it a weekday, a weekend, a holiday?
And did they buy, yes or no?
As we dig in deeper to this table for our Bayes theorem, let the event buy be A. Now remember when we looked at the coins, I said we really want to know what the outcome is.
Did the person buy or not?
And that's usually event A is what you're looking for. And the independent variables discount free delivery and day be B.
So we'll call that probability of B.
Now let us calculate the likelihood table for one of the variables.
Let's start with day, which includes weekday, weekend, and holiday. And let us start by summing all of our rows.
So we have the weekday row, and out of the weekdays, there's nine plus two, so it's 11 weekdays, there's eight weekend days, and 11 holidays.
Wow, that's a lot of holidays. And then we want to sum up the total number of days. So we're looking at a total of 30 days.
Let's start pulling some information from our chart and see where that takes us.
And when we fill in the chart on the right, you can see that nine out of 24 purchases are made on the weekday, 7 out of 24 purchases on the weekend,
and 8 out of 24 purchases on a holiday.
And out of all the people who come in, 24 out of 30 purchase. You can also see how many people do not purchase.
On the weekday, it's two out of six didn't purchase, and so on and so on.
We can also look at the totals, and you'll see on the right we put together some of the formulas. The probability of making a purchase on the weekend comes out 11 out of 30.
So out of the 30 people who came into the store throughout the weekend, weekday, and holiday, 11 of those purchases were made on the weekday.
And then you can also see the probability of them not making a purchase.
And this is done for doesn't matter which day of the week.
So we call that probability of no buy would be six over 30 or point two. So there's a 20% chance that they're not going to make a purchase no matter what day of the week it is.
And finally we look at the probability of BFA.
In this case, we're going to look at the probability of the weekday and not buying.
Two of the no buys were done out of the weekend out of the six people who did not make purchases.
So when we look at that, the probability of the weekday without a purchase is going to be 0.33 or 33%.
Let's take a look at this at different probabilities.
And based on this likelihood table, let's go ahead and calculate conditional probabilities as below.
The first three we just did, the probability of making a purchase on the weekday is 11 out of 30, or roughly 36 or 37%, 0.367.
The probability of not making a purchase at all, doesn't matter what day of the week, is roughly 0.2 or 20%.
And the probability of a weekday no purchase is roughly two out of six. So two out of six of our no purchases were made on the weekday.
And then finally we take our P of AB.
If you lucked, we've kept the symbols up there. We got P of probability of B, probability of A, probability of B if A.
We should remember that the probability of A if B is equal to the first one times the probability of no per
buys over the probability of the weekday.
So we could calculate it both off the table we created. We can also calculate this by the formula and we get the 0.367, which equals or 0.33 times 0.2 over 0.367,
which equals 0.179, or roughly 17 to 18 percent.
And that'd be the probability of no purchase done on the weekday.
And this is important because we can look at this and say, as the probability of buying on the weekday is more than the probability of not buying on the weekday,
we can conclude that customers will most likely buy the product on a weekday.
Now we've kept our chart simple and we're only looking at one aspect, so you should be able to look at the table and come up with the same information or the same conclusion.
That should be kind of intuitive at this point.
Next, we can take the same setup.
We have the frequency tables of all three independent variables. Now we can construct the likelihood tables for all three of the variables we're working with.
We can take our day like we did before, we have weekday, weekend, and holiday, we filled in this table. And then we can come in and also do that for the discount, yes or no. Did they buy, yes or no?
And we fill in that full table. So now we have our probabilities for a discount and whether the discount leads to a purchase or not, and the probability for free delivery.
Does that lead to a purchase or not?
And this is where it starts getting really exciting.
Let us use these three likelihood tables to calculate whether a customer will purchase a product on a specific combination of day, discount, and free delivery
or not purchase.
Here, let us take a combination of these factors.
Day equals holiday, discount equals yes, free delivery equals yes.
Let's dig deeper into the math and actually see what this looks like.
And we're going to start with looking for the probability of them not purchasing on the following combinations of days. We're actually looking for the probability of A equal no buy, no purchase.
And our probability of B we're going to set equal to is it a holiday? Did they get a discount? Yes.
And was it a free delivery? Yes.
Before we go further, let's look at the original equation.
The probability of A if B equals the probability of B given the condition A and the probability times probability of A over the probability of B occurring.
Now this is basic algebra, so we can multiply this information together.
So when you see the probability of A given B, in this case the condition is B, C, and D or the three different variables we're looking at.
And when you see the probability of B, that would be the conditions. We're actually going to multiply those three separate conditions out.
Probability of, you'll see that in just a second in the formula, times the full probability of A over the full probability of B.
So here we are back to this, and we're gonna have let a equal no purchase. And we're looking for the probability of B on the condition A, where A sets for three different things.
Remember that equals the probability of A given the condition B.
And in this case we just multiply those three different variables together.
So we have the probability of the discount times the probability of free delivery times the probability is the day equal a holiday.
Those are our three variables of the probability of A if B.
And then that is going to be multiplied by the probability of them not making a purchase.
And then we want to divide that by the total probabilities, and they're multiplied together.
So we have the probability of a discount, the probability of a free delivery, and the probability of it being on a holiday.
When we plug those numbers in, we see that one out of six were no purchase on a discounted day, two out of six were a no purchase on a free delivery day,
and three out of six were a no purchase on a holiday.
Those are our three probabilities of A of B multiplied out. And then that has to be multiplied by the probability of a no purchase.
And remember the probability of a no buy is across all the data.
So that's where we get the six out of 30.
We divide that out by the probability of each category over the total number. So we get the 20 out of 30 had a discount, 23 out of 30 had a yes for free delivery, and 11 out of 30 were on a holiday.
We plug all those numbers in, we get 0.178.
So in our probability math, we have a 0.178 if it's a no-buy for a holiday, a discount, and a free delivery.
Let's turn that around and see what that looks like if we have a purchase.
I promise this is the last page of math before we dig into the Python script.
So here we're calculating the probability of the purchase using the same math we did to find out if they didn't buy.
Now we want to know if they did buy. And again, we're going to go by the day equals a holiday, discount equals yes, free delivery equals yes, and let a equal buy.
Now, right about now you might be asking, why are we doing both calculations?
Why would we want to know the no buys and buys for the same data going in?
Well, we're going to show you that in just a moment, but we have to have both of those pieces of information so that we can figure it out as a percentage as opposed to a probability equation.
And we'll get to that normalization here in just a moment.
Let's go ahead and walk through this calculation.
And as you can see here, the probability of A on the condition of B, B being all three categories, did we have a discount with a purchase? Did we have a free delivery with a purchase?
And did we is a day equal to holiday?
And when we plug this all into that formula and multiply it all out, we get our probability of a discount, probability of a free delivery, probability of the day being a holiday,
times the overall probability of it being a purchase divided by, again, multiplying the three variables, out, the full probability of there being a discount,
the full probability of being a free delivery, and the full probability of there being a day equal holiday. And that's where we get this 19 over 24 times 21 over 24 times 8 over 24 times.
the P of A, 24 over 30, divided by the probability of the discount, the free delivery times the day, or 20 over 30,
23 over 30 times 11 over 30. and that gives us our 0.986.
So what are we going to do with these two pieces of data we just generated?
Well, let's go ahead and go over them. We have a probability of purchase equals 0.986.
We have a probability of no purchase equals 0.178.
So finally we have a conditional probabilities of purchase on this day.
Let us take that, we're going to normalize it, and we're going to take these probabilities and turn them into percentages.
This is simply done by taking the sum of probabilities, which equals 0.98686 plus 0.178, and that equals the 1.164. If we divide each probability by the sum, we get the percentage.
And so the likelihood of a purchase is 84.71%, and the likelihood of no purchase is 15.29%
given these three different variables.
So if it's on a holiday, if it's with a discount and has free delivery, then there's an 84.71% chance that the customer is going to come in and make a purchase. Hooray! They purchased our stuff.
We're making money. If you're owning a shop, that's like is the bottom line is you want to make some money so that you can keep your shop open and have a living.
Now, I promised you that we were going to be finishing up the math here with a few pages. So we're going to move on and we're going to do two steps.
The first step is I want you to understand why.
You want to under why you want to use the naive Bayes. What are the advantages of naive Bayes?
And then once we understand those advantages, we'll just look at that briefly, then we're going to dive in and do some Python coding.
Advantages of Naive Bayes classifier.
So let's take a look at the six advantages of the naive Bayes classifier. And we're going to walk around this lovely wheel. It looks like an origami folded paper.
The first one is very simple and easy to implement.
Certainly, you could walk through the tables and do this by hand. You've got to be a little careful because the notations can get confusing.
You have all these different probabilities, and I certainly mess those up as I put them on, you know, is it on the top or the bottom? You've got to really pay close attention to that.
When you put it into Python, it's really nice because you don't have to worry about any of that. You let the Python handle that, the Python module.
But understanding it, you can put it on a table and you can easily see how it works, and it's a simple algebraic function.
It needs less training data.
So if you have smaller amounts of data, this is a great, powerful tool for that.
Handles both continuous and discrete data.
It's highly scalable with number of predictors and data points.
So as you can see, you just keep multiplying different probabilities in there, and you can cover not just three different variables or sets. You can now expand this to even more categories.
Number five, it's fast. It can be used in real-time predictions. This is so important.
This is why it's used in a lot of our predictions on online shopping carts, referrals, spam filters, is because there's no time delay as it has to go through and figure out a neural network
or one of the other mini setups where you're doing classification.
And certainly there's a lot of other tools out there in the machine learning that can handle these, but most of them are not as fast as the naive Bayes.
And then finally, it's not sensitive to irrelevant features.
So it picks up on your different probabilities, and if you're short on data on one probability, you can kind of it automatically adjust for that.
Those formulas are very automatic, and so you can still get a very solid predictability, even if you're missing data or you have overlapping data for two completely different areas.
We see that a lot in doing census and studying of people and habits, where they might have one study that covers one aspect, another one that overlaps, and because the two overlap,
they can then predict the unknowns for the group that they haven't done the second study on, or vice versa.
So it's very powerful in that it is not sensitive to the irrelevant features, and in fact, you can use it to help predict features that aren't even in there.
So now we're down to my favorite part. We're going to roll up our sleeves and do some actual programming. We're going to do the use case text classification.
Now I would challenge you to go back and send us a note on the notes below underneath the video and request the data for the shopping cart.
So you can plug that into Python code and do that on your own time so you can walk through it since we walked through all the information on it.
But we're going to do a Python code doing text classification, very popular for doing the naive Bayes.
So we're going to use our new tool to perform a text classification of news headlines and classify news into different topics for a news website.
As you can see here, we have a nice image of the Google news and then related on the right, subgroups. I'm not sure where they actually pulled the actual data we're going to use from.
It's one of the standard sets, but certainly this can be used on any of our news headlines and classification.
So let's see how it can be done using the naive Bayes classifier. Now we're at my favorite part. We're actually going to write some Python script. Roll up our sleeves.
And we're going to start by doing our imports. These are very basic imports, including our news group, and we'll take a quick glance at the target names.
Then we're going to go ahead and start training our data set and putting it together. We'll put together a nice graph because it's always good to have a graph to show what's going on.
And once we've trained it and we've shown you a graph of what's going on, then we're going to explore how to use it and see what that looks like.
Now I'm going to open up my favorite editor or inline editor for Python.
You don't have to use this, you can use whatever your editor that you like, whatever interface, IDE you want. This just happens to be the Anaconda Jupyter Notebook.
And I'm going to paste that first piece of code in here so we can walk through it. let's make it a little bigger on the screen so you have a nice view of what's going on.
and we're using Python 3, in this case 3.5.
So this would work in any of your 3x.
If you have it set up correctly, it should also work in a lot of the 2x. You just have to make sure all of the versions of the modules match your Python version.
And in here, you'll notice the first line is your percentage matplot library inline.
Now, three of these lines of code are all about plotting the graph. This one lets the notebook notes and this is the inline setup that we want the graphs to show up on this page.
Without it, in a notebook like this, which is an explorer interface, it won't show up.
Now, a lot of IDEs don't require that.
A lot of them, like if I'm working on one of my other setups, it just has a pop-up and the graph pops up on there.
So you have that setup also. But for this, we want the mapplot library inline.
And then we're going to import numpy as np.
That's number python, which has a lot of different formulas in it that we use for both of our sklearn module.
And we also use it for any of the upper math functions in Python. And it's very common to see that as np, numpy as np.
The next two lines are all about our graphing.
Remember I said three of these were about graphing? Well, we need our mapplot library.pyplot as plt, and you'll see that plt is a very common setup, as is the SNS and just like the NP.
And we're going to import Cborne as SNS, and we're going to do the SNS.set.
Now, Cborne sits on top of pyplot, and it just makes a really nice heat map. It's really good for heat maps. And if you're not familiar with heat maps, that just means we give it a color scale.
The term comes from the brighter red it is, the hotter it is in some form of data, and you can set it to whatever you want. And we'll see that later on.
So you'll see that those three lines of code here are just importing the graph function so we can graph it.
And as a data scientist, you always want to graph your data and have some kind of visual.
It's really hard just to shove numbers in front of people and they look at it and it doesn't mean anything.
And then from the sklearn.data sets, we're going to import the fetch20 newsgroups.
Very common one for analyzing, tokenizing words and setting them up and exploring how the words work and how do you categorize different things when you're dealing with documents.
And then we set our data equal to fetch 20 newsgroups. So our data variable will have the data in it.
And we're going to go ahead and just print the target names, data.target names. And let's see what that looks like.
And you'll see here we have alt atheism, comp graphics, comp OSMS windows.misscellaneous. And it goes all the way down to talkpolitics.misscellaneous, talkreligion.misscellaneous.
These are the categories they've already assigned to this news group.
And it's called fetch 20 because you'll see there's I believe there's 20 different topics in here or 20 different categories as we scroll down.
Now we've gone through the 20 different categories and we're going to go ahead and start defining all the categories and set up our data.
So we're actually getting here, going to go ahead and get it, get the data all set up and take a look at our data.
And let's move this over to our Jupyter notebook and let's see what this code does.
First, we're going to set our categories. Now, if you noticed up here, I could have just as easily set this equal to data dot target underscore names because it's the same thing.
But we want to kind of spell it out for you so you can see the different categories.
It kind of makes it more visual so you can see what your data is looking like in the background.
Once we've created the categories, we're going to open up a train set.
So this training set of data is going to go into fetch 20 newsgroups and it's a subset in there called train and categories equals categories. So we're pulling out those categories that match.
And then if you have a train set, you should also have the testing set. We have test equals fetch 20 newsgroups, subset equals test, and categories equals categories.
Let's go down one size so it all fits on my screen.
There we go.
And just so we can really see what's going on, let's see what happens when we print out one part of that data.
So it creates train and under train it creates train.data and we're just going to look at data piece number five.
And let's go ahead and run that and see what that looks like.
And you can see when I print train dot data number five, under train, it prints out one of the articles. This is article number five. You can go through and read it on there.
And we can also go in here and change this to test, which should look identical because it's splitting the data up into different groups, train and test.
And we'll see test number five is a different article, but it's another article in here.
And maybe you're curious and you want to see just how many articles are in here. We could do length of train dot data.
And if we run that.
You'll see that the training data has 11,314 articles.
So we're not going to go through all those articles. That's a lot of articles.
But we can look at one of them just so you can see what kind of information is coming out of it and what we're looking at. And we'll just look at number five for today.
And here we have it rewording the Second Amendment IDs, VTT line 58, lines 58 in article, etc. And you can scroll all the way down and see all the different parts to there.
Now we've looked at it, and that's pretty complicated when you look at one of these articles to try to figure out how do you weight this.
If you look down here, we have different words and maybe the word from.
Well, from is probably in all the articles, so it's not going to have a lot of meaning as far as trying to figure out whether this article fits one of the categories or not.
So trying to figure out which category it fits in based on these words is where the challenge comes in.
Now that we've viewed our data, we're going to dive in and do the actual predictions. This is the actual naive Bayes.
And we're going to throw another model at you or another module at you here in just a second.
We can't go into too much detail, but it deals specifically working with words and text and what they call tokenizing those words.
So let's take this code and let's skip on over to our Jupyter notebook and walk through it.
And here we are in our Jupyter Notebook. Let's paste that in there.
And I can run this code right off the bat. It's not actually going to display anything yet, but it has a lot going on in here.
So at the top, we had the print module from the earlier one.
I didn't know why that was in there. So we're going to start by importing our necessary packages.
And from the SK LearnFeatures extraction.text, we're going to import TFIDF vectorizer.
I told you we're going to throw a module at you.
We can't go too much into the math behind this or how it works. You can look it up. The notation for the math is usually tf.idf.
And that's just a way of weighing the words. And it weighs the words based on how many times are used in a document, how many times or how many documents are used in.
And it's a well-used formula. that's been around for a while.
It's a little confusing to put this in here. But let's let it know that it just goes in there and weights the different words in the document for us. That way we don't have to wait.
And if you put a weight on it, if you remember I was talking about that up here earlier, if these are all emails, they probably all have the word from in them.
From probably has a very low weight. It has very little value in telling you what this document's about.
Same with words like in, in article, in articles, in cost of, un, maybe cost might, or where words like criminal,
weapons, destruction, these might have a heavier weight because they describe a little bit more what the article's doing. Well, how do you figure out all those weights in the different articles?
That's what this module does. That's what the TFIDF vectorizer is going to do for us.
And then we're going to import our sklearn.naibase, and that's our multinomial NB.
Multinomial Naive Bayes. Pretty easy to understand that, where that comes from. And then finally we have the Sky Learn pipeline import make pipeline.
Now the make pipeline is just a cool piece of code because we're going to take the information we get from the TFIDF vectorizer and we're going to pump that into
the multinomial NB. So a pipeline is just a way of organizing how things flow.
It's used commonly, you probably already guess what it is if you've done any businesses. They talk about the sales pipeline.
If you're on a work crew or project manager, you have your pipeline of information that's going through or your projects and what has to be done in what order.
That's all this pipeline is. We're going to take the TFID vectorizer and then we're going to push that into the multinomial NB.
Now we've designated that as the variable model.
We have our pipeline model.
And we're going to take that model, and this is just so elegant, this is done in just a couple lines of code.
Model.fit and we're going to fit the data and first the train data and then the train target.
Now the train data has the different articles in it.
You can see the one we were just looking at.
And the train dot target is what category they already categorize that that particular article as.
And what's happening here is the train data is going into the TFID vectorizer.
So when you have one of these articles, it goes in there, it weights all the words in there. So there's thousands of words with different weights on them.
I remember once running a model on this, and I literally had 2.4 million tokens go into this. So when you're dealing like large document bases, you can have a huge number of different words.
It then takes those words, gives them a weight, and then based on that weight, based on the words and the weights, and then puts that into the multinomial NB.
And once we go into our naive Bayes, We want to put the train target in there.
So the train data that's been mapped to the TFID vectorizer is now going through the multinomial in B, and then we're telling it, well, these are the answers.
These are the answers to the different documents. So this document that has all these words with these different weights from the first part is going to be whatever category it comes out of.
Maybe it's the talk show or the article on religion miscellaneous.
Once we fit that model, we can then take labels and we're going to set that equal to model.predict.
Most of the SKLearn use the term dot predict to let us know that we've now trained the model and now we want to get some answers.
And we're going to put our test data in there because our test data is the stuff we held off to the side.
We didn't train it on there and we don't know what's going to come up out of it. And we just want to find out how good our labels are. Do they match what they should be?
Now I've already run this through.
There's no actual output to it to show. This is just setting it all up.
This is just training our model, creating the labels so we can see how good it is, and then we move on to the next step to find out what happened.
To do this, we're going to go ahead and create a confusion matrix and a heat map.
So the confusion matrix, which is confusing just by its very name, is basically going to ask how confused is our answer?
Did it get it correct?
Or did it miss some things in there or have some missed labels?
And then we're going to put that on a heat map so we'll have some nice colors to look at to see how that plots out.
Let's go ahead and take this code and see how that take a walk through it and see what that looks like.
So back to our Jupyter notebook.
I'm going to put the code in there.
And let's go ahead and run that code.
Take it just a moment.
And remember we had the inline, that way my graph shows up on the inline here. And let's walk through the code and then we'll look at this and see what that means.
So make it a little bit bigger.
There we go.
No reason not to use the whole screen.
Too big.
So we have here from SKLearn Metrics import confusion matrix.
And that's just going to generate a set of data that says I the prediction was such the actual truth was either agreed with it or is something different.
And it's going to add up those numbers so we can take a look and just see how well it worked. And we're going to set a variable mat equal to confusion matrix.
We have our test target, our test data that was not part of the training.
Very important in data science, we always keep our test data separate. Otherwise, it's not a valid model if we can't properly test it with new data.
And this is the labels we created from that test data. These are the ones that we predict it's going to be.
So we go in and we create our SN heat map.
The SNS is our seaborne which sits on top of the Piplot.
So we create a SNS.heat map, we take our confusion matrix, and it's going to be mat dot t.
And do we have other variables that go into the sns dot heat map.
We're not going to go into detail what all the variables mean.
The annotation equals true, that's what tells it to put the numbers here. So you have the 166, the 1, the 0001, format D and C bar equals false have to do with the format.
If you take those out, you'll see that some things disappear. And then the X tick labels and the Y tick labels, those are our target names.
And you can see right here that's the alt atheism comp graphics, comp OSMS windows.miscellaneous.
And then finally we have our plt.x label. Remember the SNS or the C born sits on top of our mapplot library, our PLT. And so we want to just tell it X label equals a true is is true.
The labels are true, and then the Y label is prediction label.
So when we say a true, this is what it actually is, and the prediction is what we predicted.
And let's look at this graph because that's probably a little confusing the way we rattled through it.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead and flip back to the slides because they have a black background they put in there that helps it shine a little bit better
so you can see the graph a little bit easier.
So, in reading this graph, what we want to look at is how the color scheme has come out.
And you'll see a line right down the middle, diagonally, from upper left to bottom right.
What that is, is if you look at the labels, we have our predicted label on the left and our true label on the right. Those are the numbers where the prediction and the true come together.
And this is what we want to see is we want to see those lit up. That's what that heat map does. As you can see that it did a good job of finding those data.
And you'll notice that there's a couple of red spots on there where it missed.
You know, it's a little confused. We talk about talk religion miscellaneous versus talk politics miscellaneous, social religion Christian versus alt atheism.
It mislabeled some of those. And those are very similar topics, so you could understand why it might mislabel them.
But overall, it did a pretty good job.
If we're going to create these models, we want to go ahead and be able to use them.
So let's see what that looks like.
To do this, let's go ahead and create a definition, a function to run.
And we're going to call this function, let me just expand that just a notch here. There we go.
I like mine in big letters. Predict categories. We want to predict the category.
We're going to send it s, a string, and then we're sending it train equals train. We have our training model, and then we had our pipeline, model equals model.
This way we don't have to resend these variables each time.
The definition knows that because I said train equals train and I put the equal for model.
And then we're going to set the prediction equal to the model dot predict s.
So it's going to send whatever string we send to it. It's going to push that string through the pipeline, the model pipeline.
It's going to go through and tokenize it and put it through the TFIDF, convert that into numbers and weights for all the different documents and words. And then it'll put that through our naive base.
And from it, we'll go ahead and get our prediction. We're going to predict what value it is.
And so we're going to return train.target names predict of zero.
And remember that the train.targetnames, that's just categories. I could have just as easily put categories in there dot predict of zero.
So we're taking the prediction, which is a number, and we're converting it to an actual category.
We're converting it from I don't know what the actual numbers are, but let's say zero equals alt atheism. So we're going to convert that zero to the word. Or one maybe it equals comp graphics.
So we're going to convert number one into comp graphics. That's all that is.
And then we got to go ahead and and then we need to go ahead and run this.
So I load that up, and then once I run that, we can start doing some predictions.
Let me go ahead and type in predict category, and let's just do predict category Jesus Christ.
And it comes back and says it's social, religion, Christian.
That's pretty good. Now note I didn't put print on this.
One of the nice things about the Jupyter Notebook editor and a lot of inline editors is if you just put the name of the variable out, as returning the variable train.target underscore names,
it'll automatically print that for you.
In your own IDE, you might have to put in print. Let's see where else we can take this. And maybe you're a space science buff. So how about sending load to international
space station?
And if we run that, we get science space.
Or maybe you're a automobile buff.
And let's do um, oh, they were gonna tell me Audi is better than BMW, but I'm gonna do BMW is better than an Audi. So maybe your car buff.
And we run that, and you'll see it says recreational. I'm assuming that's what REC stands for.
Autos. So I did a pretty good job labeling that one.
How about if we have something like a caption running through there? President of India.
And if we run that, it comes up and says talk politics miscellaneous.
So when we take our definition or our function and we run all these things through, kudos! We made it!
We were able to correctly classify texts into different groups based on which category they belong to using the naive Bayes classifier.
Now we did throw in the pipeline, the TF IDF vectorizer, we threw in the graphs.
Those are all things that you don't necessarily have to know to understand the naive Bayes setup or classifier, but they're important to know.
One of the main uses for the Naive Bayes is with the TF IDF tokenizer or vectorizer, where it tokenizes the word and adds labels.
And we use the pipeline because you need to push all that data through and it makes it really easy and fast.
You don't have to know those to understand naive Bayes, but they certainly help for understanding the industry and data science.
And we can see our categorizer, our naive Bayes classifier.
We were able to predict the category religion, space, motorcycles, autos, politics, and properly classify all these different things we pushed into our prediction and our trained model.
Before we dive into the SVM, let's take a look at applications of the support vector machine.
At least some general ones that are commonly used with it.
Face detection, text, and hypertext categorization, classification of images, and bioinformatics.
These are only but a few of those that are used with this SVM.
As we go through this lesson, see if you can figure out what other ones you could apply it to, and also what you would want to use some other tools for.
So in this example, last week, my son and I visited a fruit shop. Dad, is that an apple or a strawberry?
So the question comes up: what fruit did I just pick up from the fruit stand? After a couple of seconds, you can figure out that it was a strawberry.
So let's take this model a step further and let's why not build a model which can predict an unknown data?
And in this, we're going to be looking at some sweet strawberries or crispy apples. We want it to be able to label those two and decide what the fruit is. And we do that by having data already put in.
So we already have a bunch of strawberries, we know our strawberries, and they're already labeled as such. We already have a bunch of apples, we know our apples and are labeled as such.
Then once we train our model, that model then can be given the new data. And the new data is this image.
In this case, you can see a question mark on it, and it comes through and goes, it's a strawberry. In this case, we're using the support vector machine model.
SVM is a supervised learning method that looks at data and sorts it into one of two categories.
And in this case, we're sorting the strawberry into the strawberry side. At this point, you should be asking the question, how does the prediction work?
Before we dig into an example with numbers, let's apply this to our fruit scenario.
We have our support vector machine.
We've taken it and we've taken labeled sample of data, strawberries and apples, and we draw a line down the middle between the two groups.
This split now allows us to take new data, in this case an apple and a strawberry, and place them in the appropriate group based on which side of the line they fall in.
And that way we can predict the unknown.
As colorful and tasty as the fruit example is, let's take a look at another example with some numbers involved, and we can take a closer look at how the math works.
In this example, we're going to be classifying men and women. And we're going to start with a set of people with a different height and a different weight.
And to make this work, we'll have to have a sample data set of female, where you have their height and weight, 174, 65, 174, 88, and so on. And we'll need a sample data set of the male.
They have a height 179, 90, 180 to 80, and so on. Let's go ahead and put this on a graph so you have a nice visual.
So you can see here we have two groups based on the height versus the weight.
And on the left side, we're going to have the women, on the right side, we're going to have the men.
Now if we're going to create a classifier, let's add a new data point and figure out if it's male or female. So before we can do that, we need to split our data first.
We can split our data by choosing any of these lines.
In this case, we draw in two lines through the data in the middle that separates the men from the women.
But to predict the gender of a new data point, we should split the data in the best possible way. And we say the best possible way because this line has a maximum space that separates the two classes.
Here you can see there's a clear split between the two different classes. And in this one, there's not so much a clear split. This doesn't have the maximum space that separates the two.
That is why this line best splits the data. We don't want to just do this by eyeballing it.
And before we go further, we need to add some technical terms to this.
We can also say that the distance between the points and the line should be as far as possible. In technical terms, we can say the distance between the support vector.
And the hyperplane should be as far as possible.
And this is where the support vectors are the extreme points in the data set.
And if you look at this data set, they have circled two points, which seem to be right on the outskirts of the woman and one on the outskirts of the men.
And hyperplane has a maximum distance to the support vectors of any class.
Now you'll see the line down the middle, and we call this the hyperplane because when you're dealing with multiple dimensions, it's really not just a line but a plane of intersections.
And you can see here where the support vectors have been drawn in dashed lines.
The math behind this is very simple.
We take D plus, the shortest distance to the closest positive point, which would be on the men's side, and D minus is the shortest distance to the closest negative point, which is on the women's side.
The sum of D plus and D minus is called the distance margin, or the distance between the two support vectors that are shown in the dashed lines.
And then by finding the largest distance margin, we can get the optimal hyperplane. Once we've created an optimal hyperplane, we can easily see which side the new data fits in.
And based on the hyperplane, we can say the new data point belongs to the male gender. Hopefully that's clear how that works on a visual level.
As a data scientist, you should also be asking what happens if the hyperplane is not optimal.
If we select a hyperplane having low margin, then there is a high chance of misclassification.
This particular SVM model, the one we discussed so far, is also called or referred to as the LSVM.
So far so clear, but a question should be coming up.
We have our sample data set.
But instead of looking like this, what if it looked like this, where we have two sets of data, but one of them occurs in the middle of another set?
You can see here where we have the blue and the yellow, and then blue again on the other side of our data line. In this data set, we can't use a hyperplane.
So when you see data like this, it's necessary to move away from a 1D view of the data to a two-dimensional view of the data. And for the transformation, we use what's called a kernel function.
The kernel function will take the 1D input and transfer it to a two-dimensional output.
As you can see in this picture here, the 1D, when transferred to a two-dimensional makes it very easy to draw a line between the two data sets.
What if we make it even more complicated?
How do we perform an SVM for this type of data set?
Here you can see we have a two-dimensional data set where the data is in the middle surrounded by the green data on the outside.
In this case, we're going to segregate the two classes.
We have our sample data set, and if you draw a line through, it's obviously not an optimal hyperplane in there. So to do that, we need to transfer the 2D to a 3D array.
And when you translate it into a three-dimensional array using the kernel, you can see where you can place a hyperplane right through it and easily split the data.
Before we start looking at a programming example and dive into the script, let's look at the advantage of the support vector machine.
We'll start with high dimensional input space, or sometimes referred to as the curse of dimensionality.
We looked at earlier one dimension, two dimension, three dimension.
When you get to a thousand dimensions, a lot of problems start occurring with most algorithms that have to be adjusted for. The SVM automatically does that in high dimensional space.
One of the high dimensional space, one high dimensional space that we work on is sparse document vectors.
This is where we tokenize the words in documents so we can run our machine learning algorithms over them. I've seen ones get as high as 2.4 million different tokens.
That's a lot of vectors to look at. And finally we have regularization parameter.
The regularization parameter or lambda is a parameter that helps figure out whether we're going to have a bias or overfitting of the data, whether it's going to be overfitted to a very
specific instance or it's going to be biased to a high or low value. With the SVM, it naturally avoids the overfitting and bias problems that we see in many other algorithms.
These three advantages of the support vector machine make it a very powerful tool to add to your repertoire of machine learning tools.
Now, we did promise you a use case study we're actually going to dive into some Python programming. And so we're going to go into a problem statement and start off with the zoo.
So in the zoo example, we have family members going to the zoo and we have the young child going, Dad, is that a group of crocodiles or alligators? Well, that's hard to differentiate.
And zoos are a great place to start looking at science and understanding how things work, especially as a young child.
And so we can see the parents sitting here thinking, well, what is the difference between a crocodile and an alligator?
Well, one, crocodiles are larger in size, alligators are smaller in size, snout width, the crocodiles have a narrow snout, and alligators have a wider snout.
And of course, in the modern day and age, the father's sitting here thinking, how can I turn this into a lesson for my son? And he goes, let a support vector machine segregate the two groups.
I don't know if my dad ever told me that, but that would be funny. Now in this example, we're not going to use actual measurements and data.
We're just using that for imagery. And that's very common in a lot of machine learning algorithms and setting them up.
But let's roll up our sleeves and we'll talk about that more in just a moment as we break into our Python script.
So here we arrive in our actual coding.
And I'm going to move this into a Python editor in just a moment.
But let's talk a little bit about what we're going to cover.
First, we're going to cover in the code the setup, how to actually create our SVM.
And you're going to find that there's only two lines of code that actually create it, and the rest of it is done so quick and fast that it's all here in the first page.
And we'll show you what that looks like as far as our data, because we're going to create some data. I talked about creating data just a minute ago.
And so we'll get into the creating data here, and you'll see this nice correction of our two blobs, and we'll go through that in just a second.
And then the second part is we're going to take this and we're going to bump it up a notch. We're going to show you what it looks like behind the scenes.
But let's start with actually creating our setup.
I like to use the Anaconda Jupyter Notebook because it's very easy to use, but you can use any of your favorite Python editors or setups and go in there.
But let's go ahead and switch over there and see what that looks like.
So here we are in the Anaconda Python Notebook or Anaconda Jupyter Notebook with Python. We're using Python 3. I believe this is 3.5, but it should be work in any of your 3x versions.
And you'd have to look at the SK Learn and make sure if you're using a 2x version, an earlier version.
let's go ahead and put our code in there.
And one of the things I like about the Jupyter Notebook is I can go up to View, and I'm going to go ahead and toggle the line numbers on to make it a little bit easier to talk about.
And we can even increase the size because this is edited in in this case I'm using Google Chrome Explorer, and that's how it opens up for the editor.
Although anyone, like I said, any editor will work. Now the first step is going to be our imports.
And we're going to import four different parts. The first two I want you to look at are line one and line two are numpy as np and matplotlibrary.pyplot as plt.
Now these are very standardized imports when you're doing work. The first one is the numbers python.
We need that because part of the platform we're using uses that for the numpy array.
And I'll talk about that in a minute so you can understand why we want to use a numpy array versus the standard Python array.
And normally it's pretty standard setup to use np for numpy. The map plot library is how we're going to view our data.
So this has you do need the np for the sklearn module, but the map plot library is purely for our use for visualization.
And so you really don't need that for the SVM, but we're going to put it there so you have a nice visual aid and we can show you what it looks like.
That's really important at the end when you finish everything, so you have a nice display for everybody to look at.
And then finally, I'm going to jump one ahead to line number four. That's the sklearn.datasets.samples generator import make blobs.
And I told you that we were going to make up data.
And this is a tool that's in the sklearn to make up data.
I personally don't want to go to the zoo, get in trouble for jumping over the fence, and probably get eaten by the crocodiles or alligators as I work on measuring their snouts and width and length.
Instead, we're just going to make up some data.
And that's what that make blobs is. It's a wonderful tool if you're ready to test your setup and you're not sure about what data you're going to put in there.
You can create this blob and it makes it real easy to use. And finally, we have our actual SVM, the SK Learn Import SVM on line three.
So that covers all our imports. We're going to create, remember, I used the make blobs to create data. And we're going to create a capital X and a lowercase y equals make blobs in samples equals 40.
So we're going to make 40 lines of data.
It's going to have two centers with a random state equals 20. So each group is going to have 20 different pieces of data in it.
And the way that looks is that we'll have under X an XY plane. So we'll have two numbers under X and Y will be 0 or 1.
That's the two different centers. So we have yes or no. In this case, alligator or crocodile. That's what that represents.
And then I told you that the actual SK learner, the SVM, is in two lines of code.
And we see it right here with CLF equals SVM dot svc kernel equals linear.
And I set c equal to one.
Although in this example, since we are not regular, since we want it to be very clear and easy to see, I went ahead, you can set it to a thousand a lot of times when you're not doing that.
But for this thing, linear, because it's a very simple linear example, we only have the two dimensions, and it'll be a nice linear hyperplane, it'll be a nice linear line instead of a full plane.
So we're not dealing with a huge amount of data.
And then all we have to do is do CLF.fit X comma y. And that's it.
CLF has been created, and then we're going to go ahead and display it.
And I'm going to talk about this display here in just a second, but let me go ahead and run this code.
And this is what we've done is we've created two blobs. You'll see the blue on the side and then kind of an orange-ish on the other side. That's our two sets of data.
They represent one represents crocodiles and one represents alligators. And then we have our measurements. In this case, we have like the width and length of the snout.
And I did say I was going to come up here and talk just a little bit about our plot. And you'll see PLT. That's what we imported. We're going to do a scatter plot.
That means we're just putting dots on there.
And then look at this notation. I have the capital X, and then in brackets I have a colon, comma zero.
That's from NumPy.
If you did that in a regular array, you'll get an error in a Python array. You have to have that in a NumPy array. It turns out that our make blobs returns a NumPy array.
And this notation is great because what it means is the first part is the colon, means we're going to do all the rows. That's all the data in our blob we created under capital X.
And then the second part has a comma zero.
We're only going to take the first value.
And then if you notice we do the same thing, but we're going to take the second value. Remember we always start with zero and then one. So we have column zero and column one.
And you can look at this as our xy plots.
The first one is the x plot and the second one is the y plot.
So the first one is on the bottom, zero, two, four, six, eight, and ten. And then the second one, x of the one, is the four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten going up the left hand side.
S equals 30 is just the size of the dots. We can see them instead of real tiny dots. And then C map equals plt.cm.paired.
And you'll also see the C equals Y. That's the color.
We're using two colors, zero, one, and that's why we get the nice blue and the two different colors for the alligator and the crocodile.
Now you can see here that we did this, the actual fit was done in two lines of code. A lot of times there'll be a third line where we regularize the data.
We set it between like minus one and one, and we reshape it. But for this it's not necessary, and it's also kind of nice because you can actually see what's going on.
And then if we wanted to, we wanted to actually run a prediction, let's take a look and see what that looks like.
And to predict some new data, and we'll show this again as we get towards the end of digging in deep, you can simply assign your new data.
In this case, I am giving it a width and length 3 4 and a width and length 5 6.
And note that I put the data as a set of brackets, and then I have the brackets inside.
And the reason I do that is because when we're looking at data, it's designed to process a large amount of data coming in. We don't want to just process one line at a time.
And so in this case, I'm processing two lines, and then I'm just going to print and you'll see CLF dot predict new data.
So the CLF and the dot predict part is going to give us an answer, and let's see what that looks like.
And you'll see 0 1. So predicted the first one, the 3-4 is going to be on the one side and the 5-6 is going to be on the other side. So one came out as an alligator and one came out as a crocodile.
Now that's pretty short explanation for the setup, but really we want to dig in and see what it's going on behind the scenes. And let's see what that looks like.
So the next step is to dig in deep and find out what's going on behind the scenes.
And also put that in a nice pretty graph.
We're going to spend more work on this than we did actually generating the original model.
And you'll see here that we go through a few steps, and I'll move this over to our editor in just a second. We come in, we create our original data.
It's exactly identical to the first part, and I'll explain why we redid that and show you how not to redo that.
And then we're going to go in there and add in those lines.
We're going to see what those lines look like and how to set those up.
And finally we're going to plot all that on here and show it.
And you'll get a nice graph with what we saw earlier when we were going through the theory behind this, where it shows the support vectors and the hyperplane.
And those are done where you can see the support vectors as the dashed lines and the solid line, which is the hyperplane.
Let's get that into our Jupyter notebook.
Before I scroll down to a new line, I want you to notice line 13, it has plot show. And we're going to talk about that here in just a second, but let's scroll down to a new line down here.
And I'm going to paste that code in.
And you'll see that the plot show has moved down below. Let's scroll up a little bit.
And if you look at the top here of our new section, one, two, three, and four is the same code we had before.
And let's go back up here and take a look at that.
We're going to fit the values on our SVM and then we're going to plot scatter it, and then we're going to do a plot show.
So you should be asking why are we redoing the same code?
Well, when you do the plot show, that blanks out what's in the plot. So once I've done this plot show, I have to reload that data.
Now we could do this simply by removing it up here, rerunning it, and then coming down here, and then we wouldn't have to rerun these first four lines of code.
Now in this, it doesn't matter too much, and you'll see the plot show is down here and then removed right there on line five. I'll go ahead and just delete that out of there.
Because we don't want to blank out our screen. We want to move on to the next setup.
So we can go ahead and just skip the first four lines because we did that before. And let's take a look at the ax equals plt.gca.
Now right now we're actually spending a lot of time just graphing. That's all we're doing here.
Okay, so this is how we display a nice graph with our results and our data.
AX is very standard note used variable when you're talking about PLT, and it's just setting it to that axis, the last axis in the PLT.
It can get very confusing if you're working with many different layers of data on the same graph, and this makes it very easy to reference the AX.
So this reference is looking at the PLT that we created and we already mapped out our two blobs on.
And then we want to know the limits. So we want to know how big the graph is.
We can find out the x limit and the y limit simply with the get x limit and get y limit commands, which is part of our Metplot library.
And then we're going to create a grid, and you'll see down here we have we've set the variable xx equal to np.line space x limit zero,
x limit one, comma thirty.
And we've done the same thing for the y space.
And then we're going to go in here and we create a mesh grid. And this is a numpy command.
So we're back to our numbers Python.
Let's go through what these numpy commands mean with the line space and the mesh grid.
We've taken xx, small s xx equals np line space, and we have our x limit zero and our x limit one, and we're going to create 30 points on it.
And we're going to do the same thing for the y axis. Now this has nothing to do with our evaluation. It's all we're doing is we're creating a grid of data.
And so we're creating a set of points between 0 and the x limit.
We're creating 30 points, and the same thing with the y. And then the mesh grid loops those all together so it forms a nice grid.
So if we were going to do this, say between the limit 0 and 10 and do 10 points, we would have a 0, 0, 1, 1, 0, 1, 0, 2,
0, 3, 0, 4 to 10, and so on. You can just imagine a point at each corner, of one of those boxes. And the mesh grid combines them all. So we take the yy and the xx we created and creates the full grid.
And we've set that grid into the yy coordinates and the xx coordinates.
Now remember we're working with numbi and python, we like to separate those.
We like to have instead of it being x, comma one, you know, x comma y and then x2, comma, y2, and in the next set of data, it would be
a column of x's and a column of y's.
And that's what we have here is we have a column of y's and we put it as a capital YY and a column of X's, capital XX, with all those different points being listed.
And finally we get down to the numpy V stack.
Just as we created those in the mesh grid, we're now going to put them all into one array, xy array.
Now that we've created the stack of data points, we're going to do something interesting here. We're going to create a value z and the z equals the CLF.
that's our support vector machine we created, and we've already trained.
And we have a dot decision function, and we're going to put the xy in there.
So here we have all this data. We're going to put that xy in there, that data, and we're going to reshape it.
And you'll see that we have the xx shape in here. This literally takes the xx, resets it up connected to the y, and the z value lets us know whether it is the left-hand
side.
It's going to generate three different values, the z value does, and it'll tell us whether that data is a support vector to the left, the hyperplane in the middle, or the support vector to the right.
So it generates three different values for each of those points. And those points have been reshaped so that they're right on a line on those three different lines.
So we've set all of our data up, we've labeled it to three different areas, and we've reshaped it, and we've just taken 30 points in each direction.
If you do the math, you have 30 times 30, so that's 900 points of data, and we separated it between the three lines and reshaped it to fit those three lines.
We can then go back to our map plot library, we've created the AX, and we're going to create a contour. And you'll see here we have contour, capital XX, capital YY.
These have been reshaped to fit those lines. Z is the labels.
So now we have the three different points with the labels in there, and we can set the colors equals k. And I told you we had three different labels, but we have three levels of data.
The alpha is just makes it kind of see-through, so it's only 0.5 of the value in there. So when we graph it, the data will show up from behind it, wherever the lines go. And finally, the line styles.
This is where we set the two support vectors to be dash dash lines, and then a single one is just a straight line. That's what all that setup does. And then finally, we take our ax.scatter.
We're gonna go ahead and plot the support vectors, but we've programmed it in there so that they look nice, like the dash dash line and the dash line on that grid.
And you can see here when we do the CLF dot support vectors, we are looking at column zero and column one, and then again we have the s
equals 100, so we're going to make them larger, and the line width equals one, face colors equals none.
Let's take a look and see what that looks like when we show it.
And you can see we get down to our end result, it creates a really nice graph.
We have our two support vectors and dashed lines, and they have the near data, so you can see those two points, or in this case the four points where those lines nicely cleave the data,
and then you have your hyperplane down the middle, which is as far from the two different points as possible, creating the maximum distance.
So you can see that we have our nice output for the size of the body and the width of the snout, and we've easily separated the two groups of crocodile and alligator. Congratulations, you've done it.
We've made it. Of course, these are pretend data for our crocodiles and alligators, but this hands on example will help you to encounter any support vector machine projects in the future,
and you can see how easy they are to set up and look at in depth. we're gonna cover the K nearest neighbors, a lot referred to as KNN.
And KNN is really a fundamental place to start in the machine learning.
It's a basis of a lot of other things, and just the logic behind it is easy to understand and incorporated in other forms of machine learning.
So today, what's in it for you?
Why do we need KNN?
What is KNN?
How do we choose the factor K?
When do we use KNN?
How does KNN algorithm work?
And then we'll dive into my favorite part, the use case.
Predict whether a person will have diabetes or not. That is a very common and popular used data set as far as testing out models and learning how to use the different models in machine learning.
By now, we all know machine learning models make predictions by learning from the past data available.
So we have our input values, our machine learning model builds on those inputs of what we already know, and then we use that to create a predicted output.
Is that a dog?
Little kid looking over there and watching the black cat cross their path.
No dear, you can differentiate between a cat and a dog based on their characteristics.
Cats.
Cats have sharp claws, uses to climb, smaller length of ears, meows and purrs, doesn't love to play around.
Dogs have dull claws, bigger length of ears, barks, loves to run around. You usually don't see a cat running around people, although I do have a cat that does that. Where dogs do.
And we can look at these, we can say we can evaluate the sharpness of the claws, how sharp are their claws, and we can evaluate the length of the ears,
and we can usually sort out cats from dogs based on even those two characteristics.
Now tell me if it is a cat or a dog. Not in question, usually little kids know cats and dogs by now. Unless you live in a place where there's not many cats or dogs.
So if we look at the sharpness of the claws, the length of the ears, and we can see that the cat has smaller ears and sharper claws than the other animals.
Its features are more like cats, it must be a cat.
Sharp claws, length of ears, and it goes in the cat group.
Because KNN is based on feature similarity, we can do classification using KNN classifier.
So we have our input value, the picture of the black cat.
It goes into our trained model and it predicts that this is a cat coming out.
So what is KNN?
What is the KNN algorithm?
K nearest neighbors is what that stands for.
It's one of the simplest supervised machine learning algorithms mostly used for classification.
So we want to know is this a dog or is not a dog? Is it a cat or not a cat?
It classifies a data point based on how its neighbors are classified.
KNN stores all available cases and classifies new cases based on a similarity measure.
And here we've gone from cats and dogs right into wine, another favorite of mine.
And here you see we have a measurement of sulfur dioxide versus the chloride level, and then the different wines they've tested and where they fall on that graph
based on how much sulfur dioxide and how much chloride. K and K and N is a perimeter that refers to the number of nearest neighbors to include in the majority of the voting process.
And so if we add a new glass of wine there, red or white, we want to know what the neighbors are. In this case we're going to put K equals five.
We'll talk about K in just a minute. A data point is classified by the majority of votes from its five nearest neighbors.
Here, the unknown point would be classified as red since four out of five neighbors are red.
So how do we choose k?
How do we know k equals five? I mean that was the value we put in there, and so we're going to talk about it.
How do we choose the factor k? K and N algorithm is based on feature similarity.
Choosing the right value of k is a process called parameter tuning and is important for better accuracy.
So at k equals three we can classify, we have a question mark in the middle as either a square or not. Is it a square or is it in this case a triangle?
And so if we set k equals to three, we're going to look at the three nearest neighbors. We're going to say this is a square.
And if we put k equals to seven, we classify as a triangle, depending on what the other data is around it.
And you can see as the k changes, depending on where that point is, that drastically changes your answer.
And we jump here and we go, how do we choose the factor of k? You'll find this in all machine learning. Choosing these factors, that's the face you get.
It's like, oh my gosh, did I choose the right k? Did I set it right? My values in whatever machine learning tool you're looking at so that you don't have a huge bias in one direction or the other.
And in terms of Kn N, the number of K, if you choose it too low, the bias is based on it's just too noisy.
It's it's right next to a couple things, and it's going to pick those things, and you might get a skewed answer.
And if your k is too big, then it's going to take forever to process. So you're going to run into processing issues and resource issues.
So what we do, the most common use, and there's other options for choosing k, is to use the square root of n.
So n is a total number of values you have, you take the square root of it.
In most cases you also, if it's an even number, so if you're using like in this case squares and triangles, if it's even you want to make your k value odd.
That helps it select better.
So in other words, you're not going to have a balance between two different factors that are equal.
So usually take the square root of n, and if it's even you add one to it or subtract one from it, and that's where you get the k value from. That is the most common use and it's pretty solid.
It works very well.
When do we use knn?
We can use KNN when data is labeled. So you need a label on it. We know we have a group of pictures with dogs, dogs, cats, cats.
Data is noise free.
And so you can see here when we have a class and we have like underweight, 140, 23, hello kitty, normal, that's pretty confusing.
We have a high variety of data coming in, so it's very noisy, and that would cause an issue.
Data set is small, so we're usually working with smaller data sets where you might get into a gig of data if it's really clean, doesn't have a lot of noise.
Because KNN is a lazy learner, i.e., it doesn't learn a discriminative function from the training set. So it's very lazy.
So if you have very complicated data and you have a large amount of it, you're not going to use the KNN.
But it's really great to get a place to start. Even with large data, you can sort out a small sample and get an idea of what that looks like using the KNN, and also just using for smaller data sets,
KNN works really good.
How does a KNN algorithm work?
Consider a dataset having two variables, height in centimeters and weight in kilograms, and each point is classified as normal or underweight.
So we can see right here we have two variables, you know, true false, they're either normal or they're not, they're underweight.
On the basis of the given data, we have to classify the below set as normal or underweight using KNN.
So if we have new data coming in that says 57 kilograms and 177 centimeters, is that going to be normal or underweight?
To find the nearest neighbors, we'll calculate the Euclidean distance.
According to the Euclidean distance formula, the distance between two points in the plane with the coordinates x, y, and ab is given by distance d equals
the square root of x minus a squared plus y minus b squared.
And you can remember that from the two edges of a triangle. We're computing the third edge since we know the x side and the y side.
Let's calculate it to understand clearly.
So we have our unknown point, and we placed it there in red, and we have our other points where the data is scattered around.
The distance d1 is the square root of 170 minus 167 squared plus 57 minus 51 squared, which is about six
seven.
And distance two is about 13, And distance three is about 13 four. Similarly we will calculate the Euclidean distance of unknown data point from all the points in the data set.
And because we're dealing with small amount of data that's not that hard to do and it's actually pretty quick for a computer.
And it's not a really complicated math. So you can just see how close is the data based on the Euclidean distance.
Hence we have calculated the Euclidean distance of unknown data point from all the points as showing, where x1 and y1 equal 57 and 170
whose class we have to classify. So now we're looking at that we're saying well here's the Euclidean distance who's going to be their closest neighbors?
Now let's calculate the nearest neighbor at k equals three.
And we can see the three closest neighbors puts them at normal.
And that's pretty self-evident. When you look at this graph it's pretty easy to say okay what you know we're just voting.
Normal normal normal three votes for normal this is going to be a normal weight.
So majority of neighbors are pointing towards normal hence as per KNN algorithm the class of 57170 should be normal.
So a recap of KNN positive integer k is specified along with a new sample.
We select the k entries in our database which are closest to the new sample.
We find the most common classification of these entries. This is the classification we give to the new sample.
So as you can see it's pretty straightforward.
We're just looking for the closest things that match what we got. So let's take a look and see what that looks like in a use case in Python. So let's dive into the predict diabetes use case.
So use case predict diabetes.
the objective predict whether a person will be diagnosed with diabetes or not.
We have a data set of 768 people who were or were not diagnosed with diabetes.
And let's go ahead and open that file and just take a look at that data.
And this is in a simple spreadsheet format. The data itself is comma separated very common set of data and it's also a very common way to get the data.
And you can see here we have columns A through I that's what one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight eight columns
with a particular attribute and then the ninth column which is the outcome is whether they have diabetes. As a data scientist the first thing you should be looking at is insulin.
Well you know if someone has insulin they have diabetes because that's why they're taking it.
And that could cause issue in some of the machine learning packages but for a very basic setup this works fine for doing the KNN.
And the next thing you notice is it didn't take very much to open it up I can scroll down to the bottom of the data there's 768. It's pretty much a small data set.
You know at 769 I can easily fit this into my RAM on my computer I can look at it I can manipulate it and it's not going to really tax
just a regular desktop computer. You don't even need an enterprise version to run a lot of this. So let's start with importing all the tools we need.
And before that of course we need to discuss what IDE I'm using.
Certainly can use any particular editor for Python but I like to use for doing very basic visual stuff the Anaconda which is great for doing demos
with the Jupyter notebook.
And just a quick view of the Anaconda Navigator which is the new release out there which is really nice. You can see under home I can choose my application we're going to be using Python 36.
I have a couple different versions on this particular machine.
If I go under environments I can create a unique environment for each one which is nice and there's even a little button there where I can install different packages
so if I click on that button and open the terminal I can then use a simple pip install to install different packages I'm working with.
Let's go ahead and go back under home and we're going to launch our notebook and I've already you know kind of like
the old cooking shows I've already prepared a lot of my stuff so we don't have to wait for it to launch because it takes a few minutes for it to open up a browser window.
In this case I'm going to it's going to open up Chrome because that's my default that I use.
And since the script is pre done you'll see I have a number of windows open up at the top the one we're working in.
And since we're working on the KNN Predict whether a person will have diabetes or not. Let's go ahead and put that title in there. And I'm also going to go up here and click on cell.
Actually, we want to go ahead and first insert a cell below.
And then I'm going to go back up to the top cell and I'm going to change the cell type to markdown. That means this is not going to run as Python. It's a markdown language.
So if I run this first one, it comes up in nice big letters, which is kind of nice. Remind us what we're working on.
And by now you should be familiar with doing all of our imports. We're going to import the pandas as PD, import numpy as np.
Pandas is the pandas data frame and numpy is a number array.
Very powerful tools to use in here.
So we have our imports. So we've brought in our pandas, our numpy, our two general Python tools.
And then you can see over here we have our train test split.
By now you should be familiar with splitting the data.
We want to split part of it for training our thing and then training our particular model. And then we want to go ahead and test the remaining data to see how good it is.
Pre-processing, a standard scalar preprocessor, so we don't have a bias of really large numbers.
Remember in the data we had like number pregnancies isn't going to get very large, where the amount of insulin they take can get up to 256. So 256 versus 6, that will skew results.
So we want to go ahead and change that so that they're all uniform between minus 1 and 1.
And then the actual tool.
This is the K neighbors classifier we're going to use.
And finally the last three are three tools to test. All about testing our model. How good is it? Let me just put down test on there. And we have our confusion matrix, our F1 score, and our accuracy.
So we have our two general Python modules we're importing, and then we have our six modules specific from the SKLearn setup.
And then we do need to go ahead and run this so that these are actually imported.
There we go.
And then move on to the next step.
And so in this set we're going to go ahead and load the database. We're going to use pandas. Remember pandas is pd.
And we'll take a look at the data in Python. We looked at it in a simple spreadsheet, but usually I like to also pull it up so that we can see what we're doing.
So here's our dataset equals pd.readcsv.
That's a pandas command.
And the diabetes folder I just put in the same folder where my iPython script is.
If you put it in a different folder, you'd need the full length on there. We can also do a quick length of the dataset.
That is a simple Python command, L E N for length.
We might even let's go ahead and print that. We'll go print. And if you do it on its own line, length.dataset in the Jupyter Notebook, it'll automatically print it.
But when you're in most of your different setups, you want to do the print in front of there.
And then we want to take a look at the actual dataset. And since we're in pandas, we can simply do dataset head. And again, let's go ahead and add the print in there.
If you put a bunch of these in a row, you know, the dataset one head, dataset 2 head, it only prints out the last one.
So I usually always like to keep the print statement in there.
But because most projects only use one data frame, pandas data frame, doing it this way doesn't really matter. The other way works just fine.
And you can see when we hit the run button, we have the 768 lines, which we knew. And we have our pregnancies. It's automatically given a label on the left.
Remember the head only shows the first five lines. So we have zero through four.
And just a quick look at the data, you can see it matches what we looked at before. We have pregnancy, glucose, blood pressure all the way to age, and then the outcome on the end.
And we're going to do a couple things in this next step.
We're going to create a list of columns where we can't have zero.
There's no such thing as zero skin thickness or zero blood pressure, zero glucose. any of those you'd be dead.
So not a really good factor if they have a zero in there because they didn't have the data.
And we'll take a look at that because we're going to start replacing that information with a couple of different things. And let's see what that looks like.
So first we create a nice list, as you can see. We have the values talked about glucose, blood pressure, skin thickness.
and this is a nice way when you're working with columns is to list the columns you need to do some kind of transformation on.
A very common thing to do. And then for this particular setup, we certainly could use the there's some panda tools that will do a lot of this where we can replace the NA.
But we're going to go ahead and do it as a dataset column equals dataset column dot replace. This is this is still pandas. You can do it direct, there's also one that's that you look for your N-A-N.
A lot of different options in here.
But the N-A-N, NumPyNA N is what that stands for, is is none It doesn't exist. So the first thing we're doing here is we're replacing the zero with a numpy none. There's no data there.
That's what that says.
That's what this is saying right here.
So put the zero in and we're gonna replace zeros with no data.
So if it's a zero, that means the person's well, hopefully not dead. Hopefully they just didn't get the data.
The next thing we want to do is we're gonna create the mean, which is the integer from the dataset from the column dot mean where we skip NA's. We can do that.
That is a pandas command there, the skip NA. So we're gonna figure out the mean of that data set.
And then we're gonna take that dataset column and we're going to replace all the NPNAN with the means. Why did we do that?
And we could have actually just taken this step and gone right down here and just replaced zero and skip anything where
except you could actually there's a way to skip zeros and then just replace all the zeros.
But in this case we want to go ahead and do it this way, so you can see that we're switching this to a non-existent value. And we're going to create the mean. Well, this is the average person.
So if we don't know what it is, if they did not get the data and the data's missing, one of the tricks is you replace it with the average. What is the most common data for that?
This way you can still use the rest of those values to do your computation, and it kind of just brings that particular value of those missing values out of the equation.
Let's go ahead and take this and we'll go ahead and run it.
Doesn't actually do anything, so we're still preparing our data. If you wanted to see what that looks like, it we don't have anything in the first few lines, so it's not gonna show up.
But we certainly could look at a row. Let's do that. Let's go into our data set, let's print a data set.
And let's pick in this case, let's just do glucose.
And if I run this, this is gonna print all the different glucose levels going down. And we thankfully don't see anything in here that looks like missing data, at least on the ones it shows.
You can see it skipped a bunch in the middle. Because that's what it does. If you have too many lines in Jupyter Notebook, it'll skip a few and and go on to the next in a dataset.
Let me go and remove this. And we'll just zero out that.
And of course, before we do any processing, before proceeding any further, we need to split the data set into our train and testing data.
That way we have something to train it with and something to test it on.
And you're gonna notice we did a little something here with the uh pandas database code.
There we go, my drawing tool. We've added in this right here off the data set.
And what this says is that the first one in pandas, this is from the PD pandas, it's gonna say within the data set, we want to look at the eye location,
and it is all rows. That's what that says. So we're gonna keep all the rows, but we're only looking at zero, column zero to eight.
Remember column nine, here it is right up here, we printed it in here, is outcome.
Well, that's not part of the training data, that's part of the answer. Yes, column nine, but it's listed as eight, number eight.
So zero to eight is nine columns. So uh eight is the value.
And when you see it in here, zero, this is actually zero to seven. It doesn't include the last one.
And then we go down here to y, which is our answer, and we want just the last one, just column eight.
And you can do it this way with this particular notation.
And then if you remember we imported the train test split.
That's part of the SK learn right there.
And we simply put in our X and our Y. We're going to do random state equals zero. You don't have to necessarily seed it. That's a seed number. I think the default is one when you seed it.
I'd have to look that up. And then the test size. Test size is 0.2. That simply means we're going to take 20% of the data and put it aside so that we can test it later.
That's all that is.
And again, we're going to run it.
Not very exciting. So far we haven't had any printout other than to look at the data. But that is a lot of this is prepping this data. Once you prep it, the actual lines of code are quick and easy.
And we're almost there, but the actual running of our KNN, we need to go ahead and do a scale the data.
If you remember correctly, we're fitting the data in a standard scalar, which means instead of the data being from you know five to three hundred and three in one column
and the next column is one to six. We're going to set that all so that all the data is between minus one and one. That's what that standard scalar does. Keeps it standardized.
And we only want to fit the scalar with the training set, but we want to make sure the testing set is the X test going in
is also transformed. So it's processing it the same.
So here we go with our standard scalar. We're going to call it sc underscore x for the scalar.
And we're going to import the standard scalar into this variable. And then our x train equals sc underscore x.fit transform. So we're creating the scalar on the x train variable.
And then our x test, we're also going to transform it. So we've trained and transformed the x train and then the x test isn't part of that training. It isn't part of that of training the transformer.
It just gets transformed. That's all it does. And again, we're going to go ahead and run this.
If you look at this, we've now gone through these steps, all three of them.
We've taken care of replacing our zeros for key columns that shouldn't be zero.
And we replace that with the means of those columns.
That way that they fit right in with our data models.
We've come down here and we split the data. So now we have our test data and our training data.
And then we've taken and we've scaled the data.
So all of our data going in. Now no, we don't trait we don't train the Y part, the Y train and Y test.
That never has to be trained. It's only the data going in.
That's what we want to train in there. Then define the model using K neighbors classifier and fit the train data in the model.
So we do all that data prep, and you can see down here we're only going to have a couple lines of code where we're actually building our model and training it.
That's one of the cool things about Python and how far we've come. It's such an exciting time to be in machine learning because there's so many automated tools.
Let's see, before we do this, let's do a quick length of and let's do y. We want, yeah let's just do length of y.
And we get 768. And if we import math, we do math dot square root, let's do y train. There we go.
It's actually supposed to be x train.
Before we do this, let's go ahead and do import math and do math square root length of y test.
And when I run that, we get twelve point four oh nine. I want to see show you where this number comes from, we're about to use. Twelve is an even number.
So if you know if you're ever voting on things, remember the neighbors all vote. Don't want to have an even number of neighbors voting. So we want to do something odd.
And let's just take one away and we'll make it eleven.
Let me delete this out of here. That's one of the reasons I love Jupyter Notebook because you can flip around and do all kinds of things on the fly.
So we'll go ahead and put in our classifier. We're creating our classifier now, and it's going to be the K neighbors classifier. N neighbors equal eleven.
Remember we did 12 minus 1 for 11, so we have an odd number of neighbors.
P equals 2, because we're looking for is it are they diabetic or not? And we're using the Euclidean metric.
There are other means of measuring the distance. You could do like square square means value. There's all kinds of measure this. But the Euclidean is the most common one and it works quite well.
It's important to evaluate the model.
Let's use the confusion matrix to do that.
And we're going to use the confusion matrix, wonderful tool, and then we'll jump into the F1 score.
And finally accuracy score, which is probably the most commonly used quoted number when you go into a meeting or something like that.
So let's go ahead and paste that in there, and we'll set the CM equal to confusion matrix.
Y test y predict.
So those are the two values we're going to put in there. And let me go ahead and run that and print it out.
And the way you interpret this is that you have the y predicted, which would be your title up here.
We could do uh let's just do P R E D.
Predicted across the top and actual going down.
Actual.
It's always hard to write in here, actual.
That means that this column here down the middle, that's the important column.
And it means that our prediction said 94, and prediction in the actual agreed on 94 and 32.
This number here, the 13 and the 15, those are what was wrong.
So you could have like three different, if you're looking at this across three different variables instead of just two, you'd end up with the third row down here and the column going down the middle.
So in the first case we have the the, and I believe the zero is it, 94 people that don't have diabetes. The prediction said that 13 of those people did have diabetes and were at high risk.
And the 32 that had diabetes it had correct, but our prediction said another 15 out of that 15 it classified as incorrect.
So you can see where that classification comes in and how that works on the confusion matrix.
Then we're going to go ahead and print the F1 score. Let me just run that. And you see we get a 0.69 in our F1 score.
The F1 takes into account both sides of the balance of false positives, where if we go ahead and just do the accuracy account,
and that's what most people think of, is it looks at just how many we got right out of how many we got wrong.
So a lot of people, when you're a data scientist and you're talking to other data scientists, they're going to ask you what the F1 score, the F score is.
If you're talking to the general public or the decision makers in the business, they're going to ask what the accuracy is. And the accuracy is always better than the F1 score.
But the F1 score is more telling. It lets us know that there's more false positives than we would like on here.
But 82%, not too bad for a quick flash look at people's different statistics in running an SK Learn and running the KNN, the K nearest neighbor on it.
So we have created a model using KNN, which can predict whether a person will have diabetes or not, or at the very least,
whether they should go get a checkup and have their glucose checked regularly or not.
The print accuracy score, we got the 0.818, was pretty close to what we got, and we can pretty much round that off and just say we have an accuracy of 80%.
Tells us it is a pretty fair fit in the model.
So what is K-means clustering?
K-means clustering is an unsupervised learning algorithm.
In this case, you don't have labeled data, unlike in supervised learning.
So you have a set of data.
And you want to group them.
And as the name suggests, you want to put them into clusters, which means objects that are similar in nature, similar in characteristics,
need to be put together.
So that's what k means clustering is all about.
The term k is basically a number.
So you need to tell the system how many clusters we need to perform.
So if k is equal to two, there will be two clusters, if k is equal to three, three clusters, and so on and so forth. That's what the k stands for.
And of course, there is a way of finding out what is the best or optimum value of k for a given data. We will look at that.
So that is k means clustering.
So let's take an example. K means clustering is used in many, many scenarios, but let's take an example of cricket, the game of cricket.
Let's say you receive data of a lot of players from maybe all over the country or all over the world, and this data has
information about The runs scored by the people or the by the player and the wickets taken by the player.
And based on this information, we need to cluster this data into two clusters, batsmen and bowlers.
So this is an interesting example.
Let's see how we can perform this.
So we have the data which consists of primarily two characteristics, which is the runs and the wickets.
So the bowlers basically take wickets and the batsmen score runs.
There will be, of course, a few bowlers who can score some runs, and similarly, there will be some batsmen who will who would have taken a few wickets.
But with this information, we want to cluster those players into batsmen and bowlers.
So how does this work?
Let's say this is how the data is.
So there are information, there is information on the y-axis about the run scored and on the x-axis about the wickets taken by the players.
So if we do a quick plot, this is how it would look.
And
when we do the clustering, we need to have the clusters like shown in the third diagram out here.
So we need to have a cluster which consists of people who have scored high runs, which is basically the batsmen, and then we need a cluster with people who have taken a lot of wickets,
which is typically the bowlers.
There may be a certain amount of overlap, but we will not talk about it right now.
So with k-means clustering, we will have here that means k is equal to two, and we will have two clusters, which is batsmen and bowlers.
So how does this work?
The way it works is the first step in k-means clustering is the allocation of two centroids randomly.
So two points are assigned as so-called centroids. So in this case we want two clusters, which means k is equal to two.
So two points have been randomly assigned as centroids. Keep in mind these points can be anywhere, they are random points. They are not initially, they are not really the centroids.
Centroid means it's a central point of a given data set, but in this case, when it starts off, it's not really the centroid.
Okay, so these points, though in our presentation here we have shown them one point closer to these data points and another closer to these data points, they can be assigned randomly anywhere.
Okay, so that's the first step.
The next step is to determine the distance of each of the data points from each of the randomly assigned centroids.
So for example, we take this point and find the distance from this centroid and the distance from this centroid.
This point is taken and the distance is found from this centroid and this centroid, and so on and so forth.
So for every point, the distance is measured from both the centroids, and then whichever distance is less,
that point is assigned to that centroid.
So, for example, in this case, visually it is very obvious that all these data points are assigned to this centroid,
and all these data points are assigned to this centroid, and that's what is represented here in blue color and in this yellow color.
The next step is to actually determine the central point or the actual centroid for these two clusters.
So we have this one initial cluster, this one initial cluster, but as you can see, these points are not really the centroid.
Centroid means it should be the central position of this data set, central position of this data set.
So that is what needs to be determined as the next step.
So the central point or the actual centroid is determined, and the original randomly allocated centroid is repositioned to the actual centroid of these new clusters.
And this process is actually repeated. Now what might happen is some of these points may get reallocated.
In our example, that is not happening probably, but it may so happen that the distance is found between each of these data points once again with these centroids.
And if there is if it is required, some points may be reallocated. We will see that in a later example, but for now we will keep it simple.
So this process is continued till the centroid repositioning stops.
And that is our final cluster.
So this is our so after iteration, we come to this position, this situation where the centroid doesn't need any more repositioning,
and that means our algorithm has converged.
Convergence has occurred, and we have the cluster, two clusters, we have the clusters with a centroid.
So this process is repeated.
The process of calculating the distance and repositioning the centroid is repeated till the repositioning stops, which means that the
algorithm has converged, and we have the final cluster with the data points and the centroids.
So this is what you're going to learn from this session.
We will talk about the types of clustering, what is k-means clustering, application of k-means clustering.
K-means clustering is done using distance measure. So we will talk about the common distance measures, and then we will talk about how K-means clustering works and go into the details of K-means
clustering algorithm.
And then we will end with a demo and a use case for K-means clustering.
So let's begin.
First of all, what are the types of clustering?
There are primarily two categories of clustering hierarchical clustering and then partitional clustering.
And each of these categories are further subdivided into agglomerative and divisive clustering and k means and fuzzy C means clustering.
Let's take a quick look at what each of these types of clustering are.
In hierarchical clustering, the clusters have a tree like structure and hierarchical clustering is further divided into agglomerative and
divisive.
Agglomerative clustering is a bottom-up approach. We begin with each element as a separate cluster and merge them into successively larger clusters. So for example, we have A, B, C, D, E, F.
We start by combining B and C form one cluster, D E and E form one more, then we combine D, E, and F one more bigger cluster, and then add B C to that, and then finally A to it.
Compare to that, divisive clustering or divisive clustering is a top-down approach.
We begin with the whole set and proceed to divide it into successively smaller clusters. So we have A, B, C, D, E, F.
We first take that as a single cluster and then break it down into A, B, C, D, E, and F.
Then we have partitional clustering split into two subtypes, k-means clustering and fuzzy c means.
In k means clustering, the objects are divided into the number of clusters mentioned by the number k. That's where the k comes from.
So if we say k is equal to 2, the objects are divided into two clusters, c1 and c2.
And the way it is done is the features or characteristics are compared and all objects having similar characteristics are clubbed together.
So that's how k-means clustering is done. We will see it in more detail as we move forward.
And fuzzy c -means is very similar to k-means in the sense that it clubs objects that have similar characteristics together.
but while in k -means clustering, two objects cannot belong to or any object. a single object cannot belong to two different clusters.
in c -means objects can belong to more than one cluster.
So that is the primary difference between k means and fuzzy c means.
So, what are some of the applications of K-means clustering?
K-means clustering is used in a variety of examples or variety of business cases in real life, starting from academic performance,
diagnostic systems, search engines, and wireless sensor networks and many more.
So let us take a little deeper look at each of these examples. Academic performance. So based on the scores of the students, students are categorized into A, B, C, and so on.
Clustering forms a backbone of search engines.
When a search is performed, the search results need to be grouped together.
The search engines very often use clustering to do this.
And similarly, in case of wireless sensor networks, the clustering algorithm plays the role of finding the cluster heads which collects all the data in its respective cluster.
So clustering, especially k-means clustering, uses distance measure.
So let's take a look at what is distance measure.
So while these are the different types of clustering, in this video we will focus on k-means clustering.
So distance measure tells how similar some objects are.
So the similarity is measured using what is known as distance measure.
And what are the various types of distance measures?
There is Euclidean distance, there is Manhattan distance, then we have squared Euclidean distance measure and cosine distance measure.
These are some of the distance measures supported by k-means clustering.
Let's take a look at each of these.
What is Euclidean distance measure? This is nothing but the distance between two points.
So we have learnt in high school how to find the distance between two points.
This is a little sophisticated formula for that, but we know a simpler one is square root of y2 minus y1 whole square plus x2
minus x1 whole square.
So this is an extension of that formula. So that is the Euclidean distance between two points.
What is the squared Euclidean distance measure?
It's nothing but the square of the Euclidean distance as the name suggests.
So instead of taking the square root, we leave the square as it is.
And then we have Manhattan distance measure. In case of Manhattan distance, it is the sum of the distances across the x-axis and the y-axis.
And note that we are taking the absolute value so that the negative values don't come into play.
So that is the Manhattan distance measure. Then we have cosine distance measure.
In this case, we take the angle between the two vectors formed by joining the points from the origin.
So that is the cosine distance measure.
Okay, so that was a quick overview about the various distance measures that are supported by k-means.
Now let's go and check how exactly k-means clustering works.
Okay, so this is how k-means clustering works. This is like a flowchart of the whole process.
There is a starting point, and then we specify the number of clusters that we want. Now there are a couple of ways of doing this.
We can do by trial and error.
So we specify a certain number. maybe k is equal to 3 or 4 or 5 to start with. and then as we progress, we keep changing until we get the best clusters.
or there is a technique called elbow technique whereby we can determine the value of k.
what should be the best value of k?
how many clusters should be formed?
So once we have the value of k, we specify that, and then the system will assign that many centroids.
So it picks randomly that to start with randomly that many points that are considered to be the centroids of these clusters.
And then it measures the distance of each of the data points from these centroids and assigns those points to the corresponding centroid from which the distance is minimum.
So each data point will be assigned to the centroid which is closest to it.
And thereby we have k number of initial clusters.
However, this is not the final clusters.
The next step it does is
For the new groups, for the clusters that have been formed, it calculates the main position, thereby calculates the new centroid position.
The position of the centroid moves compared to the randomly allocated one.
So it's an iterative process. Once again, the distance of each point is measured from this new centroid point.
And if required, the data points are reallocated to the new centroids and the mean position or the new centroid is calculated once again.
If the centroid moves, then the iteration continues, which means the convergence has not happened, the clustering has not converged.
So as long as there is a movement of the centroid, this iteration keeps happening.
But once the centroid stops moving, which means that the cluster has converged or the clustering process has converged,
that will be the end result.
So now we have the final position of the centroid and the data points are allocated accordingly to the closest centroid.
I know it's a little difficult to understand from this simple flowchart, so let's do a little bit of visualization and see if we can explain it better.
Let's take an example.
If we have a data set for a grocery shop, so let's say we have a data set for a grocery shop and now we want to find out how many clusters this has to be spread across.
So how do we find the optimum number of clusters?
There is a technique called the elbow method.
So when these clusters are formed, there is a parameter called within sum of squares.
And the lower this value is, the better the cluster is. That means all these points are very close to each other.
So we use this within sum of squares as a measure to find the optimum number of clusters that can be formed for a given data set.
So we create clusters, or we let the system create clusters of a variety of numbers, maybe of ten
clusters.
and for each value of k, the within SS is measured, and the value of k, which has the least amount of within SS, or WSS,
that is taken as the optimum value of k.
So this is the diagrammatic representation.
So we have on the y-axis the within sum of squares or w ss and on the x axis we have the number of clusters.
So as you can imagine, if you have k is equal to one, which means all the data points are in a single cluster, the within SS value will be very high
because they are probably scattered all over.
The moment you split it into two, there will be a drastic fall in the within SS value.
And that's what is represented here.
But then as the value of k increases, the decrease, the rate of decrease will not be so high.
It will continue to decrease, but probably the rate of decrease will not be high.
So that gives us an idea. So from here we get an idea, for example, the optimum value of K should be either 2 or 3 or at the most four.
But beyond that, increasing the number of clusters is not dramatically changing the value in WSS because that pretty much gets stabilized.
Okay, now that we have got the value of K and let's assume that these are our delivery points, the next step is basically
to assign two centroids randomly.
So let's say C1 and C2 are the centroids assigned randomly.
Now the distance of each location from this centroid is measured and each point is assigned to the centroid which is closest to it.
So for example, these points are very obvious that these are closest to C1, whereas this point is far away from C2.
So these points will be assigned which are close to C1 will be assigned to C1, and these points or locations which are close to C2
will be assigned to C2.
And then so this is the how the initial grouping is done.
This is part of C1 and this is part of C2.
Then the next step is to calculate the actual centroid of this data because remember C1 and C2 are not the centroids, they have
been randomly assigned points, and only thing that has been done was the data points which are closest to them have been assigned.
But now in this step, the actual centroid will be calculated, which may be for each of these data sets somewhere in the middle.
So that's like the mean point that will be calculated, and the centroid will actually be positioned or repositioned there.
Same with C2.
So the new centroid for this group is C2 in this new position and C1 is in this new position.
Once again, the distance of each of the data points is calculated from these centroids.
Now remember, it's not necessary that the distance still remains the or each of these data points still remain in the same group.
By recalculating the distance, it may be possible that some points get reallocated.
Like so. You see this?
So this point earlier was closer to C2 because C2 was here.
But after recalculating repositioning, it is observed that this is closer to C1 than C2.
So this is the new grouping. So some points will be reassigned.
And again, the centroid will be calculated. And if the centroid doesn't change, so that is a repetitive process, iterative process.
and if the centroid doesn't change, once the centroid stops changing, that means the algorithm has converged.
and this is our final cluster.
with this as the centroid, c1 and c2 as the centroids.
these data points as a part of each cluster.
So I hope this helps in understanding the whole process, iterative process of k-means clustering.
So let's take a look at the k-means clustering algorithm.
Let's say we have x1, x2, x3, n number of points as our inputs, and we want to split this into
k clusters or we want to create k clusters.
So the first step is to randomly pick k points and call them centroids. They are not real centroids because centroid is supposed to be a center point, but they are just called centroids.
And we calculate the distance of each and every input point from each of the centroids.
So the distance of X1 from C1, from C2, C3, each of the distances we calculate.
And then find out which distance is the lowest and assign x1 to that particular random centroid.
Repeat that process for x2.
Calculate its distance from each of the centroids, C1, C2, C3 up to CK and find which is the lowest distance and assign x2 to that particular centroid. Same with x3 and so on.
So that is the first round of assignment that is done.
Now we have k groups because there are we have assigned the value of k.
So there are k centroids and so there are k groups.
All these inputs have been split into k groups.
However, remember we picked the centroids randomly, so they are not real centroids.
So now what we have to do?
We have to calculate the actual centroids for each of these groups, which is like the mean position.
Which means that the position of the randomly selected centroids will now change and they will be the mean positions of these newly formed K
groups.
And once that is done, we once again repeat this process of calculating the distance, right?
So this is what we are doing as a part of step 4.
We repeat step 2 and 3. So we again calculate the distance of x1 from the centroid C1, C2, C3, and then C which is the lowest value and assign x1 to that.
Calculate the distance of x2 from C1, C2, C3 or whatever up to CK and find whichever is the lowest distance and
assign x2 to that centroid and so on.
In this process, there may be some reassignment.
X1 was probably assigned to cluster C2, and after doing this calculation, maybe now X1 is assigned to C1.
So that kind of reallocation may happen.
So we repeat the steps 2 and 3 till the position of the centroids don't change or stop changing.
And that's when we have convergence.
So let's take a detailed look at it at each of these steps.
So we randomly pick k cluster centers, we call them centroids because they are not initially, they are not really the centroids.
So we let us name them c1, c2 up to ck, and then step two, we assign each data point to the closest center.
So what we do? We calculate the distance of each x value from each c value.
So the distance between x1, c1, distance between x1, c2, x1, c3, and then we find which is the lowest value,
right? That's the minimum value we find.
And assign X1 to that particular centroid.
Then we go next to X2.
Find the distance of X2 from C1, X2 from C2, X2 from C3, and so on up to CK, and then assign it to the point
or to the centroid which has the lowest value and so on.
So that is step number two.
In step number three, we now find the actual centroid for each group. So what has happened as a part of step number two?
We now have all the points, all the data points grouped into k groups because we we wanted to create k clusters,
right?
So we have k groups, each one may be having a certain number of input values, and they need not be equally distributed by the way.
Based on the distance, we will have k groups.
But remember the initial values of the C1, C2 were not really the centroids of these groups, right? We assign them randomly.
So now in step three we actually calculate the centroid of each group, which means the original point which we thought was the centroid
will shift to the new position, which is the actual centroid for each of these groups.
Okay?
And we again calculate the distance. So we go back to step two, which is what?
We calculate again the distance of each of these points from the newly positioned centroids, and if required,
we reassign these points to the new centroids.
So as I said earlier, there may be a reallocation.
So we now have a new set or a new group. We still have K groups, but the number of items and the actual assignment may be different from what was in
step two here.
Okay, so that might change.
Then we perform step three once again to find the new centroid of this new group.
So we have again a new set of clusters, new centroids, and new assignments.
We repeat this step two again, once again, we find, and then it is possible that after iterating through three or four or five times,
the centroid will stop moving in the sense that when you calculate the new value of the centroid, that will be the same as the original value, or there will be very marginal change.
So that is when we say convergence has occurred, and that is our final cluster.
That's the formation of the final cluster.
Alright, so let's see a couple of demos of K-means clustering.
We will actually see some live demos in Python Notebook using Python Notebook.
But before that, let's find out what's the problem that we are trying to solve.
The problem statement is let's say Walmart wants to open a chain of stores across the state of Florida and
it wants to find the optimal store locations.
Now the issue here is if they open too many stores close to each other, obviously the they will not make profit, but
if they if the stores are too far apart, then they will not have enough sales.
So how do they optimize this?
Now for an organization like Walmart, which is an e-commerce giant, they already have the addresses of their customers in their database.
So they can actually use this information or this data and use K means clustering to find the optimal location.
Now, before we go into the Python notebook and show you the live code.
I wanted to take you through very quickly a summary of the code in the slides and then we will go into the Python notebook.
So in this block we are basically importing all the required libraries like NumPy, Matplotlib, and so on.
And we are loading the data that is available in the form of let's say the addresses.
For simplicity's sake, we will just take them as some data points.
Then the next thing we do is quickly do a scatter plot to see how they are related to each other with respect to each other.
So in the scatter plot we see that there are a few distinct groups already being formed.
So you can actually get an idea about how the cluster would look and how many clusters, what is the optimal number of clusters.
And then starts the actual k-means clustering process.
So we will assign each of these points to the centroids and then check whether they are the optimal distance,
which is the shortest distance, and assign each of the points, data points, to the centroids, and then go through this iterative
process till the whole process converges.
And finally, we get an output like this.
So we have four distinct clusters, and
which is, if we can say that this is how the population is probably distributed across Florida state.
and these centroids are like the location where the store should be, the optimum location where the store should be.
So that's the way we determine the best locations for the store, and that's how we can help Walmart find the best locations for their stores in Florida.
So now let's take this into Python notebook. Let's see how this looks when we are learning running the code live.
Alright, so this is the code for k-means clustering in Jupyter Notebook.
We have a few examples here which we will demonstrate how k-means clustering is used, and even there is a small implementation of k-means clustering as well.
Okay, so let's get started. Okay, so this block is basically importing the various libraries that are required, like Macplotlib and NumPy and so on and so forth,
which would be used as a part of the code. Then we are going and creating blobs which are similar to clusters. Now, this is a very neat feature which is available in ScikitLearn.
Make blobs is a nice feature which creates clusters of data sets. So that's a wonderful functionality that is readily available for us to create some test data kind of thing.
Okay, so that's exactly what we are doing here. We are using make blobs and we can specify how many clusters we want. So centers we are mentioning here.
So it will go ahead and so we just mentioned four, so it will go ahead and create some test data for us, and this is how it looks, as you can see.
Visually, also we can figure out that there are four distinct classes or clusters in this data set, and that is what make
blobs actually provides.
Now, from here onwards, we will basically run the standard k-means functionality that is readily available. So we really don't have to implement k-means itself.
The k-means functionality or the function is readily available. You just need to feed the data and we'll create the clusters. So this is the code for that.
We import k-means and then we create an instance of k-means and we specify the value of k. This n underscore clusters is the value of k.
Remember, k means in k means k is basically the number of clusters that you want to create, and it is a integer value.
So this is where we are specifying that. So we have k is equal to 4.
And so that instance is created.
We take that instance, and as with any other machine learning functionality, fit is what we use the function or the method, rather,
fit is what we use to train the model. Here there is no real training uh kind of thing, but that's the call. Okay, so we are calling fit, and what we are doing here, we are just passing the data.
So X has these values, the data that has been created, right?
So that is what we are passing here, and uh, this will go ahead and create the clusters, and uh
then we are using.
After doing uh fit, we run a predict which basically assigns for each of these observations which cluster
it belongs to.
Alright, so it will name the clusters. Maybe this is cluster one, this is two, three, and so on, or will actually start from zero, cluster zero, one, two, and three, maybe,
and then for each of the observations, it will assign based on which cluster it belongs to, it will assign a value. So that is stored in y underscore k means.
When we call predict, that is what it does, and we can take a quick look at these uh y underscore k means or with the cluster numbers that have been assigned for each observation.
So this is the cluster number assigned for observation one, maybe this is for observation two, observation three, and so on. So they we have how many about I think 300 samples, right?
So all the 300 samples, there are 300 values here, each of them the cluster number is given, and the cluster number goes from 0 to 3.
So there are four clusters, so the numbers go from 0, 1, 2, 3.
So that's what is seen here. Okay, now so this was a quick example of generating some dummy data and then clustering that.
Okay, and this can be applied if you have proper data, you can just load it up into X, for example, here, and then run the K-means.
So this is the central part of the K-means clustering program example.
So you basically create an instance and you mention how many clusters you want by specifying this parameter and underscore clusters, and that is also the value of k,
and then pass the data to get the values.
Now, the next section of this code is the implementation of a k-means. Now, this is kind of a rough implementation of the k-means algorithm. So we will just walk you through.
I will walk you through the code uh at each step what it is doing, and then we will see a couple of more examples of how k-means clustering uh can be used in maybe some real life examples,
real life use cases. All right. So in this case, here what we are doing is basically implementing the k-means clustering, and there is a function
or a library calculates for a given two pairs of points, it will calculate the the distance between them and see which one is the closest and so on.
So this is like this is pretty much like what k-means does, right? So it calculates the distance of each point or each data set from predefined centroid, and then based on whichever is the lowest,
this particular data point is assigned to that centroid. So that is basically available as a standard function, and we will be using that here.
So, as explained in the slides, the first step that is done in case of k-means clustering is to randomly assign
some centroids.
So, as a first step, we randomly allocate a couple of centroids which we call here, we are calling as centers.
And then we put this in a loop and we take it through an iterative process.
For each of the data points, we first find out using this function pairwise distance argument.
For each of the points, we find out which one, which center or which uh randomly selected centroid is the closest, and accordingly,
we assign that data or the data point to that particular centroid or cluster.
And once that is done for all the data points, we calculate the new centroid by finding out the mean position
with the the center position, right? So we calculate the new centroid, and then we check if the new centroid is the coordinates or the position is the same as the previous centroid,
the positions we will compare. And if it is the same, that means the process has converged. So remember, we do this process till the centroids or the centroid doesn't move anymore, right?
So the centroid gets relocated each time this reallocation is done. So the moment it doesn't change anymore, the position of the centroid doesn't change anymore, we know that convergence has occurred.
So till then, so you see here this is like an infinite loop. While true is an infinite loop, it only breaks when the centers are the same, the new center and old center positions are the same.
And once that is uh done, uh we return the centers and the labels.
Now, of course, as explained, this is not a very sophisticated and advanced implementation, very basic implementation, because one of the flaws in this is that sometimes what happens is the centroid,
the position will keep moving, but in if the change will be very minor. So, in that case, also with that is actually convergence.
Alright, so for example, the change is 0.0001. We can consider that as convergence. Otherwise, what will happen is this will either take forever or it will be never ending.
So that's a small flaw here. So that is something additional checks may have to be added here. But again, as mentioned, this is not the most sophisticated implementation.
This is like a kind of a rough implementation of the k-means clustering.
Okay, so if we execute this code, this is what we get as the output. So this is the definition of this particular function, and then we call that find underscore clusters and we pass our data
x and the number of clusters, which is four.
And if we run that and plot it, this is the output that we get. So this is of course each cluster is represented by a different color.
So we have a cluster in green color, yellow color, and so on and so forth. And these big points here, these are the centroids, this is the final position of the centroids.
And as you can see visually, also this appears like a kind of a center of all these points here, right? Similarly, this is like the center of all these points here and so on.
So this is the example, or this is an example of an implementation of k-means clustering, and next we will move on to see a couple of examples of how k-means
clustering is used in maybe some real life scenarios or use cases. In the next example or demo, we are going to see how we can use k-means clustering to perform color compression.
We will take a couple of images, so there will be two examples, and uh we will try to use k-means clustering to compress the colors.
This is a common situation in image processing when you have an image with millions of uh colors, but then you cannot render it on some devices which may not have enough memory.
Uh, so that is the scenario where where something like this can be used.
So
before again we go into the Python notebook, let's take a look at quickly the the code.
As usual, we import the libraries and then we import the image and uh then we will flatten it.
So the reshaping is basically we have the image information is stored in the form of pixels, and uh
the image is like for example 427 by 640 and it has three colors, so that's the overall dimension of the of the initial image.
We just reshape it and then feed this to our algorithm, and this will then create clusters of
only 16 clusters. So these this colors there are millions of colors, and now we need to bring it down to 16 colors. So we use k is equal to 16, and this is how when we visualize this is how it looks.
There are these are all about 16 million possible colors.
The input color space has 16 million possible colors, and we just some compress it to 16 colors.
So this is how it would look when we compress it to 16 colors, and this is how the original image looks, and after compression to 16 colors,
this is how the new image looks. As you can see, there is not a lot of information that has been lost, though the image quality is definitely
reduced a little bit. So this is an example which we are going to now see in Python notebook.
Let's go into the Python, and once again, as always, we will import some libraries and load this image called flower.jpg.
Okay, so let we load that and this is how it looks. This is the original image, which has I think 16 million colors, and uh this is the shape of this image, which is basically what is the
shape is nothing but the overall size, right? So this is 427 pixel by 640 pixel, and then there are three layers which is this three basically is for RGB, which is red, green,
blue.
So color image will have that, right? So that is the shape of this. Now, what we need to do is data. Let's take a look at how data is looking.
So let me just create a new cell and show you what is in data. Basically, we have captured this information.
So, data is what let me just show you here.
Alright, so let's take a look at China. What are the values in China? And if we see here, this is how the data is stored. This is nothing but the pixel values.
Okay, so this is like a matrix, and each one has about for this 427 by 640p pixels. Alright, so this is how it looks now.
The issue here is these values are large, the numbers are large, so we need to normalize them to between zero and one,
right? So that's why we will basically create one more variable which is data, which will contain the values between zero and one, and the way to do that is divide by 255.
So we divide China by 255, and we get the new values in data.
So let's just run this uh piece of code and this is the shape. So we now have also, yeah, what we have done is we changed using reshape;
we converted into the three-dimensional into a two-dimensional data set, and let us also take a look at how
—let me just insert
uh probably a cell here —and take a look at how data is looking. Alright, so this is how data is looking, and now you see this is the values are between zero and one, right?
So if you earlier noticed in case of China the values were large numbers, now everything is between zero and one. This is one of the things we need to do.
Alright, so after that, the next thing that we need to do is to visualize this, and uh we can take a random set of maybe 10,000 points
and plot it and check and see how this looks. So let us just plot this. And so this is how the original the color the pixel distribution is.
These are two plots, one is red against green, and another is red against blue, and this is the original distribution of the color.
So then what we will do is we will use k-means clustering to create just 16 clusters for the various colors
and then apply that to the image. Now, what will happen is since the data is large because there are millions of colors, using regular k-means may be a little time consuming.
So there is another version of k-means which is called mini batch k-means.
So we will use that which is which processes in the overall concept remains the same, but this basically processes it in smaller batches, that's the only thing.
Okay, so the results will pretty much be the same. So let's go ahead and execute this piece of code and also visualize this so that we can see that there are these.
This is how the 16 colors uh would look. So this is red against green, and this is uh red against blue. There is uh quite a bit of similarity between this original color schema and the new one, right?
So it doesn't look very, very completely different or anything like that. Now we apply this the newly created colors to the image, and we can take a look how this is uh looking now.
We can compare both the images. So this is our original image, and this is our new image. So as you can see, there is not a lot of information that has been lost.
Uh it pretty much looks like the original image. Yes, we can see that, for example, here there is a little bit, uh it appears a little dullish compared to this one, right?
Because uh we kind of took off some of the finer details of the color, but overall the high-level information has been maintained.
At the same time, the main advantage is that now this can be this is an image which can be rendered on a device which may not be that very sophisticated.
Now let's take one more example with a different image.
In the second example, we will take an image of the summer palace in China and we repeat the same process.
This is a high definition color image with millions of colors and also uh three-dimensional.
Now we will reduce that to 16 colors using k-means clustering, and um.
we do the same process like before: we reshape it, and then we cluster the colors to 16, and then we render the image once again.
and we will see that the color, the quality of the image slightly deteriorates, as you can see here.
This has much finer details in this.
Which are probably missing here, but then that's the compromise because there are some devices which may not be able to handle this kind of uh high density images.
So let's run this code in Python notebook.
Alright, so let's apply the same technique for another picture which is uh even more intricate and has probably a much complicated
color schema. So this is the image now. Once again, uh we can take a look at the shape, which is 427 by 640 by 3.
And this is the new data would look somewhat like this compared to the flower image.
So we have some new values here
and we will also bring this as you can see the numbers are much big, so we will uh much bigger, so we will now have to uh
scale them down to values between 0 and 1, and that is done by dividing by 255.
So let's go ahead and uh do that
and reshape it, okay.
So we get a two-dimensional matrix,
and uh, we will then, as a next step. we will go ahead and visualize this: how it looks, the the 16 colors.
and this is basically how it would look —16 million colors —and. now we can, uh create the clusters out of this. The 16k means clusters we will create.
So, this is how the distribution of the pixels would look with the 16 colors, and then we go ahead and uh apply this
and visualize how it is looking for with the with the new just the 16 colors.
So, once again, as you can see, this looks much richer in color, but at the same time, and this probably doesn't have, as we can see,
it doesn't look as rich as this one, but nevertheless, the information is not lost, the shape and all that stuff.
and this can be also rendered on a uh slightly, uh device, which is, uh, probably uh, not that sophisticated. Okay, so that's pretty much it.
So we have seen two examples of how color compression can be done, uh, using k-means clustering.
and we have also seen in the previous examples, uh of how to implement k-means at the core, to roughly how to implement. uh k-means. uh clustering.
and we use some sample data using uh blob to just execute the k-means clustering.
We talk about the principal component uh analysis.
We're gonna cover dimensionality reduction, principal component analysis. What is it?
Ever wondered how to build an AI project that actually gets noticed by Google, OpenAI, or top startups, not just a chartboard or recycle homework.
Today I'm going to walk you through 10 AI project ideas for 2026 that are practical, futuristic, and portfolio
ready. I'll tell you exactly which models, framework, and data sets to use so that you can start coding immediately.
Now, before we jump into, hit that like button, share, and subscribe because keeping up with future-proof AI projects is going to give you a massive edge. Let's start with the AI shopping buddy.
This project acts like a personal stylist and interior designer. Users upload photos of their room, outfit, or even face, and the AI suggests products that match color, style, and preferences.
This isn't just about throwing recommendations at someone, it's about computer vision to understand images, generative AI to create style suggestions
and recommendation algorithms to find the perfect products. Personalized recommendation systems drive massive engagement and conversions, which is why companies like Amazon, Flipkart, Mintra,
or Herbal Lado would be thrilled to hit someone who can build this.
Completing a project like this demonstrates skills in deep learning, computer vision, generative AI, and full-stack deployment for web
or mobile app. While shopping and lifestyle AI is exciting, the next project takes up to our health and wellness.
The Smart Health Analyzer predicts stress, burnout, or sleep issues by analyzing voice, facial microexpressions,
and wearable data. It uses multimodal AI that integrates time series analysis. For wearable data, NFD for voice and text, and computer vision for microexpressions.
Healthcare startups in India and globally, like Healthy Vy, CureFit, Fitbit, and Apple Health, are looking for engineers who can make predictive
wellness tools. Building this project demonstrates your ability to work with multi-model AI, pre-process complex data sets, train models,
and visualize results. Moving from personal health to professional efficiency, the AI Productivity Agent automates your daily workflow.
It reads emails, scans your calendar, understands priorities, and builds an optimized schedule.
It uses NLP to parse emails, API integration with other tools like Gmail, Slack, and Notion and optimization algorithms to prioritize tasks efficiently.
Productivity loss is a major issue for companies, which is why tech giants like Google, Workspace, Microsoft 365, and startups in workflow automation
would be very interested in this project. It is a great way to demonstrate automation, NLP, API integration, and practical problem-solving skills.
Taking automation to the next level, the voice-to-action system allows users to speak commands and have the AI perform multi-step
action such as booking flights, organizing files, or generating reports. It relies on speech-to-text models, intent classification using NLP and task automation pipelines.
You can train intent classification models using dataset into the SNPS NLU dataset.
This project builds directly on productivity AI and is exactly the kind of work that Amazon, OpenAI, or Apple would notice for voice-driven automation solutions.
Once we have automated tasks, why not explore creativity? Genvete AI Story Maker allows you to create full stories including scripts, characters, and visuals based on just a few keywords.
Now it uses large language models for text generation and image generation models like stable diffusion, DALI 3 for visuals, and you can also train fine-tuned models on datasets
like CMU Book Summary Corpus on writing prompts. Text-to-speech libraries such as Cokeweek TTS or GTTS can add narration.
Media companies like Netflix, Ubisoft, and Adobe are actively investing in generative AI, and a project like this would definitely stand out.
Building on the idea of multiple AI capabilities working together, the multi-agent AI team project introduces collaboration between AI agents.
Multiple AI agents are assigned specialized roles such as researching, writing, criticing, and summarizing.
They communicate and coordinate to complete complex tasks using multi-agent reinforcement, learning and communication protocols.
Enterprise AI and automation platforms are investing heavily in this approach, and companies like Entropic, OpenAI,
AI workflow startups are actively seeking engineers who can build collaborative AI systems.
From collaboration to observation, the AI body language reader analyzes microexpressions, tone of voice and posture
to provide feedback on communication skills. It can be applied in interviews, public speaking, or remote coaching.
Computer vision tools such as open pose or media pie poles track gestures and posture, while audio processing libraries such as Librosa
Analyze Tone. Models can be trained using datasets like Ravdesk for audio and CK Plus for facial expressions.
HR Tech companies like HighView, Pymetrics, and AI coaching startups would highly value this type of project as it helps
bridge human behavior and AI analysis. Narigation is also another area being transformed by AI.
The personalized tutor with adaptive difficulty creates an AI tutor that adjusts lessons in real time based on student performance.
Knowledge tracing models like deep knowledge tracing combined with transformers for content generation allow the AI to adapt to each learner.
Data sets such as assessments or ednits can be used for training. Now this AI Can generate new questions, explanations, and motivational feedback based on learning phase.
Companies like Baijues, Vedanto, Coursera, and Udemy are constantly looking for talent that can build adaptive learning platforms.
Next, we move into research augmentation with the autonomous research agent.
This AI can answer research questions by reading academic papers, extracting insights, summarizing information, and citing sources automatically.
It uses the S2 Org dataset for academic papers, Cyborg for scientific text embeddings, and Hugging Face
Transformers or LandChain for reasoning and summarization. Citation extraction can be done with NLP passwords or rejects academic platforms.
AI labs and companies like Google Research, OpenAI, ResearchGate, and LCBO would hire engineers who can build this system.
This project connects perfectly with education-focused AI, extending learning into automated research capabilities.
Finally, we arrive at real-world robotics control with the AI, the ultimate demonstration of cutting-edge skills.
This project trains AI to control robotic arms or humanoids based on goals rather than just rigid instructions.
It uses PyBullet or Volts for simulation, stable baseline 3 or R Link for reinforcement learning, and OpenCV
or Media Pipe for vision input. Simple real transfer techniques bring simulations into real-world scenarios.
Robotics companies like Boston Dynamics, Artronic, Amazon Robotics, and AjiBot are seeking engineers capable of end-to-end
AI-driven robotics systems. After exploring software-based AI projects, robotics is the next step to show mastery of AI applied in the physical world. These 10 AI projects are more than just ideas.
They are a step-by-step career blueprint for 2026. Building even one of these projects properly will make your portfolio stand out globally.
So let's start with beginner level questions and number one is what is machine learning?
So machine learning is a subset of artificial intelligence that involves the use of algorithms and statistical models to enable computers to perform tasks without explicit instructions.
That is, by relying on patterns and interference.
And now moving to number second question, that is what are the different types of machine learning?
So the three main types of machine learning are number one is supervised learning, and then comes unsupervised learning, and then there is reinforcement learning.
Now moving to the next question that is third.
That is what is supervised learning?
So supervised learning involves training a model on a label data set, which means each training example is paired with an output label.
The model learns to predict the output from the input data.
Now moving to the fourth question, that is what is unsupervised learning.
So unsupervised involves training a model on data that does not have labeled responses.
The model tries to learn the patterns and the structure from the input data.
So guys, these are the beginner level questions.
And now we'll move to the fifth question. That is what is reinforcement learning.
So reinforcement learning is a type of machine learning where an agent learns to make decisions by performing actions and receiving rewards or penalties.
The goal is to maximize the accumulative reward.
So now moving to the sixth question, that is what is a model in machine learning.
So a model in machine learning is a mathematical representation of a real-world process.
It is trained on data to recognize patterns and make predictions or decisions based on new data.
So now moving to the seventh question, that is what is overfitting.
So overfitting occurs when a machine learning model performs well on the training data, but poorly on new unseen data.
It indicates that the model has learned the noise and details in the training data instead of the actual patterns.
So now coming to question number eight, that is what is underfitting.
So underfitting occurs when a machine learning model is too simple to capture the underlying patterns in the data.
It performs poorly on both the training data and new data.
Now moving to the next question, that is ninth question, and the question is what is a confusion matrix?
So confusion matrix is a table used to evaluate the performance of a classification model.
It summarizes the number of correct and incorrect predictions made by the model and that is categorized by each class.
Now moving to the tenth question, that is what is cross-validation.
So cross-validation is a technique for assessing how the results of a statistical analysis will generalize to an independent dataset.
It involves partitioning the data into subsets, training the model on some subsets, and validating it on the remaining subsets.
So this was all about that is the 10th question or the overall 1 to 10 questions for beginner level.
Now we'll move to intermediate level and here we'll cover 10 questions.
So we'll start with 11th question that is what is a ROC curve.
So ROC that is receiver operating characteristic curve.
It is a graphical representation of a classifier's performance across different thresholds.
It plots the true positive rate that is TPR against a false positive rate that is FPR.
Now moving to the 12th question, that is what is precision and recall.
So precision is the ratio of correctly predicted positive observations to the total predicted positives.
And recall is the ratio of correctly predicted positive observations to all actual positives.
So the formula is precision equal to TP slash TP plus FP and the recall is TP slash TP plus Fn.
So now we'll move to the 13th question that is what is the F1 score?
So the F1 score is the harmonic mean of precision and recall.
It provides a balance between the two metrics and is useful when you need to balance precision and recall.
F1 score is equal to twice into precision into recall and that is divided by precision plus recall.
Now we'll move to the 14th question and here we will cover regularization.
So the question is what is regularization?
So it is a technique used to prevent overfitting by adding a penalty to the model's complexity.
And the common types of regularization include L1, that is lasso, and L2, ridge regularization.
Now we'll move to the 15th question that is what is the bias variance trade-off.
So the bias variance tradeoff is a fundamental issue in machine learning that involves balancing the error introduced by the model's assumptions
and the error due to model complexity.
So a good model should have low bias and low variance.
Now we'll move to the question number 16, that is what is feature engineering.
So feature engineering is the process of creating new features or modifying existing ones to improve the performance of a machine learning model.
It involves techniques like normalization and coding categorical variables and creating interaction terms.
So now we'll move to question number 17 and that is about gradient descent.
So the question is what is gradient descent?
And your answer is gradient descent is an optimization algorithm used to minimize the cost function in machine learning models
and it iteratively adjusts the model parameters in the direction of the steepest descent of the cost function.
So with this we'll move to the 18th question and that we'll cover with the difference between bagging and boosting.
So the question is what is the difference between bagging and boosting?
And you could answer this with starting with bagging, that is bootstrap aggregating.
That involves training multiple models on different subsets of the data and averaging their predictions.
Then comes boosting that involves training models sequentially with each new model focusing on correcting the errors of the previous ones.
And then we have the question number 19, that is what is a decision tree.
So a decision tree is a known parametric supervised learning algorithm used for classification and regression.
It splits the data into subsets based on the value of input features, resulting in a tree-like structure of decisions.
Now we'll move to question number 20, that is what is a random forest.
So random forest is an ensemble learning method that combines multiple decision trees to improve the accuracy and robustness of the model.
It builds each tree using a random subset of features and data points and then averages their predictions.
So these were the questions that are for the intermediate level.
And these are just the basic questions, or I will just say the theoretical questions that can be asked in an interview.
So be prepared for that. Now we'll move to the advanced level interview questions and we'll start with question number 21.
And here also we'll cover the 10 questions.
So number one question, or that is 21 question, and the question is what is a support vector machine?
So support vector machine is a supervised learning algorithm used for classification and regression.
It finds the optimal hyperplane that maximizes the margin between different classes in the feature space.
And then comes question number 22, that is what is principal component analysis.
So principal component analysis is a dimensionality reduction technique that transforms high-dimensional data into a lower dimensional space by finding the directions,
that is, principal components that maximize the variance in the data.
And then comes the question number 23, that is what is a neural network.
So a neural network is a series of algorithms that attempt to recognize underlying relationships in a set of data through a process that mimics the way the human brain operates.
It consists of a layer of interconnected nodes or neurons.
And then comes the question number 24, that is what is deep learning.
So deep learning is a subset of machine learning that involves neural networks with many layers, that is,
deep neural networks, and it is particularly effective for tasks like image and speech recognition.
Now I'll move to question number 25, that is, what is convolutional neural network, that is CNN.
So we will start the answer by answering the interviewer that a convolutional neural network is a type of deep running model specifically designed for processing structured grid data like images.
It uses convolutional layers to extract special features or the spatial features and patterns from the input data.
Now we'll move to the question number 26.
That is, what is a recurrent neural network or RNN?
So a recurrent neural network is a type of neural network designed for sequential data and it has connections that form directed cycles,
allowing it to maintain a memory of previous inputs and process sequences of data.
So this is all about question number 26, and now we will cover the question number 27 that is what is the difference between batch gradient descent and
stochastic gradient descent.
So batch gradient descent computes the gradient of the cost function using the entire training dataset, while stochastic gradient descent that is
SGD computes the gradient using only one training example at a time.
So SGD is faster but noisier.
Now we'll move to question number 28.
That is what is dropout in neural networks.
So dropout is a regularization technique used in neural networks to prevent overfitting, and it involves randomly setting a fraction of the neurons to zero during training,
forcing the network to learn more robust features.
And now we'll move to question number 29 and that will be about transfer learning.
And your question is, what is transfer learning?
So we'll answer this to the interviewer by starting that transfer learning is a technique in machine learning where a model developed for one task is reused
as the starting point for a model on a second related task.
It is particularly useful when there is limited data available for the second task.
Now we'll move to the last question and the 30th question.
So that is what is a generative adversarial network that is GN.
So you can start answering this.
So generative adversarial network is a type of deep learning model consisting of two neural networks, a generator and a discriminator that are trained simultaneously.
The generator creates fake data while the discriminator tries to distinguish between real and fake data, leading to the generator producing increasingly realistic data.
And these questions and answers are over, and these covers a wide range of topics in machine learning and should help prepare for interviews at various levels.
Today we will learn about some of the machine learning and deep learning interview questions.
So let's begin with the first question.
The first question is how to detect outliers in data.
So in data analytics and machine learning,
you often find data points that lie at an abnormal distance from other points in a random sample from a population.
Those are called outliers.
Now outliers in data can significantly impact any prediction analysis.
There are majorly three different methods to treat outliers.
First, we have the univariate method.
It is one of the simplest methods for detecting outliers.
The univariate method uses box plots.
A box plot is a graphical display for describing the distributions of the data.
Box plots use the median and the lower and upper quartiles.
This method looks for data points with extreme values on one variable.
Next, we have the multivariate method.
So the multivariate outliers can be found in an n-dimensional space having n features.
We look for unusual combinations of all the variables in this method.
Finally, we have Minkowski error.
This method reduces the contribution of potential outliers in the training process.
The Minkowski error is a loss index that is more insensitive to outliers than the standard mean squared error.
Now moving on to the second question:
What is a confusion matrix?
So a confusion matrix is a table that is used to describe the performance of a classification model and a set of test data for which the true values are already known.
The target variable has two values, positive or negative.
The columns represent the actual values of the target variable, which you can see here.
The rows represent the predicted values of the target variable, which you can see here.
Now there are four important terms that are related to confusion matrix.
First, we have true positive, which is this one.
So in true positive, the predicted value matches the actual value.
So the actual value was positive and the model also predicted a positive value.
Then we have true negative,
which is also represented as Tn.
The true negative depicts the predicted value matches the actual value.
Now the actual value was negative and the model predicted a negative value.
Next we have false positive.
Now false positive is also known as type 1 error.
In false positive, the predicted value was falsely predicted.
The actual value was negative, but the model predicted a positive value.
Finally, we have false negative, now false negative is also known as type 2 error.
So, in false negative, the predicted value was falsely predicted.
The actual value was positive, but the model predicted a negative value.
Now moving to a third question,
which is explain the ROC curve.
Now the ROC curve is one of the most important evaluation matrix for checking the performance of any classification model.
ROC stands for receiver operating characteristic.
Receiver operating characteristic or ROC curve is a method to compare the diagnostic tests.
The ROC curve is created by plotting the true positive rate against the false positive rate at various threshold settings.
So here on the y-axis you have the true positive rate, on the x-axis we have the false positive rate.
The true positive rate indicates the proportion of observations that were correctly predicted to be positive out of all positive observations.
Similarly, the false positive rate is the proportion of observations that are incorrectly predicted to be positive out of all negative observations.
You can take an example, suppose in medical testing, the true positive rate is the rate in which people are correctly identified to test positive for the disease in question,
let's say the coronavirus testing.
ROC does not depend on any class distribution.
This makes it useful for evaluating classifiers predicting rare events such as diseases or disasters.
Now moving to the fourth question, we have
what are the assumptions for linear regression?
So linear regression analysis is used for modeling the relationship between a single dependent variable y and one or more feature or predictor variables.
Some of the important assumptions for linear regression are so first
they should have linearity.
So linear regression needs the relationship between the independent and the dependent variables to be linear.
It is also crucial to check for outliers since linear regression is sensitive to outlier effects.
Next, we have homo schedasticity.
Homo schedasticity illustrates a situation in which the error term, that is, the noise or random disturbance
in the relationship between the features and the target variable is the same across all levels of the dependent variables.
Third, we have independence, so observations should be independent of each other.
Finally, we have no multi-colinearity, so there should be little or no multi-colinearity.
Independent variables should not be too highly correlated.
Now moving to our fifth question in our list of interview questions.
The question is What is regularization in machine learning?
Explain the L2 regularization.
So regularization is a machine learning technique that is used to reduce the errors by fitting the function appropriately on the training set in order to avoid overfitting of data.
So overfitting happens when a model learns the detail and noise in the training data to the extent that it negatively impacts the performance of the model on new data.
So here you can see we have
a nice plot which shows how overfitting of data can be visualized.
And here
we have a good fit line over the same data points.
So this is also known as the regression line.
Now L2 regularization is also known as ridge regression.
So ridge regression modifies the overfit and model by adding the squared magnitude of coefficient as a penalty term to the loss function.
So on the right you can see a set of data points plotted and we have our linear regression line, and here we are calculating the cost function for the ridge regression line.
So our cost function is actually loss plus lambda into summation of W squared where loss is actually the sum of squared errors or squared residuals.
Lambda stands for penalty for the errors, W is called the slope of the curve or line.
Now consider a case
where there are two points passing through the linear regression
line. Now if you calculate the cost function,
we get the value as 1.69.
So here we have assumed that loss is 0 since the two points lie directly on the line.
We have taken lambda to be 1 and w is 1.3.
So if you use this function or this formula,
you get the cost function as 1.69.
Now moving ahead, let's consider another situation where we will calculate the same cost function for the ridge regression line.
There is some loss for both the points as they are not on the same line.
So here you can see the sum of squared residuals is 0.05, which actually is the sum of 0.2 square, I am assuming this as 0.2
and 0.1 for this one.
So, if you square both and add it, the value is 0.05, lambda is again 1, and w we have assumed to be 0.6.
Now, if you find the cost function, the value is 0.41.
Let's draw the linear regression line and the ridge regression line with all the points.
We find that the ridge regression line has the best fit since its cost function is less.
If getting your learning started is half the battle, what if you could do that for free? Visit scale up by Simply Learn. Click on the link in the description to know more.
Now coming to the sixth question,
what are the different methods to split a tree in a decision tree algorithm?
So there are three methods to split a decision tree.
First, we have variance.
So reduction in variance is an algorithm that is used for continuous target variables.
This algorithm uses the standard formula of variance to choose the best split.
So here you can see the standard formula of variance which is summation of x that is all the individual points minus x bar which is the mean
squared divided by the total number of observations.
Now the split with lower variance is selected as the criteria to split the population.
Now the steps to calculate variance is you need to calculate variance for each node and then you need to calculate for each split as the weighted average of each node variance.
Moving ahead, the second method we have is information gain.
So information gain is used for splitting the nodes when the target variable is categorical.
It works on the concept of entropy.
Now the degree of disorganization in a system is known as entropy.
So here you can see the formula for information gain which is 1 minus entropy.
Finally, we have Gini impurity.
So Gini impurity is the probability of incorrectly classifying a randomly chosen element in the dataset if it were randomly labelled according to the class distribution in the dataset.
So below you can see the formula for Gini impurity.
So we have 1 minus summation of PI whole square where n represents the number of classes and P of I represents the probability of randomly picking an element of class I.
Now moving to the seventh question.
So the question is how do we find the optimum cluster value in k means clustering algorithm?
Now there are two methods to find the optimum cluster value.
So first we have the elbow method, which is one of the most well known for finding the optimum number of clusters.
So in this method, you need to calculate the within cluster sum of squared errors for different values of k and choose the k for which within cluster
sum of squared errors first starts to diminish.
So in the below plot of squared errors versus the number of clusters k,
you can see at k is equal to 4 the squared error starts to diminish, so hence our optimum k value is 4.
Next we have the siloid method.
So the siloid method measures how similar a point is to its own cluster compared to other clusters.
The average silloid method computes the average siloid of observations for different values of k.
The optimum number of clusters k is the one that maximizes the average siloid over a range of possible values for k.
The siloid score reaches its global maximum at the optimal k.
So in our case, the average silloid reaches maximum at k is equal to 2, which you can see here. So our optimum cluster value will be 2 here.
Moving ahead,
the eighth question in our list is
how does the pooling layer work in a convolutional neural network?
So the pooling layer performs a downsampling operation in order to reduce the dimensionality of the feature map.
So in the pooling operation, you slide a two dimensional filter over each channel of feature map and summarize the features lying within the region covered by the filter.
It is a common practice to periodically insert a pooling layer in between successive convolutional layers in a convolutional neural network architecture.
So the pooling layer operates independently on every depth slice in the input and resizes it spatially using the max operation.
So in the diagram shown here, you can see we have a rectified feature map.
We are using a 2 cross 2 filter and performing a max pooling operation.
So consider this as the filter if you perform the max operation over the values,
let us say 0, 5, 3, and 1. So considering this one, our pool feature map maximum value will be 5.
Similarly, for this chunk of data, it is going to be 7.
Next, if you slide the filter over this square frame, you get 8, and similarly, here you get 6.
So this is also known as a pooled feature map.
Moving ahead,
the ninth question in our list is how does LSTM network work?
So long short-term memory networks are a type of recurrent neural networks that are capable of learning audit dependence and sequence prediction problems.
So remembering information for long periods of time is practically their default behavior.
Now LSTMs also have this chain-like structure which you can see here,
but the repeating module has a different structure.
So instead of having a single neural network layer, there are four interacting in a very special way.
Now you can see these are called as gates.
These gates contain sigmoid activations.
A sigmoid activation is similar to the tan H activation.
Instead of squishing values between minus 1 and plus 1, it squishes values between 0 and 1.
An LSTM has four gates.
Now these are called forget, remember, learn and use or output.
So if you see this, in the first step, we use the forget gate that decides what information should be thrown away or kept.
The information from the previous hidden state and the information from the current input is passed through the sigmoid function.
Values come out between 0 and 1.
So if the value is closer to 0, it means you need to forget that information.
And if the value is closer to 1, it means you need to keep that information.
Next, we have the input gate.
So the input gate is used to update the cell state.
First, we pass the previous hidden state and the current input into a sigmoid function.
That decides which values will be updated by transforming the values to be between 0 and 1.
0 means not important and 1 means important.
You also pass the hidden state and current input into the Tanage function to flatten the values between minus 1 and plus 1.
This helps to regulate the network.
Then you multiply the Tanage output with the sigmoid output.
The sigmoid output will decide which information is important to keep from the Tanage output.
And finally in step 3, we have the output gate.
This output gate is used to decide
what the next hidden state should be.
First, we pass the previous hidden state and the current input into a sigmoid function.
Then we pass the newly modified cell state into the Tanage function.
We then multiply the TANH output with the sigmoid output to decide what information the hidden state should carry.
The output is the hidden state.
The new cell state and the new hidden state is then carried over to the next time step.
Finally, talking about the last question in our list of interview questions, we have explained the concept of gradient descent in deep learning.
Now, gradient descent is an optimization algorithm which is mainly used to find the minimum of a function.
In machine learning, gradient descent is used to update the parameters in a model.
Parameters can vary according to the algorithms such as coefficients in linear regression and weights in neural networks.
You can see
we have these maps, and on the y-axis we have the loss,
on the x-axis we have the weight, and here we are trying to find the local minimum or the global minimum.
Now, this gradient descent method is used to minimize the cost function and update the parameters of the learning model.
The gradient always points in the direction of the steepest increase in the loss function.
The gradient descent algorithm takes a step in the direction of the negative gradient in order to reduce the loss as quickly as possible.
To determine the next point along the loss function curve, the gradient descent algorithm adds some fraction of the gradient's magnitude to the starting point.
Now this process is repeated to find the global minimum. We know humans learn from their past experiences, and machines follow instructions given by humans.
But what if humans can train the machines to learn from their past data and do what humans can do and much faster? Well, that's called machine learning.
But it's a lot more than just learning, it's also about understanding and reasoning. So today we will learn about the basics of machine learning. So that's Paul. He loves listening to new songs.
He either likes them or dislikes them. Paul decides this on the basis of the song's tempo, genre, intensity, and the gender of voice. For simplicity, let's just use tempo and intensity for now.
So here, tempo is on the x-axis ranging from relaxed to fast, whereas intensity is on the y axis ranging from light to soaring.
We see that Paul likes the song with fast tempo and soaring intensity, while he dislikes the song with relaxed tempo
and light intensity. So now we know Paul's choices. Let's say Paul listens to a new song. Let's name it as song A. Song A has fast tempo and a soaring intensity. So it lies somewhere here.
Looking at the data, can you guess whether Paul will like the song or not? Correct. So Paul likes this song.
By looking at Paul's past choices, we were able to classify the unknown song very easily, right? Let's say now Paul listens to a new song. Let's label it as song B.
So song B lies somewhere here with medium tempo and medium intensity. Neither relaxed nor fast, neither light nor soaring. Now can you guess whether Paul likes it or not?
Not able to guess whether Paul will like it or dislike it? Are the choices unclear? Correct. We could easily classify song A. But when the choice became complicated, as in the case of song B, yes.
And that's where machine learning comes in. Let's see how.
In the same example, for song B, if we draw a circle around the song B, we see that there are four votes for like, whereas one vote for dislike.
If we go for the majority votes, we can say that Paul will definitely like the song. That's all. This was a basic machine learning algorithm also. It's called K nearest neighbours.
So this is just a small example in one of the many machine learning algorithms. Quite easy, right? Believe me, it is. But what happens when the choices become complicated? As in the case of song B.
That's when machine learning comes in. It learns the data, builds the prediction model, and when the new data point comes in, it can easily predict for it.
More the data, better the model, higher will be the accuracy. There are many ways in which the machine learns. It could be either supervised learning, unsupervised learning, or reinforcement learning.
Let's first quickly understand supervised learning. Suppose your friend gives you 1 million coins of three different currencies, say 1 rupee, 1 euro, and 1 dirham. Each coin has different weights.
For example, a coin of 1 rupee weighs 3 grams, 1 euro weighs 7 grams, and 1 dirham weighs 4 grams. Your model will predict the currency of the coin.
Here, your weight becomes the feature of coins while currency becomes their label. When you feed this data to the machine learning model, it learns which feature is associated with which label.
For example, it will learn that if a coin is of 3 grams, it will be a 1 rupee coin. Let's give a new coin to the machine.
On the basis of the weight of the new coin, your model will predict the currency. Hence, supervised learning uses labeled data to train the model.
Here the machine knew the features of the object and also the labels associated. Associated with those features. On this note, let's move to unsupervised learning and see the difference.
Suppose you have a cricket dataset of various players with their respective scores and the wickets taken.
When we feed this data set to the machine, the machine identifies the pattern of player performance. So it plots this data with the respective wickets on the x-axis while runs on the y-axis.
While looking at the data, you will clearly see that there are two clusters.
The one cluster are the players who scored high runs and took less wickets, while the other cluster is of the players who scored less runs but took many wickets.
So here we interpret these two clusters as batsmen and bowlers. The important point to note here is that there were no labels of batsmen and bowlers.
Hence, the learning with unlabeled data is unsupervised learning. So we saw supervised learning where the data was labeled and the unsupervised learning where the data was unlabeled.
And then there is reinforcement learning, which is reward-based learning. Or we can say that it works on the principle of feedback.
Here, let's say you provide the system with an image of a dog and ask it to identify it. The system identifies it as a cat.
So you give a negative feedback to the machine saying that it's a dog's image.
The machine will learn from the feedback and finally, if it comes across any other image of a dog, it will be able to classify it correctly. That is reinforcement learning.
To generalize machine learning model, let's see a flowchart. Input is given to a machine learning model, which then gives the output according to the algorithm applied.
If it's right, we take the output as a final result. Else, we provide feedback to the training model and ask it to predict until it learns.
I hope you've understood supervised and unsupervised learning. So let's have a quick quiz. You have to determine whether the given scenarios uses supervised or unsupervised learning. Simple, right?
Scenario 1. Facebook recognizes your friend in a picture from an album of tagged photographs. Scenario 2. Netflix recommends new movies based on someone's past movie choices. Scenario 3.
Analyzing bank data for suspicious transactions and flagging the fraud transactions. Think wisely and comment below your answers.
Moving on, don't you sometimes wonder how is machine learning possible in today's era? Well that's because today we have humongous data available.
Everybody is online either making a transaction or just surfing the internet, and that's generating a huge amount of data every minute. And that data, my friend, is the key to analysis.
Also, the memory handling capabilities of computers have largely increased, which helps them to process such a huge amount of data at hand without any delay.
And yes, computers now have great computational powers. So there are a lot of applications of machine learning out there.
To name a few, machine learning is used in healthcare where diagnostics are predicted for doctor's review.
The sentiment analysis that the tech giants are doing on social media is another interesting application of machine learning,
fraud detection in the finance sector, and also to predict customer churn in the e-commerce sector.
While booking a gap, you must have encountered search pricing often where it says the fare of your trip has been updated. Continue booking. Yes please, I'm getting late for office.
Well, that's an interesting machine learning model which is used by global taxi giant Uber and others, where they have differential pricing in real time based on demand,
the number of cars available, bad weather, rush hour, etc. So they use the search pricing model to ensure that those who need a cab can get one.
Also, it uses predictive modeling to predict where the demand will be high, with the goal that drivers can take care of the demand and search pricing can be minimized. Great.
Hey Siri, can you remind me to book a cab at 6 pm today? Okay, I'll remind you. Thanks. No problem.
Comment below some interesting everyday examples around you where machines are learning and doing amazing jobs. These days we usually ask Siri, hey Siri, how far is the nearest fuel station?
Whenever we ask Siri something, the powerful speech recognition system gets to work and converts the audio into its actual form.
This is then sent to the Apple server for further processing.
And then machine learning algorithms are run to understand the user's intent.
And then finally, Siri tells you the answer.
Well, this is happening because of these machine learning algorithms.
Think about it, not too long ago, most tasks were done by people.
Whether it was building things, performing surgeries, or even playing games like chess.
Humans were in control.
But now things are changing fast.
Almost all manual tasks are becoming automated, meaning machines and computers are taking over those jobs.
This shift is redefining what we consider manual work.
Machine learning, a type of artificial intelligence, is at the heart of this transformation.
There are so many different machine learning algorithms out there, each designed to help computers learn and get better at task.
From playing chess like Grandmaster to performing delicate surgeries with amazing precision.
These algorithms are making technology smarter and more personal everyday.
So now that we have covered a brief about ML, I want you guys to quickly check out the quiz attached below in the description section.
Take a moment to answer and let me know your thoughts in the comment section as well.
In today's video, we are going to cover the top 10 machine learning algorithms that every aspiring machine learning engineer should know.
Whether you are building models to predict the future, analyzing data, or creating smart apps.
Mastering these algorithms will help you make the most of machine learning.
So now let's get started with what is an algorithm.
What is an algorithm?
In computer programming, an algorithm is a set of well-defined instructions to solve a particular problem.
It takes a bunch of information sources and delivers the ideal result.
Most of us must be using Snapchat to apply filter on our faces while making videos or capturing photographs.
But do you know how does Snapchat recognize your face while capturing videos or photographs and put filters on it?
Even if there are multiple phases, it applies filter on every face accurately.
This became possible with the help of the face recognition technique, which uses machine learning algorithms to detect faces and apply required filters on them.
So this is the basic idea of how an algorithms work.
So let's move ahead in this video and we'll see now how algorithm works in machine learning.
So, how do algorithm works?
Everyone knows the algorithm is a step-by-step process to approach a particular problem.
So there are numerous examples of algorithms from figuring out sets of numbers to finding rules through maps to showing data on the screen.
Let's understand this by using example.
Every algorithm is built on inputs and the outputs.
Google search algorithm is no different.
The input is a search field and the output is the page of results that appears when you enter a particular phrase or keyword.
Also known as SERP or search engine result page.
Google has algorithms so it can sort its result from various websites and provide the user with the best result.
When you start, you will see the search box will attempt to guess what you are looking for.
In order to better understand what the user is looking for, the algorithm is trying to gather as many suggestions from them as possible.
The result from the search field that best matches the query will then be ranked.
They choose which website will rank and in what position using more than 200 ranking variables.
Now that we have covered a brief about how algorithms work, I want you guys to quickly check out the quiz attached below in the description section.
Take a moment to answer and let me know your thoughts in the comment section as well.
Moving forward, let's see types of machine learning.
So machine learning is classified into supervised learning, unsupervised learning, and reinforcement learning.
There are two sorts of problems in supervised learning: classification and regression.
Certain types of machine learning algorithms fall under the classification are decision tree algorithms, KNN algorithm, logistic algorithm, name-based algorithm,
support vector machine algorithm, SVM.
However, in regression, types of machine learning algorithms are linear regression, regression trees, non-linear regression, Bayesian linear regression.
Now talking about unsupervised learning, there are two sorts of problems in unsupervised learning, which are clustering and association.
Algorithms that fall under the clustering problems include K means clustering algorithms, principal component analysis.
However, algorithms that fall under association problem are a priori algorithm and FP growth.
In reinforcement learning, there are two types positive reinforcement and negative reinforcement.
Reinforcement learning algorithms are mainly used in AI application and gaming application.
The main used algorithms are Q learning, state action reward, state action, SAR SA, and Deep Q Neural Network DQN and Markov
decision process.
After discussing what algorithm says and its types, so now let's see some popular machine learning algorithms.
The first one is linear regression, and the second one is logistic regression.
third one is decision trees, and the fourth one is SVM support vector machine, and the fifth one is PCA principal component analysis,
and the sixth is K-Means clustering, and seventh is random forest, and eighth is autoencoders, and ninth is DBSCAN.
It's known as density-based spatial clustering of application with noise.
And the last one we have is hierarchical clustering.
So now let's see these algorithms one by one.
So first one we have linear regression, a statical method used to model the relationship between a dependent variable, which is known as the target variable, and one or more independent variables,
which are the predictors.
It assumes a linear relationship between the inputs and the output.
Real life example is house price prediction.
Predicting house prices based on features like size, location, and number of rooms.
So, for example, on average, large houses cost more is the linear trend identified by this algorithm.
Some applications are real estate price prediction, sales forecasting, and stock price prediction.
And the second one is logistic regression.
A classification algorithm used to predict binary outcomes that is yes or no or true or false.
It uses a logistic function to model the probability of a particular class.
Real life example is email spam filter.
Identifying spam emails based on certain features, keywords and a number of links.
For instance, an email with claim your free gift now is classified as a spam.
Application are email spam filtering, medical diagnosis, and customer churn prediction and many more.
The third one we have decision trees.
A flowchart-like tree structure used to make decisions.
Each node in the tree represents a decision based on a feature and each branch represents a possible outcome.
Real life example is loan approval process.
A bank using decision trees might ask is the applicant credit score above 700 and proceed with further question to approve or deny the loan.
Application R loan approval, medical diagnosis, and marketing campaign analysis.
The fourth one we have random forest, an ensemble method that combines multiple decision trees to improve accuracy.
Each tree gives a vote on the outcome and the majority of vote determines the final decision.
Real life example is medical diagnosis.
Diagnosing diseases based on a patient data like age, cholesterol level, and blood pressure.
Each decision tree in the forest makes a prediction and majority vote decides the diagnosis.
Applications are healthcare, disease prediction, fraud detection, and customer segmentation.
Number 5th, we have support vector machine SVM, a classification algorithm that finds the optimal boundary to separate data into different classes,
often used for binary classification.
Real life example is image recognition, basically phase detection.
SVM can be used to detect faces in an image by classifying regions of the image as either phase or non phase based on pixel value.
Applications are facial recognition, speech recognition, and handwritten digit recognition.
Before we move forward, allow the future of AI with a comprehensive program in collaboration with ENI City Academy IIT Gohati.
In just a few months, you will master cutting-edge skills in generative AI, large language models, and machine learning.
From learning tools like ChatGPT and DALE 2 to gaining hands-on experience with Python and TensorFlow.
This course will equip with to lead AI projects and qualify for top rules like machine learning engineer or data science.
Plus, with an IIT certificate on your resume, you will stand out the best employers in the tech. So don't forget to check out the course link from the description box below and the pin comments.
So now let's move forward and see some unsupervised learning algorithms.
The number one is K means clustering.
A clustering algorithm that groups data into specified number K of a cluster based on similarity.
The goal is to minimize the distance between data points in each cluster.
Real life example is customer segmentation in marketing.
Grouping customers into segments like high spenders, frequent shoppers based on their purchasing behavior to personalize marketing efforts.
Applications are customer segmentation, market basket analysis, and social media grouping.
In number seven, we have hierarchical clustering, a clustering algorithm that creates a tree-like structure, which is also known as dendrogram,
by grouping similar data points, which can be either agglomerative, which is bottom-up, or divisive, which is top-down.
Real life example is gene clustering and healthcare, clustering genes with similar expression patterns to study cancer cells.
The dendograms help researchers identify genes that behave similarly in response to treatment.
Application are gene-expressive analysis, customer behavior analysis, and document clustering.
In MRAID, we have DB S E N.
The full form is density-based special clustering of application with noise.
A density-based clustering algorithm that identifies cluster based on the density of data point.
It can also handle noise, which is outliers by labeling them as noise point.
Real life example is identifying crime hotspot detecting areas with frequent criminal activity by clustering location based on crime density with outlier
being excluded.
Applications are crime hotspot detection, anomaly detection, and geospecial analysis.
Number ninth, we have principal component analysis PCA, a dimension reduction that transforms data into smaller set of uncorrelated variables,
which are principal components to capture the most variance in the data.
Real life example is image compression, compressing image by reducing the number of variables, retaining key features that preserve most of the images
information, thus reducing storage space.
Applications are data compression, dimension reduction, and data visualization.
The last one we have autoencoders, a type of neural network used to learn efficient representation of data, typically for dimensional detection or anomaly detection.
It encodes input data into a compressed representation and then reconstructs it back.
Real life example is fraud detection in financial transaction, detecting unusual transactions by training and encoders or normal transaction data.
When an outlier transaction occurs, it is flagged as potentially fraud.
Application are fraud detection, image denoising, and recommendation system.
So these algorithms are the part of many real systems that we interact with daily from predicting what product you might want to buy online to directing
frauds in your bank account.
They are used in various industries such as healthcare, finance, retail, and security.
Artificial intelligence, machine learning, and deep learning represent the evolution of computer science towards creating intelligent systems.
AI is the broader concept, striving to build machines capable of human-like intelligence. ML is a subset of AI, emphasizing algorithms that learn from data to make predictions or decisions.
DL, in turn, is a specialized branch of ML that employs deep neural networks to model complex patterns. Imagine an AI-powered voice assistant like Apple Siri.
It utilizes ML to understand and respond to user queries, learning from interactions over time.
Deep learning comes into play when Siri recognizes speech patterns or interprets natural language, using neural networks to process intricate features.
The better it becomes at understanding diverse accents or refining responses, exemplifying the continuous learning inherent in these technologies.
AI seeks to emulate human intelligence, ML harness data for learning, and DL employs deep neural networks for intricate tasks.
The integration of these technologies manifests in everyday applications, transforming how we interact with and benefit from intelligent systems. So without any further ado, let's get started.
So let's start with what is artificial intelligence. Artificial intelligence imparts data and human-like intelligence to machines, aiming to create autonomous systems that can emulate human behavior.
These machines learn and solve problems, simulating natural intelligence to tackle complex tasks. Consider an illustration of an AI-driven product, the Amazon Eco.
The Amazon Eco stands as a smarter speaker employing Amazon's virtual assistant AI technology known as Alexa.
This technology enables voice interaction, allowing the device to play music, set alarms, present audiobooks, and provide up-to-date information on topics like news, weather,
sports, and traffic reports, etc. Let's move forward and see what is machine learning.
Machine learning is a subset of artificial intelligence that focuses on developing algorithms and models capable of learning and making predictions or decisions without being explicitly programmed.
ML systems leverage data to recognize patterns, adapt and improve their performance over time. There are several types of machine learning. Number one, supervised learning.
The algorithm is trained on a labeled dataset where each input is associated with a corresponding output. Number two comes is unsupervised learning.
Unsupervised learning deals with unlabeled data to find inherent patterns or structures within the information. And then comes the reinforcement learning.
This type involves training agents to make sequences of decisions by interacting with an environment. And then comes semi-supervised learning.
Semi-supervised learning combines supervised and unsupervised learning elements, typically using a small amount of labeled data and a larger pool of unlabeled data.
Let us move forward and see what deep learning is. Deep learning, a branch of machine learning, focuses on algorithms inspired by the human brain structure and functionality.
It excels in processing vast amounts of both structured and unstructured data. At the heart of deep learning are artificial neural networks, empowering machines to make decisions.
The key distinction between deep learning and machine learning lies in data presentation.
Machine learning algorithms typically demand structured data, while deep learning networks operate through multiple layers of artificial neural networks, allowing them to handle diverse data formats.
So let's start with the difference between artificial intelligence, machine learning, and deep learning. And this we'll show in a tabular form. So starting with the definition.
So, definition of artificial intelligence. So, broad field of machine learning or creating machines with intelligent behavior is artificial intelligence.
And when we talk about machine learning, it's the subset of AI focusing on algorithms learning from data.
And then comes the deep learning, that is a specialized subset of ML using deep neural networks. And now we'll see the difference with the learning approach between all these three.
So, in learning approach, artificial intelligence can include rule-based systems, expert systems, and more. And in machine learning, it learns from data patterns without explicit programming.
And then comes the deep learning, where it learns hierarchical representation using neural networks. And if we talk about scope, it encompasses various techniques beyond learning from data.
And in machine learning, it primarily focuses on learning patterns from data. And then the deep learning, it specifically utilizes deep neural networks for complex tasks.
And now we'll move to the next difference and we'll start with an example. So in artificial intelligence, the example is autonomous vehicles, chat boards, or expert systems.
And for machine learning, it's spam filters, recommendation systems, image recognition. And in deep learning, it is image and speech recognition, natural language processing.
And now we'll see the difference for the data requirements. So it depends on the specific application and problem solving approach.
And in machine learning, it requires labeled or unlabeled data or training. And for the deep learning, it relies on large amounts of labeled data for training deep networks.
And now for the complexity, artificial intelligence addresses a wide range of tasks, including those beyond ML.
And in machine learning, it deals with moderate to complex tasks depending on algorithms.
And for the deep learning, it is well suited for intricate tasks often requiring substantial computational resources. And now see the flexibility.
So for the artificial intelligence, it can be rule-based, evolving, and adaptive. And for the machine learning, the flexibility adapts to patterns and the changes in data.
And for the deep learning, it adapts to hierarchical representations and diverse data types. And then comes the training process.
So in artificial intelligence, the training process varies based on specific AI techniques used.
And in machine learning, training involves feeding data and adjusting modal parameters. And in deep learning, training involves optimizing neural weights and structures.
And now we'll talk about the applications between all these three terms that is AI ML and deep learning.
So for artificial intelligence, the applications are robotics, natural language processing, gameplaying.
And for machine learning, it's predictive analytics, fraud detection, and healthcare diagnostic. And for the deep learning, that is image recognition, speech synthesis, and language translation.
We have Rahul who will take you through the various applications of machine learning and how you can be a machine learning engineer.
Machine learning has improved our lives in a number of wonderful ways.
Today, let's talk about some of these. I'm Rahul from Simply Learn and these are the top 10 applications of machine learning.
First, let's talk about virtual personal assistants Google Assistant, Alexa, Cortana, and Siri.
Now we've all used one of these at least at some point in our lives.
Now these help improve our lives in a great number of ways.
For example, you could tell them to call someone, you could tell them to play some music, you could tell them to even schedule an appointment.
So how do these things actually work?
First, they record whatever you're saying, send it over to a server which is usually in a cloud, decode it with the help of machine learning and neural networks, and then provide you with an output.
So if you ever notice that these systems don't work very well without the internet, that's because the server couldn't be contacted.
Next, let's talk about traffic predictions.
Let's say I wanted to travel from Buckingham Palace to the logical ground.
The first thing I have to probably do is to get on Google Maps.
So
here we have the path you should take to get to Lodge Cricket Ground.
Now here the map is a combination of red, yellow, and blue.
Now the blue regions signify a clear road, that is, you won't encounter traffic there.
The yellow indicates that they are slightly congested, and red means they are heavily congested.
So let's look at the map, a different version of the same map.
And here, as I told you before, red means heavily congested, yellow means slow moving, and blue means clear.
So how exactly is Google able to tell you that the traffic is clear, slow moving, or heavily congested?
So this is with the help of machine learning and with the help of two important measures.
First is the average time that's taken on specific days at specific times on that route.
The second one is the real-time location data of vehicles from Google Maps and with the help of sensors.
Some of the other popular map services are Bing Maps, Maps.me, and here we go.
Next up, we have social media personalization.
So say I want to buy a drone and I'm on Amazon and I want to buy a DJI Mavic Pro.
The thing is it's close to one lap, so I don't want to buy it right now.
But the next time I'm on Facebook, I'll see an advertisement for the product.
Next time I'm on YouTube, I'll see an advertisement.
Even on Instagram, I'll see an advertisement.
So here, with the help of machine learning, Google has understood that I'm interested in this particular product. Hence, it's targeting me with these advertisements.
This is also with the help of machine learning.
Let's talk about email spam filtering.
Now, this is a spam that's in my inbox.
Now, how does Gmail know what's spam and what's not spam?
So Gmail has an entire collection of emails which have already been labeled as spam or not spam.
So after analyzing this data, Gmail is able to find some characteristics like the word lottery or winner.
From then on, any new email that comes to your inbox goes through a few spam filters to decide whether it's spam or not.
Now some of the popular spam filters that Gmail uses is content filters, header filters, general blacklist filters, and so on.
Next, we have online fraud detection.
Now there are several ways that online fraud can take place.
For example, there's identity theft where they steal your identity, fake accounts where these accounts only last for how long the transaction takes place and stop existing after that,
and man in the middle attacks where they steal your money while the transaction is taking place.
The feedforward neural network helps determine whether a transaction is genuine or fraudulent.
So what happens with feed forward neural networks are that the outputs are converted into hash values, and these values become the inputs for the next round.
So for every real transaction that takes place, there's a specific pattern. A fraudulent transaction would stand out because of the significant changes that it would cause with the hash values.
Stock market trading.
Machine learning is used extensively when it comes to stock market trading.
Now you have stock market indices like Nikai. They use long short-term memory neural networks.
Now these are used to classify, process, and predict data when there are time lags of unknown size and duration.
Now this is used to predict stock market trends.
Assistive medical technology.
Now medical technology has been innovated.
With the help of machine learning, diagnosing diseases has been easier, from which we can create 3D models that can predict where exactly there are lesions in the brain.
It works just as well for brain tumors and ischemic stroke lesions.
They can also be used in fetal imaging and cardiac analysis.
Now, some of the medical fields that machine learning will help assist in is disease identification, personalized treatment, drug discovery, clinical research, and radiology.
And finally, we have automatic translation.
Now say you're in a foreign country and you see billboards and signs that you don't understand. That's where automatic translation comes of help. Now, how does automatic translation actually work?
The technology behind it is the same as the sequence-to-sequence learning, which is the same thing that's used with chatbots.
Here the image recognition happens using convolutional neural networks and the text is identified using optical character recognition.
Furthermore, the sequence-to-sequence algorithm is also used to translate the text from one language to the other.
And today I'm going to tell you how you can become a machine learning engineer.
But before we begin, let me tell you what a machine learning engineer actually does.
A machine learning engineer creates and maintains machine learning solutions to solve business problems.
They constantly tweak and optimize the solutions for maximum performance and scalability.
They solve business problems like reducing customer churn, running targeted marketing campaigns, and improving product experience.
They also help with predicting whether a particular hypothesis will be profitable in the future.
They contribute to cutting edge research in AI and machine learning.
Now, before you can start off on your journey to becoming a machine learning engineer, there's a certain number of steps that you need to follow.
On this learning path, your first step is to improve your math skills.
Mathematics plays a very important role in helping you understand how machine learning and its algorithms work.
Among the many concepts that you need to understand, three of the most important ones are probability and statistics, linear algebra and calculus.
Now let's have a detailed look at probability and statistics.
Firstly, you have the Bayes theorem.
This is used in the Navebase algorithm to help categorize your data.
Then we have probability distribution.
This helps you determine how frequently a particular event will take place.
For example, you can determine what your premium for your insurance will be based on the probability distribution of expenditure pertaining to insurance claims.
You must also learn how sampling and hypothesis testing works.
Now let's look at linear algebra.
Now linear algebra has two main concepts matrices and vectors.
They're both used widely in machine learning. Now matrices are used for image recognition where the entire image that you're using is already in the form of a matrix.
You need to be able to work with matrices, perform simple operations like addition, subtraction, multiplication, inverse, transpose, and so on.
Now the recommended systems that you see in applications like Netflix or Amazon actually work on vectors.
This vector is the customer behavior vectors and they use distance measures.
Now let's have a closer look at calculus.
You have differential calculus and integral calculus.
Now these help in determining the probability of events.
For example, in finding the posterior probability in a nave-based model.
In your next step to becoming a machine learning engineer, you need to develop good programming skills.
And let me tell you, there are a huge number of options from which you can choose.
There's Python, there's C, there's C, there's Java, and so much more.
Now here's a graph of the job postings from 2014 to 2017.
And you can see that there are two languages that dominate since 2015, Python and R.
Now these are one of the most wanted languages when it comes to machine learning engineers.
These are closely followed by JavaScript and C.
Hence we would like to recommend that you learn Python and R as they are the best options when it comes to coding in machine learning algorithms.
So here are a few things that you need to know about Python and R.
Python is an object-oriented language, which means their main emphasis is on the object.
R is a functional language, which means their emphasis is on creating and manipulating functions.
Python relies on its mini packages, and R is slightly faster than Python because it has inbuilt packages.
Now Python is generic and is suitable if you need to integrate it with any other software.
R works a little more closer with statistical analysis.
Your next step is to get yourself some data engineering skills.
Now these skills are important as they help you analyze and process your data as soon as you get it.
Now there are three major steps when it comes to data engineering.
Firstly, there's data pre-processing.
Now these refer to all the steps that you need to perform before data can be processed by the machine learning algorithm.
You have cleaning, parsing, correcting, and consolidating the data.
Then you have ETL or extract, transform, and load.
You need to know how data can be extracted from the internet or a local server.
You need to know how to transform the data.
For example, not all formats of data would be accepted by the program.
So you need to convert the data into a format that is accepted by the program.
Then you need to know how the data is loaded into your program.
The final step is to have knowledge about database management softwares or DBMS.
You need to be well versed with MySQL, the Oracle database, and NoSQL.
Your next step is to learn machine learning algorithms.
Now among all the machine learning algorithms that you can see on screen, you can divide them into two different categories.
Ones that fall under supervised machine learning and the others that fall under unsupervised machine learning.
Even after such a division, you can further subdivide them into classification and regression algorithms.
Now all algorithms except linear regression fall under the category of classification, which is used to determine whether a particular data falls into a particular category.
On the other hand, you have linear regression that falls under regression algorithms.
This is used to predict a particular value.
Then you have k-means clustering and hierarchical clustering.
Now these fall under the category of clustering.
This is used to group data into clusters based on certain similar attributes.
Then you have the a priori algorithm that falls under the concept of association.
Association is used to determine patterns of association among variables in large data sets.
So now that you know about these algorithms, let me tell you where you can learn about them.
Let's take a look at our Simply Learn channel and let's go to playlists.
And on this, we have a dedicated set of playlists that talk about machine learning.
Here you have videos on machine learning, how machine learning is different from deep learning and artificial intelligence, machine learning with Python, K-means clustering, decision trees, and so on.
If you want to learn more, you could also go through some deep learning algorithms like convolutional neural networks, recurrent neural networks, long short-term memory networks, and so on.
In fact, we have a detailed playlist that talks about the concepts of deep learning.
Here you can find videos on what is deep learning, TensorFlow, what is a neural network, convolutional neural networks, and recurrent neural networks.
Now, after you master these algorithms, you need to learn how you can select the right algorithm for your problem.
Then you need to create a good model with one or more algorithms.
After which you need to keep tweaking and optimizing the model so that you can get the maximum accuracy.
For further reading, you can go through GitHub where there's more than 21,000 repositories under machine learning.
You can also recreate published research papers, adding to your experience of working with machine learning.
And now for your last step learning machine learning frameworks.
Machine learning frameworks help make the lives of developers as well as users a whole lot easier.
They help remove the complex part of machine learning and make it available for everyone who wants to use it, be it developers or other users.
Now let's look at the widely used machine learning frameworks.
There's TensorFlow, Theano, Torch, ScikitLearn, and so on.
Now let's look at some of them in detail.
First, let's look at TensorFlow.
TensorFlow is the most widely used machine learning framework.
It's used for machine learning as well as deep learning.
Now it's an open source software library which performs numerical computations, which is done with the help of data flow graphs.
Google Translate is one of the most popular use cases of TensorFlow.
Now let's look at Theano.
Tiano helps you define, optimize, and evaluate mathematical expressions.
It was developed in the University of Montreal.
Lasagne, Blox, and Keros are its most popular libraries.
Now let's look at Spark ML library.
Now this is Apache Spark's machine learning component.
It also provides libraries for machine learning which are built on top of RDDs or resilient distributed datasets.
It's very good at providing iterative computation and provides very high algorithmic performance.
Now let's look at ScikitLearn.
ScikitLearn is able to provide a huge range of supervised as well as unsupervised algorithms for machine learning. It is built on existing libraries like NumPy, SciPy, and Matplotlib.
ScikitLearn actually started off as a Google Summer of Code project and now has 23,000 GitHub commits.
And that's it.
Congratulations, you're now a machine learning engineer.
Now let's look at the job opportunities in machine learning.
Now if you have a look at this graph, it kind of speaks for itself.
Before 2015, machine learning was much less popular than big data and cloud computing.
But all of that suddenly changed.
And right now, a machine learning engineer earns around $114,000 per annum.
And this is a clear indication that organizations are ready to invest heavily in people who are skilled in the concepts of machine learning.
You can also make the learning process easier by using Simply Learn's machine learning certification.
Simply Learn's Machine Learning Certification course provides 36 hours of instructor-led training, provides 25 plus hands-on exercises,
gives you practical applications of 15 plus machine learning algorithms, and helps you master the concepts of supervised and unsupervised learning.
It also introduces you to artificial intelligence, tells you the techniques of machine learning, data processing, regression, classification, and so much more.
So if you want to take your first step to getting certified and getting ahead, I'll now begin with what has changed in machine learning by 2026.
So you might be wondering what's changed in machine learning and why is it the best time to get into it now?
Well, let's go back a few years. In the past, machine learning was more about building models based on historical data.
It was about training algorithms to predict specific outcomes like classifying emails, spam or not spam, predicting house prices based on past data.
But fast forward to 2026 and the landscape has changed dramatically.
Today, machine learning isn't just about making predictions, it's about building systems that can learn, adapt, and improve over time.
We're no longer creating algorithms to just run experiments offline.
Now, machine learning systems are integrated into real-world operations and are capable of making decisions that impact the business immediately.
Here's an example to make it clearer. In the past, an e-commerce website might use machine learning to predict what products a customer might want based on their past purchases.
Now, the systems can constantly learn from new customer data, continuously refining those predictions in real time as customers' preferences are changing.
The world of machine learning has evolved from theory to practice, and this has created a huge demand for machine learning engineers
who can build scalable systems and make them work in real world environments.
The impact of machine learning is now directly tied to business outcomes, and machine learning engineers are at the center of that transformation.
You might be thinking, okay, I get it, machine learning is impactful, but what exactly does a machine learning engineer do compared to other roles in tech?
That's a great question.
In the world of machine learning, you'll hear about a few key roles such as data scientist, machine learning, and AI engineer. Let's break them down so you know exactly where you fit in.
Data scientists are like the detectives of data.
They spend their time analyzing large data sets, finding trends, and trying to extract meaningful insights.
They build models, but their main focus is usually on data exploration and experimenting with various algorithms. They don't typically focus on deploying those models into production environments.
Machine learning engineers. On the other hand, these are architects. They take the models built by data scientists and with scalable, deployable systems.
They work on creating solutions that will not only work in the short term, but can also scale to handle real-world data in massive volumes.
The machine learning engineer is responsible for ensuring that machine learning systems are integrated into businesses that can work seamlessly with existing technologies.
AI engineers focus more on the application side of things.
They build AI-powered products like chatbots, voice assistants, and real-time systems.
While their work often overlaps with ML engineers, they are typically more focused on the user-facing product and how machine learning fits into it.
As an ML engineer, your primary focus is to take models and turn them into actionable solutions that are deployed in real-world systems.
We shall now move on to why 2026 is the right time to enter machine learning.
Now that you know the role of an ML engineer, let's talk about why 2026 is the perfect time for you to jump into the field.
You've probably heard that machine learning is a hot topic, but what does that mean for you as someone starting out in this field?
So I'll help you break that down for you.
First, the demand for ML engineers has skyrocketed. The world is full of problems that need solving, and machine learning has proven to be one of the most effective tools to solve them.
From predicting customer preferences to automating critical business functions, machine learning is changing how businesses operate.
Secondly, the tools used to build machine learning systems are more accessible than ever before.
In the past, machine learning was viewed as something experimental, something that required a lot of effort just to set up.
But today, machine learning platforms and frameworks such as TensorFlow, PyTorch, and ScikitLearn have matured significantly.
These tools make it easier to build and deploy models that can scale to handle real-world data.
We shall now move on to why is this the right time for you to get started out as a machine learning engineer?
So, how do you get started? The first step is to build a strong foundation.
You might be excited to start building models and diving into algorithms, but before that, you need to understand the core concepts that drive all the machine learning systems.
These include mathematics, programming, and data handling.
You don't need to be an expert in all of these areas, but you do need to understand the basics.
Think of these as building blocks of everything that you will need to learn machine learning.
Let's start with mathematics. You don't need to be a math genius, but you do need to understand the basics.
There are three main areas of math that will help you get started out as an ML engineer, and those are linear algebra.
This is the study of vectors and matrices which are used to manipulate and process data in machine learning models.
If you've heard terms like feature vectors or matrix operations, that's linear algebra at play.
This is the core of how machine learning algorithms operate.
This is the math behind optimizing models. You'll use calculus to adjust the parameters of machine learning models and minimize the error between predicted and the actual values.
Specifically, derivatives are used to find the best way to fit a model into the data.
Statistics.
Machine learning is all about working with uncertainty, and statistics will help you make sense of it.
Whether you're dealing with probability distributions or hypothesis testing, statistics can help you understand patterns in data and make decisions with uncertain information.
These mathematical concepts will help you build a more accurate model and optimize it effectively.
Let's move on to programming stack.
If you're new to programming, don't worry. Python is the language that you will want to learn.
It's simple to get started with and has a huge ecosystem of libraries, especially designed for machine learning.
The key libraries that you will need to master include NumPy.
This library is used to handle large arrays of matrices and data, which is the backbone of most machine learning algorithms.
If you plan on working with large data sets, you'll be using NumPy a lot.
Pandas, this library is great for data manipulation and analysis.
You'll use pandas to clean, organize, and transform data, making it ready for machine learning models.
ScikitLearn, this library provides simple, easy-to-use tools for building machine learning models.
It covers everything from data pre-processing to models like regression and classification.
Once you're comfortable with these tools, you'll be able to start building machine learning models and working with real-world data.
Next up is SQL, which stands for Structured Query Language.
As an ML engineer, you will be working on lots of data and SQL will help you query databases to retrieve information that you need.
You'll use SQL to extract data, filter it, and join tables together, making sure that you have the right data to your models.
Once you have your data, the next step is data wrangling.
Data wrangling is a huge part of your job, and if you master it, it'll save you a lot of time and frustration while building models.
We shall now move on to types of machine learning.
Let's talk about the different types of machine learning.
There are three main categories which are supervised learning, unsupervised learning, and reinforcement learning.
Speaking of supervised learning, this is when you have label data. You train your model on data where the answers are already known.
The goal is for the model to learn the relationship between inputs and outputs so it can predict the future outcomes.
Unsupervised learning. In this case, the model works with unlabeled data and it tries to find hidden patterns and groupings in the data.
This is useful for tasks like clustering or anomaly detection.
Reinforcement learning.
This type of learning involves training an agent to make decisions by interacting with its environment and receiving rewards or penalties based on its actions.
This is often used in game AI or robotics.
We shall now move on to feature engineering and evaluation. After cleaning your data, the next step is feature engineering.
This is the process of transforming raw data into meaningful features that help your model make better predictions.
Once you've engineered your features, it's time to evaluate the model. You'll use metrics like accuracy, precision, and recall to see how well your model is performing.
Proper evaluation ensures that your model is ready for real world applications and that it can handle data in production.
We shall now move on to the six month learning plan in order to become an ML engineer in 2026.
So, how do you actually get started?
Here's your six month learning plan to guide your journey.
Firstly, focus on learning Python, Mathematics, and SQL.
Dive into machine learning algorithms and hands-on projects. Then learn deep learning and work with frameworks like TensorFlow or PyTorch.
By the sixth month, you can work on a capstone project that covers the full pipeline from data collection to deployment.
We shall now speak about the ML Engineer Tool Stack.
So let's talk about the tools that you will need as a machine learning engineer.
You must be wondering what tools should I be learning to become a successful ML engineer in 2026.
So let's simplify this.
Git and GitHub are the first things on your list. At first glance, version control might seem like something that only coders need to worry about.
However, it can be really crucial.
Why?
Because version control allows you to track every change that you make to your code, collaborate with teams, and roll back changes if something goes wrong.
Imagine you're working on a huge project and you mess something up. Without version control, you could lose hours of work.
But with Git and GitHub, you could go back and fix to any point and time.
You might be thinking, okay, I get that Git is useful, but what about the tools that can actually help me build and deploy machine learning models? Now that's a great question.
So let's talk about the cloud platforms like AWS, Google Cloud, and Azure.
In the past, machine learning models were often built and tested upon local machines, but we quickly realized that it wasn't scalable.
These cloud platforms give you the ability to handle large data sets, run models on high-powered servers, and scale them as your projects grow.
Instead of relying on your personal laptop to do all of the heavy lifting, you can leverage the cloud to train models much faster and handle massive data
sets without worrying about memory limitations.
We shall now move on to the next topic, which is on MLOps lifecycle.
You have now got all of your tools in place. But how do you go from all of these tools coming together in the MLOps lifecycle?
So you must be wondering, what does all of the MLOps lifecycle tools even look like?
And how do I manage the process from starting to finish?
Well, here's the thing. MLOps is like a well-oiled machine. It involves a series of stages that ensure that your models remain reliable, scalable, and adaptable to new data over time.
Think of it like a car assembly line.
First, you train the car and then you deploy it into the real world.
After that, you need to monitor it and see if it runs smoothly.
If it breaks down, you will have to retrain it.
Let's break it down into key steps.
Training your model. This is where you create the model using your training data.
This is a very experimental phase where you try different algorithms, tweak parameters, and optimize the model for better performance.
Deploying it to production.
Now that your model is ready, it's time to put it into action.
This means making the model available to users or clients.
Whether it's in a mobile app or a web service, deployment is where the magic happens.
Monitoring performance. Once your model is live, you can't just forget about it.
It's like checking the car's tire pressure after it's been on the road for a while.
You need to continuously track how well your model is doing.
If it starts to slip or underperform, it's time for tweaks and adjustments.
Lastly, we have retraining. Over time, your model may need to be retrained with new data to stay accurate.
This is especially true in industries where the environment is constantly changing.
Like e-commerce or finance. This training ensures that the model stays relevant and continues to provide value.
You may be wondering that this sounds like a lot of work.
And that's true.
That's where MLOps tools like MLSO help you streamline this process.
By automating and managing this lifecycle, you can spend less time dealing with the backend and more time focusing on building innovative solutions.
We shall now move on to experiment tracking.
As you dive deeper into machine learning, you'll quickly realize how important it is to track your experiments.
At first, this might seem a little overwhelming. You might be thinking, I can just run a model and hope for the best, right?
But trust me, tracking your experiments is one of the best habits that you can develop early on.
Think of it like logging your workout progress. Even if you don't track the results, how will you know whether you're improving or not?
The same goes for machine learning.
By using experiment tracking tools, airflow and weights and biases, you can keep a detailed record of every model and every hyperparameter
and every evaluation metric.
Now imagine you're building a recommendation system for an online store. You try different adjustments, algorithms, and get different results.
With experiment tracking, you can easily compare which configurations work best. You can easily compare which configurations work best and learn from the past mistakes.
You'll always know which experiment gives you the best results and which needs tweaking.
Tracking experiments also helps in collaboration.
If you're working with a team, being able to see everyone's experiments in one place makes it easier to understand their approach and build on each other's work.
We shall now move on to projects and portfolio.
Now that you've got your tools and workflow in place, it's time to focus on building a strong portfolio. You might be thinking, how do I make my portfolio stand out to potential employees?
That's a great question. The answer is simple real-world projects.
Think about it. Employers want to see what you can do in practice.
They don't just want to see theoretical knowledge, they want to see that you can solve problems and build working systems that can make a difference.
So for that reason, we have mini project examples.
At this point, you're probably itching to start building something yourself.
Well, hands-on projects are the best way to solidify what you have already learned.
For example, you could create a customer churn prediction model or a fraud detection system.
These are practical real-world projects that demonstrate your ability to build solutions from start to finish.
Make sure you document your projects clearly on GitHub and always include a detailed explanation of your approach, challenges, and results.
Remember, the goal is to show that you understand the problem and build a working solution.
I'll now move on to Kaggle and open source.
As you continue to build your portfolio, I highly recommend diving into Kaggle competitions and contributing to open source projects.
Kaggle is an amazing platform where you can work on real-world data sets and solve problems that companies and research institutions are facing.
Not only will you improve your skills, but you'll also have the opportunity to see how top data scientists and machine learning engineers approach similar problems.
Contributing to open source projects is another excellent way to showcase your skills.
It shows that you can work well with others, understanding existing systems and contribute to the community.
Plus, it's a great way to gain visibility and make connections with other engineers.
We shall now speak about the resumes which work for you.
Speaking about your resume, when it comes to landing a job as a machine learning engineer, your resume needs to be focused on real-world projects and practical experience.
So be sure to highlight the projects that you've worked on, the tools you've used, and most importantly, the impact that your work has had.
If you build a recommendation engine that boosted product sales by 20%, make sure that you include that.
Employers want to see how your work contributes to solving real business problems.
Don't forget to include links, Calvert profile, or any other open source contributions that you have made.
Employers love seeing code and showing them your projects is the best way to stand out.
We shall now speak about what interviewers test in 2026.
By now you must be wondering what do employers actually look for in an ML engineer?
So in 2026, interviews are not just about technical knowledge.
Employers just want to see how well you can communicate your thought process and real-world problems.
You'll likely face practical tests that challenge you to build a model or analyze data in real time.
You'll also be tested on how well you explain your approach and justify the decisions that you made during the project.
Prepare to discuss things like why you choose a specific algorithm for a problem, or how you handle issues like data imbalance or overfitting,
along with what metrics you use to evaluate your model's performance.
Being able to communicate clearly your process and how you arrive at your solution is a skill that will set you apart from other candidates.
We shall now speak about the ML trends that you will need to follow.
Machine learning is evolving fast and staying up to date is key to remaining relevant in this field.
So here are a few trends to keep an eye on in 2026.
Generative models. These models can generate new data based on patterns they learned and they're used for things like text generation, image creation, and even music composition.
Although ML, automated machine learning tools are making it easier for non-experts to build machine learning models.
As a result, more people will be able to contribute to this field without needing to become experts.
Privacy first models.
As privacy concerns grow, machine learning models are being designed to work securely and ethically, and these don't compromise on user privacy.
Staying on top of these trends will help you remain competitive and innovative in the ever-evolving field of machine learning.
So, in conclusion, I will say consistency is key in machine learning.
You don't need to know everything right away, but you must stay committed to learning and building.
Start small, keep experimenting, and keep improving. The road to become a machine learning engineer may seem long, but with the right tools and mindset you can get.
Welcome to Math Refresher Probability and Statistics.
In this lesson, we are going to explain the concepts of statistics and probability.
Describe conditional probability, define the chain rule of probability, discuss the measure of variance, identify the types of Gaussian distribution.
Basic of statistics and probability.
Probability and statistics Data Science relies heavily on estimates and predictions.
A significant portion of data science is made up of evaluations and forecast.
Statistical methods are used to make estimates for further analysis.
Probability theory is helpful for making predictions.
Statistical methods are highly dependent on probability theory, and all probability and statistics are dependent on data.
Data is information acquired for reference or research
via observations, facts, and measurements.
Data is a set of facts structured in the form that computers can interpret, such as numbers, words, estimations,
and views.
Importance of data.
Data aids in seeing more about the information by identifying possible connections between two features.
Data assists in the detection of distortion by uncovering hidden patterns.
Based on prior information patterns, data may be utilized to anticipate the future or predict the current state of affairs.
Also, data aids in determining whether two pieces of information have any instance in common or not.
Types of data.
Data might be quantitative.
That is data that can be measured or counted in numbers, or it may be qualitative, which is data which is generally divided into groups or in simpler words,
which cannot be counted or measured in numbers.
Let's consider an example.
A customer information data of a bank may contain quantitative and qualitative data.
Consider this snapshot where we have customer ID, surname, geography, gender, age, balance, has seen or card
is active member.
Amongst these variables we can see surname is mostly qualitative as it cannot be counted and measured in numbers.
Geography and gender are also qualitative as they cannot be counted in numbers and are mostly groups.
Has C or card, that is, has credit card and is active member, although are containing numerical in form.
But these are categorical.
That means these have been divided into groups of one and zero
that represent yes and no as an answer.
Hence these two variables are also qualitative.
Customer ID is again, although in numerical data.
However, the significance or intuition behind customer ID is categorical.
Hence, it may be kept in the qualitative data also.
However, age and balance.
These are numerical information which have been measured or counted and numerical operations can be performed on them.
Hence, these are under quantitative data categories.
Introduction to descriptive statistics.
Descriptive statistics.
A descriptive measurement is summary measure that quantitatively portrays the most important features of a set of data.
Allowing for a better comprehension of the information, data can be measured as different levels.
The levels of measurement describe the nature of information stored in the data assigned to the variables.
Qualitative data can be measured as nominal or ordinal.
Quantitative data can be measured in terms of interval and ratio type.
Nominal data.
The data is categorized using names, labels, or qualities.
For example, brand name, zip code, and gender.
Ordinal data can be arranged in order or ranked and can be compared.
Examples include grades, star reviews, position and race, and date.
Interval data is the data that is ordered and has meaningful differences between the data points, example, temperature in Celsius,
and year of birth.
Ratio data is similar to the interval level with the added property of inherent zero.
Mathematical calculations can be performed on both interval as well as ratio data.
For example, height, age, and weight.
Population versus sample.
Before analyzing the data, it's important to figure out if it's from a population or a sample.
Population is a collection of all available items as well as each unit in our study.
Sample is a subset of the population that contains only a few units of the population.
Population data is used for study when the data pool is very small and can give all the required information.
Samples are collected randomly and represent the entire population in the best possible way.
Measures of central tendency.
The central tendency is a single value that aids in the description of the data by determining its center position.
Measures of central tendency are sometimes known as summary statistics or measures of central location.
The most popular measurements of central tendency are mean, median, and mode.
The normal distribution is a bell-shaped, symmetrical distribution in which mean, median, and mode all are equal.
The curve over here shows the bell-shaped curve or the normal distribution of variable x.
The point over here that is x1
is the point which represents the mean median and mode of this distribution.
Mean.
Mean is calculated by dividing the sum of all data values by the total number of data values.
It gets affected when there are unusual or extreme values.
It is sensitive to the outliers.
Mean can be calculated as summation over all the values of x in a collection divided by the size of the collection.
For example, we have a collection where we have values as 7, 3, 4, 1, 6, and 7.
We find out the sum of these values which is 28, and there are a total of 6 values.
So 28 divided by 6 gives us a mean value of 4.66.
Median.
It is the middle value in the set of the data that has been sorted in ascending order.
It is a better alternative to mean, since it is less impacted by outliers and skewness.
It is closer to the actual central value.
Median is calculated differently for different sizes of data.
Differentiated as if the total number of values is odd.
Or if the total number of values is even.
If the size of the data is odd.
For example, in this case, we have five elements.
After sorting, whatever middle value we get.
That means n plus 1 by tooth term in this case.
5 plus 1 divided by 2.
That is the third term, which is 4 is the median value.
In case when the total number of values is even like here, there are 6 values.
The average or the mean of the two central values is considered as the median.
In this case, the median is the mean of 6 and 4, which is 5.
Mode.
Mode represents the most common value in the dataset.
It is not at all affected by extreme observations.
It is the best measure of central tendency for highly skewed or non-normal distribution.
Mode for categorical data is determined by estimating the frequencies for each categories,
and then the category with the highest frequency is considered to be mode.
Like in this case, 7 has the highest frequency, hence 7 becomes the mode value.
However, in case of continuous data or quantitative data, the calculation of mode is slightly different.
The first step in calculation of mode is dividing the data into classes which are equal width, then getting the frequency of data points lying in within that range of classes,
and finally selecting the class with the highest frequency.
Using the range of that class and the frequencies, we can get the final mode value.
Using the formula L plus
Fm minus F1 multiplied to H divided by Fm minus F1 plus Fm minus F2.
Here L is the lower limit or the lower observation of the mode class.
h is the size of the mode class.
Fm is the frequency of the mode class.
F1 is the frequency of the class proceeding to mode.
And F2 is the frequency of the class succeeding to mode.
This gives us the final mode value.
Mean versus expectation.
Now let's talk about mean versus expectation.
So in general, we use the expected value or expectation when we want to calculate the mean of a probability distribution
that represents the average value we expect to occur before collecting any data.
And mean, on the other hand, mean is basically used when we want to calculate the average value of a given sample.
This represents the average value of raw data that we may have already collected.
We can understand this by using a simple example.
Now, to calculate the expected value of this probability distribution, we can use a specific formula from the previous discussion.
This is going to be the expected value where x is going to be the data value, and this px is the probability of value.
For example, we could calculate the expected value for this probability distribution to be has shown.
So here, it will be 1.45 goals.
So this represents the expected number of goals that the team will score in any given game.
And then if you talk about calculating mean, so we typically calculate the mean after we have actually collected raw data.
For example, suppose we record the number of goals that a soccer team will score in 15 different games.
Now to calculate the mean number of goals scored per game,
we can use the following formula,
where sum of x is basically the sum of all the goals divided by n and the number of records, or we can say the sample size.
It is as shown on the screen.
So this represents the mean number of goals scored per game by the team.
Measures of asymmetry.
The difference between the three distinct curves can be studied in this image.
The central curve is the normal or no skewness curve.
Here mean, median, and mode all lie on the same point.
This normal curve is symmetrical about its mean, median, and mode.
That means the left hand side of the curve is a mirror image of the right hand side of the curve.
However, in case of negatively skewed data,
the tail is elongated on the left hand side,
and the mean is smaller than the mode and the median values, or is on the left hand side of the mode,
hence indicating that the outliers are in the negative direction.
On the other hand, in case of positively skewed the data, is concentrated on the left hand side of the curve,
while the tail is elongated or longer on the right hand side of the curve.
The mean is greater than the mode and median,
or is on the right hand side of the mode and median indicating that the outliers are in the positive direction.
Let's consider an example.
The graph here shows the global income distribution for the year 2003, 2013, and a projection for 2035.
If we see the global income distribution statistics for 2003, it is highly right-skewed.
We can observe in the previous graph that in 2003,
the mean of $3,451
was higher than the median of $1090.
The global income is definitely not evenly distributed.
The majority of people make less than $2,000 each year,
while only a small percentage of the population earns more than $14,000.
Measures of variability.
Dispersion, the measure of central tendencies provide a single value that addresses the full worth.
However, the central tendency cannot depict the viewpoint entirely.
The metric of dispersion helps us focus on the inconsistency in the data spread.
Measures of dispersion describe the spread of the data.
The range, interquartile range, standard deviation, and variance are examples of dispersion measures.
Range.
The range of distribution is the difference between the largest and the smallest amount of data.
The range, for example, does not include all of a series positive aspects.
It concentrates on the most shocking aspects and ignores that aren't considered critical.
For example, for a set 13, 33, 45, 67, 70,
the range is 57.
That is, the maximum of this, which is 70 minus the minimum over here,
which is 13.
Variance.
Variance is the average of all square deviations.
It is defined as the sum of square distance between each point and the mean or the dispersion around the mean.
The standard deviation is used as variance suffers from a unit difference.
Variance can be computed as sigma square summation over x minus mu square
divided by n,
where mu is the mean of the data,
x is the individual data point,
and n is the size of the data.
This representation is for a population data.
For a sample data variance can be computed as x minus
x bar whole square summation
over it divided by n minus one.
Here x bar is the mean of these sample data,
and n is the sample size.
The units of values and variance are not equal,
so another variability measure is used.
Standard deviation.
Standard deviation is a statistical term used to measure the amount of variability or dispersion around a mean.
The standard deviation is calculated as the square root of variance.
It depicts the concentration of the data around the mean of the dataset.
Standard deviation as indicated previously can be computed as square root of variance.
For a population data, standard deviation sigma can be computed as square root of summation over xi
minus mu whole square divided by n,
where mu is the mean of the data.
Let's consider an example.
Let's find out the mean, variance, and standard deviation for this data.
The data values are 3, 5, 6, 9, and 10.
To find out the mean, we first find the sum of all these data values.
That is 33 and divide it by the count, which is 5.
We get the mean of 6.6.
To compute the variance, we start by computing the deviation.
That is x minus the mean of x.
Here 3 is one of the values of the data, and 6.6 is the mean.
So 3 minus 6.6 square, and we do that
to find out some of all the deviations divided by the count,
which is 5.
We end up getting an overall variance of 6.64.
Standard deviation, as we know, is measured at square root of variance, that is square root of 6.64,
which amounts to 2.576.
Measures of relationship.
Measures of relationship, covariance.
Covariance is the measure of joint variability of two variables.
It measures the direction of the relationship between the variables.
It determines if one variable will cause the other to alter in the same way.
Covariance between variable x and y
can be computed as summation over the product of xi minus x bar
and yi minus y bar the whole divided by n minus one.
Here x bar and y bar are the mean of x and y respectively.
The value of covariance can range from minus infinity to a plus infinity.
Correlation.
Correlation is normalized covariance.
It measures the strength of association between two variables.
The most common measure for correlation is the Pearson correlation coefficient.
Correlation between two variables
x and y can be measured with respect to covariance as covariance between x
and y divided by the standard deviation of x and standard deviation of y.
The value of correlation ranges from a negative one to positive one.
Types of correlation.
Correlation can be either a positive correlation,
zero correlation, or a negative correlation.
The first picture over here represents a perfect positive correlation,
wherein a straight line with a positive slope
is representing the relationship between the two variables.
Zero correlation means that the line representing the relationship between the two variables is horizontal to the x-axis.
Perfect negative correlation can be represented by a straight line with a negative slope.
Correlation equals to one implies a positive relationship.
That is when one variable increases the other variable also increases.
A correlation value of negative one implies a negative relationship.
That is when one variable increases the other decreases.
The correlation coefficient of zero shows that the variables are completely independent of each other.
Let's consider an example.
Here, we have two variables, height and weight.
To compute the correlation between height and weight,
we use the correlation formula as covariance of x
and y divided by standard deviation of x and standard deviation of y.
Here height is the x variable and weight is the y variable.
First to compute covariance, we compute the x minus x bar and y minus y bar values, and then the product of them.
We then compute x minus x bar square
and y minus y bar square values to compute the standard deviations of height and weight respectively.
Correlation, as we know, has been defined as covariance of x and i and y divided by standard deviations of x and y.
This can also be represented as summation over x minus x bar multiplied to y minus y bar
divided by square root of summation over sum of squared deviations.
That is x minus x bar square multiplied to square root of summation over y minus y bar whole square.
That is sum of square deviations for y.
Now, let's find out values to put into this formula.
First, we find out the overall sum of height to get the mean of height,
which is 5.14.
Similarly, we get the sum of weight to get the mean of weight as 50.
We now get the summation over x minus x bar multiplied to y minus y bar to get the numerator for the formula.
Then we compute x minus x bar square summation
and y minus y bar square, that is sum of squared deviation of x and y respectively.
Now we put in the values in this final correlation formula to get a correlation value of 0.889.
This indicates that height and weight have a positive relationship.
It is evident that as height grows, weight also increases.
In this module, we will be talking about expectation and variance.
So the expected value, or we can say mean of a given variable, that we can denote by x is a discrete random variable where it is a weighted average of the possible values that x can take,
and each value is going to be according to the probability of that specific event occurring.
So usually the expected value of x is denoted by a simple formula, where we can define the expectation based on the x parameter,
which is going to be the sum of each possible outcome multiplied by the probability of the outcome occurring.
So, in more concrete terms, the expectation is what we would expect the outcome of an experiment to be on average.
We can take an example for the coin.
If a coin is being tossed 10 times,
then one is most likely to get 5 heads and 5 tails.
Same logic can be discussed if we talk about another example of rolling a die.
So there are 6 possible outcomes when you roll a die, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
And each of these has a probability of 1 by 6 of occurring.
So we can say that the expectation is going to be 1 multiplied by the probability of that happening, which is going to be 1 by 6
plus 2 by 6 plus 3 by 6 plus 4 by 6 plus 5 by 6 plus 6 by 6.
And that is going to give us 3.5 as an output.
The expected value is 3.5.
So if you think about it, 3.5 is halfway between the possible values that I can take.
And this is what we should have expected.
Next, we talk about the concept of variance.
So variance of a random variable allows us to know something about the spread of the possible values of the variable.
So for a discrete random variable x, the variances of x is going to be denoted by using a simple formula that is going to be var
x equals ex minus m, the whole square where m is basically the expected value of the expectation of x.
So this is more like a standard deviation of x, which can also be represented by using this formula.
So the variance does not behave in the same way as expectation when we multiply and add constants to random variables.
So now there are two different types of variants that we can have a fair understanding on.
First of all, we have low variance, and then we have high variance.
So low variance simply means that there is a small variation in the production of the target function, with changes in the trading data set and at the same time,
high variance as we can see here.
High variance shows a large variation in prediction of the target function with changes in the trading data set.
So a model that shows high variance learns a lot and perform well with the trading data set.
And it does not generalize well with the unseen data set.
And that's why, as a result, such a model gives good results with training data set, but shows high error rates on the test data set.
And since the high variance a model learns too much from the data set, it leads to an overfitting of the model.
So model with high variance will be having a couple of issues, like it may lead to overfitting, or it may also lead to increase in model complexities.
Next, we have skewness.
So skewness in simple terms is basically a measure of asymmetry of a distribution.
So distribution is asymmetrical when it's left, and right sides are not the mirror images.
Right now, this is a mirrored image, and a distribution can have right positive or we can say negative or it can have zero skewness.
So right skewed in this scenario is basically the distribution is longer on the right side of its peak.
And a left skewed distribution is going to be we can say where it is longer on the left side.
So we can see we have this one as a part of the right side.
It is more elongated towards the right side.
And this one is more elongated towards the left side.
So we can think of skewness in terms of tails.
A tail is long tampering and the end of a distribution.
So it simply indicates that they are observations at one end of the distribution, but that they are relatively infrequent.
So a right skew distribution has a long tail on the right side, as you can see here.
So the number supports observed.
Let's say we have a data on a per year basis.
So again, we can have a more skewness towards the right side, where data is being dropping as we continue to increase the number of years.
For example, we may have a high sales towards the beginning of year, suppose in 2022.
But again, as we proceed to 2023, second half we are seeing the dip in performance.
So that is rightly skewed.
And same way, let's suppose if we started with the sales figure, it was really less in suppose 2002.
But again, as we proceeded to 2023 now, our sales have been gradually increasing.
So it's more like skew towards the left section as a part of negative skew.
Next we have kurtosis.
So kurtosis is basically a measure of the tailedness of a distribution.
So tailedness is how often the outliers occur and acts as kurtosis.
Is the tailedness of the distribution related to a normal distribution?
So distribution with medium kurtosis is called as mesocurtic, a distribution with low kurtosis like this one.
This is called as the platycurtic and then distribution with high kurtosis like this one.
This is called as the leptocurtic.
So tails here they are tapering ends on either side of a distribution like this.
So they represent the probability or the frequency of values that are extremely high or extremely low to the mean.
In other words, tails here represents how often the outliers occur.
So there are three types of kurtosis.
We have platycurtic, which is negative, leptocurtic, which is a positive towards the upper end, and then we have mesocurtic, which is a normal distribution.
So mesocurtic is the medium tail, so normal distributions they have a kurtosis of three.
So any distribution with a kurtosis of a prox value of three is going to be mesocurtic, and kurtosis is described in terms of excess kurtosis,
which is kurtosis minus three.
And since normal distribution, they have a kurtosis of three axis curtosis makes comparing a distribution kurtosis to a normal distribution even easier.
Introduction to probability.
Probability theory.
Probability is a measure of the likelihood that an event will occur.
Let's consider an example of coin toss,
where the chances of getting heads on a coin are 1 by 2 or 50%.
The probability of each given event is between 0 and 1, both inclusive.
Sum of an event's cumulative probability cannot be greater than 1.
Hence the probability of an event x lies between 0 and 1.
This means that the integral of probability of distribution over x equals to 1.
Conditional probability.
Conditional probability of any event A is defined as the probability of occurrence of A,
given that event B has previously occurred.
Condition probability of event A given B can be estimated as probability of A intersection B, that is
probability of both A and B happening together,
divided by the probability of B.
It is also written as that probability of A intersection B equals to probability of A given B multiplied to probability of B.
Let's consider an example.
In a coin, we are doing a two coin flip.
Coin one gets heads, tails, heads, and tails in subsequent flips.
While coin two gets tails, heads, heads, and tails in the subsequent flips.
Now the probability that coin one will get a head is two out of four.
While the probability that coin two will get heads is again two out of four.
The probability that both coin one and coin two will have a heads is just one out of the four flips.
Hence the probability that coin one will get heads given that coin two is already heads can be computed as probability of coin one
edge intersection coin two edge,
that is one by four divided by probability of coin two edge.
That's a given that is two by four, which is going to be 0.5 or 50% based.
Base theorem.
Base theorem calculates the conditional probability of an event based on its prior probabilities.
Basically, base theorem incorporates the prior probability distribution to predict the posterior probabilities. base theorem for conditional probability
can be expressed as: probability of A given B equals probability of B given A divided by probability of B
multiplied to probability of A.
Bayes theorem allows updating the probability values by using new information or evidence.
Here probability of A is known as prior probability.
That is the probability of event before any new data is collected.
Probability of A given B is known as the posterior probability.
It is the revised probability of an event occurring after taking into consideration the new information probability of B given A is known as the likelihood
and probability of B is probability of observing an evidence, Bayes model.
An example.
Consider an example for calculating the likelihood of having diabetes based on frequency of fast food consumption.
Here is the observed data.
Let's say the fast food audience is 20%.
Diabetes prevalence is 10%, and 5% is fast food and diabetes.
The chances of diabetes given fast food that is the conditional probability of D given B can be calculated as probability of diabetes and fast food together divided by probability of fast food.
That means 5% divided by 20%.
That equals 25%.
Define an analysis can state eating fast food increases the chance of having diabetes by 25%.
The multiplication rule of probability.
If events A and B are statistically independent and probability of A intersection B can be given as probability of A
given B multiplied to probability of B.
However, probability of A intersection B is also given as probability of A multiplied to probability of B.
Here, probability of A given B equals to probability of A when we assume that probability of B is non-zero.
Similarly, probability of B equals probability of B given A, assuming probability of A is non-zero.
Chain rule of probability joint probability distributions over many random variables can be reduced into conditional distributions over a single variable.
It can be expressed as probability of x1, x2, so on until xn equals probability of x1 intersection
probability of xi, given probability of x1 till xi minus 1.
For example, the joint probability of A, B, and C can be given as probability of A given B.
C multiply to probability of B given C multiply to probability of C.
Logistics sigmoid.
The logistics function is a type of sigmoid function that aims to predict the class to which a particular sample belongs.
Its outcome is discrete binary value, a probability between 0 and 1.
The logistics sigmoid is a useful function that follows the yes curve.
It saturates when the input is very large or very small.
Logistics sigmoid is expressed as sigma of x equals 1 upon 1 plus e to the power minus x.
The logistics sigmoid can be expressed as sigmoid function of x is given as 1 upon 1 plus e to the power minus x,
where e is the Euler's number.
Gaussian distribution.
The Gaussian distribution is a type of distribution in which data tends to cluster around a central value with little or no bias to the left or right.
It is often referred to as normal distribution.
In absence of prior information, the normal distribution is frequently a fair assumption in machine learning.
Equation.
The formula for calculating Gaussian distribution is described as the normal distribution of x.
That is the function of x, given mean as mu and variance is sigma square, can be calculated as 1 upon sigma square root of 2 pi
e to the power minus half x minus mu divided by sigma whole square,
where mu is the mean or peak value, which also is the expected value of x.
Sigma is the standard deviation, sigma square is the variance.
A standard normal distribution has a mean of zero and a standard deviation of one.
Gaussian distribution can be univariate,
which describes the distribution of a single variable x.
It can also be multivariate where it can just use to describe the distribution of several variables.
It is represented in 3D of ND formats.
Law of large numbers.
Now let's talk about law of large numbers.
The law of large numbers states that an observed sample average from a large sample will be close to the true population average,
and that it will get closer in the larger sample.
So the law of large number does not guarantee that a given sample, spatially a small sample, will reflect the true population characteristics,
or that a sample does not reflect the true population will be balanced by a subsequent sample.
This is for the law of large numbers to express the relationship between scale and growth rate.
So there are multiple examples through which we can understand.
And it is widely used in statistical analysis in working with the central limit theorem in terms of the business growth.
So there are multiple real times set up in which these are going to be used.
So if you talk about tossing a coin, so tossing a coin in a number of times will give us two different types of outcomes.
The result will spread evenly between head and tails, and the expected average value is going to be half.
That means 50 times tails and 30 times heads.
But again, if you toss a coin 1000 times, then the result can be in different manners, because out of 1000, let's say 850 times it has been head
and only 150 times it has been tails and so on.
So that's why the possibility of one event occurring is going to be changed in large sample sets as compared to a small sample sets,
as in let's say 10 times.
So the number of heads and tails unbalanced for lower number of trials, so we can see it is unbalanced.
But again, as soon as we toss more number of coins, more leans towards the balance value, or we can see the observed averages.
Next we have p-value.
So p-value is basically a number calculated from the statistical test that describes how likely we are to have found a particular set of observations if the null hypothesis were true.
So p-values are used in hypothesis testing to help decide whether to reject the null hypothesis.
And the smaller the p-value, the more likely we are to reject the null hypothesis.
So we have a term called as null hypothesis.
So all statistical tests, they have null hypothesis.
So for most tests, the null hypothesis is that there is no relationship between our variables of in first or that there is no difference among groups.
For example, in a two-tail t-test, the non-hypothesis is that the difference between two groups is going to be zero.
So p-value is going to tell us how likely it is that our data could have occurred under the null hypothesis.
It is done by calculating the likelihood of a test statistic,
which is the number calculated by a statistical test using our data. so p-value tells us how often we would expect to see a test statistic as extreme or more extreme
than one calculated by a statistical test.
if the null hypothesis of the test was true.
So there are multiple limitations as well.
So first one is the results can be significant, but again, they are they may not be practical as we have compared.
It can be based on multiple hypotheses for a game for the healthcare test.
If the test is going to be positive or not, it may show even values of the effect of a variable, but not the magnitude in real life.
What exactly is going to be the application of a drug test being failed in PharmaCompany?
Therefore, it is recommended to use confidence and levels in addition to the p-values to quantify or we can say to give a solid figure to the reserve,
which we are going to get.
The p-values they are interpreted as supporting or we can say refuting the alternative hypothesis.
So p-value can only tell you whether or not the null hypothesis is supported.
It cannot tell us whether our alternative hypothesis is true or why.
So the risk of rejecting the null hypothesis is often higher than the p-value.
So especially when we are looking at a single study or when using small sample sizes.
So this is because the smaller frame of reference, the greater are the chances that as we stumble across a statistically significant pattern completely by accident.
Key takeaways.
Probability and statistics structure the premise of the data.
The data helps in anticipating the future or gauging in view of the past patterns of information.
The central tendency is a single value that helps to describe the data by identifying these central positions, the mean, median,
and mode, are the measures of central tendencies.
The distribution where the data tends to be around a central value with a lack of bias or minimal bias towards the left or right
is called as Gaussian distribution.
My name is Richard Kirshner with the Simply Learn team that's get certified, get ahead.
We're going to cover mathematics for machine learning.
So today's agenda is going to cover data and its types.
Then we're going to dive into linear algebra and its concepts.
Calculus, statistics for machine learning, probability for machine learning, hands-on demos.
And of course, thrown in there in the middle is going to be your matrixes and a few other things to go along with all this.
Data and its types.
Data denotes the individual pieces of factual information collected from various sources.
It is stored, processed, and later used for analysis.
And so we see here just a huge grouping of information, a lot of tech stuff, money, dollar signs, numbers.
And then you have your performing analytics to drive insights.
And hopefully you have a nice share, your shareholders gather it at the meeting and you're able to explain it in something they can understand.
So we talk about data's types of data.
We have in our types of data, we have a qualitative, categorical.
You think nominal or ordinal, and then you have your quantitative or numerical, which is discrete or continuous.
And let's look a little closer at those data types.
Vocabulary, always people's favorite is the vocabulary words.
Okay, not mine.
But let's dive into this what we mean by nominal.
Nominal, they are used to label various uh label our variables without providing any measurable value.
Uh country, gender, race, hair, color, etc.
It's something that you either mark true or false.
This is a label. It's on or off. Either they have a red hat on or they do not.
So a lot of times when you're thinking nominal data labels, uh think of it as a true-false kind of setup.
And we look at ordinal, this is categorical data with a set order or a scale to it. Uh and you can think of salary range as a great one. Uh movie ratings, etc.
You can see here the salary range, if you have 10,000 to 20,000, number of employees earning that rate is 150, 20,000 to 30,000,
100, and so forth.
Some of the terms you'll hear is bucket.
Uh this is where you have 10 different buckets and you want to separate it into something that makes sense into those 10 buckets.
And so when we start talking about ordinal, a lot of times when you get down to the brass bones, again we're talking true-false.
Uh so if you're a member of the 10 to 20k range, uh so forth. Those would each be uh either part of that group or you're not.
But now we're talking about buckets, and we want to count how many people are in that bucket.
Quantitative numerical data uh falls into two classes, discrete or continuous.
And so data with a final set of values which can be categorized: class strength questions answered correctly, and runs hit and cricket.
A lot of times when you see this, you can think integer and a very restricted integer, i.e., you can only have a hundred questions on a test, so you can
it's very discrete. I only have a hundred different values that it can attain.
So think usually you're talking about integers but within a very small range. They don't have an open end or anything like that.
Uh so discrete is very solid, simple to count, set number.
Continuous, on the other hand, uh, continuous data can take any numerical value within a range.
So water pressure, weight of a person, etc.
Usually we start thinking about float values where they can get phenomenally small in their in what they're worth.
And there's a whole series of values that fall right between discrete and continuous.
You can think of the stock market. You have dollar amounts, it's still discrete, but it starts to get complicated enough when you have, like, you know, jump in the stock market from $525.33
to $580.67.
There's a lot of point values in there.
It'd still be called discrete, but you start looking at it as almost continuous because it does have such a variance in it.
Now we talk about no, we did we went over nominal and ordinal, uh almost true-false charts, and we looked at quantitative and numerical data, which
we're starting to get into numbers.
Discrete, you can usually, a lot of times discrete will be put into it could be put into truefalse, but usually it's not.
So we want to address this stuff, and the first thing we want to look at is the very basic, which is your algebra.
So we're going to take a look at linear algebra.
You can remember back when your Euclidean geometry, we have a line.
Well, let's go through this. We have a linear algebra is the domain of mathematics concerning linear equations
and their representations in vector spaces and through matrixes.
I told you we're going to talk about matrixes.
So a linear equation is simply
2x plus 4y minus 3z equals 10.
Very linear.
10x plus 12.4y equals z. And now you can actually solve these two equations by combining them. And that's where we're talking about a linear equation.
In the vectors, we have a plus b equals c.
Now we're starting to look at a direction.
And these values usually think of an xyz plot.
So each one is a direction, and the actual distance of like a triangle AB is C.
And then your matrix can describe all kinds of things.
I find matrices confuse a lot of people, not because they're particularly difficult, but because of the magnitude and the different things they're used for.
And a matrix is a chart or a you know, think of a spreadsheet, but you have your rows and your columns.
And you'll see here we have A times B equals C.
Very important to know your counts. So depending on how the math is being done, what you're using it for, making sure you have the same rows and the number of columns or a single number.
There's all kinds of things that play in that that can make matrixes confusing, but really it has a lot more to do with what domain you're working in.
Are you adding in multiple polynomials where you have like
ax squared plus by plus, you know, you start to see that it can be very confusing versus a very straightforward matrix.
And let's just go a little deeper into these, because these are such primary, this is what we're here to talk about, is these different math uh mathematical computations that come up.
So when we're looking at linear equations, let's dig deeper into that one.
An equation having a maximum order of one is called a linear equation.
Uh so it's linear because when you look at this, we have uh ax plus b equals c, which is a one variable.
We have uh two variables, ax plus by equals c, ax plus b y plus z
equals d, and so forth.
But all of these are to the power of one. You don't see x squared, you don't see x cubed.
So when we're talking about linear equations, that's what we're talking about.
In their addition, if you have already dived into say neural networks, you should recognize this ax plus b y plus cz um
setup plus the intercept, uh, which is basically your your neural network, each node adding up all the different inputs.
And we can drill down into that.
Most common formula is your y equals mx plus c.
So you have your uh y
equals the m, which is your slope, your x value plus c, which is your um y-intercept. I kind of labeled it wrong here.
Uh threw me for a loop. But the the c would be your y-intercept.
So when you set x equal to zero, y equals c.
And that's that's your y-intercept right there.
Uh and that's they just had a reversed value of y when x equals zero, it equals the y-intercept, which is c, and your slope gradient line, which is your m.
So you get your y equals 2x plus 3.
And there's lots of easy ways to compute this.
This why, this is why we always start with the most basic one when we're solving one of these problems.
And then of course the uh uh one of the most important takeaways is the slope gradient of the line.
Uh so the slope is very important, that m value.
Uh in this case we went ahead and solved this.
If you have y equals 2x plus 3, you can see how it has a nice line graph here on the right.
So, matrixes. A matrix refers to a rectangular representation of an array of numbers arranged in columns and rows.
So we're talking uh m rows by n columns. Here a11 is denotes the element of the first row in the first column.
Similarly, A12, and it's really pronounced A11 in this particular setup.
So it's uh row 1, column 1.
A12 is a of row 1, column 2, uh first row and second column, and so on.
And there's a lot of ways to denote this.
I've seen these as like a capital letter A, smaller case A for the top row, or I mean you can see where they can go all kinds of different directions as far as the value.
You just take a moment to realize there needs to be some designation as far as what row it's in and what column it's in.
And we have our uh basic operations, we have addition. So when you think about addition, you have uh uh two matrices of two by two, and you just add each individual number in that matrix,
and then when you get to the bottom, you have uh in this case the solution is 12, 10 plus 2 is 12, 5 plus 3 is 8, and so on.
And the same thing with subtraction.
Now again, you're counting matrixes, you want to check your um dimensions of the matrix, the shape. You'll see shape come up a lot in programming.
So we're talking about dimensions, we're talking about the shape.
If the two shapes are equal, this is what happens when you add them together or subtract them.
And we have multiplication.
When you look at the multiplication, you end up with a very uh slightly different setup going.
Now if we look at our last one, we're uh uh we're like why this always gets to me when we get to matrixes, because they don't really say why you multiply matrices.
Um
my first thought is one times two, four times three, but if you look at this, we get one times two plus four times three, one times three plus four times five,
uh six times two plus three times three, six times three plus three times five.
If you're looking at these matrices, uh think of this more as an equation.
And so we have uh if you remember when we went back up here for our multiple line equations, let's just go back up a couple slides where we were looking at uh two variable.
So this is a two variable equation, ax plus by equals c.
Um and this is a way to make it very quick to solve these variables, and that's why you have the matrix, and that's why you do.
The multiplication the way they do.
And this is the dot product of 1 times 2 plus 4 times 3.
1 times 3 plus 4 times 5.
6 times 2 plus 3 times 3.
6 times 3 plus 3 times 5. And it gives us a nice little 14, 23, 21, and 33 over here.
Which then can be used and reduced down to a sample
formula as far as solving the variables as you have enough inputs.
And then in matrix operations, when you're dealing with a lot of matrix, uh now keep in mind multiplying matrixes is different than finding the product of two matrixes.
Okay? So when we're talking about multiplication, we're talking about solving uh for equations.
When you're finding the product, you are just finding one times two.
Keep that in mind, because that does come up. I've had that come up a number of times where I am altering data and I get confused as to what I'm doing with it.
Uh transpose.
Flipping the matrix over its diagonal.
Comes up all the time where you have you still have 12, but instead of it being uh 12, 8, it's now 12, 14, 8, 21. You're just flipping the columns in the rows.
Uh and then of course you can do an inverse, um changing the signs of the values across this main diagonal.
And you can see here we have the inverse a to the minus one and ends up with uh instead of 12, 8, 14, 12, it's now minus 22 minus 12.
Vectors.
Uh vector just means we have
a value and a direction.
And we have down four numbers here on our vector.
Uh in mathematics, a one-dimensional matrix is called a vector. Uh so if you have your x plot and you have a single value, that value is along the x-axis and it's a single dimension.
If you have two dimensions, you can think about putting them on a graph.
You might have x and you might have y, and each value denotes a direction.
And then of course the actual distance is going to be the hypothesis of that triangle.
And you can do that with three dimensionals, x, y, and z.
Uh and you can do it all the way to nth dimensions.
So when they talk about the k means uh for categorizing and how close data is together, they will compute that based on the Pythagorean theorem.
So you would take uh the square of each value, add them all together, and find the square root, and that gives you a distance as far as where that point is,
where that vector exists, with an actual point value.
And then you can compare that point value to another one, and it makes a very easy comparison versus comparing uh fifty or sixty different numbers.
And that brings us up to eigenvector and I gene values.
Uh gene vectors, the vectors that don't change their span while transformation, and I gene values, the scalar values that are associated to the vectors.
Conceptually, you can think of the vector as your picture. You have a picture, it's uh uh two dimensions, x and y.
And so when you do those two dimensions and those two values, or whatever that value is, um
that is that point.
But the values change when you skew it.
And so if we take and we have a vector a
and that's a set value, uh b is um your is your you have a and b which is your eigen vector.
2 is the eigene value. So we're altering all the values by 2. That means we're uh maybe we're stretching it out one direction, making it tall uh if you're doing picture editing.
Um that's one of the places this comes in. But you can see when you're transforming uh your different information, how you transform it is then your eigenvalue.
And you can see here uh vector after line transition, uh we have 3a, a is the igene vector, 3 is the igene value.
So a doesn't change, that's whatever we started with, that's your original picture, and 3 uh is skewing it one direction, and maybe uh
uh B is being skewed another direction, and so you have a nice tilted picture because you altered it by those by the hygiene values.
So let's go ahead and pull up a demo on linear algebra.
And to do this, I'm gonna go through my trusted Anaconda into my Jupyter notebook, and we'll create a new uh notebook called Linear Algebra.
Since we are working in Python, uh we're gonna use our NumPy, always import that as NP or NumPy Array, probably the most popular
module for doing matrixes and things in.
Given that this is part of a series, I'm not going to go too much into NUMPy.
We are going to go ahead and create two different variables, a for a numpy array 1015, and B 29.
We'll go ahead and run this, and you can see there's our two arrays, 1015, 29. And I went ahead and added a space there in between, so it's easier to read.
And since it's the last line, we don't have to put the print statement on it unless you want, we can simplify but we can simply do a plus b.
So when I run this, uh we have 101529, and we get 3024, which is what you expect.
10 plus 20, 15 plus 9.
You could almost look at this addition as being um
just adding up the columns on here coming down.
And if we wanted to do it a different way, we could also do a dot t plus b dot t.
Remember that t flips them.
And so if we do that, we now get them uh we now have 3024 going the other way.
We could also do something kind of fun. There's a lot of different ways to do this.
Uh as far as a plus b. I can also do a plus b dot t, and you're gonna see that that will come out the same, the 3024, whether I transpose
a and b or transpose them both at the end.
And likewise we can very easily subtract two vectors. I can go a minus b
and we run that, and we get minus 10 six.
Now remember this is the last line in this particular section, that's why I don't have to put the print around it.
Um and just like we did before, we can transpose either the individual or we can transpose the main setup, and then we get a minus 106
going the other way.
Now we didn't mention this in our notes, but you can also do a scalar multiplication.
Let me just put down the scalar so you can remember that.
Uh and what we're talking about here is I have uh this array here, u, and if I go a times
u,
uh we'll take the value 2, we'll multiply it by every value in here. So 2 times 30 is 60, 2 times 15.
And just like we did before, uh this happens a lot because when you're doing matrixes, you do need to flip them. You get 6030 coming this way.
So in NUMPY, uh we have what they call dot product.
And uh with this this is in a two-dimensional vectors, it is the equivalent of two matrix multiplication.
And remember we were talking about matrix multiplication, uh, where it is the
well let's walk through it.
We'll go ahead and start by defining two um numpy arrays. We'll have uh 10, 20, 25, 6, or our u and our v.
Uh and then we're gonna go ahead and do if we take
the values, uh, and if you remember correctly,
an array like this would be 10 times 25 plus 20 times six. We'll go ahead and uh print that.
There we go.
And then we'll go ahead and do the uh np dot dot of u, comma
v.
And we'll find when we do this, we go ahead and run this, uh we're gonna get uh 370, 370.
So this is a strain multiplication where they use it to solve uh linear algebra uh when you have multiple numbers going across.
And so this could be very complicated. We could have a whole string of different variables going in here.
But for this, we get a nice uh value for our dot multiplication.
And we did um addition earlier, which is just your basic addition.
Uh and of course the matrix you can get very complicated on these, or uh in this case we'll go ahead and do um let's create two
complex matrices.
This one is a matrix of um you know 121046431.
We'll just print out A so you can see what that looks like. Here's print A.
When we print A out, you can see that we have a um
two by three layer matrix for A.
And we can also put together, always kind of fun when you're playing with print values. Uh we could do something like this. We could go in here.
There we go. Uh we could print A, we have it end with uh equals A, run, and this kind of gives it a nice look. Uh here's your matrix, that's all this is.
Comma and means it just tags it on the end. That's all that is doing on there.
And then we can simply add in what is A plus B, and you should already guess, because this is the same as what we did before, there's no difference.
Uh we do a simple vector addition, we have 12 plus 2 is 14, 10 plus 8 is 18, and so on.
And just like we did the uh matrix addition, we can also do a minus b and do our matrix subtraction.
And we look at this, uh we have what, 12 minus 2 is 10, 10 minus 8, uh where are we?
Oh there we go.
8 minus uh
confusing what I'm looking at, I should have reprinted out the original numbers. Uh but we can see here 12 minus 2 is of course 10, 10 minus 8 is 2, uh 4 minus 46 is minus 42, and so forth.
So same as a subtraction as before, we just call it matrix subtraction, it's identical.
Now if you remember up here we had uh scalar addition, we're adding just one number to a matrix, you can also do scalar multiplication.
Uh and so simply if you have a single value a and you have b which is your array, we can also do a times b.
When we run that, uh you can see here we have two times four is eight, uh, five times four is twenty, and so forth.
You're just multiplying the four across each one of these values.
And this is an interesting one that comes up.
A little bit of a brain teaser is uh matrix and vector multiplication.
And so when we're looking at this,
uh we are just do a regular array, so it doesn't necessarily have to be a numpy array.
We have a
which has our um an array of arrays, and b which is a single array.
And so we can from here
do the dot
a b
and this is gonna return two values. And the first value is that is it's you could say it's like uh uh we're doing the this array, B array, first with A and then with a
second one.
And so it splits it up. So you have a matrix of vector multiplication and you can mix and match.
When you get into really complicated uh back end stuff, this becomes more common because you're now you've got layers upon layers of data, and so you you'll end up with a matrix and a set of bolt
uh vector matrices that you want to multiply.
Now keep in mind that if you're doing data science, a lot of times you're not looking at this. This is what's going on behind the scenes.
So if you're in um the sci kit looking at sklearn, where you're doing linear regression models, this is some of the math that's hidden behind the scenes
that's going on.
Other times you might find yourself having to do part of this and manipulate the data around so it fits right, and then you go back in and you run it through the psy
kit.
And if we can do um
up here where we did a uh matrix and vector multiplication, we can also do matrix to matrix multiplication.
And if we run this where we have the two matrices, uh you can see we have a very complicated array that of course comes out on there for our dot.
And just to reiterate it, we have our transpose a matrix, which is your dot T.
And so if we create a matrix A and then we do uh transpose it, you can see how it flips it from 5, 10, 15, 20, 25, 30 to 5, 15, 25,
10, 20, 30, uh rows and columns.
And certainly with the math, this comes up a lot. It also comes up a lot with XY plotting.
When you put it into pi plot, you have one format where they're looking at pairs and numbers and then they want all of x's and all y's.
So you know the transpose is an important tool both for your math and for plotting and all kinds of things.
Another tool that we didn't discuss is your identity matrix.
And this one is more definition.
The identity matrix, we have here one where we just did uh two, so it comes down as one zero zero one, uh,
one zero zero zero one zero.
It creates a diagonal of one.
And what that is, is when you're doing your identities, you could be comparing all your different features to the different features and how they correlate.
And of course, when you have uh feature one compared to feature one to itself, it is always one, uh, where usually it's between zero and one
depending on how well it correlates. So when we're talking about identity matrix, that's what we're talking about right here, is that you create this preset matrix
and then you might adjust these numbers depending on what you're working with and what the domain is.
And then another thing we can do uh to kind of wrap this up, we'll hit you with the most complicated uh piece of this puzzle here, is an inverse
A matrix.
And let's just go ahead and put the um it's a lengthy description.
Let's go ahead and put the description. This is straight out of the uh the website for um NumPy.
Uh so given a square matrix A, here's our square matrix A, which is 210010121, keep in mind
three by three, it's square, it's gotta be equal. It's gonna return the matrix A inverse, satisfying dot a um a inverse. So here's our matrix multiplication.
Um and then it of course it equals the dot uh yeah, a inverse of a um with an identity shape of uh a
dot shape zero. This is just reshaping the identity.
That's a little complicated there. Uh so we go ahead and have our here's our array.
Uh we'll go ahead and run this, and you can see what we end up with is we end up with uh an array 0.5 minus 0.5
and so forth with our 211 going down 210010121.
Uh getting into a little deep on the math, understanding when you need this is probably really is is what's really important when you're doing data science
versus uh handwriting this out and looking up the math and handwriting all the pieces out. You do need to know about the linear algorithm inverse of A.
Uh so if it comes up you can easily pull it up or at least remember where to look it up.
You took a look at the algebra side of it. Let's go ahead and take a look at the calculus side of uh what's going on here with the machine learning.
So calculus, oh my goodness, and differential equations, you gotta throw that in there because that's all part of the bag of tricks,
especially when you're doing large neural networks, but it also comes up in many other areas.
The good news is most of it's already done for you in the back end. Uh so when it comes up, you really do need to understand from the data science, not data analytics.
Data analytics means you're digging deep into actually solving these math equations.
Uh and a neural network is just a giant differential equation.
So when we talk about calculus, we're going to go ahead hell and understand it by talking about cars versus time and speed.
So it helps to calculate the spontaneous rate of change.
So suppose we plot a graph of the speed of a car with respect to time.
So as you can see here, going down the highway, probably merged into the highway from an on-ramp, so I had to accelerate, so my speed went way up.
Stuck in traffic, merged into the traffic, traffic opens up, and I accelerate again up to the speed limit, and maybe a peters
off up there.
So you can look at this as
the speed versus time. I'm getting faster and faster because I'm continually accelerating. And if I hit the brakes, it'd go the other way.
So the rate of change of speed with respect of time is nothing but acceleration.
How fast are we accelerating?
The acceleration is the area between the start point of x and the end point of delta x.
So we can calculate a simple if you had x and delta x, we could put a line there, and that slope of the line is our acceleration.
Now that's pretty easy when you're doing linear algebra, but I don't want to know it just for that line and those two points. I want to know it across the whole of what I'm working with.
That's where we get into calculus.
So when we talk about the distance between x and delta x, it has to be the smallest possible, near to zero, in order to approximate the acceleration.
So the idea is that instead of, I mean, if you ever did took a basic calculus class, they would draw bars down here and you would divide this area up, um,
let's go back up a screen.
You divide this area of this time period up into maybe ten sections, and you'd use that and you could calculate the acceleration between each one of those ten
sections kind of thing. Uh and then we just keep making that space smaller and smaller until delta x is almost uh infinitesimally small.
And so we get a function of a uh equals a limit as h goes to zero of uh function of a plus h minus a function of a
over h.
And that is your computing the slope of the line.
We're just computing that slope under smaller and smaller and smaller samples.
Uh and that's what calculus is.
Calculus is the integral. You can see down here we have our nice uh integral sign, looks like a giant s.
And that's what that means is that we've taken this down to as small as we can for that sampling.
Uh so we're talking about calculus, we're finding the area under the slope is the main process in the integration.
Similar, small intervals are made of the smallest possible length of x plus delta x, where delta x approaches almost an infinitisme
small space.
And then it helps to find the overall acceleration by summing up all the lengths together.
Uh so we're summing up all the accelerations from the beginning to the end.
And so here's our integral we sum of a of x times d of x equals a plus c.
Uh that is our basic calculus here.
So when we talk about multivariate calculus, uh multivariate calculus deals with functions that have multiple variables.
And you can see here we start getting into some very complicated equations. Um change in W over change of time equals change of w over change of z, the differential of z to dx,
differential of x to dt.
It gets pretty complicated.
Uh and it really translates into the multivariate integration using double integrals.
And so you have the the sum of the sum of f of x of y of d of a equals the sum from c to d and a to b of f of x of y,
dx dy equals uh the sum of a to b, sum of c to d of f x of y dy dx.
Understanding the very specifics of everything going on in here and actually doing the math is use the calculus 1, calculus 2, and differential equations.
Uh so you're talking about three full-length courses to dig into and solve these math equations.
What we want to take from here is we're talking about calculus, uh, we're talking about summing of all these different slopes.
And so we're still solving a linear uh expression. We're still solving y equals mx plus b.
But we're doing this for infinitismally small x's, and then we want to sum them up. That's what this integral sign means the the sum of a of x d of x equals a plus c.
And when you see these very complicated multivariate differentiation using the chain rule, when we come in here and we have the change of W to the change of T equals a change of W
dz
and so forth.
That's what's going on here. That's what these means. We're basically looking for the area under the curve, which really comes to how is the change changing?
Speed's going up, how is that changing?
And then you end up with a multiple layer.
So if I have three layers of neural networks, how is the third layer changing based on the second layer changing, which is based on the first layer changing?
And you get the picture here that now we have a very complicated multivariate integration with integrals.
The good news is we can solve this mathematically, and that's what we do when you do neural networks and reverse propagation.
So the nice thing is that you don't have to solve this on paper unless you're a data analysis and you're working on the back end of integrating these formulas and building the
script to actually build them.
So we talk about applications of calculus. It provides us the tools to build an accurate predictive model.
So it's really behind the scenes.
We want to guess at what the change of the change of the change is.
That's a little goofy. I know. I just threw that out there. It's kind of a meta term. But if you can guess how things are going to change, then you can guess what the new numbers are.
Multivariate calculus explains the change in our target variable in relation to the rate of change in the input variables.
So there's our multiple variables going in there.
If one variable is changing, how does it affect the other variable?
And then in gradient descent, calculus is used to find the local and global maxima.
And this is really big. We're actually going to have a whole section here on gradient descent because it is really.
I mean, I talked about neural networks and how you can see how the different layers go in there, but gradient descent is one of the most key things for trying to guess the best answer to something.
So let's take a look at the code behind gradient descent.
And uh before we open up the code, let's just do a real quick uh gradient descent.
Let's say we have a curve like this, and most common is that this is going to represent your error.
Oops.
Error.
There we go.
Ah, hard to read there.
And I want to make the error as low as possible.
And so what I'm looking at it is I want to find this line here,
which is the minimum value.
So we're looking for the minimum.
And it does that by uh sampling there.
And then it based on this, it guesses it might be someplace here, and it goes, hey, this is still going down.
It goes here and then goes back over here and then goes a little bit closer. And it's just playing a high low until it gets to that spot, that bottom spot.
And so we want to minimize the error. And
on the flip note, you could also want to be maximizing something. You want to get the best output of it.
Uh that's simply uh minus the value.
Uh so if you're looking for where the peak is, this is the same as a negative for where the valley is.
I'm looking for that valley.
Uh that's all that is, and this is a way of finding it.
So the cool thing is um all the heavy lifting's done.
Um I actually ended up putting together one of these a while back is uh when I didn't know about Psychic and I was just starting.
Uh boy, it's a long while back.
And uh is playing high low. How do you play high low, not get stuck in the valleys, uh, figure out these curves and things like that?
Well, you do that, and the back end is all the calculus and differential equations to calculate this out.
The good news is you don't have to do those.
Uh so instead we're going to put together the code.
And let's go ahead
and see what we can do with that.
So, uh, guys in the back put together a nice little piece of code here, which is kind of fun.
Uh, some things we're gonna note, and this is this is really important stuff because when you start doing your data science and digging into your machine learning models,
uh, you're gonna find these things are stumbling blocks.
The first one is current X. Where do we start at?
Uh keep in mind your model that you're working with is very generic. So, whatever you use to minimize it, the first question is where do we start?
Um and we started at this because the algorithm starts at x equals three.
So we are arbitrarily picked five.
Learning rate is uh how many bars to skip going one way or the other. Um in fact I'm gonna separate that a little bit because these two are really important.
Um if we're dealing with something like this where we're talking about um uh well here's our here's the function we're gonna use, our um gradient of our function,
um two times x plus five, keep it simple.
So that's the function we're gonna work with.
So if I'm dealing with increments of a thousand, point one is gonna be a very long time.
And if I'm dealing with increments of 0.001, uh 0.1 is gonna skip over my answer, so I won't get a very good answer.
Um and then we look at precision. This tells us when to stop the algorithm. So again, very specific to what you're working on.
Uh if you're working with money and you don't convert it into a float value, uh you might be dealing with 0.01, which is a penny. That might be your precision you're working
with. Um, and then of course the previous step size, max iterations, uh we want something to cut out at a certain point.
Usually that's built into a lot of minimization functions. And then here's our actual uh formula we're gonna be working with.
And then we come in and we go, while previous step size is greater than precision and it's less than max and max iters.
Let's say that ten times fast.
Um
we're just saying if it's uh if we're if we're still greater than our precision level, we still got to keep digging deeper.
Um and then we also don't want to go past a thousand or whatever this is, a million or ten thousand uh running. That's actually pretty high.
Um we almost never do max iterations more than like a hundred or two hundred.
Rare occasions you might go up to four or five hundred if it's uh depending on the problem you're working with.
Uh so we have our previous equals our current.
That way we can track time wise.
Uh the current now equals the current minus the rate times the formula of our previous x.
So now we've generated our new version. Uh previous step size equals the absolute current previous.
Uh so we're looking for the change in x.
Iters equals iterations plus one. That's how we know to stop if we get too far.
And then we're just going to print the local minimum occurs at x on here.
And if we go ahead and run this,
uh you can see right here it gets down to this point and it says, hey, um
local minimum is minus 3.3222 for this particular series we created.
Uh and this is created off of our formula here, lambda x2 times x plus five.
Now, when I'm running this stuff, uh you'll see this come up a lot
in uh with the sklearn kit.
And and one of the nice reasons of breaking this down the way we did is I could go over those top pieces.
Uh those top pieces are everything when you start looking at these minimization toolkits in built-in code.
And so from um we'll just do it's actually docs.cipy.org. And we're looking at the sci kit.
There we go.
Um, optimize, minimize.
You can only minimize one value.
You have the function that's going in. This function can be very complicated. Uh so we used a very simple function up here.
It could be uh there's all kinds of things that could be on there. And there's a number of methods to solve this as far as how they shrink down. Uh and your X naught.
There's your there's your start value.
So your function, your start value.
Um, there's all kinds of things that come in here that we can look at, which we're not going to.
Um optimization automatically creates, constraints, bounds.
Some of this it does automatically, but you really the big thing I want to point out here is you need to have a starting point.
You want to start with something that you already know is mostly the answer.
Uh if you don't, then it's gonna have a heck of a time trying to calculate it out.
Or you can write your own little script that does this and does a high-low guessing and tries to find the max value.
That brings us to statistics.
What this is kind of all about is figuring things out.
A lot of vocabulary and statistics.
So statistics, well, I guess it's all relative. It's definitely not an et al class. So a bunch of stuff going on statistics.
Statistics concerns with the collection, organization, analysis, interpretation, and presentation of data.
That is a mouthful.
So we have from end to end, where does it come from? Is it valid? What does it mean? How do we organize it? How do we analyze it?
And then you got to take those analyses and interpret it into something that people can use, kind of reduce it to understandable.
And nowadays you have to be able to present it. If you can't present it, then no one else is going to understand what the heck you did.
So when we look at the terminologies,
there is a lot of terminologies depending on what domain you're working in. So clearly, if you're working in a domain that deals with
viruses and T cells, and
how does you know where does that come from? And you're studying the different people, then you can have a population. If you are working with
mechanical gear, you know, a little bit different. If you're looking for the wobbling statistics to know when to replace a rotor on a machine or something like that, that can be a big deal.
You know, we have these huge fans that turn in our sewage processing systems. And so those fans they start to wobble and hum and do different things.
If the sensors pick up, at one point do you replace them instead of waiting for it to break, in which case it costs a lot of money. Instead of replacing a bushing, you're replacing the whole fan unit.
An interesting project that came up for our city a while back. So population.
All objects are measurements whose properties are being observed.
So that's your population, all the objects. It's easy to see it with people because we have our population in large, but in the case of the sewer fans, we're talking about how many
the fan units, that's the population of fans that we're working with.
You have a parameter, a matric that is used to represent a population or characteristic.
You have your sample, a subset of the population studied.
You don't want to do them all because then you don't have a, if you come up with a conclusion for everyone, you don't have a way of testing it.
So you take a sample. Sometimes you don't have a choice. You can only take a sample of what's going on. You can't study the whole population.
And a variable, a metric of interest for each person or object in a population.
Types of sampling.
We have probabilistic approach, selecting samples from a larger population using a method based on the theory of probability.
And we'll go into a little bit more deeper on these. We have random, systematic, stratified.
And then you have a non-probabilistic approach, selecting samples based on the subjective judgment of the researcher rather than random selection.
It has to do with convenience, trying to reach a quota, or snowball.
And they're very biased. That's one of the reasons you'll see this big stamp on it that says biased. So you've got to be very careful on that.
So probabilistic sampling.
When we talk about a random sampling, we select random sized samples from each group or category.
So we it's as random as you can get.
So we kind of split it up. This would be like a time setup or our different categories. And you might ask your question well, what is a category or a group?
If you look at, I'm going to go back a window. Let's say we're studying economics of different of an area,
we know pretty much that based on their culture and where they came from, they might need to be separated. And so and when I say separated, I don't mean separated from their place where they live.
I mean as far as the analysis, we want to look at the different groups and make sure they're all represented. So if we had like an 80%
of a group that is, say, Hispanic and or Indian, and also in that same area, we have 20%, 20%
who are let's call our expatriates who left America and they're nice and your Caucasian group.
We might want to sample a group that is representative of both.
So we're talking about stratified sampling, and we're talking about groups. Those are the groups we're talking about.
And that brings us to stratified sampling, selecting approximately equal-sized samples from each group or category.
This way we can actually separate the categories and give us an insight into the different cultures and how that might affect them in that area.
So you can see these are very, very different, kind of depends on what you're working with as far as your data and what you're studying.
And so we can see here, just to go a little bit more, we'd have selecting 25 employees from a company of 250 employees randomly.
Don't care anything about them, what groups they're in, which office they're in, nothing. And we might be selecting one employee from every 50 unique employees in a company of 250 employees.
And then we have selecting one employee from every branch in the company office. So we have all the different branches. There's our group or our categories by the branch.
And the category could depend on what you're studying. So it has a lot of variation on there. You see this kind of grouping and categorizing is also used to generate a lot of misinformation.
So if you only study one group and you say this is what it is, then everybody assumes that's what it is for everybody.
And so you've got to be very careful of that, and it's a very unethical thing to kind of do.
So types of statistics.
There are so many different terms in statistics to break it up.
So we so we're talking about a particular setup.
So we're talking about descriptive and inferential uh statistics, you can do the base of the word describe is pretty solid.
You're describing the data.
What does it look like?
With inferential statistics, we're going to take that from the small population to a large population.
So if you're working with a drug company, uh you might look at the data and say, these people were helped by this drug.
They did uh 80% better as far as their health or 80% better survival rate than the people
who did not have the drug. So we can infer that that drug will work in the greater populace and will help people.
So that's where you get your inferential.
So we are predicting how it's going to affect the greater population.
So descriptive statistics. It is used to describe the basic features of data and form the basis of quantitative analysis of data.
So we have a measure of central tendencies, we have your mean, median, and mode, and then we have a measure of spread, like your range,
your interquartile range, your variance, and your standard deviation.
And we're going to look at all these a little deeper here in a second.
But one of them you can think of is
how the data difference.
Differences, you know, what's the max, min range, all that stuff is your spread. And anything that's just a single number is usually your central tendencies, measure of central tendencies.
So we talk about the mean, it is the average of the set of values considered.
What is the average outcome of whatever's going on?
And then your median separates the higher half and the lower half of data.
So where's the center point of all your different data points?
So your mean might have some a couple really big numbers that skew it so that the average is much higher than if you took those outliers out,
where the median would, by separating the high from the low, might give you a much lower number. You might look at it and say, oh, that's that's odd. Why is the average so much higher than the median?
Well, it's because you have some outliers, or why is it so much lower?
And then the mode is the most frequent appearing value.
This is really interesting if you're studying economics and how people are doing, you might find that the most common income, like in the US, was uh 1.24,000 a year,
where the average was closer to 80,000.
And it's like, wow, what a difference. Well, there's some people who have a lot of money, and so that skews that way up. So the average person is not making that kind of money.
And then you look at the median income, and you're like, well, the median income is a little bit closer to the average.
Uh so it does create a very interesting way of looking at the data. Again, these are all uh central tendencies, single numbers you can look at for the whole spread of the data.
And we look at the measure of central tendencies, the mean is the average marks of a student in a classroom. So here we have the mean, some of the marks of the students, total number of students.
And as we talked about the median, uh if we have zero through ten, and we take half the numbers and put them on one side of the line, half the numbers on the other side of the line,
uh, we end up with five in the middle. And then the mode. What mark was scored by most of the students in a test?
In a simple case where most people scored like an 82% and got certain problems wrong, easy to figure out.
Uh, not so easy when you have different areas where like you have like the um, oh let's go back to economy,
a little bit more difficult to calculate if you have a large group that scores that makes 30,000, and a slightly bigger group that makes 26,000.
So what do you put down for the mode?
Uh certainly there's a number of ways to calculate that, and there's actually a different variation depending on what you're doing.
So now we're looking at a measure of spread. Uh range. What's the difference between the highest and the lowest value?
First thing you want to look at. You know, it's uh we had everybody in the test scored between 60 and 100%. Somebody got 100%, or maybe 60 to 90 percent.
It was so hard that a lot of people could not get 100%.
Um, then you have your inter-quartile range. Quartiles divide a rank-ordered data set into four equal parts.
Very common thing to do as part of all the basic packages, whether you're working in uh data frames with pandas, whether you're working in scala,
whether you're working in R.
You'll see this come up where they have range, your min, your max, and then it'll have your interquartile range. How does it look like in each quarter of data?
Variance measures how far each number in the set is from the mean, and therefore from every other number in the set.
Uh so you have like a how much turbulence is going on in this data.
And then the standard deviation. It is the measure of the variance or the dispersion of a set of values from the mean.
And you'll usually see uh if I'm doing a graph, I might have the value graphed, and then based on the the error,
I might graph graph the standard deviation in the error on the graph as a background so you can see how far off it is. So standard deviations used a lot.
So measurement of spread. Uh marks of a student out of 100, we have here from 50 to 63 or 50 to 90.
Uh so the range, maximum marks, minimum marks, we have 90 to 45, and the spread of that is 45, 90 minus 45.
And then we have the interquartile range using the same marks over there.
You can see here where the median is, and then there's the first quarter, the second quarter, and the third quarter based on splitting it apart by those values.
And to understand the variance and standard deviation, we first need to find out the mean.
So here's our our you know calculating the average there.
We end up at approximately 66 for the average.
And then we look at that the variance. Once we know the means, we can do equals the marks minus the mean squared.
Why is it squared?
Because one, you want to make sure it's you don't have like if you if you're putting all this stuff together,
you end up with an error as far as one's negative, one's positive, one's a little higher, one's a little lower. Uh so you always see the squared value and over the total observations.
And so the standard deviation equals the square root of the variance, which is approximately 16.
And if you were looking at a predictable model, you would be looking at the deviation based on the error. How much error does it have?
Uh and that's again really important to know if your if your prediction is predicting something, what's the chance of it being way off or just a little bit off?
Now that we've looked at the tools as far as some of the basics for doing your statistics and what we're talking about, let's go ahead and pull up a
little demo and show you what that looks like in Python code.
Uh so you can get some little hands-on here.
For that, let's go back into our Jupyter Notebook in Python.
Now, almost all of this you can do in NumPy.
Last time we worked um in NumPy. This time we're going to go ahead and use pandas.
And if you remember from pandas on here, uh this is basically a data frame, rows, columns.
Let's just go ahead and do a printdf.head
and run that.
And you can see we have uh the name Jane, Michael, William, Rosie, Hannah, and their salaries on here.
And of course, instead of having to do uh all those hand calculations and add everything together and divide by the total, we can do something very simple on this, uh
like use the command uh mean in pandas. And so if I go ahead and do this, print df, pick our column, salary, because we want to find the means of that colory.
We want to find the means of that column.
Uh and we go ahead and print this out, and you can see that the uh average income on here is 71,000.
Uh and let's just go ahead and do this. We'll go ahead and put in uh means.
And if we're gonna do that, we also might want to find the median.
And the median is uh very similar,
except it actually is just median.
Uh we're used to means and average, it's kind of interesting that those are they use the two different words.
Uh there can be in some computations slight differences, but for the most part, the means is the average.
Uh and then the median.
Whoops, let's put a
median here.
DF salary, that way it displays a little better.
We can see the median is 54 um thousand. So the halfway mark is significantly below the average.
Why? Because we have somebody in here who makes 189,000.
Darn you rosy for throwing off our numbers.
Um but that's something you'd want to notice.
This is this is uh the difference between these is huge, and so is what is the meaning behind that when you're studying a populace and looking at uh the different data coming in.
And of course, we also want to find out hey, what's the most uh common
income that people make
in this little tiny sample? And so we'll go ahead and do the mode.
And you can see here with the mode, uh it's at 50,000.
So this is this is very telling that most people are making 50,000.
The middle point is at 54,000, so half the people are making more than that.
What that tells me is that if the most common income is way is below the median, then there's a few, there's a skin,
there's a lot of high salaries going up, but there's some really low salaries in there.
And so this trend, which is very common in statistic when you're analyzing the economy and different people's income, is pretty common.
And the bigger difference between these is also very important when we're studying statistics.
Uh and when you hear someone just say, hey, the average income was, you might start asking questions at that point, why aren't you talking about the median income?
Why aren't you talking about the mode, the most common income?
What are you hiding?
Uh and if you're doing these analyses, you should be looking at these saying, hey, why why are these discrepancies? Why are these so different?
And of course, with any uh analysis, it's important to find out the minimum and the maximum.
So we'll go ahead, it's it's just simply uh um dot min will pull up your minimum and then dot max pulls up the maximum.
Pretty straightforward on as far as um
translating it and knowing what your you know what the your lowest value and what your highest value is here, um, which you'll use to generate like a spread later on.
And real quick on mode, uh note that it puts mode zero.
Like I said, there's a couple different ways you can compute the mode.
Um, although you know the standard one's pretty good. We can of course do the range, which is your max minus your min.
So now we have a range of 149,000 between the upper end and the lower end.
And you might want to be looking up the individual values on all of these. But it turns out there is a describe
feature in pandas.
And so in pandas we can actually do df salary describe.
And if we do this, you can see we have that there's seven uh setups.
Here's our mean, uh our standard deviation, which we didn't compute yet, which would just be a dot std.
And you gotta be a little careful because when it computes it, it it looks for axes and things like that.
Uh we have our minimum value, and here's our quartiles,
uh, our maximum value, and then of course the name salary.
Uh so these are the these are the basic statistics you can pull them up and like just describe.
This is a dictionary, so I could actually do something like um
in here I could actually go uh count and run, and now it just prints the count.
Uh so because this is a dictionary, you can pull any one of these values out of here.
It's kind of a quick and dirty way to pull all the different information and then split it up depending on what you need.
Now, if I just walked in and gave you this information um in a meeting, at some point you would just kind of fall asleep.
That's what I would do anyway.
Um, we want to go ahead and see about graphing it here.
And we'll go ahead and put it into a histogram and plot that graph on it of the salaries.
And let's just go ahead and put that in here.
So we do our mapplot inline. Remember, that's a Jupyter's notebook thing.
Uh a lot of the new version of the mapplot library does it automatically.
But just in case, I always put it in there. Uh import mapplot library, pi plot as plt, that's my plotting.
And then we have our data frame. I guess I really don't need to respell the data frame.
Maybe we could just remind ourselves what's in it. So we'll go ahead and just print DF.
That way we still have it.
And then we have our salary df salary, salary.plot history title, salary distribution, color gray,
plot axv line, salary, the mean value. So we're going to take the mean value,
color violet, line style dash. This is just all making it pretty.
What color, dash line, line width of two, that kind of thing.
And the median.
And let's go ahead and run this just so you can see what we're talking about.
And so up here we are taking on our plot.
So here's the data.
Here's our data frame, print it out so you can see it with the salaries.
We're looking at the salary distribution.
And just look at this, the way the salary is distributed.
You have our, in this case, we did, let's see, we had red for the median, we have violet
for our average or mean.
And you can just see how it really here's our outlier. Here's our person who makes a lot of money.
Here's the average, and here's the median.
And so as you look at this, you can say, wow, based on the average, it really doesn't tell you much about what people are really taking home.
All it does is tell you how much money is in this, you know, what the average salary is.
So some of the things you want to take away in addition to this is that it's very easy to plot um
an AXV line.
These are these up and down lines for your markers.
And as you display the data, I mean you can add all kinds of things to this and get really complicated.
Keeping it simple is pretty straightforward. I look at this and I can see we have a major outlier out here. We can definitely do a histogram and stuff like that.
But you know, picture's worth a thousand words.
What you really want to make sure you take away is that we can do a basic describe, which pulls all this information out and we can print any of the individual information from the describe
because this is a dictionary.
And so if we want to go ahead and look up
the mean value, we can also do describe mean. So if you're doing a lot of statistics, uh being able to
it doesn't have the print on there, so it's only going to print um the last one, which happens to be the mean.
Uh you can very easily reference any one of these.
And then you can also, if you're doing something a little bit more complicated and you don't need just the basics, you can come through and pull any one of the individual um
references from the from the pandas on here.
So now we've had a chance to describe our data.
Uh let's get into inferential statistics.
Inferential statistics allows you to make predictions or inferences from data.
And you can see here we have a nice little picture: movie ratings. And um, if we took this group of people and said, "Hey, how many people like the movie, dislike, it, can't say
?". And then you ask just a random person who comes out of the movie who hasn't been in this study, uh, you can infer that 55% chance of saying
liked, 35% chance of saying disliked, or a 10 or 11% chance of can't say.
So that's real basics of what we're talking about you're going to infer that the next person is going to follow these statistics.
So let's look at point estimation.
It is a process of finding an approximate value for a population's parameter, like mean or average from random samples of the population.
Let's take an example of testing vaccines for COVID-19.
Vaccines and flu bugs, all that, it's a pretty big thing of how do you test these out and make sure they're going to work on the populace.
A group of people are chosen from the population.
Medical trials are performed.
Results are generalized for the whole population.
So here's a protected, here's our small group up here where we've selected them.
We run medical trials on them, and then the results work for the population.
Nice diagram with the arrows going back and forth and the very scary COVID virus in the middle of one.
And let's take a look at the applications of inferential statistics.
Very central is what they call hypothesis testing and the confidence interval, which go with that.
And then as we get into
probability, we get into our binomial theorem, our normal distribution, and central limit theorem.
Hypothesis testing.
Hypothesis testing is used to measure the plausibility of a hypothesis, assumption, by using sample data.
Now, when we talk about theorems, theory, hypothesis, keep in mind that if you are in a philosophy, class,
theory is the same as hypothesis, where theorem is a scientific statement.
that is something that has been proven, although it is always up for debate, because in science, we always want to make sure things are up to debate.
So a hypothesis is the same as a philosophical class calling a theory.
Where theory in science is not the same. Theory in science says this has been well proven.
Gravity is a theory.
So if you want to debate the theory of gravity, try jumping up and down.
If you want to have a theory about why the economy is collapsing in your area, that is a philosophical debate.
Very important. I've heard people mix those up and it is a pet peeve of mine.
When we talk about hypotheses testing, the steps involved in hypotheses testing is first we formulate a hypothesis.
We figure out the right test to test our hypothesis, we execute the test, and we make a decision.
And so when you're talking about a hypothesis, you're usually trying to disprove it.
If you can't disprove it and it works for all the facts, then you might call that a theorem at some point.
So in a use case, let's consider an example.
We have four students were given a task to clean a room every day.
Sounds like working with my kids. They decided to distribute the job of cleaning the room among themselves.
They did so by making four chits, which has their names on it and the name that gets picked.
Up has to do the cleaning for that day.
Rob took the opportunity to make chits and wrote everyone's name on it.
So here's our four people Nick, Rob, Imlia, Imlia, and Summer.
Now Rick, Imlia, and Summer are asking us to decide whether Rob has done some mischief in preparing the chits, i.e., whether Rob has written his name on one of the chit.
For that we will find out the probability of Rob getting the cleaning job on first day, second day, third day, and so on till 12 days.
The probability of Rob getting the job decreases every day, i.e., his turn never comes up, then definitely he has done some mischief while making the chits.
So the probability of Rob not doing work on day one is uh three out of four. There's a 0.75 chance that he didn't do work.
Uh two days, three fourths times three fourths equals 0.56.
3 days, you have 3 fourths, 3 fourths, 3 fourths, which equals 0.42.
When you get to day 12, it's 0.032, which is less than 0.05.
Remember this 0.05. Uh that comes up a lot when we're talking about certain values when we're looking at statistics.
Rob is cheating as he wasn't chosen for 12 consecutive days. That's a very high probability when on day 12 he still hasn't gotten the job cleaning the room.
So we come up to our important important terminologies.
We have null hypothesis,
a general statement that states that there is no relationship between two measured phenomena or no association among the groups.
Alternative hypothesis.
Contrary to the null hypothesis, it states whenever something is happening, a new theory is preferred instead of an old one.
And so the two hypotheses go hand in hand. So your null, this is always interesting in when talking about data science and the math behind it, it's about proving that the things have no correlation.
Null hypothesis says these two have zero relation to each other.
Where the alternative hypothesis says, hey, we found a relation, this is what it is.
We have p-value. The p-value is a probability of finding the observed or more extreme results when the null hypotheses of a study question is true.
And the t-value, it is simply the calculated difference represented in units of standard error.
The greater the magnitude of t, the greater the evidence against the null hypothesis.
And you can look at the t-value as being specific to the test you're doing, where the p-value is derived from your t value and you're looking for what they
call the 5% or the 0.05, showing that it has a high correlation.
So digging in deeper, let's assume that a new drug is developed with the goal of lowering the blood pressure more than the existing drug.
And this is a good one because the null value here isn't that you don't have any drug, the null value here is that it's better than the existing drug.
The new drug doesn't lower the blood pressure more than the existing drug.
Now, if we get that, uh that says our null hypothesis is correct, there is no correlation, and the new drug is not doing its job.
The alternative hypothesis, the new drug does significantly lower the blood pressure more than the existing drug.
Yay, we got a new drug out there, and that's our alternative hypothesis or the H1 or HA.
And we look at the P-value, results from the evidence like medical trials showing positive results which will reject the null hypothesis.
And again, they're looking for a 0.05 or 5%.
And the T value comparing all the positive test results and finding means of different samples in order to test hypothesis.
So this is specific to the test.
What percentage of increase did they have?
And this leads us to the confidence intervals.
A confidence interval is a range of values we are sure our true values of observations lie in.
Let's say you asked a dog owner around you and asked them, how many cans of food do you buy for your uh per year for your dog?
Through calculations, you got to know that the on an average around 95% of the people bought around 200 to 300 cans of food.
Hence, we can say that we have a confidence interval of 200, 300, where 95% of our values lie in that data spread.
And this the graph really helps a lot, so you can start seeing what you're looking at here where you have the 95%,
you have your peak, in this case it's a normal distribution, so you have the nice bell curve equal on both sides, it's not asymmetrical.
And 95% of all the values lie within a very small range, and then you have your outliers, the 2.5% going each way.
So we touched upon hypothesis, uh, and we're going to move into probability.
Uh so you have your hypothesis, once you've generated your hypothesis, we want to know the probability of something occurring.
Probability is a measure of the likelihood of an event to occur.
Any event can be predicted with total certainty and can only be predicted as a likelihood of its occurrence.
So any event cannot be predicted with total certainty, it can only be predicted as a likelihood of its occurrence.
Uh score prediction, how good you're going to do in uh whatever sport you're in, weather prediction, stock prediction.
If you've studied physics and chaos theory, even the location of the chair you're sitting on has a probability that it might move three feet over.
Granted, that probability is one in like uh I think we calculated as under one in trillions upon trillions. So it's the better the probability, the more likely it's going to happen.
There are some things that have such a low probability that we don't see them.
So we talk about a random variable.
Uh random variable is a variable whose possible values are numerical outcomes of a random phenomena.
So uh we have the coin tossed, how many heads will occur in the series of 20 coin flips?
Probably, you know, the on average they're 10, but you really can't know because it's very random.
How many times a red ball is picked from a bag of balls if there's equal number of uh red balls and blue balls and green balls in there?
How many times the sum of digits on two dice uh result or five each?
Um so you know there's how often are you going to roll two fives on your pair of dice?
So in a use case, uh let's consider the example of rolling two dice. We have a random variable outcome equals y.
You can take values two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten, eleven, twelve.
So we have a random variable and a combination of dice.
And instead of looking at how many times both dice will roll five, let's go ahead and look at a total sum of five.
And you have in as far as your random variables, you can have a one, four equals five, four, one, two, three, three, two.
So four of those rolls can be four, if you look at all the different options you have, four of those random rolls can be a five.
And if we look at the total number,
which happens to be thirty-six different options, uh, you can see that we have four out of thirty-six chance every time you roll the dice that you're gonna roll a total of five.
You're gonna have an outcome of five.
And uh we'll look a little deeper as to what that means.
Uh, but you could think of that at what point if someone never rolls a five or they always roll a five, can you say, hey, that person's probably cheating?
Uh we'll look a little closer at the math behind that.
But let's just consider this as one of the cases is rolling two dice and gambling.
There's also binomial distribution.
It is the probability of getting success or failure as an outcome in an experiment or trial that is repeated multiple times.
And the key is is by meaning two, binomial. Uh so passing or failing an exam, winning or losing a game, and getting either head or tells.
So if you ever see binomial distribution, it's based on a truefalse kind of setup. You win or lose.
Let's consider a use case and let's consider the game of football between two clubs. Barcelona and Dortmund.
The teams will have to play a total of four matches, and we have to find out the chances of Barcelona winning the series.
So we look at the total games, and we're looking at five different games or matches.
Let's say that the winning chance for Barcelona is 75% or 0.75.
That means at each game they have a 75% chance that they're going to win that game.
And losing chances are 25% or 0.25.
Clearly, 0.75 plus 0.25 equals 1. So that accounts for 100% of the game. Probability for getting K wins in N matches is calculated.
And we we're talking like so if you have five games and you want to know if I play how many wins in those five games should I get, what's a percentage on those?
And the probability for getting k wins in n matches is calculated by Px equals K equals NCK P to the K,
Q to the N minus K.
Here, P is the probability of success and Q is the probability of failure.
And so we can do total games of N equals 5, where K equals 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, P, which is the chance of winning, is 0.75,
Q the chance of losing, equals 1 minus P, which equals 1 minus 0.075, which equals 0.25.
The probability that Barcelona will lose all of the matches can then just plug in the numbers, and we end up with a 0.0009765625. So a very small chance they're going to lose all their matches.
And we can plug in the value for two matches.
Probability that Barcelona will win at least two matches is 0.0878.
And of course we can go on to probability that Barcelona will win three matches, the 0.26, and of course four matches, and so on.
And it's always nice to take this information and let's find the cumulative discrete probabilities for each of the outcomes.
Where Barcelona has won three or more matches x equals three, x equals four, x equals five.
And we end up with the P equals 0.264 plus 0.395 plus 237, which equals 0.89.
In reality, the probability of Barcelona winning the series is much higher than 0.75.
And it's always nice to
put out a nice graph so you can actually see the number of wins to the probability and how that pans out with our binomial case.
Continuing in our important terminology, location.
The location of the center of the graph depends on the mean value.
And this is some very important things. So much of the data we look at, and when you start looking at probabilities, almost always has a normalized look, like the graph in the middle.
But you do have left skewed where the data is skewed off to the left and you have more stuff happening off to the left, and you have right skewed data.
And so when this comes up and these probabilities come up where they're skewed, it's really important to take a closer look at that.
Mostly you end up with a normalized set of data, but you gotta also be aware that sometimes it's a skewed data. And then the height. Height of the slope inversely depends upon the standard deviation.
So you can see down here the standard deviation is really large, it kind of squishes it out.
And if the standard deviation is small, then most of your data is going to hit right there in the middle, you're gonna have a nice peak.
And so being aware of this, that you might have a probability that fits certain data, but it has a lot of outliers.
So you're if you have a really high standard deviation, if you're doing stock market analysis, this means your predictions are probably not going to make you much money.
Uh where if you have a very small deviation, you might be right on target and set to become a millionaire.
Which leads us to the Z-score. Z-score tells you how far from the mean a data point is.
It is measured in terms of standard deviations from the mean.
Around 68% of the results are found between one standard deviation. Around 95% of the results are found between two standard deviations.
And you read the symbols, of course they love to throw some Greek letters in there. We have uh mu minus two sigma.
Mu is just a quick way, it's a kind of funky U. It just means the mean.
Uh and then the sigma is the standard deviation, and that's the O with a little arrow off to the right, or the little waggly tail going up, the O with it with the line on it.
Uh so mu minus two sigma is your uh 95% of the results are found between two standard deviations.
Central limit theorem, this goes back to the skew. If you remember we were looking at the skew values on this previous slide, have left skewed, normalized, and right skewed.
When we're talking about it being skewed or not skewed, the distribution of the sample means will be approximately normally distributed, evenly distributed,
not skewed, if you take large random samples from the population with the mean, mu, and the standard deviation, sigma,
with replacement.
And you can see here, um uh of course we have our uh mu minus two sigma and the spread down here, the mean, the median, and the mode. And so when you're talking about very large populations,
these numbers should come together and you shouldn't have a skewed value. If you do, that's a flag that something's wrong.
That's why this is so important to be aware of what's going on with your data, where your samples are coming from, and the math behind it.
And if we're going to do all this, we've got to jump into conditional probability.
The conditional probability of an event A is a probability that the event will occur given the knowledge that an event B has already occurred. And you'll see this as Bayes' theorem, B-A-Y-E-S, Bayes.
Uh and this is read.
I mean, you have these funky looking little P brackets, A B.
This is the probability of A being true while B is already true.
And you have the probability of B being true when A is already true, so P, B of A.
Probability of A being true divided by the probability of B being true.
And we talk about Bayes' theorem, which occurred back in the 1800s when he discovered this. This is such an important formula.
And it's really, it's not if you actually do the math, you could just kind of do
XY equals JK, and then you divide them out, and you're going to see the same math. But it works with probabilities, which makes it really nice.
And so if you have a set you might have uh eight or nine different studies going on in different areas, different people have done the studies, they brought them together.
If we look at today's COVID virus, the virus spread, uh certainly the studies done in China versus the studies the way they're done in the US,
that data is different in each of those studies.
But if you can find a place where it overlaps, where they're studying the same thing together, you can then compute the changes that you need to make in one study to make them equal.
And this is also true if you have a study of
one group and you want to find out more about it. So this formula is very powerful, and it really has to do with the data collection part of the math and data science
and understanding where your data is coming from and how you're going to combine different studies in different groups.
And we'll go ahead and go into a use case. Let's find out the chance of a person getting lung disease due to smoking.
And this is kind of interesting the way they word this. Let's say that according to medical report provided by the hospital, states that around 10% of all patients they treated suffered
lung disease. So we have kind of a generic medical report. They further found out by a survey that 15% of the patients that visit them smoke.
So we have 10% that are lung disease and 15% of the patients smoke.
And finally, 5% of the people continued smoke even when they had lung disease.
Not the brightest choice, but you know, it is an addiction, so it can be really difficult to kick.
And so we can look at the probability of A. Prior probability of 10% people having lung disease.
And then probability B, probability that a patient smokes is 15%.
And the probability of B,
if B then A, the probability of a patient smokes even though they have lung disease is 5%.
And probability of A is B, probability that the patient will have lung disease if they smoke.
And then when you put the formulas together, uh you get a nice solution here. You get the probability of A to B, probability that the patient will have lung disease if they smoke.
And you can just plug the numbers right in, and we get a 3.33% chance. Hence there is a 3.33% chance that a person who smokes will get a lung disease.
So we're gonna pull up a little Python code, always my favorite, roll up the sleeves.
Keep in mind we're gonna be doing this kind of like the back end way.
So that you can see what's going on.
And then later on, we're gonna create
we'll get into another demo which shows you some of the tools that are already pre-built for this.
Let's start by creating a set. So we're gonna create a set with curly braces.
This means that our set has um only unique values. So you have a list, uh you have your tuples, which can never change, and then you have um in this case the set.
So 4.7, you can't create a 4-7, 4. It'll delete the 4 out. So it's only unique values.
And if you use dictionaries,
quick reminder, this should look familiar because it is a dictionary where you have a value, and that value is assigned to, or that key is assigned to a value.
Uh so you could have a key value set up as a dictionary. So it's like a dictionary without the value, it's just the keys and they all have to be unique.
And if we run this, we have a uh set of four seven.
We can also take a list, a regular setup, and I'm going to go ahead and just throw in another number in here, 4, and run it.
And you can see here if I take my list 1, 2, 3, 4, 4, and I convert it to a set, and here it is, my set from list
equals set my list.
The result is 1, 2, 3, 4. So it just deletes that last 4 right out of there.
And with the sets, you can also go in there and print here is my set, my set,
3 is in the set, and then if you do 3 in my set,
that's going to be a logic function.
And 1 in my set, 6 is not in the set, and so forth. If we run this,
we get 3 is in the set true, 1 is in the set false, because 3, 5, 7 is another one.
6 is in the set, 6 is not in the set, so not in my set.
You can also use this with a list. We could have just used 3, 5, 7, and it would have the same response on there is 3 and usually you do if 3 is in, but 3 in my set
is still works on just a regular list.
And we'll go ahead and do a little iteration. We're going to do kind of the dice one. Remember
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
And so we're going to bring in the iteration tool and import product as product.
And I'll show you what that means in just a second.
So we have our two dice. We have dice A,
and it's going to be a set of values.
They can only have one value for each one. That's why they put it in a set. And if you remember from range, it is up to 7. So this is going to be 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
It will not include the 7. And the same thing for our dice B.
And then we're going to do is we're going to create a list which is the product of A and B. So what's A plus B.
And if we go ahead and run this, it'll print that out, and you'll see in this case when they say product because it's an iteration tool,
we're talking about creating a tuple of the two.
So we've now created a tuple of all possible outcomes of the dice, where dice A is 1, 2, 3, 1 to 6, and dice B is 1 to 6. And you can see 1 to 1, 1 to 2, 1 to 3, and so forth.
You can remember we had a slide on this earlier where we talked about the different all the different outcomes of a dice.
We can play around with this a little bit. We can do n dice equals 2, dice faces, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
Another way of doing what we did before, and then we can create an event space where we have a set which is the product of the dice faces.
Repeat equals n dice. And we'll go ahead and just run this.
And you can see here it just again puts it through all the different possible variables we can have.
And then if we want to take the same set on here and print them all out like we had before, we can just go through for
outcome and event space, outcome end equals.
So the event space is creating
a sequence. And as you can see here, when we print it out, it stacks them versus going through and putting them in a nice line.
And we'll go ahead and do something. Let's go print.
Since we have the end printing with a comma, that just means it's just gonna it's not gonna hit the return going down to the next line. And we'll go ahead and do the length
of our event space.
And we might want to calculate something like um what about the multiple of three? What if we want to have uh the probability of the multiple of three in our setup?
And so we can put together the code for the outcome in event space of xy equals outcome.
If x plus y
remainder 3. So we're going to divide by 3 and look at the remainder and it equals 0,
then it's a favorable outcome. And we're going to pop that outcome on the end there.
And we'll turn it into a set. So the favor outcome equals a set. Not necessary because we know it's not going to be repeating itself, but just in case we'll go ahead and do that.
And if we want to print out the outcome, we can go ahead and see what that looks like. And you can see here these are all multiples of three.
1 plus 2 is 3, 5 plus 4 is 9, which divided by 3 is 3, and so forth.
And just like we looked up the length uh of the one before, let's go ahead and print the length of our f
outcome.
So we can see what that looks like.
There we go.
And uh of course I did forget to add the print in the middle because we're looping through and putting an end on the on the setup on there, so we're going to put the print in there.
And if I run this, you can see uh
we end up with 12.
So we have 36 total options.
Uh we have 12 that are multiple that um add up to a multiple of three.
And we can easily convert compute the probability of this uh by simply taking the length of our favorable outcome over the length of the event space.
And if we print it out, let me put that in there, probability, last line, so we can just type it in, we end up with a 0.3333
chance.
And it's roughly a third.
And we might want to make this look nice. So let's go ahead and put in another line there. The probability of getting the sum, which is a multiple of three, is
0.3333.
We can compute the same thing for five dice.
And if we do this for five dice and go ahead and run it, you can see we just have a huge amount of choices.
Uh so it just goes on and on down here.
And we can look at the uh length of the event space.
And we have over 7,776 choices. That's a lot of choices.
And if we want to ask the question like we did above, uh what is the sum where the sum is a multiple of five but not a multiple of three,
we can go through all of these different options, and then uh you can see here uh d1, d2, d3, d4, d5 equals the outcome.
And if uh you add these all together and the
division by five does not have a remainder of zero, but the remainder is also of a division by three is not equal to zero.
So the multiple of five is equal to zero, but the multiple of three is not, we can just append that on here, and then we can look at that uh favorable outcome.
We'll go ahead and set that, and we'll just take a look at this. What's our length of our favorable outcome?
It's always good to see what we're working with.
And so we have 904 out of 776,
and then of course we can just do a simple division to get the probability on here. What's the probability that we're going to roll a multiple of 5 when you add them together, but not a multiple of 3.
And so we're just going to divide those two numbers, and you can see here we get uh 0.116255 or 11.62%.
And so you can really have a nice visual that this is not really complicated math right here on probabilities.
It's just how many options do you have and how many of those are you possibly going to be able to come up with with the solution you're looking for.
And this leads us to a confusion matrix.
A confusion matrix is a table which is used to describe the performance of a classification model on a set of test data for which the true values are known.
And so you'll see in the left we have the predicted and the actual.
And we have a negative, false negative, positive, true positive,
and then we have false positive and true negative.
And you can think of this as your predicted model.
What does that mean?
That means if you divided your data and you used two-thirds of it to create the model, you might then test it against an actual case for the last third to see how well it comes out.
How many times was it true positive versus uh false positive? It gave a false positive response.
And you can imagine in medical situations, this is a pretty big deal.
You don't want to give a false positive.
So you might adjust your model accordingly so you don't have a false positive, say with a COVID virus test.
It'd be better to have a false negative and they go back and get retested than to have 30% false positives where then the test is pretty much invalid.
So in a use case like cancer prediction, let's consider an example where a cancer prediction model is put to the test for its accuracy and precision.
Actual result of a person's medical report is compared with the prediction made by the machine learning model.
And so you can see here, here's our actual predicted, whether they have cancer or not. You know, cancer, a big one. You don't want to have a false positive.
I mean a false negative. In other words, you don't want to have it tell you that you don't have cancer when you do.
So that would be something you'd really be looking for in this particular domain. You don't want a false negative.
And this is again, you know, you've created a model, you have uh hundreds of people or thousands of pieces of data that come in.
There's a real famous case study where they have the imagery and all the measurements they take, and there's about 36 different measurements they take.
And then if you run the uh a basic model, you want to know just how accurate it is.
How many negative results do you have that are either telling people they have cancer that don't, or telling people that don't have cancer that they do.
And then we can take these numbers and we can feed them into our accuracy, our precision, and our recall.
So accuracy, precision, and recall, accuracy metric to measure how accurately the results are predicted.
And this is your total true where you got the right results, you add them together, the true positive, the true negative, over all the results.
So what percentage of them were accurate versus what were wrong.
When we talk about precision, is a metric to measure how many of the correctly predicted cases are actually turned out to be positive.
So we have a precision on true positive.
Again, if you're talking about like uh COVID testing with the viruses, uh you really want this to be a high number.
You want this true that to be the center point where you might have the opposite if you're dealing with cancer, where you want no false negatives.
Uh so this is your metric on here. Precision is your test positive, uh, true positive plus uh false positive.
And then your recall, how many of the actual positive cases we were able to predict quickly with our model?
Uh so test positive is the test positive plus the false negative on there.
And we'll want to go ahead and do a demo on the naive Bayes classifier. Before I get too far into uh naive Bayes classifier, because we're gonna pull it from the SK Learn or the uh SciKit.
Um let's go ahead.
Kind of an interesting page here for classifiers. When you go into the SK Learn kit, there's a lot of ways to do classification. And I'll just zoom up in here so you can see some of the titles.
Uh there's everything from the nearest neighbor, linear.
Um, but we're gonna be focusing on the naive bays over here.
And this is just um a sample data set that they put together, and you can see how some of these have a very different output.
The naive bays, remember, is set up as probably the most simplified uh calculator or um set of predictions out there.
And so what we've been talking about with the truefalse and stuff like that, where there's a uh
And then uh belief that there is a independent assumption between the features, where the features are very assumed to have some kind of connection, uh
then we can go ahead and use that for the prediction. And so that's what we're using as a naive Bayes classifier versus many of the other classifiers that are out there.
For this, we're gonna use uh the social network ads. It's a little data set on here.
And uh let me go ahead and just open that up the file.
Uh here we go.
It has user ID, gender age, estimated salary uh purchased.
And so we have uh you can see the user ID mail 19, uh estimated salary 19,000, and purchase
zero. Uh so it's either gonna make a purchase or not.
So look at that last one, zero one. We should be thinking of binomials, we should be thinking of uh simple naive base classifier kind of setup.
So if we close this out, we're gonna go ahead and import our numpy as NP.
We're gonna be nice to have a good visual of our data, so we'll put it in our mapplot library.
Here's our pandas, our data frame.
Uh, and then we're gonna go ahead and import the data set. And the dataset's gonna be we're gonna read it from the social network ads.csv.
Then we're gonna print the head just so you can see it again, uh, even though I showed you it in the file.
And x equals the dataset i location, uh two, three values, and y is gonna be the four, uh column four.
Let me just run this so it's a little easier to go over that.
Um you can see right here we're gonna be looking at uh 0, 1, 2 is age and estimated salary, so 2, 3.
And that's what iLocation just means that we're
looking at the number versus a regular location. Uh regular location you'd actually say age and estimated salary.
And then column 4 is did they make a purchase? They purchased something.
Uh so those are the three columns we're going to be looking at when we do this.
And we've gone ahead and imported these and imported the data, so now our data set is all set with this information in it.
And we'll need to go ahead and split the data up. Uh so we need our from the SK Learn model selection, we can import train test split.
Uh this does a nice job. We can set the random state so it randomly picks the data.
And we're just going to take uh 25% of it's going to go into the test, our X test and our Y test, and the 75% will go to X
train and Y train.
That way, once we create our model, we can then have data to see just how accurate or how well it has performed with our prediction.
The next step in pre-processing our data is to go ahead and do feature scaling.
Now, a lot of this is starting to look familiar. If you've done a number of the other modules and setup, you should start noticing that we bring in our data, we take a look at what we're working with,
we go ahead and split it up into training and testing.
Uh in this case, we're going to go ahead and scale it.
Scale it means we're putting it between a value of minus one and one, uh, or someplace in the middle ground there.
This way, if you have any huge set you don't have this huge um setup, if we go back up to here where salary, the salary is twenty
thousand versus age 35.
Well, there's a good chance with a lot of the back end math that 20,000 will skew the results and the estimated salary will have a higher impact than the age
instead of balancing them out and letting the calculations weigh them properly.
And finally, we get to actually create our Naive Bayes model.
And then we're going to go ahead and import the Gaussian Naive Bayes.
And the Gaussian is is the most basic one.
That's what we're looking at now.
It turns out, though, if you go to the SK Learn Kit, they have a number of different ones you can pull in there. There's a Bernoulli, I've never used that one. Categorical.
Compliment, and here's our Gaussian.
So there's a number of different options you can look at.
Gaussian, when you come to the Naive Bayes, is the most commonly used.
So we're talking about the Naive Bayes. That's usually what people are talking about when they're pulling this in.
And one of the nice things about the Gaussian, if you go to their website to SK Learn, the Naive Bayes Gaussian, there's a lot of cool features. One of them is you can do partial fit on here.
That means if you have a huge amount of data, you don't have to process it all at once.
Once you can batch it into the Gaussian NB model.
And there's many other different things you can do with it as far as fitting the data and how you manipulate it.
We're just doing the basics. So we're going to go ahead and create our classifier.
We're going to equal the Gaussian NB.
And then we're going to do a fit. We're going to fit our training data and our training solution. So X train, Y train.
And we'll go ahead and run this. It's going to tell us that it ran the code right there.
And now we have our trained classifier model.
So the next step is we need to go ahead and run a prediction.
We're going to do our y predict equals the classifier.predict X test.
So here we fit the data, and now we're going to go ahead and predict.
And now we get to our confusion matrix. So from the SK Learn Matrix metrics, you can import your confusion matrix.
Just as saves you from doing all the simple math that does it all for you.
And then we'll go ahead and create our confusion metrics with the Y test and the Y predict.
So we have our actual and we have our predicted value.
And you can see from here, this is the chart we looked at. Here's predicted. So true positive, false positive, false negative, true negative.
And if we go ahead and run this, there we have it.
65, 3, 7, 25.
And in this particular prediction, we had 65 or predicted the truth as far as a purchase. They're going to make a purchase, and we guessed three wrong.
And then we had 25 we predicted would not purchase and seven of them did.
So there's our confusion matrix.
At this point, if you were with your shareholders or a board meeting, you would start to hear some snoozing if they were looking at the numbers. And you say, hey, here's my confusion matrix.
So let's go ahead and visualize the results.
We're going to pull from the mapplot library colors, import listed color map.
And this is actually my machine's going to throw an error because this is being
because of the way the setup is. I have a newer version on here than when they put together the demo.
And we need our X set and our Y set, which is our X train and Y train.
And then we'll create our X1, X2, and we'll put that into a grid.
And we set our X set minimum stop and our X set max stop.
And if you come all the way over here, we're going to step 0.01.
This is going to give us a nice line, is what that's doing. And then we're going to plot the contour, plot the X limit, plot the Y limit, and put the scatter plot in there.
And let's go ahead and run this. To be honest, when I'm doing these graphs, there's so many different ways to do that. There's so many different ways to put this code together.
To show you what we're doing, it's a lot easier to pull up the graph and then go back up and explain it.
So the first thing we want to note here when we're looking at the data
is this is the training set.
And so we have those who didn't make a purchase. We've drawn a nice area for that.
So even our training set isn't going to be a hundred percent.
We couldn't do that. And so we're looking at our different data coming down.
We can kind of arrange our X1, X2 so we have a nice plot going on, and then we're going to create the contour.
That's that nice line that's drawn down the middle on here with the red green.
That's where that's what this is doing right here with the reshape. And notice that we had to uh do the dot T.
If you remember from NumPy, if you did the NUMPy module, you end up with pairs, you know, X uh X1, X2, X1,
X2, next row, and so forth. You have to flip it so it's all one row. You have all your X1s and all your X2s. Um this is what we're kind of looking for right here on this setup.
Uh and then the scatter plot is of course your scattered data across there. We're just going through all the points. That puts these nice little dots onto our setup on here.
And we have our estimated salary and our a, and then of course the dots are did they make a purchase or not?
And just a quick note, this is kind of funny. You can see up here where it says x set y set equals uh x train y train, which seems kind of a little weird to do.
Um this is because this is probably originally a definition.
Uh, so it's its own module that could be called over and over again, and which is really a good way to do it because the next thing we're going to want to do is do the exact same thing,
but we're going to visualize the test set results.
Uh, that way we can see what happened with our test group, our 25%.
And you can see down here we have um the test set, uh, and it if you look at the two graphs next to each other, this one obviously has um
75% of the data, so it's gonna show a lot more.
This is only 25% of the data.
You can see that there's a number that are kind of on the edge as to whether they could guess by age and income they're gonna make a purchase or not.
Um, but that said, it's still pretty clear, it's pretty good as far as how much the estimate is and how good it does.
Now, graphs are really effective for showing people what's going on, but you also need to have the numbers.
And so we're gonna do from SK Learn, we're gonna import metrics, and then we're gonna print our metrics classification report from the Y test and the Y
predict.
And you can see here we have precision, uh precision of zeros is 90. There's our recall 0.96.
We have an F1 score and a support, and we have our precision, the recall on getting it right, uh, and then we can do our accuracy,
the macro average, and the weighted average. Uh so you can see that it pulls in pretty good as far as how accurate it is.
You could say it's gonna be about 90%, is gonna guess correctly that it that they're not gonna purchase, and we had an 89%
chance that they are gonna purchase. Um, and then the other numbers as you get down have a little bit different meaning, but it's pretty straightforward on here.
Here's our accuracy, and here's our micro average, and the weighted average, and everything else you might need.
And if you forgot the exact definition of accuracy, it is the true positive, true negative over all of the different setups.
Precision is your true positive over all positives, true and false.
And recall is a true positive over true positive plus false negative.
And we can just real quick flip back there
so you can see those numbers on here.
Uh, here's our precision, here's our recall, and here's our accuracy on this.
Welcome to this exciting journey into the world of statistics for data science. Have you ever wondered how data transforms from raw numbers into powerful insights that drive decisions?
Well, statistics is the magic behind it all.
Today, we will uncover how statistical methods help us summarize data, model uncertainty, test hypotheses, and find relationships that can predict the future.
So, Bakalab, we are about to turn numbers into knowledge.
Without any further ado, let's get started. Now, to start off, here is a key question. What are statistics in data science?
Now, statistics is the science of collecting, analyzing, and interpreting data. By applying statistical methods, we can uncover patterns in the data and make informed decisions.
Now, as we continue, you notice how these essential concepts will form the backbone of many data science practices.
Let's explore the key functions of statistics in data science. First, statistics helps summarize data using measures like mean, median, and variance.
Next, it models uncertainty with probability and distributions so we can better understand risk and variability in our data.
It also tests hypotheses such as when we use A B testing to compare different outcomes.
Statistics finds relationships through methods like regression and correlation, revealing how variables impact each other.
And finally, all these tools enable data-driven decision making, turning raw numbers into actionable insights.
Now let's talk about why does statistics matter in data science?
Statistics form the backbone of data science, providing the mathematical framework needed to make sense of data and draw reliable conclusions.
Without statistics, it would be impossible to turn raw data into meaningful insights or make confident evidence-based decisions.
Now let's have a look at the main branches of statistics.
Descriptive statistics and inferential statistics. So first let's talk about the definition. Then we have got methods and measures.
Now in the case of descriptive statistics, now let's have a look at the main branches of statistics. So basically there are two core branches: descriptive statistics and inferential statistics.
Descriptive statistics summarizes and describes data using measures like mean, median, mode, range, and standard deviation.
Its purpose is to organize and present data typically with charts, graph or summary tables.
The scope of descriptive statistics is limited to the sample data itself.
On the other hand, inferential statistics makes inferences about populations based on samples.
It uses methods like hypothesis testing, confidence intervals, and regression.
The purpose here is to draw conclusions and make predictions with common examples including A B testing and survey analysis.
The scope of inferential statistics extends beyond the sample to the larger population. Understanding both these branches is essential for analyzing and interpreting data in any data science project.
Now let's take a closer look at the descriptive statistics, starting with measures of central tendency.
The first measure here is mean, which is the average of all the values simply calculated as the sum of all the data points divided by the total count.
Next is the median, which represents the middle value when the data is sorted from lowest to highest. This is especially useful when dealing with skewed distributions.
And finally, the mode is the most frequently occurring value in the data set, helping us identify common patterns or repeated outcomes.
Let's continue our deep dive into descriptive statistics by looking at the measures of variability.
First, we've got the range.
This is simply the difference between the maximum and minimum value in a dataset, showing us the spread of our data, which measures the average of the square differences from the mean.
This tells us how much the values in our data set differ from the average.
Closely related is the standard deviation, which is the square root of the variance. It gives us a more intuitive sense of how much the values typically deviate from the mean.
And finally, we've got the interquartile range, or we say IQR.
This shows us the range of the middle 50% of our data, helping us understand how data is distributed across the center and avoid the effect of outliers.
Understanding these four measures allows us to summarize not just the center of our data but how spread out and varied our data set is.
Now let's look at some practical applications of descriptive statistics.
One major use is the data exploration and summarization, where we quickly get an overview and basic understanding of complex data sets,
helping track performance and detect problems early in fields like manufacturing or operations.
And finally, they are central to business reporting and dashboards, where concise summaries are essential for managers to review trends and make data-driven decisions.
So, in short, descriptive statistics help transform raw data into clear, actionable information across many business,
scientific, and operational contexts. Let's explore the first type of data in statistics qualitative or categorical data.
This type of data includes descriptive information that cannot be measured numerically, such as categories or labels and yes or no responses.
These are all about qualities or characteristics rather than quantities. Qualitative data can be further divided into two types: nominal, where the categories have no specific order, and ordinal,
where the categories do have an order or ranking.
Recognizing and classifying qualitative data is very important as it affects how information is analyzed and interpreted in statistics.
Now let's discuss the second main type of data in statistics, which is quantitative or numerical data.
This type of data includes information that can be measured and expressed with numbers, making it ideal for mathematical analysis. Quantitative data is further divided into two main categories.
First, there is discrete data.
These are countable values with specific fixed points such as the number of students, cars sold, or website clicks.
Second, there is continuous data, which includes infinite possible values within a given range. Examples of continuous data include height, weight, temperature, or time.
Understanding the distinction between discrete and continuous data is very important as it determines which statistical methods and visualizations
will be most appropriate.
Now let's dive into the fundamentals of probability. Probability measures the likelihood of an event occurring and it's always expressed as a value between 0 and 1. Here are some key concepts.
If the probability or p equals to 0, that means the event will never occur.
If p is equal to 1, the event will always occur.
And if p is equal to 0.5, the event has an equal chance of occurring or not occurring. It's truly a 50-50% scenario.
Now understanding these basic principles helps us quantify uncertainty and make informed predictions about future outcomes.
Now let's look at the different types of probability. First, there's classical probability. This is based on equally likely outcomes such as flipping a fair coin or rolling a balanced die.
Next, empirical probability, which relies on observed frequency.
It's calculated from actual data, such as the proportion of rainy days over the past month. Let's say for example, the probability of it's raining today given that it's cloudy.
Understanding these three types helps us choose the right approach for different situations whether we are predicting outcomes, analyzing data,
or making decisions under uncertainty.
Now, probability has a wide range of powerful applications in data science.
First of all, it is used in predictive modeling and machine learning where algorithms estimate future outcomes based on existing data.
Probability also plays a key role in risk management and decision making, helping businesses and researchers evaluate the likelihood of different scenarios and plan accordingly.
Conditional probability calculating the chance of one event given that the another has occurred. This is crucial in fields like healthcare, fraud detection, and marketing analytics.
And finally, probability is foundational in A B testing and experimental design, allowing us to measure the effectiveness of new strategies
or products. These applications show how probability enables smarter, evidence-driven progress in modern data science.
Let's look at one of the most common probability distributions, the normal distribution.
This distribution is famous for its well-shaped symmetric curve, which shows that most values cluster around the mean,
with fewer and fewer values appearing as you move away from the center.
Now many natural phenomena like heights, test scores, and measurement errors tend to follow this pattern, making the normal distribution a key concept in statistics.
It's characterized by two main parameters: the mean which determines the center of the curve and the standard deviation which controls its spread.
Recognizing the distribution helps analysts make predictions, calculate probabilities, and apply statistical techniques to real-world data.
Next, let's explore the binomial distribution, which is another common probability distribution.
The binomial distribution is discrete and is used for situations with binary outcomes like success or failure.
It is based on a fixed number of trials where each trial has a constant probability of success, such as flipping a coin a certain number of times
or tracking pass fail rates.
Examples of binomial experiments include coin flips and measuring how many students pass or failure test.
This distribution helps us model and analyze outcomes when only two possibilities exist in each trial. Now let's focus on the poison distribution, another key type of probability distribution.
The poison distribution is a discrete distribution specifically used to model rare events.
It's particularly helpful for modeling events that occur independently over a fixed interval of time or space.
For example, it predicts how many times an event like a customer arriving on a website receiving a visit might happen in a certain period.
Typical examples include customer arrivals at a store, defect rates and manufacturing or counts of website visits over a set period.
This distribution is a great tool for understanding and predicting random independent events that don't happen very often but are important to track.
It's a branch that allows us to make inferences, predictions or generalizations about a larger population using sample data. Here are some key concepts.
First is the population versus sample. The population represents the entire group we want to know about, while the sample is the subset we actually collect data from.
Next concept is sampling distribution, which refers to the distribution of a statistic across multiple samples from the same population.
Standard error measures how much the sample statistic is expected to vary due to random sampling.
And finally, margin of error tells us how much we can expect our estimates to differ from the true population value.
Together, these concepts form the foundation for drawing reliable insights from sample data in inferential statistics.
Let's review some of the main techniques used in inferential statistics. First, we've got hypothesis testing.
This method allows us to test claims or ideas about population parameters based on sample data, helping us determine if observed results are statistically significant.
And reliability of our estimate. Next are confidence intervals. These provide a range of likely values for a population parameter, giving us a sense of possible variation, reliability of our estimate.
And lastly, regression analysis is used to model and analyze the relationships between variables, allowing us to make predictions,
uncover trends, and understand how changes in one factor might affect another.
Now let's work through the hypothesis testing process. The first step is to formulate hypothesis. Start with null hypothesis represented as H0, which states that there is no effect or difference.
Then there is the alternative hypothesis represented as H1, which suggests that an effect or difference does exist.
Now, after setting up the hypothesis, the next step is to choose a significance level noted by alpha.
Common choices for significance levels include 0.05, 5%, 0.01, 1%, 0.010, which is 10%.
The significance level is important because it controls the likelihood of making a type 1 error, also known as false positive.
And now each step in the process is critical for ensuring that statistical results are both meaningful and reliable.
The next step is to collect and analyze sample data. Ensure the data is represented by choosing a good sample. Then calculate the appropriate and test statistic for your hypothesis test.
Once that's done, it's time to make a decision. Compare the p-value to the chosen significance level alpha.
Now if the p-value is less than or equal to alpha, you reject the null hypothesis. If the p-value is greater than alpha, you fail to reject the null hypothesis. And finally, interpret your results.
Draw your conclusions with respect to the context and problem at hand, always keeping the bigger picture in mind.
Following these steps helps ensure your hypothesis test is robust, clear, and meaningful.
Let's review the common types of hypothesis test using statistics.
The one sample test compares the mean of a sample to a known value, and the one sample Z test is used when the population standard deviation is known.
Next, we have two sample tests. The independent samples t test compares to the means of two different groups, while pair samples t-test compares before and after measurements for the same subject.
For categorical data test, the Xi square test checks for the independence or goodness of fit.
And Fisher's exact test is useful for small sample sizes. And lastly, non-parametric tests such as the Man Whitney U test and Wilcoxon signed RANG test serve as alternatives to the T
test when data doesn't meet certain parametric assumptions. Choosing the right hypothesis test depends on your data type and the specific question you want to answer.
Let's explore the central limit theorem or CLT of foundation for inferential statistics.
The central limit theorem states that as the sample size increases, the distribution of sample means approaches a normal distribution,
even if the original data isn't normally distributed.
This sample works for any population distribution, making it incredibly powerful.
Now for good results, the sample size should typically be 30 or more.
What's interesting is the sample mean distribution, which will have the same mean as the population.
The standard error which measures variability by the sample mean equals sigma divided by the square root of n, and this gets smaller as the sample size grows.
And finally the formula shown here, which is z is equal to x minus minus nu divided by sigma.
Divided by sigma over the square root of n. Let's standardize and compare sample needs. The CLT makes most parametric statistics possible and is the backbone for many statistical tests.
Let's review the main types of regression analysis which are used to model and understand relationships between variables. First up is linear regression.
This technique analyzes the relationship between a continuous variable and another variable, resulting in a straight line. It's commonly used in predicting sales or prices.
Next is logistic regression. Unlike linear regression, this method is used for binary outcomes, helping estimate probabilities such as whether an email is spam
or a patient has a disease. Moving to multiple regression, this allows us to account for the effect of several variables at once, modeling more complex relationships
like determining house prices. Lastly, polynomial regression, which is used for non-linear relationships.
The resulting curve rather than a straight line lets us capture growth trends and other patterns that aren't linear.
Understanding these types of regression helps analysts choose the right model for the data and business's problem at hand.
Let's clarify the important differences between correlation and causation. Correlation is statistical measure of how two variables move together. Correlation values range from minus 10 to plus 1.
But remember, correlation does not imply causation.
On the other hand, causation means that one variable actually causes changes in another.
Establishing causation requires controlled experimentation and is much stronger relationship than simple correlation. Always be careful when interpreting results.
Just because two variables move together doesn't mean one caused the other.
Let's look at some common problems with interpreting correlation and causation.
First is the third variable problem, which happens when a hidden variable affects both variables in a question, leading to a misleading connection.
There's also this directionality problem where it's unclear which variable is causing others to change. But both are actually caused by a third variable, which is the hot weather.
This demonstrates that correlation does not mean one variable causes the other, so always look for hidden factors before assuming causation.
Let's talk about statistical errors, specifically type 1 and type 2 errors.
Type 1 error, also called as false positive, occurs when we reject the true null hypothesis.
In other words, we wrongly conclude there's an effect when there's actually isn't. The probability of making this error is equal to the significance level alpha.
For example, concluding a drug works when it actually doesn't.
On the other hand, type 2 error is false negative, means failing to reject a false null hypothesis. That's when we miss a real effect or difference.
The probability of type 2 error is beta, for example, missing the real effect of a drug and saying it doesn't work when it actually does.
Understanding these errors is key for designing good experiments and interpreting statistical results properly.
Let's look at three common sampling methods using statistics. The first one is random sampling. Here, every individual in the population has an equal chance of being selected.
Where every Nth individual is chosen, random sampling is crucial for ensuring representative sample. Next is stratified sampling.
The population is divided onto homogeneous subgroups or strata, and then a random sample is drawn from each group.
This approach makes sure all the groups are represented in the sample. And finally, cluster sampling divides the population into clusters, often based on geography.
Entire clusters are then randomly selected.
It's cost effective and useful for large spread out populations.
Choosing the right method ensures the data truly represents the whole population and strengthens the study's conclusions.
So, guys, let's wrap up with some real world applications of statistics. In business analytics, statistics are used for A B testing to optimize websites, customer segmentation and targeting,
sales forecasting and demand planning and quality control, and also process improvement. These techniques help businesses make smarter, data-driven decisions every day.
Statistics play a vital role in healthcare and medicine as well. They are key for analyzing clinical trial results, conducting epidemiological studies, evaluating treatment, effectiveness,
and identifying risk factors. By using these approaches, healthcare researchers and practitioners can improve patient outcomes in public health from businesses to medicine.
Statistics transform raw information into actionable insights that create real impact.
Statistics has a huge impact in technology, data science and finance and power recommended systems that personalize what users see.
In finance, statistics help with risk assessment and management, optimizing investment portfolios, determining credit scores,
and supporting market research and analysis. Now these applications show how statistical techniques help make smarter decisions and solve complex challenges across high
impact industries. Are you one of the many who dreams of becoming a data scientist?
Keep watching this video if you're passionate about data science because we will tell you how it really works under the hood.
Emma is a data scientist.
Let's see how a day in her life goes while she's working on a data science project.
Well, it is very important to understand the business problem first.
In our meeting with the clients, Emma asks relevant questions, understands and defines objectives for the problem that needs to be tackled.
She is a curious soul who asks a lot of eyes.
One of the many traits of a good data scientist.
Now, she gets up for data acquisition.
To gather and scrape data from multiple sources like web servers, logs, databases, APIs, and online repositories.
Oh, it seems like finding the right data takes both time and effort.
After the data is gathered, comes data preparation.
This step involves data cleaning and data transformation.
Data cleaning is the most time-consuming process as it involves handling many complex scenarios.
Here, Emma deals with inconsistent data types, misspelled attributes, missing values, duplicate values, and whatnot.
Then, in data transformation, she modifies the data based on defined mapping rules.
In her project, ETL tools like Talent and Informatica are used to perform complex transformations that helps the team to understand the data structure better.
Then understanding what you actually can do with your data is very crucial.
For that, Emma does exploratory data analysis.
With the help of EDA, she defines and refines the selection of feature variables that will be used in the model development. But what if Emma skips this step?
She might end up choosing the wrong variables, which will produce an inaccurate model. Thus, exploratory data analysis becomes the most important step.
Now she proceeds to the core activity of a data science project, which is data modeling. She repetitively applies diverse machine learning techniques like Canon, decision tree, knife base to the data.
To identify the model that best fits the business requirements.
She trains the models on the training dataset and tests them to select the best performing model.
Emma prefers Python for modeling the data.
However, it can also be done using R and SAS.
Well, the trickiest part is not yet over.
Visualization and communication.
Emma meets the clients again to communicate the business findings in a simple and effective manner to convince the stakeholders.
She uses tools like Tableau, Power BI, and ClickView that can help her in creating powerful reports and dashboards.
And then finally, she deploys and maintains the model.
She tests the selected model in a pre-production environment before deploying it in the production environment, which is the best practice, right?
After successfully deploying it, she uses reports and dashboards to get real-time analytics.
Further, she also monitors and maintains the project's performance.
Well, that's how Emma completes the data science project.
We have seen the daily routine of a data scientist is a whole lot of fun, has a lot of interesting aspects, and comes with its own share of challenges.
Now, let's see how data science is changing the world.
Data science techniques along with genomic data provide a deeper understanding of genetic issues and reaction to particular drugs and diseases.
Logistic companies like DHL, FedEx have discovered the best routes to ship, the best suited time to deliver, the best mode of transport to choose,
thus leading to cost efficiency.
With data science, it is possible to not only predict employee attrition, but to also understand the key variables that influence employee turnover.
Also, the airline companies can now easily predict flight delay and notify the passengers beforehand to enhance their travel experience.
Well, if you're wondering, there are various roles offered to a data scientist, like data analyst, machine learning engineer, deep learning engineer,
data engineer, and of course data scientist.
The median base salaries of a data scientist can range from $95,000 to $165,000.
So that was about the data science.
Are you ready to be a data scientist?
If yes, then start today.
The world of data. Picture this you're shopping online and suddenly you see a product that feels like it was made just for you. How did they know? It's not by chance, it's data science.
Data science helps businesses understand what you like, predict what you need next, and improve the way we shop and use technology.
And here's the best part Data Science isn't just about watching Netflix, it's one of the fastest growing careers in the world right now.
In fact, the US Bureau of Labor Statistics says that data science jobs are expected to grow 36% by 2033. Way faster than most of the other jobs.
Companies everywhere are using data to make smarter decisions. That means the demand for data scientists is huge.
And let's talk about the salary. You're probably wondering how much I can earn actually. Well, for entry level position, data scientists in the US are earning around 152,000 per year right now.
And by 2025, some can make as much as 230,000. And in India, starting salaries range from 50,000 rupees to 1 lakh per month. And experienced professionals can earn more than 5 lakh rupees per month.
That's impressive, right? But the best part is, as a data scientist, you won't just stop here.
The skills you develop in this role, like machine learning, data visualization, and statistics, are highly transferable and crucial for moving into AI roles.
So whether it's becoming an AI engineer or an AI specialist, the foundation you build in data science will help you level up and pursue exciting,
hyping opportunities in the AI field. Now, if you're thinking this sounds great, but where do I even start?
Well, that's exactly what the professional certificate course in data science from IIT Kanpur and Simply Learn is designed to do.
It will get you started and make sure you're ready for this booming industry.
In this 11-month live online interactive program, you will learn the skills you need to become a data science professional. No more theory, no more fluff.
You get hands-on projects, live classes, and mentorship from IIT Kanpur faculty plus real-world industry expert who will help you build your skills.
So this course comes with exciting, amazing features that makes learning even more impactful. Eight times higher interaction in live online classes with industry experts.
Regular live online classes conducted by experienced professionals who bring real world knowledge into every session.
You'll also get to master 13 plus key skills including generative AI, prompt engineering, charge GBT, explainable AI, conversional AI,
NLP, and many more. These are the skills that top companies use every day, and you'll gain hands-on experience with 14 plus industry tools like Python, SQL, Tabu, Dali
2, Midjourney, TensorFlow, and more. And by the end of this course, you will be ready to tackle real world challenges using these powerful tools and techniques.
But we are not just talking about textbook and theory. You'll work on 25 plus real world projects, giving you hands-on experience with the tools and skills you'll use in the industry.
For example, our first project would be about sales analysis.
You'll use Python to analyze a clothing company fourth quarter sales data across Australian state, helping the company make informed decisions.
The next project would be about employee performance analysis, where you learn how to build machine learning models to understand the factors influencing employees'
turnover. Our third project would be about e-commerce, which will help Amazon improve its recommendation engine to offer better recommendations to customers.
Upon successful completion, you'll receive a program certificate directly issued by the EI City Academy IT Kanpur within 45 days of completing your cohort.
This prestigious certificate will help you boost your resume and show potential employers that you have mastered the skills needed to succeed.
You'll also benefit from masterclasses delivered by distinguished IT Kanpur faculty who bring their deep expertise in this course.
Plus, you will be exposed to trending tools like Charge B2, Gen AI, and prompt engineering. Now, if you're wondering who will be teaching all of this, then the IT Kanpur faculty is here for you.
These experts have been in this field for years and have worked with the top companies. You'll also get masterclasses from them and they will guide you through the learning process.
You're not just learning from a textbook, you are learning from the people who have been there and done that.
And the best part is, once you have learned the skills, Simptilearn's career assistance team will help you take to the next step, which will help you to build a killer
resume, show you how to stand out top recruiters, and even give you access to mock interviews.
Plus, you will also gain access to exclusive networking events and hackathons to connect with industry professionals.
Along with Simply Learn's job assistant, you'll also get access to ID Conpourse career services, helping you connect with top recruiters and learn interviews with leading tech companies.
So upon finishing this course, you'll be ready for top data science roles like data scientist, machine learning engineer, AI specialist, and business analyst.
The good news is top companies like Amazon, EY, Fidelity Investment, Johnson Johnson, Vodafone, Accenture, Enforces, and Nvidia
is looking for professionals just like you. And with salaries in the US hitting around $230,000 plus, and in India reaching up to $5 lakh per month, your career outlook looks great.
So, what will you be actually learning in this course?
So here's a sneak peek of the syllabus which you'll be learning in this course, which is the foundation in Python, SQL and Mathematics, Core Data Science like Machine Learning,
Data Visualization, NLP, special topics like Gen AI, Char GPT, prompt engineering, and you'll also work on industry projects which we have already mentioned before.
You'll also have the option to choose electives like data storytelling with PowerPoint DI and Business Analytics with Excel to tailor
your learning experience and focus on the areas that interest you the most. So don't wait, hurry up, and enroll down. Find the course link in the description box below and in the pinned comments.
Have you ever wondered how your favorite online store seems to know exactly what you are looking for?
Every time you browse, add to cut or wish list an item, you are leaving clues about your style, favorite colors, brands, and even shopping times.
Data scientists jump in, analyze these patterns, and create a super personalized shopping experience.
Suddenly the store is showing you just the right pieces at just the right time, almost like it's reading your mind. That's data science, turning your clicks into a shopping spree crafted just for you.
Hello everyone. Welcome back to SimplyLearn's YouTube channel. If you're already a data science enthusiast or just got curious about this exciting field, you're in the right place.
Today in this video, I am diving into 10 essential steps to help you become the next in-demand data scientist and land that dream job.
No more waiting, let's dive right in and get you on the path to your future in data science.
So let's see the 10 essential steps to become the next data scientist in demand.
Step number one is programming languages.
Starting with Python is a beginner is a great move because it's simple, versatile, and widely used in data science.
Python's straightforward syntax makes it beginner friendly, helping you grasp programming basics quickly and dive into data science libraries like Pandas,
NumPy, and Matplotib with ease.
Adding R to your skill set is valuable because it excels at statistical analysis and data visualization, two essential parts of data science.
You can be comfortable with Python and R within a month or two.
So, moving on to the next step that is version control system.
Learning a version control system like Git is essential because it allows you to track, manage, and collaborate and code effectively.
With Git, you can save different versions of your work, making it easy to backtrack if something goes wrong or to experiment without losing progress.
This is especially useful when working with complex data science projects where you might try out different models of analysis techniques.
One or two weeks of practice along with Python and R is good to get started. Now moving on to the third step that is data structures and algorithms.
Learning data structures and algorithms is crucial for becoming a data scientist because they provide the foundation for efficient data handling and problem solving.
Data structures like arrays, stacks, queues, and trees help you store and organize data in ways that make it easier and faster to access, process, and analyze.
Algorithms, on the other hand, give you strategies to perform tasks like searching, sorting, and optimizing data operations, which are essential for handling large data sets.
While many candidates struggle with DAC, mastering it gives you an age helping you stand out in the interviews and shine as a skilled data scientist
capable of tackling the toughest data problems.
Spend about two months in this, you will get in the shape for sure.
Now moving on to the step number four that is SQL.
Learning SQL is essential for data scientists because it enables you to access, manage, and manipulate data directly within databases where most real
world data resides.
With SQL, you can create new tables, alter existing ones, delete unnecessary records and run queries to filter,
sort and aggregate data.
These abilities allow you to retrieve, clean, and organize data effectively.
Core skills needed for any data science role.
It's easy and you don't have to spend more than a month to have a deep understanding of it.
Now moving on to the fifth step that is mathematics and statistics.
Mathematics and statistics are essential for data science because they form the backbone of data analysis, model building and interpretation.
Topics like linear algebra, calculus, probability, and statistics give data scientists the tools to understand data patterns, perform accurate analysis, and make data-driven decisions.
Mastering these areas enables you to build robust models, validate results, and tackle complex problems confidently, making you a well-rounded and skilled data scientist.
Make sure you spend two months to grab these topics.
Now moving on to the step number six that is data pre-processing and visualization.
Learning data pre-processing and visualization is essential for a data scientist because these skills make you data accurate, insightful, and easy to understand.
Python libraries like NumPy and Pandas are crucial for manipulating and creating data, enabling you to handle missing values,
filter out noise, and prepare data for analysis.
Once the data is ready, visualization lets you uncover patterns and communicate results effectively.
Libraries like Matplottib and Cbone help create clear, impactful visuals, allowing you to interpret trends and convey insights in a way that's easily understood by others.
Together with these tools, make data pre-processing and visualization fundamentals for effective data science.
If you have a solid foundation on Python and mathematics, you will get a good understanding of data pre-processing and visualization in a month or two.
Now moving on to the seventh step that is machine learning fundamentals.
Machine learning fundamentals involve understanding how algorithms enable computers to learn from data and make predictions or decisions without explicit programming.
The two main categories are supervised learning and unsupervised learning.
In supervised learning, models are trained on label data to make predictions, while in unsupervised learning, models find patterns in unleveled data.
Popular tools like TensorFlow, PyTorch help build and train complex models, especially for deep learning, while SkyKit Learn is essential
used for simpler machine learning algorithms and data pre-processing. These tools make it easier to implement machine learning fundamentals effectively and build intelligent data-driven decisions.
Dedicate about three months to understand the core of machine learning.
Now coming to the next step that is deep learning. Deep learning is a subset of machine learning that focuses on algorithms inspired by the structures of the human brain called neural networks.
Deep learning uses neural networks with multiple layers, often dozens or hundreds, to learn complex patterns from large data sets.
Specialized types like convolutional neural networks, that is CNNs, are great for image processing, while recurrent neural networks
are used for sequence data like text or time series.
Essential tools like TensorFlow, PyTorch, make building training and deploying deep learning models more accessible, allowing you to create powerful AI solutions across various domains.
I think it will take about two months to have a good hold on deep learning concepts and how to implement them.
Now moving on to the ninth step that is specializations.
Once you have grasped the deep learning, it's like reaching a new level as a data scientist.
Just as doctors specialize in areas in nephrology and cardiology, data scientists often choose to specialize in fields like natural language processing or computer vision.
Natural language processing focuses on teaching machines to understand and generate human language, enabling applications like chatbot, sentiment analysis,
and language translation.
It's about making computers read, write, and even interpret human emotions through text or speech.
Computer vision, on the other hand, is all about enabling machines to see and interpret images or videos.
This field powers innovations like facial recognition, object detection, and autonomous driving.
Now you don't need to learn both.
You can choose what interests you the most.
Now spend one to two months diving deep into one of these areas.
Now moving on to the last but not less step that is big data.
Big data refers to extremely large volumes of data generated rapidly from sources like social media and sensors.
For data scientists, learning to handle big data is crucial as it requires specialized tools like Hadoop and Spark to analyze and extract insights effectively.
With companies relying on data-driven decisions, big data skills make you a highly in-depth and professional in the field.
Focus for about two months and you will be able to spot trends and patterns from datasets very easily.
Once you are ready, it's time to build a killer resume partner projects that showcase your new skills.
Start applying to jobs on platforms like Nocri and InDate and supercharge your LinkedIn, connect with data scientists, see what skills they are mastering and learn from their journeys as well.
Keep sharpening your own skills, and when the time comes, you will be ready to crush those interviews and land your dream data scientist role in 2025. Yeah, step by step we will go through all of this
and uh we'll make sure that we learn everything and we bring everything together towards the end. Right?
Without further ado, let me just
straight away deep dive to business, right?
To learn
data science,
right?
And with this data science, there is also something which is prefixed, which is applied data science.
And suffix for this is
right? Applied data science with Python, right?
So there are there are two key concepts which are going to be a part of this course.
The first one is the knowledge about data science, that what data science is, and then because we are doing an applied course, right?
We are doing an applied course, I will try to tie up these concepts which we will understand in data science with a tool, right, which is Python for
you, right?
We already know about uh 60-65 percent of Python, right, which is the fundamental Python, and now we will be moving to the next step
to advanced Python,
And using Python, right, leveraging Python, we will be solving a lot of problems of data science, right? Using this.
Okay,
so the first few sessions, right? The first few sessions will be about making you abreast with Python, what Python is, right? What are and what packages do we have, how do they work in reality, right?
And all those things, and then we will be coupling it up with the data science concepts, and then finally, towards the end of the session in the last few classes, we will be doing uh,
we will be taking a real data set, and on that data set, we will be applying all these concepts, right?
To understand the data better, and we will be drawing inferences from that to convert that into information to take actionable insights, or
using that actionable insights, taking a better decision, right?
We'll do all of that in in the
actual way, okay.
So now, guys, if you understand this, then the next point of contention is
data science,
One of the most famous keywords on the planet right now, right? One of the most famous keywords on the planet right now.
Do you think that these two things are okay? Let me put it differently.
What do you think that can be the possible uh
explanation about this term data science?
You know data, you know science.
What do you think is going to follow in these sessions?
What is data science to you
as per these two words?
Okay, so this is people made up of two words, right? Data and science, right?
So
what we are trying to do is we are
Trying to understand data,
right? We are trying to understand data, right?
And then do something to it, right?
Understanding its science, understanding the uh nature, the behavior of this data, and converting it in something called as information,
right?
Do you do we know the difference between data and information?
Data is something which is completely raw.
Okay, it is completely raw, it has no meaning.
Right? It has no meaning, isn't it?
For example,
I give you the stats of some player, like suppose say Dhuni.
I give you stats of Mahindra Singh Dhuni, right?
That what were his scores?
Uh, what is his name?
What is his age, and you know, all those things.
Now,
everything is there, right?
But we don't know what to do about it, right? Do you think the score of Dhuni has any context, people?
It has any context?
No, right?
But when I deep down, but I when I go and deep dive about it, right? What is the first thing you find out of scores?
What is the first thing you find out of score scores?
You try to find the average of score, isn't it?
That in last 10 innings,
right? In last 10 innings, before this, also you need something which is called as a problem statement, isn't it?
Now, for example, the problem statement is selectors want to understand, selectors want to understand that whether Mahindrasing Dhoni
should be picked up.
So there's a problem now, right? Selectors want to see that whether Dhoni is fit for the next tournament or not.
So, what we will do, we will now try to take the mean of the scores, right?
For last 10 innings.
And if this score is suppose X, we will try to compare this with Y.
What is Y? Y is a reference.
Right? Y is a reference that we want to compare it against.
Now, when you are doing this comparisons, when you are applying these techniques to the score, this is now slowly becoming information,
right?
And at the end of the day, once you have the strike rate, once you have the mean score of Dhuni, once you have his age,
once you have his fitness score, all those things will now help you to take this particular decision.
Because now what you have is called as information, right? Because this has context,
right? This has meaning.
And this is usually processed.
Right. This is usually processed, right? This is usually processed.
Now, what did we do?
Now, what did we do here?
If you will go and read about data science, data science says
data science says
it is the art of collecting,
right?
Cleaning,
analyzing,
modeling,
improving,
right, and visualizing.
Right, visualizing
the data, right?
If a person is adept in doing all these things, this person is cumulatively called a data scientist,
That person is called a data scientist, right?
So before going to the definition of data scientists now, I will give you some more examples, right? I'll give you some more examples.
Data science people, as I said, is a combination of these things, right? You have to collect the data,
right? You have to collect the data,
right? And this has a lot of things.
Data can be connected from two types in two types.
One is primary,
and the second one is secondary,
right? What is the primary way of collecting data from your IoT devices, right? From sensors,
from your inbuilt machines,
right?
Then from your surveys,
which you float, right?
Questionnaires,
right? All these things are primary ways. What is the secondary way of collecting data?
Purchasing data,
right?
Using internet data.
Because you have not generated it, you are just using someone else's data, right?
Something like uh transfer learning.
What is transfer learning?
Transfer learning is a technique where suppose I am bank A
and you are bank B, right?
So bank A has created some model, right?
Trained on their data.
Now you are going to use the exact same model, right? You're going to use the exact same model, right?
Maybe you are not seeing the data, but you are just using the property of data, like mean, median, mode, and a lot of modeling things which will come,
we will learn about them.
And you use this model on your particular data, right?
So, in a way, you did not have enough data to create the model yourself, but you are now using someone else's model to run your data on it, right? So, this is called as transfer learning.
So, this kind of collection is basically secondary data collection.
So, you can collect the data,
right?
Then you can perform
right? You can perform data analysis, right? How will you perform this data analysis using complex
right? Using complex algorithms, right?
Some statistics,
right?
You can use artificial intelligence,
right? Artificial intelligence, you can use machine learning,
right?
Right, you can use all these things for data analysis, then you can transform
transform
the patterns
into predictions.
Right, you can transfer these patterns into predictions, right?
Which can be used for business
Right, for business decision making.
Then you can validate the results,
right?
And present the results.
The first one is
domain knowledge.
Right.
So what is domain knowledge?
First of all, I told you, right, there will be a problem, right? You will be solving a problem in any project of data science, you'll be trying to solve a problem, right?
And the problem will be belonging to a particular domain.
Even if you are working for yourself, right? Even if you're an entrepreneur, then also you'll be solving a problem.
So this domain knowledge part includes things like understanding.
It's a very important diagram.
Understanding client requirement.
Right. Understanding the client requirement, right?
Important criterions,
right? Important
criteria knowledge.
Right.
For example, to give an example, suppose we have created a machine learning model, okay? Understanding the data.
We have created a machine learning model whose accuracy is 90%, right? Is 90% a good accuracy?
Yeah, fairly decent accuracy.
Yes.
Suppose you have to predict sales, right? You are selling something.
Suppose you are selling clothes and you want to predict what will be the sales for the next week.
When you use this model, whatever the output model gives you, what is going to be the accuracy of your output using this model?
How much accuracy?
90%.
But my question is
model is 90%.
But my question to you is that if 90% accuracy is on sales data, a person like me will be very, very happy.
Okay, very, very happy.
I'll be probably dancing, right?
But if you try to apply the same model, right, for a medical diagnosis
case, will you be interested in getting operated in such a hospital or an institution where the accuracy is coming as 90%?
Domain knowledge, right? Domain knowledge.
We need to understand what are the exact requirements. We need to understand what are the exact expectations, right?
And we need to know how much do we need to pivot, right?
So the first thing in data science is these accuracies and everything are subjective, right? They are subjective.
So for that, you need domain knowledge.
Domain knowledge part, very important, guys. Very important these three things, which I'm going to tell you.
Second part is people,
the game changer, right?
The second part is
computer science.
Now, if I take you back in history, okay, if I take you back in history in the 1980s or somewhere, then do you okay? How many of you think that data science is a new concept?
How many of you think that data science is a new concept?
I hope you all know it's not a new concept.
Everyone knows that.
Yep.
It has been happening for ages.
Just like
you guys will be shocked if you already don't know.
AI was coined in the year 1956.
1956 at the University of Damouth, AI was coined by Paul McCarthy.
Right?
And we saw the boom of AI in the year 2010, right?
Such a long journey.
Same case with data science.
Because people, back in the day, data science was called as
data mining.
Everyone heard about it?
Data mining, knowledge databases.
Yeah. We need to we used to mine the data.
Now, what were the problems?
What were the hiccups of data mining?
The hiccups for data mining was that we were doing everything,
everything manually.
Right now, if I give you hundred points, can you calculate the mean?
Or let's say if I give you two points to multiply, two multiplied by three,
how much time will you take?
Two seconds?
Yep.
How much time will a computer will take?
Two seconds?
If I give you to multiply two,
two, four, eight, nine multiplied by two hundred.
How much time will you take to calculate this?
Say five seconds.
How much time will computer take?
Two seconds.
Now, if I give you to multiply two, four, eight, nine into one five, one, nine, five, four, three, eight, six.
How much time will you take to calculate this manually?
Maybe say one minute?
80 seconds, one minute.
How much time a computer will take?
Right? Still two seconds.
Right?
And if I give you to calculate this over 200 times, you will take 200 minutes, right? Using parallel computing, computer will still take about three to five seconds.
Right? So are you understanding the power of computer?
Do you understand this concept in this relationship?
What was happening back then?
What computer science did people was it revolutionized the way data mining was happening.
And that thing now is called as that again, that thing now is called as data science, in which computer science is one of the most important contributors.
So this is just one reason.
Now, manually, right? Manually, if I give you, say, one million rows of data, right? One million rows of data, right?
So how many pages will you wait pages will you need
to store this data?
Suppose your notebook is like this,
right? These boxes, and here you are storing the data, one million.
So maybe you can buy n number of notebooks.
But now do you think it's as easy in storing something in computer?
Because back in the day, people, we had memory issues,
isn't it?
Memory constraints.
So there is something called as Murray's law, right?
Which says as the
advancement in microprocessors will increase, the price of microprocessor will decrease, right? So this is what is happening right now.
Back in the 1980s, if I show you, right, guys, right?
Yeah, 2.5 kg exactly, right? It was the size of a fridge, hard disk, but now it fits in your palm, right?
So this was enabled the storage techniques, right? The processing techniques, the infrastructure, right?
Things like big data.
What kind of data do you think we will be dealing with, people in data science?
You all know the term.
Very famous term.
The kind of data,
big data, right? Everyone knows about big data. What is big data?
Yes, a data which is fast, right?
It has velocity, veracity,
variety, right?
So this kind of data needs to be stored. This kind of data needs to be processed.
So which thing brought all these things into data science?
It was given to us by computer science, right? So computer science people included things like database management,
Data validation, right? Data infrastructure,
right? Data infrastructure,
right?
Then we had
languages, computer languages,
which is Python right now for us,
Again, do you think when you do this thing manually, right?
Suppose you do this thing manually, how easy do you think it will become using something like Python or any other computer language to create complex models?
How easy it will be to do that?
To create the complexity in models, right?
Where you can capture the non-linear nature,
isn't it, people?
Isn't it?
For example, for example, let me tell you this
one, two, four, six, eight, ten.
What do you think is the next number, guys?
12. If I tell you to define this to me
in okay, let's leave that.
What do you think is going to be the next number here?
What is the next number?
11.
Next number?
25.
Perfect. Now guys, if I ask you to write these numbers, right, the way you predicted them, can you give me a function?
F of x is equal to
what is the f of x here?
It's 2x, right?
It's 2x.
F of x is equal to 2x.
If I tell you to create a function, it will be f of x is equal to 2x.
What will be the function here, guys?
f of x
will be equal to
x plus 1.
Yeah. X plus 1.
Yeah.
And here f of x
will be equal to
x square.
Yeah.
Now the last example.
Right? Last example.
What is the next number here?
I don't want the number. I want the function.
I want this so that I can generalize.
Isn't it?
How did you reach this figure?
How many of you think it's not possible to determine this?
How many
of
you
think
it is not
possible
to determine this?
Yeah.
How many of you think?
What if I just change this question and ask you how many of you think it is not possible to determine this
manually?
Same response, but now I say how many of you think it is not possible to determine this
with computers?
Will your answer still remain no?
Do you think I cannot approximate this function using computers?
We have something called as deep
neural networks.
And they are called as universal function approximators.
Right?
So this is the problem, people. This is the problem, right? I will show this to you when the time comes, right? I will remember this example and I will show this to you.
But now what I'm trying to tell you is the things which seemed impossible manually were solved by what?
It was solved by computers.
The distribution of this is like this.
Can you figure it out yourself?
No, right?
We cannot, isn't it?
We cannot do that.
So this kind of approximation will be given by what?
It will be only given by machines, right?
And this is people what data science is all about, right? It is what computer science did inside data science, right? I hope this is clear.
I'm assuming a lot of you will be going for interviews and everything after these course, right? So this will be a very, very important thing for you to know, right?
Often it is asked why data science is having computer science in it, right? The reason is this.
Okay.
So this is the role of computer science inside data science.
Now, people, the third thing, the third circle, which is one of the most
parts, is
maths
and stats,
right?
Mathematics, statistics, which was optimization.
Right? Optimization of your models, right.
Design
of model.
Right now, guys, if you look carefully, if you look carefully, in order to approximate this, what will you be playing with?
You will be playing with a lot of data.
You will be playing with a lot of mathematical tools, mathematical concepts, and statistical concepts, isn't it?
How did you what do you call this? This is maths, right?
This is statistics and mathematics.
Finding mean, median, mode, standard deviations, probability, statistics, all these will lead to this kind of result,
isn't it?
So this becomes the third wheel of this particular uh of this particular diagram, and this point of intersection,
right?
The suite point of intersection is basically data science. So
yeah,
is particularly data science.
Right.
So now people, this point, okay, this point
is basically representing data engineering, right? Data engineering, right?
Data engineering is people the part of data science which enables us to capture the correct data, right?
How the data will flow, how the data will be stored, how the data will be clean, right?
All this is done by whom?
It is done by data engineering.
Just because, so am I right, guys? You will go for interviews, right? After this, and try to fetch yourself jobs in this domain, data science, AI, ML.
If my understanding is correct, is that the aim? Yes.
So now, guys, there will be three types of companies.
Or let's say to simplify it, let's say two types.
One is small
and the other one is big, right?
So, in a small organization, if you become a part of a small organization and you are the data scientist there, you can be involved in all of these things,
right? All of these things possible, right?
Your bosses and your management will expect you to construct all these flows, right?
No computer science, you should know maths and stats, and you should have the domain knowledge, and you will be asked to do all of this.
But if you are going to become a part of a big organization, usually all these roles are fragmented.
All of these roles are fragmented, right? There is a separate data infrastructure team, there's a step separate data governance team.
Now, guys, when you go on to collect the data, can you collect any sensitive data about is it possible?
Ethically, it's not right and legally also it's not right.
My question to you is who will look after this compliance?
Whose responsibility indeed it is to look after this compliance?
Data scientist.
So this is about fragmentation. If you are part of a big organization, this thing will be taken by someone else, right?
But if you are a part of a small organization, you will be no, you will be expected to do this all by yourself.
In if if you are part of a big organization, then do you think you need to have this domain knowledge?
The answer is no.
Why?
Because there will be a separate set of people who are called as what?
Who are called as business analyst.
Have you heard about this position, people?
Business analyst.
What is a business analyst role?
It is basically a technical translator, right?
Who knows technical, who knows domain.
And that person goes and talks to the client, talks to the client in a layman language, convert it into technical requirement coupled with the domain knowledge, and give you the document.
This is basically a medical engineering problem.
So we need this, this, this, this, this, and you need to fulfill this, this, this, this criteria.
But again, if you're part of a small organization, who needs to take care of that?
Who needs to make sure that you know everything about a domain?
Right? You yourself.
Right?
Then, people, this area
usually represents whom?
This area represents research.
And analysis.
Why?
Because they we have people who have domain knowledge and we have people who are knowledge of math stats.
Have you heard about a position called as actuary
in the world?
Actuarial science.
For example, finance domain, right?
Finance is all about numbers.
So there we go, actuarial science, and we have math stats, optimization, model development, all of those things happening there.
We are also at a at this point of time, people belonging to which section research and data analysis, right?
And then people, there is a third intersection, right? There is a third,
the third intersection, which is this part, and this people is called as machine learning.
Right? Machine learning. Why machine learning?
If you can combine the power of maths, stats,
right? And you can combine the power of computer science, you will find yourself to be in a position where you can call yourself a machine learning engineer.
Right?
How does a machine learning engineer become a data scientist?
When they couple it up with the domain expertise, right?
So in this course, people, in this course, we will teach you computer science, we will teach you a little bit about math stats, but what we cannot teach you is domain knowledge.
Yeah?
And making the base of what we are about to do very, very important to understand.
Right? If you understand this, then half the battle is won.
Right?
So now to answer the question which was posted earlier, uh answer to the question which was posted earlier, there are different things in the world of data science,
right?
So you can pick and choose anything or you can do everything by yourself.
If you guys are engineers, then I think you can be at this sweet spot going forward in life if you choose a domain for yourself.
For example, you choose to be a part of the automobile industry, you choose to be a part of medical industry, you choose to be a part of, say, retail industry,
you choose to be a part of the aeronautics industry, right?
You choose to be a part of the finance industry, right?
So, whatever you will choose, this thing will get developed over time, right? This is the most difficult out of these three.
Try to give you the example, right?
My domain was agricultural industry, right?
The agri products.
I have worked extensively in agricultural industry, right?
So, again, for now, in my current role, this is something which I don't have.
I have this expertise, I have this expertise.
So, the same will be with you, and you guys will develop this knowledge over the time.
Now, I will try to give you an example, right?
Elections to make you understand how data science can be used in one particular use case. Okay, maybe we can extend that to a lot of other use cases and examples, right?
Talking about election season, right? Talking about the election season, right?
We will we will try to understand how do we use data science because it is very extensively used in this data science, right
now.
Let me talk about the first phase.
Let's say this is pre-election phase.
Right.
Right, this is pre-election phase.
In this pre-election phase, what do you think will be the tasks which which an agency like election commission of India will be doing?
The first task can be that they will be
doing the voter
registration,
voter,
right? Voter registration and data management, isn't it?
Yeah, it will start with that.
And what will be the things inside this?
The first thing will be data collection.
Right? First thing will be data collection.
So you will collect the data from all the registered voters, right?
Maybe it can be their demographic information, where they live, what is their age, what is their gender, right?
What is their past polling behavior, have they turned out previously or not?
Right?
All these details we can collect.
Then can we also do data cleaning?
Because I have told you, right, that there can be a lot of redundancies.
Some person's name can appear twice, right?
Some people can be uh mismatched. Suppose, for example, we have learned this in Python Raghav.
Raghav.
Right. All these are what people.
This is belonging to the same name.
Right? This is me.
But for a computer, for a computer, how many Raghavs are there?
Different ones? All are different.
Right?
So, example like these, right? Some people might have died, they might not be existing anymore.
So, all this part will be taken care of where people?
In the data cleaning process, right? Removing the duplicates, updating the new addresses, right?
Correcting the information about every voter, all those things, right?
And now, lastly, we can also include a flavor of data analytics.
Right? What will data analytics include in this?
We can analyze the demographic data to identify eligible voters, isn't it?
Yeah, people.
Till now we haven't understood this.
Why it is not automated?
How will you pick up all the how will you pick up all the details and nuances?
Suppose you are filling a form, right? By mistake, you have suppose you are 25 years of age.
Suppose you have written 250.
So does that mean I remove this?
I remove this entry of yours?
Because by mistake, you have written your age as 250.
Is age 250 possible in our current world?
Never, right?
So I will have to tell the machine that because this is a mistake, please convert it to 225.
Isn't it?
This is called as imputation.
So this is mostly a manual task, not manual, but you have to understand the problem manually and then code it on
computer.
Suppose someone has written their state
as
E D
L H I, right?
And country
as I D I N, right? So what is this state referring to? What is this country referring to?
We humans are very smart.
India, right? We can say this is India.
And if this is India, then what is this pointing out to
Delhi?
Just because you said and it's a it's a leading question. I wanted to explain this.
Tell me, is it possible to do this automatically?
No, right?
We have to employ manual rules, right?
We have to tell because we who's more intelligent?
Humans or machines?
Humans, right?
Machines are just more optimized, right? So we know through human intelligence that this is pointing to Delhi and this is not EDLHI.
So this is data cleaning, right?
Lastly, we have data analytics.
So do you think people, based on these data points, we can understand that who are the eligible voters
and maybe who are not registered yet, maybe who have not voted in the past.
Can we do all those analytics
and reach out to those peoples
and persons?
That's the first part.
This is just the first part, pre-election phase.
Now, moving on to the second part, right?
Moving on to the second part.
Let's say uh we say public
opinion
regarding the polling, right?
The polling which is about to happen.
The first thing will be you want to collect information about people, right?
So can can you go out and reach all 1.8 billion people in this country?
That what is their likable vote
for which party?
Is it possible?
1.8 billion.
Do you think it's possible for 1 billion?
Do you think it's possible for 500 million?
Do you think it's possible for 100 million?
No, right?
So basically, I'm talking about what I have something which is called as a population.
Right?
And if I have to study about this population, which is 1.8 billion people, which is impossible, which you just said, what do I need to do? Should I stop my process?
No, right?
I will go and collect something which is called a sample.
Right?
We always work in samples, right?
Suppose someone says that a Coca-Cola bottle does not contain 500 ml of liquid, which it claims,
right?
Suppose someone has put this allegation. Possible that Coca-Cola bottles do not have
500 ml liquid which they promise.
Now there are two ways to deal with this.
Right? There are two ways to deal with this.
Either I go and collect all the bottles of Coca-Cola in the world.
Possible?
Never right.
So what will I do? I will go and pick up a handful of bottles.
Right?
Handful of bottles.
So what is that handful of bottles?
Those are called as samples.
One last thing.
Suppose someone says that because of an industry,
all the fishes of the lake are dying or they are infected.
Is it possible to go and collect and check all the fishes in the pond or lake?
No, right?
What will we do?
We will collect again a handful of fishes and we will test them.
Right?
Again, samples.
Now, how does the raw data collected?
Raw data hasn't.
I hope you understand this.
This is no more about population.
With this step being told, now you're dealing with samples.
So now do you want to ask me how is sample created?
Yeah.
Now I'm coming to that.
Now, guys, there are a lot of second point is
how to sample.
Right? How to sample.
Right?
So we have sampling techniques, people. One is called as probabilistic, and one is called as non-probabilistic.
I will not go in detail right now. I just want to tell you an overview.
Probabilistic is suppose uh you are manufacturing t-shirts, right? You are manufacturing t-shirts, right?
And suppose you created
100 lots
of
thousand t-shirts,
right? So this is box one, box two, box three, box four, up to up to hundred, right? Hundred boxes.
And in each box, how many t-shirts are there?
Thousand, right?
Now, suppose you are a quality inspector.
You are a quality inspector.
Is it possible you for you to go over all the hundred lots with all checking all the thousand t-shirts one by one?
No, right? What will you do?
You will sample again. You will sample.
Now, the most common way of sampling these kind of problems is probabilistic sampling.
What is probability? What is the probability of getting heads or tails when you spin the when you flip the coin?
Equally likely, one by two and one by two.
What is the probability of getting one, two, three, four, five, six on a roll of a dice?
One by six.
Now, what is the probability of picking any t-shirt from this first lot out of thousand t-shirts?
One by thousand.
Yes? So do you think all the t-shirts have equally probable equal probability of being picked up without any bias?
If you decide to draw five t-shirts, right, from each of this box, right? And suppose say two are defective and three are not defective.
What will you do? Will you accept the lot or reject the lot?
We have majority of t-shirts of non-defective.
Or let's say we will reject the lot. We will reject the lot.
We will reject the lot.
Let's say we will reject the lot.
Okay.
Though this is basically subjective as per the company policies.
But let's say we reject it. Now,
people, my question to you is what if this entire batch had only two defected t-shirts?
But now what will happen?
The entire batch will be rejected.
Yes.
Let's say you sampled one t-shirt.
Let's let's change the use case.
I say you sampled only one t-shirt and that t-shirt was defected.
Now you will reject the batch.
And that is equally likely case.
So this is called as probabilistic sampling, people.
And there is no way you can go back.
There is no way. You cannot say that, hey sir, please uh allow this batch to pass because there is a chance that the rest of the t shirts are not defective.
No, it is not the way that happens, it happens randomly.
So, right, this is called as random sampling.
Right, random sampling.
Now, suppose you are doing a cancer research, right? You're doing a cancer research.
Right.
So, for your cancer research people, what kind of people will you need?
People who had had cancer in the past, isn't it?
To know more about their problem, to know more about their medical condition.
So, is it possible, people, that in this use case you can go and pick up any person from the population
and ask them questions?
No, right?
That is not possible.
So now is the probability equally likely or it has changed when you pick the sample.
It has changed.
Now there is a bias which is introduced that you only want people who had cancer, right?
So that kind of sampling people is called as non-probabilistic sampling.
Right?
Non-probabilistic sampling.
Clear?
Now, sampling technique.
Right now, third thing in this same scheme can be people what it can be the data collection,
right? Data collection mode,
right? That how do you collect the data?
You can float a survey
on
say internet.
You can go and stand outside a mall
or office.
Isn't it? How will you how will you you can probably interview someone?
Right? Interview someone, right? You can have a group discussion.
Yeah, all these techniques.
Yes, no, maybe, right? In the same part, public opinion polling, right now, guys.
Uh, so this was a brief introduction, right?
And this can be extended to any industry, right?
As of now, you can have example in the medical science,
right? You can have an example in automobile,
right? You can have an example in retail,
right?
Right.
Then you can have example in manufacturing,
right?
You can have example in education,
You can have example in sports,
right? IPL analysis, cricket analysis, all these sports analysis, right?
These are the most famous domains, right? They are the most famous domains.
They are not topics, they are domains, right? In which data science is used extensively. So I'm just gonna check, guys.
In automobiles, there's a biggest example, self-driving cars.
Yeah,
autonomous driving.
How do you think that's possible?
Data science again,
like Tesla.
Absolutely.
Tesla is level three.
We have five levels.
Level three is narrow AI, level four is AGI, and level five is super AI.
We are going to move first, right, with the
technical aspect, right? With the technical aspect in our data science course, right?
Right, which is based on Python,
right, because that is our base language, which we have learned so far, right?
So in Python people, we will start and cover four of the packages
right now.
And as we move on to machine learning and other uh deep learning and everything, you will explore more and more packages.
The first package we have to cover will be numpy.
Right. I'll explain you in detail what numpy is, then we will cover pandas.
Then we will cover matplotlib.
And then finally, we will cover something called as c bond.
Right, we will cover something called as c bond.
So these four packages inherently we have to cover in Python
to make sure we are able to reduce
the time
encoding.
Right, we are able to reduce the time encoding, and using these packages immediately help us in getting the desired results. Right. I hope you all remember the concept of modules.
We have covered in Python.
Do you all remember functions and modules?
You can use Jupyter Notebook.
If your Jupyter notebook is not installed, you can use something which is called as Google Colab.
Right? Go to Google, type
Right? Let's say you write collab.
Right. And then you will see this option.
Click on Google Colab and it will allow you to code in Python.
Right?
So we are now going to discuss about the numpy package in Python.
Okay, numpy package in Python.
So numpy is a
fundamental
package
for
data science
in
Python.
Right? It is one of the most fundamental packages for
practicing data science in Python.
Right.
Why is that?
Why so why is numpy so fundamental? What is so special?
Numpy package
gives us
a new data type
for handling
data
in Python
called as
nd
arrays.
right?
Nd arrays, which stands for
this stands for
arrays, right? N-dimensional arrays, right? This stands for n-dimensional arrays.
So till now,
till now we have studied
about
list,
integer
tuples,
strings,
right?
Out of which,
out of which
the data types,
such as list
pupils,
have been used to store data.
Store data, right?
And
range
used for
generating
new data, which is primarily sequential,
Now there is one now there is one problem, right? There is one problem, and there should be a question that
there should be a
question.
Why do we need a new
data type
to work
with data science?
Right?
Why do we need this? Yep.
So the answer to this question, people, the answer to this question uh lies in a small explanation, right?
Yep.
Lies in a small explanation, which is that
Python
is a
high
level
Python is a high level language, right?
And
A high level language
is usually
very
distant
from
hardware.
A high level language is close to hardware or distant from the hardware?
Did you not attend the Python programming essentials?
What is the type of programming language which is closest to hardware?
A low level language?
If this is my hardware,
yeah.
This is my OS.
This is my application layer, right? So hard level language, high-level languages here, and low level languages here, right? Which is closest.
So binary languages,
assembly languages,
right?
All these are closest to the hardware.
Because where is the processing happening? Where is the processing happening of the data?
At the hardware?
Isn't it?
Processing of data
is happening
at hardware.
No worry. Actually, it is happening at hardware, right? What is processing?
Processing is signals of zeros and ones, right?
What are zeros and ones? These are electric signals.
These are the electric signals, right?
Which is basically on and off,
right? And it is communicated to the hardware through the help of resistors
and microprocessors.
Right?
Isn't it right? Why a computer only knows zeros and ones?
Because zero is off and one is on, which is the electric current.
Right?
Electric current to activate or deactivate certain things, right? True and false gates.
Right? So it is happening in hardware.
So now, people,
if you understand this part, then try to logically connect it to what I'm going to say.
When you are studying data science,
what kind of data will you be dealing with?
Big data.
Right? And as the name suggests, it will have a lot of volume.
Right?
It will have a lot of volume, other than a lot of other things, right?
It will be very, very big.
And on this large volume of data, you will be doing processing.
You will be doing processing.
What does processing mean?
What does processing means? Operations.
So where is this operation happening? This is happening in hardware.
And for hardware, which is the closest language to hardware?
A low-level language.
But now, people, but now we have a situation in front of us.
What is the situation?
That what are we trying to do beta science with?
What are we trying to do data science with
Python?
Right?
And Python is what?
A high level language,
isn't it?
Yeah.
So there's a discrepancy.
Yeah, a big one.
Because hard level, a high level language, these
are
slow
Right, these are very slow in processing.
Right?
So, for these kind of languages to handle this kind of data and these kind of operations,
yeah, is very difficult.
Right.
So let's let's keep let's keep this part aside if you understand this.
Now let's go to the second point.
Right,
when you learned Python
on a scale of 1 to 10, how easy was it?
The ease of use of Python?
It's relatively a higher number, right?
Relatively a higher number.
So now guys, when I talk about data science, right? When I talk about
data science, okay,
right? When I talk about data science,
my thing is that this will be used by masses,
right?
Will be used by masses, a lot of people, managers, programmers, business analysts, data analysts,
possible, right?
Who are from non-technical background, who don't know coding, they also can do data science because data science is a general thing, isn't it?
Understanding the data, it should not be limited by your capability to understand the uh technicalities of a very complex language.
So for these people, which language is suitable?
Which is Python, right?
It is easiest to understand, it's a high-level language, almost like English.
Yeah.
So Python is a simple language. So in this part, people, Python fits the bill, right? Which is a bigger thing.
In the second part, when we talk about the operations,
when you talk about the operations,
in this part, there is a problem, right?
Python fails,
right?
right? Because it's a high-level language.
We said that okay, there is a language called as C, right? Which is a middle level language.
Right?
And C language people is used to create OS operating systems, it is used to create networks,
networking applications,
it is used to create games,
right?
All the things which are close to hardware,
C is used, right?
So C fits this bill, right?
C fits this bill.
said that okay, if C fits the bill, and Python is written
in C, written on C, right? It's written on top of C language.
Now what happened was Python said, okay, if my intrinsic data types, my intrinsic processing is not suitable for data science,
but my high-level nature is let's do one thing.
Let's take C language and use its power, right? Use its power that it is very close to hardware, and let's create a new data type, right?
Let's create a new data type
which is written on top of C and which can integrate with Python seamlessly.
And people, this new data type
was called as array.
And this was given to you by something called as numpy package, right? Numpy package.
It defined a new data type which was array, and along with defining the array, it gave various operations.
Right, it gave various operations
one could
perform
on
arrest.
Right, one could perform on arrests.
It's simple, right? Program the power of processing lied with C, right? It was lying with C.
So we developed a new data type using C on top of Python, and that new data type was called as array.
And this array was defined in a new module, which was called as numpy module, which told you how to create the arrays
and then how to manipulate those arrays
for doing data science.
We had options like Java, we had options like C,
right? We had options like uh photon to be used for data science, but we chose Python because of its simplicity and the simple syntaxes
that people from non-programming background could also use Python to do data science.
Right now, the limitation was that because it is slow, because of being high level, we needed something which could make it fast,
and that was using an external data type which is not internal to Python, and that was array.
And this array is defined inside a new uh module or a library called as numpy, which is
numerical python, right? Numerical Python
back to the programming, right, where we have understood right about this question, right?
So,
NumPy
essentially is
based on top of
C
language, which is
compatible
with Python.
It leverages the power of closeness of C
with hardware,
right?
C with hardware,
which eventually
makes the processing
faster than
Python, right?
So this is what the first part is, right? This is what a first part is, right?
Now the second thing is people, so this is about the performance bit, right? These are the performance bit.
The above
is about
the
performance
of
it, right now coming to the next part, which is the memory
efficiency, right? Memory efficiency,
right?
So,
arrays created
by
numpy
in
python
are
less memory
exhaustive
than lists in Python.
And I will prove these points later on to you through code, right?
In list, right? In list,
each item is
an object, right? Each item is an object, right? I hope you remember this, guys.
Each item is an object, right?
And it holds, right? It holds
meta information
like
references
and types,
right, etc.
Right. A lot of information it holds, right?
This
makes
list
consume
more
memory, right?
But but
arrays in
numpy
are contiguous.
Which means
that
they do not
create objects,
but rather
directly store
the data
continuous
memory
blocks,
one after
another, right?
Also, the arrays are homogeneous in nature, right? You can only store the homogeneous data in array, unlike lists.
In list you could store different data types, right? But in arrays you cannot, right?
You have to store the same kind of data in the array, homogeneous.
So it's a contiguous memory block, which is meaning that you can store data in continuity, right? One after another in the memory block.
So the access is faster, the memory location and the memory efficiency is very higher, right? As compared to the native data type like lists or tuples in Python.
Arrays
are basically
right? I'll talk to about talk about to you with vectors. What are vectors, right? They are the vectorized operations, and they are way more convenient
to deal with
as compared to list
in python, right? In list you have to go through a lot of loops, right? We saw that you have to go through the list comprehension, but you will see in Python pandas, sorry in Python numpy,
the vectorized operations are very, very simple, right? They are very, very simple, right?
Again, for all this, I will give you examples, but uh it will take some time
because you have to understand what arrays are first, right?
Okay,
then
the most important
other packages,
which are
pandas,
matplotlib,
cbond,
sklearn, psypy.
all are written
on top
of
numpy
package.
That's the reason.
For this reason,
it's called as
fundamental
package.
All the other packages which make your life easier as a data scientist, where you don't have to worry about code.
All these packages
make our
data science
journey smooth
because
we have to worry
less about code and more about
logic.
Yes?
So for these understand for the understanding of these packages, it's very important that we understand numpy first and then we move forward.
Right
now,
then let's get started.
So the first step, right? The first step which you have to uh see, right? The first step which you have to see while using numpy package is basically from where will you import the package, right?
From where you will you import the package.
So to import
the
package, numpy, we write import
numpy as np, right?
Where np
is an alias, right? It's an alias.
Right?
So please do this import numpy as np.
Right.
If you don't get any result for this, then you can write pip install numpy, right? Pip install numpy and just execute this,
When you will execute this, it will give you this message, or it will give you, it will download this package for you, right?
Pip stands for
python
index
package,
right?
It is basically like Play Store,
App Store,
right?
Or Windows Store
for Python,
right?
So you are just going to these Play Store
Windows Store App Store of your Python and asking them to download this for you, right?
It is also called as the
package manager,
right? Pip.
If it is done, you can also check the version.
You can say np dot underscore underscore version underscore underscore and it will give you the version of numpy.
Right.
Numpy is an open source
package.
Right?
Yeah, that's about it.
Yeah, it's an open source package, people.
Right?
Open source package.
And if you want to see the code,
you can go to GitHub.
Go to Google, write
the uh code for numpy.
It will show you it on GitHub.
Right?
Done.
So let's say I okay.
So I say
we have when we so okay.
Before this, let me come to a little bit of theory before I do this with you.
So now, guys, I said that numpy
has arrays
as
data type,
right?
And this is written on C, which runs directly
on hardware.
Also, this numpy array
is basically a vector.
Right? It's basically a vector.
Now, what is a vector, people?
What is a vector?
A vector is a
quantity which has sine
plus magnitude.
Right? It has a sine and magnitude.
If I say this is a Cartesian space, this is I, this is j, and I say this, this is
3i
and 4j, right?
3i cat, 4j cat.
So this is a vector, right?
And this is the direction,
guys.
If you have studied elementary maths,
you would know this.
Yes, people.
This is a vector.
If I draw another like this,
then this is another vector.
So I will call this say
uh 2i and 5j.
Yep, this is another vector, and this is the theta,
right? This is the direction.
This is the direction, and what is the magnitude?
3i 3 square plus 4 square, which is 9 plus 16, which is 25 under root, which is 5.
So the magnitude of vector is 5 and direction is equal to theta.
This is a vector quantity.
Now,
what is this?
What is this?
This is a scalar.
This is a scalar, yeah, only magnitude,
isn't it?
This is scalar, only magnitude, and then I have 2,3.
Right?
This is what
this is a vector.
It has two dimensions
or one dimension,
only one dimension,
right?
This is one dimension vector.
Yep, one dimension vector.
Now, if I say this two, three, four, five.
What is this called?
This is called a matrix.
Right? This is called a matrix, which is what collection of vectors
and this collection of vectors matrix is called as two-dimensional, right? It is called as two-dimensional.
Now, if you have this,
so these are stacked behind each other.
This is one, this is two, this is three, right?
So we have three layers
in matrix.
So, how many dimensions will be this people?
One dimension, two dimension, and three dimension.
This is a three-dimension matrix,
right? Or three-dimension vector
or three-dimension array.
I'll repeat once again.
What is a single value?
A single value is called as a scalar, right? It only has magnitude.
Now, when you have multiple values, right?
This is called as a vector. It has a direction, it has a magnitude, and this is single dimension.
Now, multiple
vectors, right? Like this, or maybe you can say like this, right?
Are you understanding why I'm calling it one dimension? It can be either this dimension or it can be this dimension.
In any dimension, you stack two vectors, you will get yourself a matrix.
Right? You will get yourself a matrix, which is now two dimensions.
It has rows
and it has columns.
Right
now, if you stack multiple such matrix one after another, right?
This becomes a three-dimensional matrix.
And this can go up to how many dimensions, people?
How many dimensions can this go up to?
It can go up to
this,
can
go
up to n dimensions,
right? N dimensions,
right?
So now do we get it? Why do we call it n d
arrays?
Yeah, n dimension arrays.
Right. That why are we calling something water?
Right? N dimension arrays.
We are only capable of viewing three dimensions, people.
It can go up to hundred dimensions, five hundred dimensions, thousand dimensions, any dimensions.
Scalars are least important.
Vectors are more important.
So now
we have
multiple
dimensions in
arrays,
namely 0D,
1D,
2D,
3D, and so on. till the N D, right? N D arrays.
Right now, let's create our first array.
Right, let's create our first array.
And this will be a zero
dimension
Right? Zero dimension array.
How will you create this?
You will say arr0
is equal to np.array.
And you will mention what a scalar value is.
What is a scalar value?
It is a simple value.
I say 2, right? np.array equal to 2.
And when you will now check or print the type of
arr0, it will tell you class numpy nd array.
Right?
It is a zero dimension array.
And if you want to check
the dimension,
you just have to write arr0.ndim.
Right. And it shows you that there is zero dimensions present.
So what is this in short?
This
is a scalar.
I have entered a single value, people, 2, 200, 500, whatever you want to enter.
And the syntax is np.array.
np.array.
You are instructing numpy package to fetch the function array on method array and convert this into that particular
data type.
Right? Array zero.
And when you check the type, type is nd array, but what is the dimension of this nd array? This is zero, which is nothing but a scalar.
Right?
We have created this.
This is what we have created.
Right.
Now guys,
if I created this list, right?
Say LIS is equal to.
Yeah.
So this was this was a list, right? This was a list, and this was this is what people, what is this that we have
just studied according to that? What dimension is this list?
So what I'm trying to do is
I will create a
1D
array with a or let's say from a list.
Right?
Let's let me show you how do we do that.
Okay.
So I say
hurry, read the error.
Name arr not defined. Why?
Because you have created array from AAR0.
Come on, hurry.
Right?
I will create a one-dimensional array. How will I do that?
People, I will say arr1 is equal to np dot array.
And can I pass 1D list inside this?
Or can I say I can pass L I S inside this?
When I do this, people now see what will happen.
Arr1
will be equal to this, right? And if you say, let me say print
arr1,
it will be like this.
Okay.
This is your
arr1 dot in dim.
You will see that it gives you one.
Right. This is a one dimension array.
Right? One dimension array.
Yes, so for example,
when I say
right? When I say scalar, I say
thirty-five, right?
When I say vector
one D, I say
uh
so these are suppose my marks,
right? Now I say thirty-five,
forty,
fifty, right?
So now what are these?
My marks in
Yeah, marks in three subjects.
This is my say Hindi, this is English, and this is maths, right? Or let's say science,
because not everyone has Hindi.
Science, English, and maths, right, guys?
Now, if I have to create a matrix
of two dimensions, what will I write?
So that means this is one student.
This is one student, people,
isn't it, guys?
Yes, no, maybe.
So now in matrix, we will have what?
We will have multiple students.
Yes, no, maybe.
In a matrix, people will have multiple students.
Suppose this was S1. Now you will have S1, S2, S3, S4, like this,
and each student will have their own individual list of marks.
So, can I say that I'm making a nested list?
Can I say that, people?
I'm making a nested list.
So now let's make it okay.
Nested list.
Okay, a nested list.
So I'll say arr2 is equal to np dot arra list. I will have to create a list first.
LIS2 is equal to.
So this is my first bracket.
What is this bracket representing? This bigger bracket.
Now I will put another bracket inside this and I will write 112233.
I'll put a comma again, right? A comma.
Then I will say
44566, comma
seven, seven, eight, eight, nine, nine.
Right?
I'll do this
right now. I will say list should
when you will do this, you will see that an array like this has been created.
Right.
Like this ARR2.
Right?
This has been created.
When we check the dimension, it is two-dimension array.
Right?
Yep.
Marks of three different students in three different subjects.
And this is the same technique you can create a three-dimension array. How will you create a three-dimension array, people?
If I go here, how will you create a three-dimensional array now?
Now, suppose I have data in this, and this is my master list.
Okay, this is my master list.
In this, I have data,
and this can be represented like this.
This is my
first matrix, isn't it?
And this is the vector inside this
v1, v2, v3.
Then this can be called as M1.
And now to create a three-dimension setup, how many M1s do you need?
You need multiple M1s,
isn't it?
You need M1, M2, M3, multiple matrix,
like this, people,
like this,
matrix one, matrix two, matrix three.
So what will you do?
You will have, you will have what people?
You will have another yellow.
Right?
And you will have inside this yellow
multiple purples.
Isn't it
right?
Again, like this.
Yeah,
like this, you will have it, people.
So, can I say, people, can I say that as I am increasing the dimensions, as I am
increasing
the dimensions,
I am putting 1D.
sorry, zero D, right? And okay, again in this V1, in this V1, do you think you will have multiple scalars, people?
Can I say that?
Can I say multiple scalars create a vector?
Multiple vectors create a matrix, and multiple matrix create one three-dimensional matrix.
Can I say that?
Let me talk to you about an image, right?
Image, right?
What is an image made up of people?
What is an image made up of?
Pixels?
Yes or no?
No,
not frames.
Frames is basically videos.
Pixels are creating an image, right? So we have how many pixels here? One, two, one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten, eleven, twelve, thirteen, fourteen, fifteen, sixteen.
Right?
Suppose
this is one vector, right? This is one vector.
And this is one scalar.
Right? Scalar one, scalar two, scalar three, scalar four.
And this will make vector v1.
This is v2, v3, v4.
And together, together, can I call this
M1 and call this blue?
So for a colored image, how many channels are there, people?
How many channels are there? What do we call it?
We call it the image as
RGB,
RGB image.
That means red,
green,
blue.
So this is blue part.
So similarly, you will have a red part in front of it.
Then you will have a green part.
And then finally, you will have a blue part.
Yeah?
Are you understanding, guys?
Why do we require three-dimensional arrays?
Yes.
Suppose now you want to make a change at this pixel.
So you will go to the third layer, which is the blue layer.
Then you will go to the third column, which you will go to the third column and third row.
And this is how you will reach this pixel, everyone?
Yes, no, maybe.
Yes.
So this is the reason why we need to create a 3D array.
Right?
Right? To ingest information like this.
So we can create a 3D array also.
Right. And how did I tell you how many brackets will I have? Squared brackets?
I will have three squared brackets. So now this is just one student.
Right.
Now I'll put a comma here.
Right. I'll put a comma here.
And I will start.
Right. I'll do this.
I'll say this list three.
Air three.
List three.
Right. And now you will see that there is a three-dimensional array.
Right, guys?
Right, this is a three-dimensional
array.
Yep.
Moving on.
There are multiple ways
to create arrays, right?
The first one we have done.
We have done
from lists.
From list we have done.
Then second will be
from uh we can create a zero array.
Right.
We can create
ones array.
Right.
Then we can create custom array.
I will show this all to you.
Right. I'll show this all to you.
So let's start with the ones array.
Sorry, zeros array.
Right. What do you have to do?
You have to write, so let's say zero underscore arr0. Okay, a zero dimension, zero array.
So you say np dot zeros,
right?
And you create
a two.
Right.
A two.
And if I say
uh zero
dot n dim,
right? You will see it is a one-dimension array,
right? It is a one-dimension array.
Right? So two is by default taken as.
So let me just show this to you.
It will look like this, right? It is taken as horizontal. What is the dimension of this, guys? A vector.
What is the dimension of this vector?
No, no, no. It's one.
It is basically two cross one, right?
Two, one.
Sorry, one, comma two.
My bad.
One, comma two.
Isn't it?
Now, what if you had to create a two cross one?
What if what if you had to create a two cross one?
Right?
So let me just show that to you.
So I say, wait.
Like this.
Okay.
Now when I do this, I say arr once
and I say here
two,
one.
Right? I say two,
Now you will see people what will happen to this.
Now,
because you have created right specified two dimensions, right? What will this be converted to now?
What will this be converted to?
This will be converted to
a
two-dimension vector.
By default, it was this, right? Which was this vector.
Right? By default, it was this vector.
Right? What is the dimension of this vector?
One cross how many values you put here, right? One cross two, like this.
So we call this only one dimension.
We call this only one dimension.
But now when I will run this one, you will see
yes, two cross one.
And now you will see this is
two dimensional, right? You see this is two dimensional.
Clear people, just the orientation has changed, but now you see the brackets. There are two brackets now.
Because what have you now instructed?
You have now instructed Python and rather uh numpy wire to create the vector as two cross one.
So you have said give me this zero and give me this zero here.
So the moment you do this, you are now specifying the rows and columns.
Now this two one, right?
Let's say this is two, one.
Now let me create a another two cross two dimension matrix for you.
Let me call this 10
comma 10. Right?
So, how many rows and columns will it have, people?
How many rows and columns will it have?
I will say 210.
It will have 10 rows and 10 columns, like this.
You saw this?
Yeah, 10 rows and 10 columns.
Right
by default, it is 1 cross 2, like this. It is a one-dimensional vector, and this is a two-dimensional vector.
What about a three-dimensional vector?
0.0 underscore uh arr three
is equal to np dot zeros, right? Np dot zeros,
right?
Should I just write three, comma, three, comma three?
And I should check for this.
Yeah.
You will have a three cross three vector three cross three matrix with three matrix stacked behind each other.
Right?
If I say four,
this will be four.
So how do we read this?
Number of layers,
number of rows, and number of columns.
So can you help me with a syntax?
Can you help me with a syntax which can create me a 3D matrix of five layers,
three rows and three columns?
What will I write?
Five layers, three rows and three columns.
Five, three, three.
Yeah, you'll get five layers, one, two, three, four, five.
Right?
Like this.
Suppose, suppose you have to represent
an image
with,
say,
RGB, channel
and,
uh, say, 256 and 256 pixels.
How will you create this?
So I'll say img right image is equal to np dot
zeros, and I will say inside this
three channel 256 cross 256.
Right?
And when you will just run this image, it will be like this,
right? It will be like this.
This is one channel,
this is two channel, and this is three channel.
And uh we understood that numpy wire is a fundamental package for data science in Python, right?
This package gives us a new data type to work with, which is called as n-dimensional arrays, right?
Now, what are arrays?
What are arrays?
Arrays are nothing but vectors, right, which are stored in a contiguous block of memory, which means they are stored continuously one after another,
and they do not get converted into the object, unlike the list, and they are way faster, they are more memory efficient than list.
I will prove this back to you today with the help of example through the help of code, right?
So, why numpy arrays?
Because numpy is a package which is built on top of C language, which is compatible with Python, and C being a middle level language,
interacts directly with the hardware.
So, whatever operation you run, in a fact that is getting directly executed on the hardware itself, right?
That is the reason why the uh performance is way better when we try to use the n-dimensional arrays.
Along with this, these syntaxes, the type of syntaxes we use to type uh in list.
I will show that to you also today with the help of example, are way simpler when you try to do them with nd arrays, right?
So arrays are basically vectorized operations, right?
And they're also very convenient to deal with as compared to lists and other native data types in Python, right?
And the most important part is that in our data science journey, whatever other packages we will use, right?
Again, what are packages? They have predefined things stored for you so that you can leverage them and focus less on code and more on logic, right?
You need to be aware about the logic more than the knowledge of the code, right?
So we have packages for that which contains uh methods inside them which you can use, and uh without any further calculations, you can work with them directly,
right.
So that is how we started with numpy, right? And the syntax to import numpy was import numpy as np, where np was an alias, right?
Uh you could do pip install numpy if someone did not have access to numpy. If numpy was not coming by default, you can use pip install numpy, which is python index package, right?
And uh this is like Play Store, App Store, Windows Store for Python.
All the packages are stored in pip, and you can call pip, you can ask pip to download that package for you so that you can use that.
Right? It's basically the package manager.
So and numpy is an open source, and if you want to see the code, you can go to GitHub and check the code out for yourself, right?
In numpy, we have n-dimensional arrays. Now the question arises, people, that why do we need numpy? Right? So, my answer to this particular question is that when you will deal in data science, right?
When you will become a data scientist, you will be dealing with data, right?
Now, my question is how will you ingest, how will you make the machine ingest the data, right?
There has to be a way, right?
For you to input the data to the machine, right?
To make manipulations to the data, to read the data.
So all this is started as the base package of numpy arrays, right?
Other than that, it becomes very difficult and cumbersome for us to deal with that.
And this provides us a lot of ease and flexibility to deal with such massive amounts of data, which you will see along with me as we will move forward in this particular course.
Yeah, perfect.
Now, people, let me just uh pull up the PPTs.
This is what we are discussing, people.
We start with something which is called as scalar, right?
We start with something which is called as scalar, which is a quantity which only has magnitude, right? In Namti Y language, this is also called as zero D, right? It is called as zero dimension.
Then people we have vector, right? And vector has a constant dimension, it has only one dimension, right?
You can interpret it as a row or you can interpret it as a column, it doesn't really matter because this is only one single dimension, right?
So usually it will be written as five, blank, right? There will be nothing written in front of it. So this in numpy terminology and nomenclature is called as one dimension,
right?
When you move on, then you get combined couple of vectors, you get a shape, and now that is called as a matrix.
And in numpy terminology, it is called as two-dimensional, right?
And when you try to stack multiple two-dimension matrices, one before we're one after each other or one before each other, then they become something called as three-dimensional.
And now in my capability, I don't know what four-dimensional looks like, but there is a high possibility that you have n-dimensional data, right? It has it has n we are dealing with n-dimension data,
Suppose with this, I also add time, right?
At t equal to one, at t equal to two. That will serve as the fourth dimension for this data. But how do we how does it look like?
I don't really know that, right? Because humans are only capable of visualizing 3D, three dimensions at max, right? So you can go to n dimensions and hence the name n dimensional arrays, right?
N D arrays.
Post this, right? Post this, we moved on to create certain things, and I tried to explain you the data, right?
So the data
will look to you like this, right? You might have a scalar quantity, which is marks, right? One marks, right now.
If I go on to vectors in one D, it can be marks of one student,
right? Marks of one student in science,
English,
and maths, right?
35,
40, and 50 out of say 50, right? Three subjects.
So this will be characterized as a vector, right?
What will be the dimension written for this?
It will be three, comma, nothing.
This will be zero, right?
Shape will be zero.
For this matrix, suppose we have one, two, three, four students, and each student will have
Right, each student will have three marks.
So, what will be the shape of this?
We have four rows and three columns, right? So, this will be the shape of this 2D matrix.
Right.
And now, if you stack images right one behind each other, then it will be like this, right?
RGB image. I gave you an example.
So this has four cross four pixels.
So the shape will be three cross four cross four.
Right?
This will be the shape for this particular 3D matrix.
Right, guys.
So this is how you input the data.
Just to tell you a little bit more, since generative AI is very popular these days, right?
So, what if I tell you the fact that the Chat GPT,
which you use or you might have used?
right, has
never seen
a single
word
in its lifetime?
Right?
All it sees
is numbers,
right? Only numbers. How do we see numbers? Suppose I say my
name
is
Raghav.
Raghav
is a
nice
name, right?
So these are two data, right?
These are two data points.
Now we all know that computers do not understand these, right? Computers do not understand these, right?
There is nothing, no understanding for computers to know what text is, right? It only knows zero and one. Yes, Darnica.
Right? It only knows zeros and ones. So see how we will convert this. So there is something called as vocabulary,
right?
So vocabulary are nothing but the unique words,
How many unique words do I have in this?
My name is Radha 4.
This is not unique, this is repeating, this is repeating five,
six, and this is repeating. So I have six words.
So now, guys, I will do something called as word to vec,
right? Where I will convert these words into vectors. How will I convert them? Look at this.
So I will have suppose this is S1,
this is S1, and this is S2.
Right?
So I will represent
S1 as
right.
I will have a vector
of
size 6.
How?
I will say 10000.
Right?
100. How many elements does it have? Six elements, right?
Name will be 01000.
Is will be 001000.
And Raghav will be 000100.
Right. This is S1. My name is Raghav.
Now when it comes to S2,
right? When it comes to S2, how will I enter this?
S2
000100. Raghav.
What is is here?
001000.
What is a 000010?
A
nice 000001 and name will be 010000.
Right now, this will be the vector representation of these two sentences.
Just to tell you a fact,
GPT 3, right? GPT 3 model,
right?
GPT 3 or GPT 3.5, they have vocabulary
of 30,000 words, right? 30,000 words, and each word, right?
Each word
has a
dimension
of
12,500
numbers, right? What do I mean? Suppose I say Raghav.
So it will be one word and it will be represented by five eleven thousand five hundred different numbers.
Right. And like Raghav, there will be 30,000 words in this GPT model.
Right.
30,000 words in this GPT model.
And this total number of parameters which get trained in the neural network, which we will learn later on, neural networks, they are almost close to
1.75 billion
Right? 1.75 billion parameters.
So why I'm telling you all this? Because to showcase to you that what is the importance of vectors, right? In the entire machine learning and data science.
Yeah, people.
So this is the reason, people. Now my question is how will you create these vectors?
How will you read these vectors?
Right?
The answer is through numpy package because it is the base package.
Clear people?
Yeah. I hope today's class will be uh interesting for you because you will know the context.
Why are we doing it?
Yeah. So I'll try to show that to you how we convert things to vectors.
Right?
Okay.
Let me go here now.
Right. Let me go here.
So people, uh, we started using numpy. So I started with the zero dimension arrays, right? Zero dimension arrays.
So zero dimension is nothing but a scalar.
So I created ARR0, which was np.array, and I entered a single word, single uh element inside this, which is nothing but a scalar,
and then I checked the type of uh ARR0 also, right? And then I check the dimension also.
So the answer was to class was numpy n d array, and the dimension was zero, right?
Exactly what I had mentioned in my PPP.
Right?
It will be having a zero dimension like this, right?
Same thing has been proven,
right?
Because it's a scalar.
Now coming on to one dimension, right? Coming on to one dimension, I create a list which is nothing but a one-dimensional data type.
Right now I create an array which is ARR1 from array from this particular list LIS and then I check the type of
print arr1, check the type of RR1 and the dimension, right? So when I execute,
right, then you will see that it was this numpy array and the dimension was one, right? Exactly like this.
So if I show you something else, say print
arr1 dot shape,
you will see it's four, comma, empty, right? And I show it to you here.
It will be empty, right?
Empty, and this will be comma one,
So this means that it has only four elements, right? If I increase these elements to say 55, 66, 77,
then it will become seven,
black, right? Which which means it has seven elements as a vector.
Now we create something with a nested list, right? Which is like this.
So with the nest, I want one bracket which is running outside, right? Then inside this, I have one, two, and three lists inside one list, right? So this is a nested list.
This is marks of first student, second student, and the third student, right?
So I do this, and you see it is
this, right?
And I will show you the shape also,
right? It will be three cross three, three rows and three columns, three rows and three columns, right?
Now, similarly, we can also create uh
3D matrix,
right,
with
levels, right? Level one and level two and three cross three.
So the shape will be what people can someone guess the shape?
What will be the shape of this?
I've shown you here.
Right?
If this is three, four, four, then what will be this?
Three rows and three columns, right?
So when you will execute, you will get two, three, three.
Right?
Two, three, three.
Right.
Right now, people, there are multiple ways, right? There are multiple ways to create arrays, and we should know them because all of these comes uh very, very handy.
Not right now.
I don't have enough context to give you right now, but later on you will see with me or with some other trainer that how these will be used in deep learning specifically, right?
They are the key of deep learning algorithms, right? Where we initialize some weights, we initialize some biases, and those initializations are nothing but multidimensional numpy arrays,
right?
Numpy arrays,
okay.
Right, for example,
suppose I have this.
I have to multiply this with some random numbers, right?
So, how will you generate these random numbers? You will generate them through numpy, and you can generate them in a specific kind of uh shape, right?
Which is 2 cross 3, and then you can multiply them, you can multiply the matrices, and you can get your output for yourself,
right?
So this is the way they are used.
So we saw the first thing from list we have already covered.
Then now we are moving on to creating zero arrays, right?
So I create a zero array of uh one dimension, right? Of one dimension, which is zero, zero. They are represented in floats, right? They are represented in floats zero dot zero, right?
Now you can create a two-dimensional zero array, right? You can create a two-dimensional zero array, which is you have to mention just the shape inside two cross one.
So it will have two rows and one columns, right? Two rows and one columns.
The difference here is the difference here is that these are one dimension and these are two dimensions, right? You have explicitly mentioned the rows and columns.
So you can expand this to 10 cross 10 also.
Right, you can expand in 10 cross 10 or 10 cross six, whatever you feel like yourself, right?
It will have 10 rows and six columns,
right?
Now you can also create
the 3D arrays, 3D zero arrays,
right?
Which is five, three, comma three. What does five means?
What does five means?
First element represents the number of layers, so you have five layers, right?
It's five layer deep.
Then you have three rows and three columns, right? So it will look something like this.
One
1,
2, 3, 4, 5.
Right? Like this.
Something like this.
Right? It will look like this.
Stat. One, two, three, one, two, three, one, two, three.
Right? Five, three, three.
Okay.
Yes, the number of matrices, hurry.
What I represented.
Right.
Layers,
rows,
Right. Layer, rows, and columns.
Clear.
So now when you execute this, you will get an arrangement like this.
Okay.
I try to show you this thing with another example, right? Which is I created an image of an RGD image of 256 cross 256 pixels, right? Which have all zeros inside them.
And this is how it was created.
Right. Three layers RGD 256256.
So this is how the image will look like.
Right.
This is how it will look like.
Now you can also create
arrays with ones.
Right. Exactly the same way. You created it with zeros. I'll give it to you. I'll give you five minutes time to create them. I'll show you one.
So I say
a1 is equal to np dot
ones.
And inside I pass
two.
I check a1. So this is an
Right? It is an array like this.
Now you create
create two dimension
and
three dimension
arrays of one.
It is basically
as a float.
It's represented as a floater, right? It's represented as a floater.
Okay.
Right.
Perfect.
Also, guys, uh, with this, right? Also, with this, you can create the custom arrays, right? You can create the custom arrays, right?
How do we create custom arrays, people?
How do we create the custom arrays?
You have created now zeros.
You have created now ones.
Now, what is left
that you create the custom arrays?
Uh forget about this.
I will come to this later on.
Right?
Let's create
custom arrays, right?
So the syntax remains the same, right? I say cus underscore arr is equal to
np dot full, right? This is the syntax, np dot full, right? And you will say six plus six, and suppose you want an array of all fours, right?
This is the dimension six plus six, and this value after comma is basically the value which you want.
You execute this and you copy this, paste this, and you will get the arrays of fours for yourself,
right? If you want of 10, you will get of 10.
If you want 10.3, you will get 10.3, right? Anything which you want.
If you want case, you will get case, right?
All the examples.
So let me just show that to you.
Yep, like this.
Now guys, how did we create
or how did we use
range in Python?
Can you use
range to generate
numbers between 20 to 50?
Right? 20 to 50.
Can you give me the syntax quickly?
How did you do that in range?
How do we do that?
We said r is equal to
range
20 to 51, right?
And then I said
I in R
print I.
Right. And this is how I got the numbers, right?
So similar
to range in Python,
we have
a range in numpy one.
Right. How do we use a range? I say
uh
underscore arr is equal to np dot a range, right? And then same syntax, I will say 20 to 51, right? 20 to 51, and that's it. And when I will check my arr
range arr, you will see I have generated myself numbers between 20 to 50 and a range in numpy.
Right?
A range in numpy.
Yes, if you want an interval, so you can use this,
say a range one, and after comma, you pass the third argument. Suppose it's three.
So now it will jump
three times, right?
20, 23, 26, 29, 32, 35, like this, up till 50.
Now, guys, there is something which is called as lint space.
Right, what is lint space?
It stands
for
linear spacing,
which means
between two given numbers.
this function
will fit the required number of
numbers.
right?
For example,
suppose, for example,
we need to create
an interval
from
0 to 1.
People, there are infinite numbers I can have between 0 to 1, isn't it?
Infinite numbers I can have between 0 to 1.
0.000000000001.0000010101.
Right? I can go in the infinite manner, right now. For example,
you need to create numbers between 0 to 10, right? And you want to create and want to have
10 numbers in it, right? So how will you do this?
It's not float, it's about the number theory, right? Between 0 and 1, you have infinite numbers,
right? So you say length space is equal to
np dot lint space, right? np dot lens space.
You mentioned from 0 to 10, you want to have 10 numbers, right? And when you will create length space,
you will see that these are the numbers are there which have been created, right?
These are the numbers which have been created.
Right?
Nine numbers.
Now I say 100 numbers. I want evenly spaced 100 numbers, right? Evenly spaced 100 numbers.
How are they even?
You can simply subtract one number from another, and the difference for all the numbers will be exactly the same.
Subtract any two numbers, it will be 0.010101.
Right? Where do we need this?
We need this to plot the accesses, right? When you will plot graphs, you will need access between this interval. You need five values that works like this.
Okay.
Suppose you want from 0 to 10 five different values, right?
You will have five different values like this, right?
Between the gap of 0.5.
Right? If I say 1 to 10,
you will have values like this.
Right, like this.
Clear 100 values like this.
Yeah?
Clear guys, how do we use length space?
Suppose you want from 0 to 10, interval from 0 to 10, and 10 will be included. 0 will not be included.
Right? We'll start from
1. So I go to 1, it will be from
1. Why is 0 not included then?
Yeah, 0 is included.
Right? 0 is also included and 10 is also included.
100 numbers between them. Right?
Clear? This is what lens spaces.
Now guys,
now
suppose you
Logeshwaran lint space is basically used
if you want to create n numbers between the range of numbers, right?
Between 0 to 1, right? Suppose between 0 to 1, you are trying to plot a graph.
Okay, and your values are 0.2, 0.3, 0.6, right?
And you want to draw a graph.
So you will have to mark the axis, right? The x-axis and the y-axis.
So you can use length space there.
And what will it do? It will take the range, it will take the interval in between you want to add the equal space numbers.
And then the third argument here will be that how many numbers do you want between them?
So this syntax tells you that
from
0 to 1
give me 100 numbers.
How are these numbers?
Equally
spaced
Equally spaced numbers.
So when you will execute this, you will see that all there are 100 numbers which have been generated, right? 100 numbers.
And all the numbers are equidistant from each other because difference of every single number from the next number is 0.010101.
Yep.
That's what it does.
Right now, guys, now suppose we want to
generate random numbers, right? You want to generate random numbers, right? Now we are interested in generating random numbers.
So we have something called as random
dot random, right?
What will it do?
Random dot random will generate
random
float numbers
Random float numbers between zero to one.
How will this happen?
You will say
rand underscore rand is equal to np dot random dot random and inside you will mention what is the dimension that you seek.
Suppose I want six cross six.
So when you will check this, you will have all numbers for six cross six dimension, right?
Six cross six matrix.
Right now, every time you rerun this, the numbers will change because all of these are random numbers.
Right? All of these are random numbers.
Now I say hundred multiplied by rand underscore rand.
You will see all of them, all these numbers will be multiplied by 100.
Right? All of them
in one shot.
Now just like this,
we can also create
random integers, right?
How will we create random integers, guys?
I say rand int underscore rand int is equal to np dot random dot rand
int.
Right.
And here you will specify that what is the range of numbers you want from. So I say between 20 to 25.
I need random numbers and then I want it from in a 3 cross 3 format.
Right. And now when you will check your rand,
you will get random numbers generated like this.
Okay, random numbers generated like this.
Right.
If you say three cross three cross three, you will get a three cross three cross three matrix.
Even if you will only say three, you will get a one D.
Right, guys.
You can change the dimension.
So this is the range from which you want to choose the random numbers, and this is the dimension you want this matrix or vector to be in.
Now, guys, we'll move on to the next part, which is basically properties and
again there are a lot of operations, you'll have to see it yourself, right?
Properties and
attributes
of
arrays, right? Property and attributes of numpy arrays.
Okay.
Now, guys, the first one in this scheme of things is shape of array, right? Shape of array.
What is shape of array?
It tells you
dimensions of the
array
stored
in a
couple, right?
For example,
I say arr zero,
right?
Arr one,
arr
two,
arr three, right?
And then I say
print this
dot shape,
right? Like this.
And you will see that it will give you the shape of each array.
Right? 0D, 1D, 2D, and 3D.
Right, people.
Shape of the array.
Please try it out.
We have used it one or two times, but this is what shape of array actually means.
Second is people,
endim.
Right?
Is end dim.
Endim of array.
Right?
It tells you
the rank of the array, whether it's one dimensional, two-dimensional, zero dimensional, three-dimensional, four-dimensional.
So again, I will do the same thing.
I'll say end dim and you will see it will give you zero, one, two, three.
Zero dimension, zero rank, one rank, two rank, and three rank.
And it can go all the way up to end rank.
Before this, I should have also
printed these arrays.
Right.
These are the arrays.
Yep.
These are the arrays which we have, and these are the subsequent things.
Right?
Rank of the array.
Then, guys, the third thing is
the
size of
array.
Right?
It tells you
the number of elements inside.
How many elements do we have inside this array?
In ARR1, how many elements do we have?
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.
How many elements do we have in this 2 cross 2 ar2?
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, which is rows multiplied by columns, 3 multiplied by 3.
Right? And how many elements do we have in this 3D?
Which is 2 multiplied by 3 multiplied by 3, which is 18.
Right?
So now when you copy this, right, you can use this
and say
size.
Right? So it will say 1, 7, 9, 18.
Fourth stable
the D type
of array
tells you
the data type of the array, right? And I've told you we place only
homogenous
data in array, right?
What will happen if we don't do this? I will show that to you also, right?
So we do this, right?
And we say
d type.
And you will see in 64 all of them are integers, right?
All of them are integers.
That's the reason we are getting in 64.
Right.
Suppose I create a new array, arr underscore new, right?
Let me say head
rightogenous.
And I say it is like entry.array.
Let's say like this.
Right, like this.
Now, people, when you will check
arr.d type, you will see it will give you float.
Just because of one floating point number inside this entire array, it gets converted to float.
Right. Between all the integers, if you put one float, then it will be taking float directly.
Right now,
let me just copy this and let's say heterogeneous one.
And let me add another value which is string and say rather.
Right.
And when you will execute this, it will give you u32. U32 here is representing strings, right? It is all called as objects, right? These are all string values,
right? So precedence is strings, greatest, then float, and then your
uh integers, right? If you place the heterogeneous data inside the numpy array,
right?
You only need to put homogeneous data in the array
now.
Fifth is the item size
of array, right?
What is item size?
It gives you
the byte
by each element of an array, right? Because we assume that elements will be homogenous, it will give you the byte occupied by each element of the array, only one element.
Okay, so how will it happen?
So let's say arr zero
or they say arr one dot item size,
right? And you will get eight, right?
So why eight? Because
each data point, right? Each data point is occupying
the result
is
eight bytes.
Let me put this here.
8 bytes,
because each element
in ARR1 is occupying
64 bits,
equivalent to which are equivalent to
eight bytes.
right?
One byte is equal to eight bits.
So 64 bits will be equal to eight bytes, right? That is how it is giving you the result.
Now, if you are interested in knowing the entire bytes, right? Entire bytes, then you say n bytes
will give you the
total bytes
occupied
by the elements of the array,
right? You say print
arr1 dot
n bytes,
right? And write
bytes.
It will be
56 bytes.
Right? Why? Because how many elements do we have in our ARR1?
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven.
Right? Seven eights are 56, right? 56 total bytes are being occupied with by ARR1.
Now, guys, the seventh one
is
as type, right?
In array.
This will help you
change the data type
of the array, right? Change the data type of the array.
Suppose I have arr1 dot d type,
which is uh
so I say print
d type, right?
This is n64, right?
And now what I do is I say print
uh wait, let me give you a structured way print
arr one, right?
Let me say,
array
arr one,
right? D type of array.
Now,
arr two.
Sorry, ARR one is equal to arr one
dot as type, right? Dot as type, and let's say I want to convert this in np dot
right np dot
uh
int
32, right? I want to create and convert this in uh arr
int 32, right? When I do this,
and now when I will copy these same things, you will see for yourself, right?
Now the t type was in 64, and now the d type is int 32, right?
If I want, I can do this conversion in float also,
float 64, right?
And then I will just copy this
and I will paste it here,
right? And now you will see now the floating point has been activated,
right? It has been now activated.
We can go till int, we can go till int 8,
right?
I can go to 16,
And I can do this.
I can go to int
Yep, like this int 8 also.
64, 32,
so first one has to be
thirty-two low.
Whatever, right?
Like this.
Okay,
you can convert this.
Also, people, this is later on conversion.
You can define the data type
of the array while
creation time also.
How would you do that? Suppose you are creating ARR11 and you say np.array, right? And suppose you take it from a list and then you just put a comma and say d type.
So what will be the default data type here, people?
If I just do this, if I just execute this,
what will be the default data type?
N64 is the default,
isn't it?
But now suppose I want to change it right here. I say data type is equal to float 32.
Right?
Sorry, float 64.
NP dot
sorry.
My bad.
Float 64, right?
And I say arr11 and this will be float 64. If you want float 32, it will also become float 32, right? Right here while you define.
Instead of using as type, you can do it right here.
Right. These things will come in very handy, people, because you will have to save memory.
Because when your data becomes very, very big, you will be always in a crunch for memory.
Like this, you want integers, then integers will be like this
random dot rand like this.
Suppose you want to generate 0 to 6, right?
And suppose you want to generate
say 100 numbers
like this, 026.
The scores
one to six,
like this
randomly.
Right.
Suppose you want to generate hundred scores for
five different batsmen randomly.
It will be like this: batsman number one, batsman number two, batsman number three, four, and fifth.
Right?
Yep.
Understand the data, guys. Now it's the time to understand the data.
Now, guys, we have methods in
numpy arrays, right? Methods in numpy arrays.
So, what are these methods now?
The first method we have to learn is called as reshape, right? Reshape.
Yeah, so reshape is you can use this to create.
You can use this to create
a new shape of the array. Very, very powerful, guys.
Very powerful. One of the most powerful methods in numpy is uh the reshape, right? And how do we use reshape?
Suppose
we have a 1D array of 20 elements, right?
Now to reshape this,
reshape it, we need to find the factors,
right? Factors of 20.
They are what one, twenty, four, five,
two, ten.
Right?
Here are the factors.
Now see what will I do, right? Now see what will I do.
Let me create a say random array, right? Random array.
I say
underscore arr is equal to np dot random
dot rand int, right?
And let me say I want to create it from 1 to 50, right? And I want it to be having 20 elements, right? So I say random dot arr.
So you will have random values inside this, right? Random 20 values now C.
Now reshape.
First.
I will
reshape in one cross twenty, right? One, comma twenty.
How will I do that?
You just have to write
uh
print
arr.
Sorry, random dot arr random underscore arr
dot reshape dot reshape and you just pass in the dimension. I say one comma twenty.
Right.
And when you will do this, you will see it is coming now in one comma twenty format, right?
So let me just also write print
right 2D
one, 20.
Right.
And now what I'll do is I'll copy this
and I will paste this and say
20 comma 1.
Right?
You will see it will be like this 20, comma 1 immediately with reshape, right?
Let me copy this.
Let me say 2D. I'm still at 2D.
Let me say
2,
10. Right?
And you will see this is 2, 10.
Now I can reshape it in
10, 2.
Right?
10 comma 2.
Right.
Then I can reshape the same thing
in
4,5.
And I can reshape this in 5, 4.
Right?
Like this.
Guys, are you able to see the power?
One dimension. I'm able to create two dimensions.
And now I will take it a step further and I will write it in three dimensions.
Right? How will I write it in three dimensions?
Let me say this
one,
two, comma ten, right? This will also be three dimensions. Let's sorry, two, two, comma, five.
Let me say this. And now you will see I can have this in
three dimensions,
right?
Yep.
I can also say
in three dimensions, like this.
I want to have five layers
with two rows and two columns, right? So you will have it like this also, right?
So this is how people we can reshape the array very powerfully, very, very powerful,
right?
Very, very powerful.
Right. And you can take this
and save print
random dot this and you can save print
dot shape.
Right.
So this was the first one.
Yep, like this.
Also, people, if you want to visualize, we can also go this route.
We can have ten,
two, comma one, right?
It will look like this.
Right?
Ten layers.
Right? Ten layers you can have.
Great now.
Second method which we have to learn is called as
transpose.
Rice transpose method, right? What does that do?
It interchanges the
dimensions
like rows and columns, right?
Yes, absolutely.
Right.
Suppose you have a matrix, right? Which is
22, 33, 44, 55, 66, 77.
Right? This is A.
So now when you will A transpose it, right?
The dimension right now, the shape right now is 3, 2.
Now this will become 2 comma 3. And how this will happen?
Rows will now become columns, and columns will now become rows, right? So let's make
column the rows, right? Sorry, columns the rows.
It will be 22, 44, 66,
33, 55, 77.
Right?
So people in transpose, no information is lost.
It is just a change in the view, right? Which is happening, right?
22, 44, 66,
33, 55, 77.
Why do we need
transposition?
Suppose we have two matrix.
This is 11th class mathematics, right? One has
a dimension of n cross m and the second has dimension of A cross b.
If you
want to multiply
these two matrix,
say
M1 and M2.
Right.
There needs to be a satisfaction of condition.
Right. M should be equal to A.
This should be equal to this.
And the resultant vector, the resultant matrix which you will get will be of N cross B dimension.
Right.
So oftentimes suppose this is N cross M.
This is N cross M.
Right. M cross N.
And you know that M is equal to A.
So what will you do? You will transpose this matrix, right? You will transpose this matrix, then it will become N cross M. And then M can be equivalent to A.
Right. For example, what I'm saying, we have one matrix which is 2 cross 3.
And this matrix is 2 cross 5.
Right.
So can you multiply these matrix, people?
Is 3 equal to 2?
The answer is no. Right?
The answer is no.
So what will you do? You will just transpose this and this will become 3 cross 2.
And this is 2 cross 5.
And now you can multiply this, and the resultant will become 3 cross 5 matrix.
Right?
So for operations like these, we need transposition.
Right. So how do we transpose it?
How do we transpose it?
So let's say again uh arr2, right? This is arr2, and I want to transpose it.
So I say arr2 underscore t is equal to uh np dot transpose.
Sorry, sorry, arr2 dot
transpose,
right?
And now when you will see arr2 underscore t you will see rows and columns have interchanged,
right? Rows and columns have interchanged with each other.
Or let me give you one more example.
Uh if this is not clear,
let me pick up
this again.
Right now I say
dot reshape
into say
Right, this is two cross ten. And now, when you want to transpose this, so I'll say this: underscore t is equal to this dot
transpose,
and this,
and you can check this now,
and it will be this
for you, guys.
So this is gonna be
it will be like this, right?
Transpose.
And now
if you want to see
this,
this was the original shape, right?
Rows and columns have now been interchange, transposed with each other
now, guys. The third
method,
the third method which is there with us is called as flatten, right? It is called as flatten,
right? What does flatten do?
It reduces
the dimension to one dimension, right? Any dimension you have, it reduces it to one dimension. For example, I have this
right.
and now when I say
dot underscore f, this will become
this dot
flatten.
and when you will check this up,
you will see that it has now become one dimension.
No matter how many dimensions you have, it will become one dimension,
right?
Let me take this again to show you one more example,
And here I say dot reshape into
uh five cross two cross two, right? I do this.
My random arr is this right, it has five layers, two rows and two columns,
right? So now I say this
underscore flatten is equal to this dot
flatten,
and if you will check it now again, you will see it has now flattened it up.
Yeah.
Now, why do we need this? We need this for a lot of statistical operations.
We need this to feed the data into the algorithms, right?
As we will move forward, you will understand the use of flattening,
right
now, guys.
Moving on, and uh, as discussed, let me now show you
the power of
numpy,
right? Numpy
over
lists and other
data types, right? I will not take a lot of examples.
Just a second, guys.
Yeah,
okay.
Now, guys,
I told you
that
lists
take up
much more
memory
as compared
to numpy arrays. right? And I'm gonna prove this to you right
now.
Let me use,
let me create a random sequence of random numbers using range in Python, right?
And say I create range of 10,000 numbers, right? Range of 10,000 numbers. So, what will this give me?
This will give me numbers from 0 to 9999, right?
Continuous numbers, right? So this is range.
I will use
a range in
numpy
to create
a similar.
Series of numbers,
right?
So let's say array is equal to np dot arange.
Right.
Same thing, same done by both, right? I've shown you above also.
Now let me import sys
library, right?
Syspackage.
And I will use something called as get size or right. Get size of.
What does this do?
Get size of.
It's a method
which calculates
the bytes
occupied
by a single
element in
vanilla python. What is vanilla python? It is the traditional Python.
Right? Vanilla Python.
So let me just show that to you.
I'll use this and I will say print.
Now, guys, if I get
size of any random number from this range, right? Any random number.
Say I get size of 5, right? And I then multiply that bytes with the length of random.
Right?
With the length of random, this ran,
right?
Right. With the length of random.
Do you think I will get the bytes for the entire
data structure?
What am I saying is suppose
uh I used range
5. So what will this give me?
0, 1, 2, 3, 4.
Right? This will be the output.
So now I say get
size of say I say 2, right? So suppose 2 is x, and then I multiply this with the length of this series, which is 5.
So do you think I will get 5x,
which will represent the number of bytes occupied by the entire data type?
Anything randomly, any random number.
This can be 3, right?
Why not hurry?
Why not?
All of these are integers.
So integers all of 64 bits,
assuming.
So if you calculate the side of size of this, and if you multiply with the total number of numbers, you will get the total size,
isn't it?
Index is in tangent.
No, no, no, it's not about that. It's about the element, right? Homogeneous elements inside this.
I am saying when you use range 5, what is going to be the output?
0, 1, 2, 3, 4, right now, all these are elements.
Elements of
right? All of them are elements of range, right?
Now I am saying if I fetch the
size of one element and multiply it with the length of the entire range, will I get the bytes
occupied by the entire range?
For example, if I do this, right? If I do this,
this is 28, right? 28 bytes, people, 28 bytes
are occupied
by
one element of range, right?
One element of
range, right?
Now if I just I'm saying, I'm just saying if I multiply to find how many numbers range has.
How many numbers
range has
equal to 10,000?
Right?
So total
memory occupied
will be how much?
It will be
twenty eight multiplied by 10,000, which will be equal to 28,000.
Yeah, and how will you find this?
You will say print
this multiplied by length of RAM.
Right? 28,000 bytes.
Clear now?
Yes.
Now this is for the range. Now let me use another thing. So how will you calculate the length of this array?
What
uh property and attribute will you use, people?
N bytes, right? N bytes will give you total bytes occupied by the elements of the array, right? We will use n bytes here.
So I come back down and I say
using n bytes
for arrays, right?
And you will see what the result comes.
Print
uh
array.n
bytes,
right? And I say bytes.
Are you ready to see the result?
Do you see what has happened?
How many bytes this was taking?
It was taking 28,000 bytes.
How many bytes this is taking?
This is taking 80,000 bytes.
This was taking 2 lakh 80,000. This is taking 80,000.
2 lakh extra bytes of memory is taken by range.
Ran is range.
Yep.
And if I just go to million numbers,
right?
Million numbers in both.
See the difference it becomes.
Right? This is now 33
million bytes it is taking, and it is taking 8 million bytes.
20 million extra bytes are occupied, right?
Now, people, do you believe me?
Yeah, that numpys are way more efficient in memory management as compared to the traditional data types of python.
Yes.
Okay, that's the first part.
Now, second is people, performance, right? Performance.
So what I'm gonna do is what I'm gonna do is I am going to
import
time, right? It's a it's a module in Python, right? Suppose I say x is equal to range
this much, right?
Okay, and then I have y is equal to
range, say
this
to
this,
Both of them will have equal amount of numbers, same numbers, both of them will have, right?
This will have say uh
one, two, three, one, two, three, ten million values, ten
million values.
This will also have ten million values,
right? Both of them will have ten million values.
Now, what I'm trying to do is I want to add them up, right?
Byte bit by bit. I want to add them up, right? I want to add first element of this to first element of this, second of this to second of this, third of this to third of this, like this.
Okay, I want to do this now. What I'll do is I will run a counter, right? I will run a counter which is the start time,
right? And this is given by time dot time, right?
Which will give you the
this
will
give you the
current time, right?
After this, I will run the operation. I will say c is equal to x plus y
for x, comma y
in zip
right in zip x, comma y right.
Add x plus y
bit by bit, element by element for x and y in zip. Zip is a function, right, which allows you to do this operation sequentially, right? Sequentially, right?
Add the
elements
of x and y
element by
element, right? Element by element.
Right, element by element.
Right. And then I am gonna print right. So start time will start, and now I will say time dot time, which is now the end time minus start time.
So this will give me the time taken for execution, isn't it, guys?
Will give me
delta of time,
which is equal to time taken for operation
seconds,
right? These many seconds will be taken,
right?
So let me run this and it takes around say
4.3 seconds, right? To do this, right? 4.3 seconds now, guys.
See what happens.
You had to write this complex syntax in the traditional Python.
Now let me show this on arrays, right?
What will happen on arrays? I will say a is equal to np dot arange,
And inside arrange, I will pass the same values what I have taken above, right? And I will say b is equal to np dot
a range, and I will pass the same values inside,
right? Exactly the same.
Now what I'll do is I will say
same thing.
Right.
Just I will change the execution of C.
Will now simply become people A plus B.
What is simple?
This or this?
This or this.
Do you see the power?
If not, I will show this to you again, right? Later on, and let me run this.
And you see the difference.
Now let me just increase a couple of zeros, right? A couple of zeros.
Two zeros I am increasing in both the use cases.
See, it is going on and on, right?
Let's see how much time it will take
to add,
say two million, one billion numbers.
One billion numbers I have asked my system to add,
and I want to see how much time it takes.
Running, running, running.
Yep, kernel has died.
Kernel has died, people.
I'll have to restart.
Right?
I will have to import
num prewire
as NP.
So let me just remove one zero
from both.
It is taking four seconds, removing one zero from here also.
Right.
And when I do this,
it takes one second.
Do you see, guys,
what is the difference in performance also, right?
For both of these.
Yeah.
And if you didn't understand this, let me give you an example.
Range five.
This is five to ten,
right?
And this is basically
adding elements.
Right.
7 9 11 13.
So this will be what will be output of this?
This will be 0, 1, 2, 3, 4.
And this will be output what?
6 7 8 9.
Right. So 0 plus 5, 5, 6 plus 1, 7.
7 plus 2, 9.
8 plus 3, 11. 9 plus 4, 13.
And the same thing if I do here.
Then what will happen?
I say 5.
I say 5 and 10.
Right. And I say c is equal to a plus b and I say c.
Same thing you get here.
Right. We can move on.
Right. The next bit, guys, which we have to understand, the next bit which we have to understand is called as the indexing in numpy arrays.
Right. Indexing in numpy arrays.
Right. How do we index the elements?
Indexing in
numpy
Right. Indexing in numpy arrays.
So again, you know indexing from basic Python.
So let's start with 1D for 1D arrays.
Right. I will use arr1.
Yeah.
This is arr1 now, right?
This is arr1.
Okay.
Now, people, what I want to do is what I want to do is I want to fetch, right?
I want to fetch. Right. You can slice and dice.
Let's say dice.
33. Right.
So again, as per our normal indexing of list, what is 33?
What is the index of 33, people?
2. So you will say the same thing. Print.
Right.
Arr 1 squared bracket.
2. And you will get 33 by yourself.
Right.
If you wish to slice, same thing, right?
33 to say 66.
What is the index?
33 is 2, 2.
Which one?
3, 4, 5, and 6.
Right? You will write 3 to 6.
Not 5, hurry.
5 is not included. Remember?
So print
arr 1.
2 is 26.
And you will get 33, 44, 55, 66.
Right?
Simple indexing.
Please try it out.
And if you want, you can have this code also.
You can write this code.
You will always have clarity that why do we use it?
Moving on, people. Moving on.
Let's see indexing
in a 2D array.
Right. And before I explain this to you, let me take you here, right?
So a 2D array will be what?
Right. This is a 2D array.
It has three rows
and three columns, right? Rows, columns.
So now for rows, indexing will start from zero.
So if you have to
fetch this particular row,
right? So what will be the index?
It will be row zero.
If you have to fetch this particular row,
the index will be one.
And if you have to fetch this particular row, this the index will be
two.
Similarly, for column, if you have to fetch this particular column, right?
You will have column is equal to zero.
This particular column, column equal to one,
this particular column, column equal to two, right?
Indexing will start from minus one again, right? 0, 1, 2.
So let me just show that to you, right?
Let's say I call arr2.
It is my arr2.
Now
indexing
first
row, right?
How will I do that? I will say print
arr2 and I will write how?
How will I write this?
I will write row 0, right? Row zero.
So what will this give me? This will give me this, right? The syntax is
row space column, right?
So now if you just pass one, it will give you only rows, right?
Row one, row two, row three.
Right. Similarly,
if you want to create it for columns,
right?
What will you say?
Sorry.
Uh
columns
Zero.
Column one,
column two,
column three, right?
Right.
So what is my column one? Seventy-six eighty-nine ninety-eight.
Seventy-six eighty-nine ninety-eight.
Right. And if you want column two.
Oh sorry.
If you want column two, this is the column two and this is column three.
Right, guys?
90, 99, 99.
Independently.
Now, if I ask you to fetch me a particular element.
Element, right?
Say I want you to fetch me
78. Right? How will you fetch 78? You will say print arr2.
What is the row for 78?
Which row does it belong to?
012?
To which row 78 belongs?
One row?
Which column it belongs to?
012.
1.
Hurry check again.
Whether it belongs to 0 column, first column, or second column.
Right?
And you will get uh sorry.
01. So this is 2.
Right? 78. Right?
Right. Second row, first column.
How to define it as in
right. This is your
matrix.
Right now, what are the index positions for this?
This row is zero row, first row, second row.
This is your zeroth column, first column, second column.
Yeah.
Yes, no, maybe.
Are we understanding this?
This much is clear.
The indexing of rows and columns.
Now, now if you have two, so the syntax is
syntaxes, say this is matrix A.
So you will say A in this A matrix, you will write row, comma, column.
Right?
Suppose I want to access only zeroth row.
So there will be no column.
So what will you get? Row number zero.
Right?
Row number zero, and you will just put it like this, or you can put a comma and put colon.
Colon means what? Take everything.
So I want all three columns together.
Zero row and all three columns.
So this will be your.
Let me show that to you.
Right?
See this zeroth row and all the columns.
So what will be your answer? 76, 88, 90.
Right?
Then if you want to access the second row, 89, 90, 99. 89, 90, 99.
1 and like this.
Clear?
Now, similarly, for columns, what will happen?
You will take all the rows,
which column do you want? If you say 2, what will be the result for this?
What numbers will you get for this?
You will get 33, 66, 99.
Now, coming to the element, right?
Suppose now you want to fetch 55, right? So what will you write?
You will write which row does it belong?
Follow this syntax.
It belongs to the first row.
Which column does it belong to?
First column.
So what will you get?
55.
Come to this example. Now you want 78 in this particular array or matrix, right?
Where is 78? Which row does it belong to?
Is it first row?
Check carefully.
Zeroth row,
first row, second row.
Yeah?
So I put two here. Now which column does it belong to?
First column, second column.
Sorry, zeroth column, first column, second column.
Belongs to the first column.
So I put one here.
So when you put this syntax, you will get 78.
Clear?
Now the third thing is slicing
through
the array.
Right now, for this, I want, I want 90, 99, 78, 99.
That means what?
I want this, this, this, and this.
Let me take you to the PPT first.
Now, what I'm asking you to fetch me?
I'm asking you to fetch me these four numbers.
Right? These four numbers.
So here, what will you write? Which rows are included in this, people?
Which rows are included in this?
Row one to all.
Right? One to all.
Yeah.
Not two. One to all.
Right?
And you leave everything like this.
If you have the last row, you leave it empty after the colon.
Comma.
Which columns do you want for this?
One and two.
Right?
And when these will intersect, when these will intersect, you will get this area. You will get this shaded area, green shaded area.
So I will say
I need from column one
to all the columns.
Right. So what will this fetch you? What will this fetch you? This will fetch you
44,
55, 66,
and 77, 88, 99.
Right?
What will this fetch you?
This will fetch you 22, 55, 88,
33, 66, 99.
What are the commonalities between both of these?
Access.
Both of these slices. What are the commonalities?
It is only this much.
Right?
55, 66, 88, 99.
So do you think you will get your result?
Yeah, let's check it here.
Right? I say print
ARR2.
Right.
And this I say.
I need row 0, sorry, row 1 to empty, and then column 1 empty, and you will get 90, 99,
78, 90.
Indexing.
Yeah.
Now guys, let's check it for
three dimensions, right? 3D.
I say arr three, right? This is my ARR3.
Right.
So let me just put an example here.
Suppose my arrays are 11, 2, 2, 3, 3,
4, 4, 5, 6, 6,
7, 7, 8, 8, 9.
Right. This is my first.
Then behind this, I have another matrix which is uh
111 222 333
444 555 666
777 888 999.
Right?
And in my
Third one.
I have 1111 2222 3333
4444 5555 6666
999.
Is that is it qualifying for a 3D array?
Can you access anything on this particular array if given a chance separately?
Like this one.
Now, people, if you want to move between layers, right?
If you want to move between layers, do you think I have told you one particular access?
Which is what?
Which is the layers.
So what number will be given to this layer?
Layer number 0,
layer number 1,
and layer number 2.
So now if you have to access this 555, which layer will you go to first?
You will go to first layer.
Then which row will you go to?
You will go to
first row
and first column.
So if you pass this syntax, what will you get? You will get 555.
Right?
Problem solved.
The only bottleneck was the layers part, and you have additional parameter or argument for this layer.
So if I come back to my example and if you have to access this 555, right? How will you do that?
I say print
arr2, a r three, right? And this I say, and in this I say what?
I have to access this 555.
Which which layer number is this?
This is layer number 0, right?
This is layer number 0 and this is layer number 1. So I say layer number 1.
Which row is this?
In this particular layer, it is layer number.
Sorry, it is row number 1 and column number 1. And when you do this, you will get 5 by 5.
Right?
If you want 999, what you will do?
You will change this to 2,
right?
If you want 777, or let's say if you want 98, what will you do for 98?
Layer number 0, row number 2, column number 0.
And you will get this 98.
Clear, guys.
Yep.
Layer row column. In the same way you will slice it.
Right?
You will slice it.
Yep.
Right. I'll write the syntax
so that you don't get confused. It is array
squared bracket
layer row
bracket column.
Right. Layer bracket
row bracket
column.
Right. This is the syntax.
Perfect.
Right.
Great.
We can also perform some operations, right?
Plus, minus multiplication, division between two arrays very, very easily.
Right.
It should not pose any problem to us.
Right. We can do all the operations which we want to, right? Between two arrays, right?
For example, right, you had you have
operations on arrays.
So let's say
uh
let's see as a list,
right?
List.
So we have list is equal to one, two, three, four, five.
Right now, suppose you want to square
each element of the list, right?
What will you do?
You will say s unders sq underscore l
is equal to
x to the power of two
for x in power
l, right?
And then you will say print
sq underscore l and you will get the squared of list,
right?
Original list squared list. Now
in array, what will happen?
Suppose I say
one is equal to np dot array and l. I create the same array out of this list.
I say print
original
array.
Right. I say a1.
Right. This is my original array.
Same as this. Now I want to square it.
Square the elements of arrays.
Very, very simple. Nothing you require. You just say, you just say
sq underscore a1 is equal to sq underscore a1 is equal to a1 to
Right. A1 to the power of two.
Right. And then you print
the
square. Right.
You get a square R.
Suppose
you want to find the mean of
the mean of numbers
using list.
Right. So what will you do?
You will say
mean is equal to
sum of
L right list
divided by length of list,
right?
And you will get the mean,
right? Which is three for this one, right? This original list.
Now let me show you in arrays.
Right. How will you do this?
You will say mean is equal to np dot mean and you will just pass a1.
Right. And when you will check mean, you will get 3.0.
Right?
Nothing like this.
Direct.
Right. Direct like this. Right. You can you have I've already showed you add, I've already showed you uh square, and then I believe you can understand that
what all operations are possible using the arrays, right? Leveraging the power of arrays.
Right.
Also, guys, in the arrays, right? In the arrays, what you can do is you can perform,
you can
perform
some
string operations, right? Very powerful string operations, right?
So for example, let's say I have a I have I have an array, right?
I have an array of names of people, right?
So I say names is equal to
np dot array, right?
And I say
Radhav.
Uh then I say
Dinesh, right? And then I say
Madhut, right? These three names I have, right?
So you can check the names, they will be like in the array, right? And the data type will be U6, which is a representation of strings, right?
Now, guys, suppose you want to capitalize, you wish to capitalize the names,
right? Of people.
What will you do?
You will say, print me
np.care, right? np.care dot
capitalize.
Right. Capitalize.
And inside this, you will pass names
and you will see all the names have been capitalized.
Right?
You see this?
R has been capitalized, D has been capitalized, M has been capitalized.
Right.
You can convert them into upper if you want.
Print
np.car dot upper
names, and you will have all of them in caps lock.
You can say print np.car dot lower.
You will have them in lower.
Right.
You can put the title right. Suppose I say uh
T I T L E title is equal to np dot array, and I say
radav.
Right, then I say
Dinesh
Tenapati,
right?
And I say
Madhud
Varma.
Right. I say these three things now.
If I say print
np dot car dot
title, right, and I say
titles, you will see that all the words will be in capitalized mode. Ragavhoyal D and S of Dinesh Senapati, M and V of Madhu Varma are now capitalized.
I can also
replace something if I wish to suppose I want to replace a Madhu with say survi.
Right. I will say
print
right np dot care dot replace
replace right and you will say
where you want to replace.
I say title,
and in this I want to replace
Madhu
with
Surupi.
Right.
And you will say it will be Surbi underscore one.
Surbi one.
Right. Madhu has been replaced with Surbi.
Right. If you want to calculate
the characters of strings,
right, you can do that.
NP dot car
dot str underscore length of
titles, and you will get 11 characters are there in here.
15 are there here, and 11 are here
in this particular thing.
You can do much more powerful things also.
Let me show you one complex function, right? Suppose I have
fname
is equal to np.ar,
right?
And we have
ragaves
madhu.
Right.
And we have L underscore name.
We have these two things.
Now I can create a new array,
full underscore name, by simply right, by simply saying np dot car
dot add right.
And I say uh
f name
right,
comma
l underscore name, right?
Plus
full name.
In between
Anyway, right?
We can do that.
Right?
You can also people
search in arrays, right?
Very powerful again.
Search in arrays using where.
Right.
You can say suppose a2 is equal to
np dot array.
Right. And I'll say 112 334 556.
Right. And now you have to say
a is equal to np dot where.
Right. And in this you say a2 greater than 20.
Right. And when you will check a
uh it's giving me the index.
Why is it giving me the index?
Does it always return index?
One more thing is you can
find a
letter,
right?
Through a letter. You can find an element
through
a letter. Guys, these are all some tricks which you should know because you will be dealing with data and you need to pull data, right? You need to pull data a lot, right?
Based on conditions and based on things.
Suppose you want to find out the names which have g in them, right?
Or ra in them. So how will you do this? I will say print, right? And I will say
uh np.care
dot find, right? And I will say find this inside full underscore
names, right? And find me R A.
Right?
R A.
True, false, false.
Right, it returns true because it has found it here.
Right.
So I don't want to tell you indexing through this, but anyway, you should know this. Just just assume this that I am telling you to write this, okay?
Because this is much easier when we will go to pandas.
Right?
Just uh write it as a syntax, okay?
Greater than or equal to zero.
I hope this is clear. So let's start with the data science interview questions and answers.
And the number one problem we will be facing is real-world problem solving.
And the question one is handling missing data in predictive modeling. So imagine you have given a data set where 30% of the data for key predictive variable is missing.
This variable is crucial for a predictive model. How would you handle this situation to ensure the integrity and performance of the model?
And please describe your approach step by step.
So, starting with the answer, you can start with handling missing data set is a common challenge in data science, and it's important to address it carefully to maintain the accuracy of the model.
And here's how you could approach this situation. The number one point would be identify the missing data. So, first you need to understand where the missing values are in your dataset.
You can do this by using a simple code in Python with libraries like Mandas.
For example, you can use the data.isnal.sum function that will show you the count of missing values in each column.
Then you can analyze the pattern, determine if there's a pattern to the missing data.
Is it random or is it missing for a reason?
This can affect your approach. If the data is missing at random, the methods you use might be different than if the data is missing systematically.
So choosing a method for imputation.
Let's see the next method that is choosing a method for imputation.
So if the missing data is numeric, you might replace missing values with the mean or median of that column.
This is simple and effective, but can be used primarily when the data is missing completely at random.
Then comes model based imputation.
Sometimes you can use other variables in the data to predict missing values using a regression model.
This can be more accurate, but is also more complex.
Then we'll use the kneearest neighbors can algorithm.
But before that, we have a code snippet here that could be used for the implementation of imputation.
You could use Python or R.
And now moving on, we'll see the K nearest neighbors algorithm. So this method predicts the missing values based on how closely related the data points are to each other.
So after imputation, it's crucial to check how your changes have affected the oral data set and model performance.
Sometimes filling in too many missing values can introduce bias.
And then we have visualization.
To help understand before and after the imputation, you could visualize the distribution of the variable using histograms or box plots.
This helps in seeing how the imputation has changed the statistical properties of the data.
And by following these steps, you can handle missing data thoughtfully and maintain the integrity of your predictive model.
Now moving to the question number two that is based on evaluating model overfitting.
So the question is you have developed a predictive model, but you suspect it might be overfitting the training data.
How would you test and address the issue?
Please explain your steps and the techniques you would use.
So you could start the answer by explaining what is overfitting.
So overfitting is a common problem where the model performs well on training data but poorly on unseen data, indicating it's too closely fitted to the training data's specific details and noise.
So now we'll see a step-by-step guide on how to address this.
The number one step is cross-validation.
So one effective way to test for overfitting is by using cross-validation technique.
Cross-validation involves splitting your training data into multiple smaller sets that is false and then training a model on some of these sets and validating it on the others.
So this helps you understand if the model's good performance is consistent across different subsets of data.
For example, in Python you can use the cross underscore value underscore score function from sklearn.model underscore selection.
So this is the code and this is the code snippet of Python that you can use for the cross validation.
And here we are importing from sklearn that is the module, and we are importing cross underscore well underscore score.
And here we have used the cross val score function, and then we have printed the average cross validation score.
And the next step we will do is running cross validation model.
So this is your predictive model that you have already built using scikit learn.
And here's the X train, these are the X input features of your training data, and Y train these are the output labels of training data. So we are running cross validation model here.
This is your predictive model that you have already built using scikit learn.
So X train here that means these are the input features of your training data. And Y train here means these are the output labels of training data and C V equal to 5.
This parameter tests the function to split the data into five parts that is folds and the model is trained on four of these parts and the remaining part is used for testing.
So this process rotates until each part has been used for testing once and the printing results that is score.mean.
So this calculates the average of the scores obtained from each gross validation fold. This average score gives you an idea of how well your model is likely to perform on unseen data.
A consistent score across different folds suggests your model is generalizing well rather than overfitting to the training data.
So now moving to the next point that is training versus validation error.
Supplot the training and validation errors as a function of training epochs or complexity of the model.
A model that overfits will show a low error on training data and a high error on validation data as it trains further.
Then we have pruning the model. If you confirm that the model is overfitting, consider simplifying it.
This might mean reducing the number of parameters by selecting fewer features.
Using regularization techniques like lasso or ridge or choosing a less complex model. After this step, we will move to regularization technique step.
So these techniques add a penalty to the loss function used to train the model, which can discourage complex models that overfit.
Then we have common methods that include L1, that is lasso, and L2, ridge regularization. And here's how you can add L2 regularization in Python. So this is the code snippet here.
And what we have done here is we are creating the ridge model and we have applied alpha equal to 1.0. So this parameter controls the strength of the regularization.
A higher alpha value increases the regularization effect, which helps reduce model complexity and combat overfitting.
The alpha value can be tuned to find the optimal balance between bias and variance.
And now coming for the fitting the model.
So model dot fit, and in that we have X train and Y train that trains the ridge model on the training data.
It adjusts the weight of the feature in X train to predict the Y train while also considering the regularization term.
This helps prevent the model from fitting too closely to the noisy aspects of the training data.
And then we are re-evaluating the model.
After making adjustments, it's important to re-evaluate the model again using the same cross-validation technique to see if the issue of overfitting has improved.
And then we have visualization.
To help illustrate overfitting, you could create a plot showing the training and validation errors or the number of epochs or model complexity.
So by using these techniques, you can identify if a model is overfitting and take steps to correct it, ensuring it performs well not only on the training data but also on new unseen
data.
So now moving to the next question that is question number three, and it is based on real-time data stream processing.
And the question is you are tasked with building a model to predict stock prices in real time.
The data comes in every second, and you need to update your predictions accordingly.
Describe how you would set up your system to handle this type of data effectively and what tools and techniques would you use and why.
So you could start answering this question with handling real-time data.
So handling real-time data, especially for something as volatile and fast-paced as stock prices, requires a robust system that can process and analyze data quickly and accurately.
So here's how you could approach this. We will set up such a system and we'll have some steps.
So starting with the steps.
So the first step is choosing the right tools.
The right tool would be Apache Kafka.
So this is a popular tool for handling real-time data that streams because it allows you to publish and subscribe to streams of records that is data.
And it can handle high throughput with low latency.
Kafka acts as a buffer and manages the flow of data, ensuring that your system doesn't get overwhelmed.
And you can also use Apache Spark. Especially Spark streaming is excellent for processing the data.
It can process data in real time and perform complex operations like windowing, grouping data into chunks of a specified time period and aggregating, that is summarizing data.
So you can modify it and perform the predicting of stock prices. And then the step is data processing pipeline.
And the first step comes here is ingestion.
Data first enters the system typically through Kafka, which collects data sent from the stock market.
And then we do the processing.
So spark streaming takes over here. Here you can apply transformations and run your predictive models on the data.
For example, you might calculate moving averages or other indicators that feed into your stock price prediction model.
And then comes the output. Finally, the predictions are outputted. This could be to a dashboard for traders, an automated trading system, or even stored for further analysis.
And then we develop the model. Now comes the model development. You would likely use a machine learning model that can update quickly and incorporate new data as it arrives.
Models such as ARIMA for time series forecasting or more complex machine learning models like correct and neural networks, RNNs, can be suitable.
The model should be retrained or fine tuned periodically with new data to ensure it stays accurate. Now we'll come to scalability and reliability.
So ensure your system can scale as data volume increases. This might mean adding more servers or optimizing your data processing code.
Implement monitoring to catch any issues early, like delays in data processing or model performance drops.
And now we'll see the step that is visualization and monitoring.
Consider setting up a real time dashboard that shows key metrics like prediction accuracy and processing time.
This helps in quickly spotting when something goes wrong.
By setting up your system with these tools and strategies, you can effectively handle the challenge of predicting stock prices in real time.
So now we'll move to the next question that is question number four, and this will be based on scalable data analytics.
So we have covered two questions that were a bit code-based questions, and now we'll see other questions that would be based on scalable data analytics
or they might know different areas. And with the 13th question, we will start again with the coding ones. So moving with the question 4 that is based on scalable data analytics.
And the question is given a scenario where your organization suddenly needs to scale its data analysis capabilities due to an influx of data
that would be 10 times the normal volume.
How would you handle this situation to ensure your data analytics processes remain efficient and accurate? What technologies would you consider and what steps would you take?
So you can start answering this question with handling a sudden increase in data volume requires a strategic approach to scaling your analytics
infrastructure without compromising on efficiency or accuracy. So we'll see some steps from that you could effectively manage this scenario.
That you would start answering the interviewer that we can start by evaluating the current infrastructure's ability to handle increased loads.
This includes assessing your databases, servers, and analytical tools to identify potential bottlenecks or limitations.
Then you could move to the next step that would be choosing scalable technologies.
To manage the increased data volume, consider leveraging cloud-based solutions such as Amazon Web Services, Google Cloud Platform, or Microsoft Azure.
These platforms offer scalable resources which can be adjusted accordingly to the data load, ensuring you only pay for what you use.
Integrate big data technologies like Apache Hadoop for distributed storage and Apache Spark for fast data processing.
These tools are designed to handle massive volumes of data efficiently and can scale up to meet standard increased demands.
Now we'll move to the next step that would be optimizing data processing.
So implement data partitioning and indexing strategies to improve the efficiency of data queries.
This will help in managing large data sets by breaking them into smaller, manageable chunks and speeding up search operations.
And use real-time data processing frameworks like Apache Kafka or Apache Flink, which can handle high throughput and provide timely insights from large data streams.
And the next step would be automation and monitoring.
Automate routine data processing tasks to reduce the manual effort and speed up the analysis.
This can be done through scripting or using workflow automation tools. Set up comprehensive monitoring systems to track the performance of your data processes.
Tools like Promptheus for system monitoring and Grafana for analytics and monitoring dashboards are useful here.
They help ensure that the system is running smoothly and alert you to potential issues before they become critical. And the next step will be regular evaluation and scaling.
Continuously evaluate the performance of your analytics infrastructure. As your data grows, keep adjusting and scaling your resources to maintain optimal performance.
Plan for periodic reviews of your technology stack and infrastructure to ensure they remain aligned with your data needs and organizational goals.
By following these steps, you can ensure that your data analytics processes are prepared to handle sudden surges in data volume effectively, maintaining the integrity and speed of insights.
So, this was all for the question 4. Now move to the question 5, and this is based on integrating machine learning models into production.
And the question is you have developed a machine learning model that performs well in testing environment.
Now you need to integrate it into your production environment where it will be used in real-time applications.
What steps would you take to ensure the successful deployment and operations of the model in production?
So we'll start answering this by successfully deploying a machine learning model into production involves several critical steps to ensure it
performs as well in real-time operations as it does in testing.
So you would have a clear pathway to make the interviewer understand.
We will start with the pathway with the first step that would be model validation.
So before moving anything into production, revalidate your model's performance using a separate validation data set.
This helps confirm that the model generalizes well to new unseen data.
The next step will be preparing the production environment.
Ensure that the production environment is ready to handle the model.
This includes setting up the necessary hardware and software, ensuring that it can handle the expected load and that all dependencies are correctly installed and configured.
Then the next step comes that is modal wrapping.
Wrap your model in an API, that is application programming interface, making it accessible to other parts of your software infrastructure.
Frameworks like Flask for Python can be used to create a simple web server that listens for data inputs and provides modal outputs.
Then comes the next step that is deployment strategies.
Consider using containerization tools like Dokker, which can help encapsulate your model and its environment, ensuring that it works uniformly across different development and production settings.
And then we'll use deployment strategies like blue-green deployment or canary releases to minimize downtime and reduce the risk of introducing a faulty model into production.
And then comes the next step that is monitoring and logging.
Implement logging and monitoring to track the model's performance and health in real time.
Tools like Prompthears for monitoring and ELK.
Elasticsearch, logstatch, Kibana for logging help in quickly identifying and diagnosing issues in production.
And then comes the next step that is performance tuning.
Monitor the model's performance over time.
If the model's performance degrades or if new data shows different patterns, you may need to retrain or fine-tune the model to maintain accuracy.
And after this step, there's a step or feedback loop.
Set up feedback loop where predictions and outcomes can be compared.
This feedback is crucial for continuously improving the model and catching any drift in data or changes in external conditions that affect the model.
And after this comes a last step that is legal and compliance checks.
Ensure all the data used by the model in production complies with privacy laws and regulations.
This is crucial for maintaining trust and legality, especially when handling sensitive information.
So by carefully planning and executing these steps, you can smoothly transition your machine learning model from a testing environment to a fully functional component of a production system.
So this was all about the question number five. Now moving to the question number six, that would be based on data-driven decision making.
And the question is your company wants to shift towards more data-driven decision making.
You have been tasked with developing a strategy to implement this.
What steps would you take to ensure that the data at all levels of the organization is utilized effectively to make informed decisions?
And what challenges might you face and how would you address them?
So you can start answering this by implementing a data-driven decision-making strategy that will require a comprehensive approach to ensure that
reliable data is accessible and effectively used across all levels of the organization.
And now we can develop and approach this strategy, and similarly, you could tell this strategy to the interviewer.
So the number one step will be assessing current data infrastructure.
Start by evaluating the existing data infrastructure to understand what data is available, how it is stored, and how it is currently used.
This assessment will help identify gaps in data collection, storage, and access that need to be addressed.
Now we'll move to the next step that is developing a data governance framework.
Implement a data governance framework that defines who can access data, how it can be used, and who is responsible for maintaining its quality.
This framework ensures data integrity and security, which are critical for making reliable decisions.
Now we'll move to the next step that is training and empowerment.
So train employees at all levels on the importance of data-driven decision making and provide them with the tools and knowledge necessary to analyze and interpret data.
This might include training sessions, workshops, and ongoing support to ensure everyone can use data effectively.
Now move to the next step that is implementing analytical tools.
So deploy user friendly analytical tools that can integrate seamlessly into the daily workflows of employees.
Tools like Tabuew, Microsoft Power BI, or even advanced Excel techniques can provide powerful data analysis capabilities without requiring extensive technical knowledge.
After this, we'll move to the step that would be creating a centralized data platform.
Developer centralized data platform where all organizational data can be accessed and analyzed. This platform should be scalable and secure, providing a single source of truth for the organization.
And then we have the promoting a data-driven culture. So foster culture that values data-driven decision making.
Encourage experimentation and learning from data-driven initiatives.
Celebrate successes and learn from failures to continually improve the use of data-driven in decision making.
And there would be some challenges and solutions for that.
So one major challenge we know here is resistance to change, as some employees may prefer traditional decision-making methods.
So address this by demonstrating the tangible benefits of data-driven decisions through pilot projects and success stories.
So data silos can also hinder effective data use, promote cross-department collaboration, and integrate disparate data sources to overcome this challenge.
After that, you can monitor and do continuous improvement.
So by systematically implementing these steps, you can transform your organization into one that leverages data at all levels to make informed and effective decisions.
And after answering in these steps, you could make the interior have a truth and a faith in you that you could make these models.
Now moving to the next question, that is question number seven, and that is based on handling large data sets.
And the question is your project involves analyzing extremely large data sets potentially exceeding terabytes in size.
What strategies would you use to manage and analyze such large data sets effectively?
Describe the tools and techniques you might employ, and you could start this with answering that working with large data sets, especially those in terabyte range,
presents unique challenges in terms of storage, processing, and analysis.
So we'll have a structured approach to handle these challenges effectively.
We'll start with the data storage that would be use distributed file systems.
Consider using a distributed file system like Hadoop Distributed File System, SDFS, or Amazon S3.
These systems are designed to store vast amounts of data across many servers, offering high availability and poor toll nets.
And then comes the next step that is data processing.
Leverage big data processing frameworks, tools like Apache Spark are ideal for processing large data sets because they handle distributed computing effectively.
Spark can perform data processing tasks much faster than traditional disk-based processing due to its in-memory computing capabilities.
And next we could start with efficient data sampling.
So there are many sampling techniques that we can use.
So when the data set is too large to handle, even with powerful tools, consider using data sampling techniques to reduce the size to a manageable level without losing significant insights.
Ensure that the sample represents the whole data set accurately.
And then comes optimization of data queries.
Indexing and partitioning. Optimize your data queries by implementing indexing and partitioning.
This can drastically reduce the time it takes to perform queries by limiting the amounts of data scan.
And then we can do scalable analytics. And then we'll move to the next step that is scalable analytics.
And in that, we could start with the parallel computing.
Use parallel computing capabilities of frameworks like Spark or DAS to analyze data across multiple nodes. This helps in scaling up your analytics operations to handle large data sets effectively.
And now we'll move to the cloud-based analytical tools.
So consider using cloud services like Google BigQuery or AWS Redshift, which are designed to handle massive datasets and complex analytics with ease.
And after this step, we'll move to data cleaning and pre-processing.
Here we will automate pre-processing tasks. We'll use automated tools to clean and pre-process data.
This includes handling missing values, normalizing data, and removing duplicates, which can be particularly challenging with large datasets.
And after this step, we'll move to the step that will visualize large dataset.
So we'll use specialized tools.
From more detailed exploration, tools like Protly or Bouquet can be used as they offer capabilities to interactively visualize large volumes of data.
And after that, there would be steps for regular maintenance and updates. That could be continuously monitoring.
The data quality. As new data comes in, you can continuously monitor its quality.
And after this step, you could integrate all these strategies and tools into your workflow, and you can effectively manage and extract valuable insights from extremely large data sets,
thereby supporting robust data-driven decision making.
And you could answer the whole strategy to the interviewer.
Now moving to the question number eight that is based on optimizing machine learning models.
And the question is during model development, you have noticed that your machine learning model is underperforming.
What steps would you take to diagnose the problem and optimize the model's performance? What techniques and tools would you use?
So you can answer this by starting with the optimizing, and optimizing a machine learning model that is underperforming involves several steps to diagnose and improve its accuracy and efficiency.
And here we will have a structured approach to tackle this issue.
And you could start this with the number one step that is diagnosing the program.
Evaluate model metrics.
Start by thoroughly evaluating the performance metrics of your model. For classification task, for classification task, look at accuracy, precision, recall, and the F1 score.
For regression task, consider R squared, mean squared error, that is MSE, and mean absolute error, that is ME.
And then you can move to the next step. That is, use plots like ROC curves for classification models and residual plots for regression to visually assess where the model is going wrong.
After that, we'll move to the next step that is data quality and quantity check.
Inspect the data. That is sometimes the quality and quantity of data can be the root cause of poor model performance. Ensure the data is clean, well pre-processed, and sufficient.
Look for issues like missing values, outliers or imbalanced classes.
And after this, we'll move to the feature engineering step that would be experiment with creating new features or transforming existing ones to provide better predictive power.
And then we have the next step that is model tuning and configuration.
Out of feature engineering, we'll move to the next step that is model tuning and configuration.
So hyperparameter tuning. Use techniques like grid search or random search to find the optimal settings for a model's parameters.
Tools like Sikit Learns, Grid Search CV, or randomized search CV can automate this process.
And there's a cross-validation that would implement cross-validation to ensure that the model's performance is consistent across different subsets of the data set.
And then we have the next step that is trying different models. So experiment with algorithms here.
If initial models are underperforming, try different algorithms that might be better suited for the problem.
For instance, if you started with linear regression and it's not performing well, consider more complex models like random forest or gradient boosting machines.
And after this, we have ensemble methods that we can use, techniques like bagging, boosting, or stacking to combine the predictions of multiple models to improve overall performance.
After this step, we have feature selection that includes reduce dimensionality.
Use techniques like principal component analysis, that is PCA, to reduce the number of features, which might help in improving model performance by removing noise and redundancy.
And then we have select important features.
So use model-based technique to identify and keep only the most important features that impact the outcome.
And then comes the last step that is regular updates and retraining.
So here you can monitor and update that could be continuously monitoring the model's performance over time.
As new data becomes available, update and retrain the model to adapt to any changes in underlying patterns.
And after that, you could have a consultation and collaboration work with the other teams.
And by methodically addressing each of these areas, you can diagnose why your machine learning model is underperforming and can take steps to optimize its accuracy and efficiency.
So this was all about question number eight. So let's start with the question number nine, and this is based on handling unstructured data.
So the question is you are given a large amount of unstructured data, including text, images, and videos.
What strategies would you use to manage and analyze this type of data effectively? Describe the tools and techniques you might employ.
So you can start answering this question by describing that dealing with unstructured data can be challenging due to its lack of predefined format or structure.
However, with the right strategies and tools, you can effectively manage and analyze it to extract valuable insights, and there will be an approach
how you can do that. So we will discuss the approach here and starting with the steps.
So the number one step will be data categorization and organization. So the number one step in this step will be sorting and tagging.
We will begin by categorizing the data into types that will be text, images, or videos.
Use tagging to add metadata, which helps in organizing the data and makes it easier to access and analyze later.
Then and after that, particularly for text data, we'll use natural language processing NLP. We will employ NLP techniques to extract useful information from text.
Tools like NLTK, Spacey, or even more advanced models like BERT can help you perform tasks such as sentiment analysis, entity
recognition, and topic modeling.
After that, we'll do text indexing.
We can use Elasticsearch or Apache Sol to index large volumes of text.
These tools provide powerful search capabilities and can handle complex queries efficiently.
And after that, we'll move to image data. And to structure image data, we'll use image processing.
We'll use libraries like OpenCV for basic image processing tasks such as filtering and transformations.
For more advanced image analysis, consider deep learning models using frameworks like TensorFlow or PyTorch.
And then we'll feature extraction, apply techniques to extract features from images such as edges, textures, or key points, which can be used for further analysis or machine learning.
And then we'll come to video data.
And here we'll do video processing and we'll use the tools like FmPEG that can be used for basic video processing tasks such as format conversion or extracting frames.
For analyzing video content, look at machine learning models that can classify or recognize activities in the video.
And after this, we'll move to temporal analysis. For videos, temporal components are important.
Techniques like sequence modeling or recurrent neural networks
can be useful to analyze sequences of frames for activities or events.
And then we'll move to data storage and management.
Here we'll use the given volume and complexity of unstructured data and use big data platforms like Hadoop or cloud services like AWS S3 for storage.
These platforms can scale up to handle large data sizes and provide the necessary infrastructure to store and retrieve unstructured data efficiently. And then we have visualization and reporting.
Custom dashboards that we'll create here will develop custom dashboards using tools like Tablo or Power BI, which can integrate different data types and provide a unified view of the analyzed data.
And after that, we will do data summarization. Tools that provide summarization capabilities can help in considering large volumes of unstructured data into more manageable and interpretable forms.
And after that, we'll leverage these strategies and tools and can effectively manage, analyze, and derive insights from unstructured data,
which can be crucial for making informed decisions in various applications. And this is the path that you can explore and explain to the interviewer if this question has been asked.
Now moving to the question number 10, and that will be based on scaling AI solutions in enterprise.
And the question is your company wants to scale its AI operations from a few initial pilot projects to enterprise-wide implementation.
What are the key considerations and steps you would take to ensure the successful scaling of AI solutions across the organization?
And what challenges might you face and how would you address them?
So you can start answering this question with the scaling AI solutions.
You could answer him that scaling AI solutions across an enterprise requires careful planning and strategic implementation to ensure success and alignment with business objectives.
And there should be a strategic approach to implement this.
So starting with the approach, and the number one step will be in that will be strategic alignment. So identify business objectives.
Start by identifying the business objectives that the AI solutions are intending to support.
This ensures that the AI initiatives are aligned with the company's strategic goals and can demonstrate clear business value.
And then comes the stakeholder engagement.
So engage stakeholders from various departments early in the process to gather input and build support. This helps in understanding diverse needs and ensures broader acceptance of the AI solutions.
And after that comes the infrastructure and technology.
So there's an option that is assess and upgrade infrastructure. Evaluate whether your current IT infrastructure can support the expanded use of AI.
You might need to upgrade hardware, invest in cloud solutions, or adopt technologies that facilitate AI processing and data handling. And after that, we have standardization of tools.
Standardize the tools and platforms used for AI development to ensure compatibility and ease of maintenance across the organizations.
And after that, we'll move to data management.
So robust data governance that is to implement a strong data governance framework to manage enterprise data effectively.
This includes policies for data quality, security, and compliance, especially important when scaling AI solutions that rely on vast amounts of data. And after that, we will come to data accessibility.
So ensure that data is accessible across the organization but also secure against unauthorized access.
This involves setting up secure data lakes or warehouses that centralize data while allowing controlled access. And then we come to the next step that is talent and training.
So build AI competency, that is, develop in-house AI expertise through training programs and hiring.
So this builds the necessary skills within the organization to develop, manage, and scale AI solutions.
And after that, you can also perform cross-functional AI teams that could be forming cross-functional teams that include data scientists, IT professionals, and domain experts.
So this fosters collaboration and ensures that AI solutions are developed with a comprehensive understanding.
And after forming these collaborative teams, we'll move to scalable deployment models.
So pilot test and phased rollout.
Before a full-scale rollout, conduct pilot tests to gauge the AI solution effectiveness and integration capabilities based on feedback,
adjust and then gradually deploy the solutions across the organization.
And then we have modular and flexible design.
So design AI systems to be modular and scalable, allowing for adjustments and expansions as needs, and then we'll monitor and do the continuous improvement.
So there will be performance metrics that would establish metrics to regularly assess the performance of AI systems.
We will monitor these systems to ensure they met expected outcomes and adapt as necessary.
And after that, we have next step that is addressing challenges.
So there could be cultural resistance that there could be employees that would be resisting to the changes.
But we have to address this through continuous education and by showcasing successful AI use cases within the organizations.
And by carefully considering these aspects and methodically implementing steps, you can successfully scale air solutions across your enterprise, driving significant business value and innovation.
And that's all for question number 10. Now we'll move to question number 11, and that is based on ethical considerations in data science.
So the question is in your data science projects, how do you ensure that ethical considerations are addressed?
Describe the steps you take to identify and mitigate ethical risk in your projects.
What frameworks or guidelines do you follow?
So you could start answering this question with ethical considerations that they're crucial in data science to ensure that the solutions and analysis do not advertently cause harm or bias.
Here's how you can ensure that.
So there are some steps, and we will discuss those steps, starting with the number one.
That is, educate on ethical standards. So stay informed about the ethical standards in data science, such as fairness, accountability, transparency, and privacy.
Organizations like the Data Science Association and the ACM have codes of ethics that we refer to as guidelines.
And then we have ethical risk assessment.
Identify potential ethical issues that would be at the beginning of each project, conduct a thorough assessment to identify any potential ethical risk,
such as biases in data or impact on vulnerable groups.
This involves reviewing the source of data, the methodologies used for data collection, and the intended use of the data analytics results.
And then we have stakeholder analysis.
Engage with stakeholders to understand the diverse perspectives and potential impact of the project.
This helps in identifying ethical issues that may not be apparent from a purely technical standpoint. And then we'll move to mitigation strategies.
Implementing bias mitigation techniques, we will use statistical and machine learning techniques to detect and mitigate biases in data.
This might involve techniques like resampling, reweighing, or using algorithms designed to be fair.
And then we have privacy preserving methods.
Employ methods such as data anonymization, encryption, or differential privacy to protect individual privacy when analyzing sensitive data.
Then we have other methods that is transparency and explainability.
There we have model explainability, and after that, coming to documentation and reporting.
So we have to maintain thorough documentation of data sources, model decisions and methodologies.
And then we have continuous monitoring and feedback.
There you have to monitor outcomes and the feedback mechanisms should be applied.
And then we have the panels, that is collaboration and advisory panels.
Then we have ethical review boards.
So for complex projects, setting up or consulting with an ethical review board can provide oversight and diverse perspectives on the ethical implications of project methodologies.
So by proactively addressing ethical considerations through these steps, you can ensure that your data science projects uphold high ethical standards and
positively contribute to society while minimizing harm.
So this was all about question 11. Now moving to question number 12 that is based on time series forecasting for business decisions.
So the question number 12 is you are tasked with forecasting monthly sales for a retail company using time series data from the past five years.
What steps would you take to prepare and analyze this data to make accurate forecasts?
What specific tools or techniques would you use and why? So we can start answering this by time series forecasting.
And we could address them that it's a powerful tool for predicting future events based on past data, especially in business contexts like retail sales.
So we will have a structured approach here and we'll start with data collection and cleaning.
First, we will gather data and ensure that you have collected all relevant data, including monthly sale figures from the past five years,
and also considering including external factors that might affect sales, such as economic indicators, holidays, and promotional activities.
And then we'll proceed to clean data. We will check for and handle any inconsistencies or missing values.
And then we have data visualization.
This will help in identifying patterns, trends, and seasonality.
And then we have decomposition of data. So there's a seasonal decomposition, and we'll use statistical techniques to decompose the data into trend seasonally and asiduals.
So this can be accomplished with tools like the seasonal decompose function from the stats models library in Python.
And we'll understand these components separately and can improve the accuracy of our forecast.
And then the next step is model selection and forecasting.
So there are two models that is ARIMA and SARIMA models. So we have to choose appropriate forecasting models based on data's characteristics.
For instance, ARIMA, that is auto-regressive integrated moving average.
It is effective for non-season data, while SARIMA, that is seasonal ARIMA, that is suitable for data with seasonal patterns.
And after choosing the model, we will move to cross-validation. We will implement time series specific cross-validation techniques like time-based splitting to evaluate model performance.
And this will ensure your model generalizes well on unseen data.
And then we have model fitting and diagnostics.
We will fit the model, that is, by using the Cinemax class from stat models that will fit your model to the data.
And then we will carefully select parameters based on AIC, that is, ACAC information criterion.
That scores or thorough grid research technique.
And then we can do the diagnostics and forecast and validation.
And after forecast validation, we'll move to iterative improvement.
So there's a feedback loop that should be mandatory, and there should be a regular update for the model with new sales data and refining the model as needed.
So this continuous improvement cycle helps adapt to changing patterns in sales data.
And by following these steps and using these tools, you can create robust forecasts that help the retail company plan better and make informed decisions.
So this was all about question number 12. Now move to question number 13, that is, based on customer segmentation using machine learning.
So the question is you are given a data set containing demographic and purchasing behavior data for a group of customers.
Your task is to segment these customers into distinct groups based on similarities in the purchasing behavior and demographics.
So what steps would you take to perform this segmentation and can you provide a sample Python code snippet to illustrate the initial stages of data handling and modal application?
So we can start this by explaining customer segmentation, that is a powerful approach to tailor marketing strategies and improve customer service by
identifying distinct groups based on their behavior and characteristics. And here also we have a detailed approach for this task.
So we'll start with number one step that would be data exploration and pre-processing.
So there will be initial exploration, that is beginning by examining the data set to understand the features available such as age, income,
purchase frequency, etc. Then we'll look for missing values or anomalies and decide how to handle them.
That could be using imputation.
And then we'll move to feature engineering.
We will create new features that might be useful for segmentation, such as customer lifetime value or average transaction amount.
We will also use normalization, that is, normalize the data to ensure that one feature doesn't disproportionately influence the model due to its scale.
We will use standard scaling or min-max scaling as appropriate.
So then we will come to the next step that is choosing the segmentation technique.
And here we have K-means clustering.
So this is a popular method for customer segmentation.
Here we'll decide on the number of clusters by using techniques like the ALBO method or Silverte analysis to determine the optimal cluster count.
And then we have model implementation, and in that we will use data preparation and we'll prepare the data by selecting the relevant features and applying any final transformations.
And then we have model fitting.
We'll fit the k-means clustering model to the data and evaluate and interpret analyzing clusters.
And after analyzing clusters, we'll move to the next step that is strategic insights.
We will provide actionable insights based on cluster characteristics such as targeted marketing strategies for each segment.
And then we have iterative refinement that is feedback incorporation, and we'll use business feedback to refine the segmentation.
If additional data becomes available, incorporate it to enhance the model.
And now we'll see the sample Python code.
So for this, first we'll import the libraries and modules. As you can see on the screen, we have imported pandas, random forest classifier, train test split, standard scalar, classification report.
And after that, we will load the data.
And for that, we have used the pandas to read the data, that is read underscore SSV.
And after that, we are processing the data that is data pre processing, we are handling missing values and using the forward fill or FIL to fill missing values in the data set.
And then we are featuring scaling, that is normalizing the selected features that is feature one, feature two, and feature three using standard scalar.
And then we'll move to the next step that is data splitting. We'll split the data set into training and testing sets.
So that test size equal to 0.2 parameters specifies that 20% of the data will be used for testing.
And then we'll train the model, we'll initialize and train a random forest classifier with 100 trees and a random state for reproductibility.
And then we'll evaluate the model, we'll make predictions on the test set that is X underscore test using the train model and print a classification report showing precision,
recall, F1 score, and support for each class.
So this code demonstrates the process of loading, pre-processing, training, and evaluating a machine learning model that is random forest classifier
for predicting equipment failures in a manufacturing plant.
The use of techniques such as data pre-processing and splitting along with the random forest classifier highlights a standard flow for building predictive maintenance models.
So this was all about the question number 13. So now moving to the question number 14 that is based on predictive customer churn.
And the question is you are tasked with developing a model to predict which customers are likely to churn from a subscription service.
So what steps will you take to build this model and can you provide a sample Python code to illustrate the data preparation and model training process?
So we'll start answering this question about depicting what is predicting customer churn.
So predicting customer churn is crucial for businesses to implement detention strategies proactively.
And we'll have a detailed approach for building a predictive model for this purpose, starting with data collection and exploration.
And in this we will collect data, and after that, we'll perform the exploratory data analysis that is EDM. We'll perform an initial analysis to understand patterns and trends.
And then we have feature engineering, we'll create new features and derive new features that might influence churn, such as change in usage, pattern, or service upgrades,
and then we'll handle the missing values if we found any. And then we'll encode categorial variables.
We'll use techniques like one hot encoding or label encoding for categorial variables.
And then we have scale features to normalize or standardize numerical features to ensure they contribute equally to the model's performance.
And then we'll select the model, that is, we'll choose the appropriate model and start with for the knowing handling binary classification task.
That could be with logistic regression, random forest, or gradient boosting machines.
And after selecting the model, we'll train the model and evaluate it.
So fit your model on the training data, and after that, evaluate the model using appropriate metrics like accuracy, precision, recall, advanced score,
and ROC to gauge its performance.
And then we'll optimize the model using hyperparameter tuning.
We'll optimize the model parameter using grid search or random search to improve performance.
And then we have feature importance that is analyze and rank features by their importance in predicting churn to refine the model further.
And then and then the last step is deployment and monitoring.
We'll deploy the model.
Once validated, deploy the model into production environment where it can predict real-time churn.
So after deploying the model, regularly monitor the model to ensure it remains effective over time as new data comes in.
So now we'll see the sample Python code for this example.
So starting with the importing of libraries, we will import pandas, numpy, scikit learn, sklearn, tensorflow, and the tensorflow
keras and callbacks.
And after importing the modules, we'll start with data loading. We'll load the dataset from a CSV file named equipment underscore data.csv and that too with the pandas data frame.
And after that, we'll do the data preprocessing, we'll handle missing values, and for that we'll use forward fill to fill missing values in the dataset.
And then we have feature scaling that will normalize the selected features that is feature one, feature two, feature three, using standard scalar.
And after that, we'll use the data splitting.
We'll split the dataset into training and testing sets.
And the test size will be equal to 0.2.
And this parameter specifies that 20% of the data will be used for testing.
And after that, we'll start with building the model.
First, we'll see sequential model that initializes a sequential model technique.
And then we have dense layers that adds two dense layers with 64 units and RELU activation function.
Then we have dropout layers that adds two dropout layers with a dropout rate of 0.5 to reduce overfitting.
After that, we'll do the model compilation, we'll compile the model using the Adam optimizer and binary crossentropy loss function for binary classification.
And there will be an early stopping that will define an early stopping callback to stop training when the validation loss metric has stopped improving after three
books.
And after training the model, we will evaluate the model and evaluating the model on the test data and print the loss and accuracy metrics.
So this code demonstrates the process of loading, pre-processing, building, compiling, training, and evaluating a deep learning model using TensorFlow and Keras
for predicting equipment failures in a manufacturing plant.
So the use of techniques such as data pre-processing, dropout, regularization, and early stopping helps in building a robust deep learning model for predictive maintenance.
So that's all with question number 14. Now we'll start with question number 15 that is based on deep learning in NLP.
And your question is you are tasked with developing a sentiment analysis model using deep learning to understand customer opinions from reviews. So what steps would you take to build this model?
And can you provide a sample Python code snippet to illustrate how you would pre-process data and train a simple deep learning model?
So we'll start answering this with sentiment analysis.
That sentiment analysis using deep learning allows businesses to coach customer sentiment from text data like reviews or comments effectively.
And we'll have a detailed approach for building a sentiment analysis model. We'll start with data collection and cleaning.
We'll collect the data, gather a substantial data set of text reviews and their associated sentiments, typically labeled as positive, negative, or neural.
And then we'll clean the data, pre-process the data by removing noise such as HTML tags, special characters, and so words.
And we'll normalize the text by converting into lowercase. And then we have text preprocessing.
We'll convert text into tokens, words or phrases.
And then we have vectorization that transforms tokens into numerical format using techniques like word embeddings or TFIDF that is term frequency inverse document frequency.
And then we'll use the padding. And then we have the option of model selection.
We'll choose a model architecture based on a basic approach and use a RNN or more advanced architecture like LSTM that is
long short-term memory or GRU that is catered recurrent units, which are effective for sequence data like text.
And then we have model training.
We'll compile the model, define the model architecture, and compile it with the loss function suited for classification like categorical, cross entropy,
and an optimizer like Adam.
And then we'll train the model, we'll fit the model on our pre-processed data.
We'll evaluate and optimize it.
Evaluating model performance here use the metrics such as accuracy, precision, recall, and F1 score to assess the model.
And then we have hyperparameter tuning. We'll optimize the model by adjusting parameters like learning rate, number of layers, and units per layer. And then coming to deployment.
We'll deploy the model and integrate the model into the existing review processing pipeline so it can automatically classify new reviews.
So let's see the sample Python code and we'll have a basic approach for that.
Here we'll import numpy tensor flow sequential embedding LSTM dense dropout.
So embedding converts positive integers that is indexes into dense factors of fixed size and LSTM that is long short-term memory layer
that is used for learning dependencies in sequence data.
And then we have dense that is a regularly densed connected NN layer.
And then we will import pad underscore sequences.
And after that, we have the data set and the sample text data representing customer reviews that will store in variable text.
And then we have labels that has binary labels indicating sentiment one for positive, zero for negative.
And now we'll start with the pre processing of data.
Here we have declared that tokenizer. We will initialize a tokenizer that will help only the top thousand most frequent words.
And then we have fit underscore on underscore text that is update the internal vocabulary based on the list of text.
It essentially creates a dictionary of word to index pairs. And then we have text to sequences that will transform each text in text to a sequence of integers.
And then we have pad sequences that will ensure all sequences have the same length by padding shorter sequences with zeros up to the maximum length. And then we'll start building the model.
Here we have sequential model that will set up a linear stack of layers, and then we have embedding layer that will map each word index to an embedding vector of size 64.
So the input length is set to 10, that is the length of the input sequences.
Then we'll start with LSTM layers.
So two LSTM layers are added. The first one returns sequences to allow the next LSTM layer to process these sequences.
And after that, we have the dropout layer that applies dropout with a rate of 0.5 with the first LSTM layer to reduce overfitting.
And after that, we'll come to dense layer that has output of a single scalar that represents the predicted settlement and using sigmoid activation to output a probability.
And now we'll start with model compilation and training.
So we'll configure the model for training and we'll use binary cross entropy as the loss function that is suitable for binary classification and the atom optimizer
and tracks constantly accuracy as a metric.
And then we have the fit that trains the model for a specified number of epochs, that is, iterations or the entire dataset. And then we'll predict the model.
That is after training, the model can predict the sentiment of the reviews in the dataset.
This is useful for checking how the model performs on the training data itself.
So this breakdown explains each step of the coding process, detailing how the data is prepared and how the model is configured.
And then we'll compile it and use for training and prediction. So its detailed explanation should help in understanding how to implement a simple LSTA model for sentiment analysis in TensorFlow.
Now moving to the question number 16.
So let's start with question number 16 that is based on anomaly detection in transaction data.
So the question is you are tasked with identifying unusual transactions in a company's financial data that might suggest fraudlend activity.
So what steps would you take to develop an anomaly detection model and can you provide a sample Python code snippet to illustrate how you would pre-process the
data and apply an anomaly detection technique?
So we'll start answering this with anomaly detection technique.
That is anomaly detection is essential for preventing fraud by identifying transactions that deviate significantly from typical patterns.
And now we'll see the structured approach to building an anomaly detection model for transaction data.
We'll start with data collection and cleaning and we'll collect all the compiling transaction data, which should include details like transaction amount, time, user ID, and transaction type.
Then we'll move to feature engineering and develop features that capture the essence of transaction such as time of day and the day of the week.
And then we have data normalization.
We'll use scaling techniques such as min-max scaling or standardization to ensure that the model is perfectly normalized.
And then we have choosing the anomaly detection technique.
So here we have to choose the technique which is effective for high-dimensional data sets and works for isolating anomalies instead of profiling normal data points.
After choosing the anomaly technique, we'll train anomaly identification, we'll fit the chosen model to the data,
and the anomalies that would have been chosen will be those transactions that the model identifies.
And after this, we come to the last step that is review and action.
Here we have manual review, that is, transactions flagged as potential anomalies should be reviewed manually to confirm fraudulent activity.
And then we have continuous improvement.
That is, we can regularly update the model with the new data and feedback from the review process to improve accuracy.
And now moving to the prediction that is, after training the model, we can predict the sentiment of the reviews in the dataset.
And this is useful for checking how the model performs on the training data itself.
Now we'll see the Python code to see how you can set up this model for anomaly detection.
We'll start by importing the libraries and module, and after that, we'll load and prepare data.
That is, we'll load transaction data from a CSV file into the Pandas data frame.
And after that, we'll convert that transaction time column to date time format, which allows the extraction of additional time-based features.
And after that, we'll perform feature engineering that will extract the hour of the day from the transaction time column.
This feature can be important as transactions occurring at unusual hours may be indicative of fraud.
And then we'll move to the normalization of data.
This will apply standard scaling to the amount and hour of the day feature.
This normalization process involves subtracting the mean and dividing by the standard deviation for each feature,
ensuring that the feature contributes equally to the analysis and improving the performance of many machine learning algorithms.
And after that, we'll start with anomaly detection with isolation forest.
That's a technique.
We will initialize an isolation forest model with 100 trees, that is, n estimators equal to 100, setting the proportions of outliers,
that is, contamination, to 1% of the data. So this parameter is crucial as it influences the threshold of marking and observation as an anomaly.
Then we'll fit the model to the scaled amount and R of the D data and predict the anomaly status for each transaction.
And then we'll start with filter and display anomalies.
We'll filter out transactions identified as anomalies, that is, anomaly equal or equal to minus one.
We'll display these transactions which can be reviewed manually to determine if they represent actual float lent activity.
So this code snippet provides a systematic approach to detecting anomalies in transaction data, leveraging the isolation forest
algorithm's ability to handle complex and high-dimensional data set effectively.
So the pre-processing steps ensured that the data is appropriately formatted and normalized for optional model performance.
So this was all about question number 16. Now moving to question number 17, and that is based on integrating machine learning models into web applications.
And your question is you have developed a machine learning model to predict real estate prices based on various features like location, size, and amenities.
How would you integrate this model into a web application to allow users to get real-time price predictions?
Can you provide a sample Python code snippet to illustrate how you would prepare the model for integration and handle user request?
So, starting with the approach that is integrating a machine learning model into a web application, this will involve several steps to ensure the model is accessible and perform
well in a live environment.
So here's how you can approach this task.
We could divide into steps and we'll start with number one step that is model preparation.
We'll finalize and save the model.
So once your model is trained and validated, save it using a format that can be easily loaded into a web application.
So Python's Pickle module or TensorFlow's same model format are commonly used for this purpose.
Then we can use web application backend setup.
For this, select a suitable web framework.
So Flask is popularly known for its simplicity and effectiveness in integrating Python-based machine learning models.
And after that, we'll develop the API.
After developing the API within your Flask app, that you can receive user inputs for model features, load the model, make prediction, and return the result.
And after this, we'll develop the UI.
We'll design a user-friendly interface, we'll create a simple and intuitive UI that lets users input the feature like location, size, and submit them for prediction.
And after that, we'll move to the deployment phase.
We'll use a cloud platform like Heroku, AWS, or Google Cloud to deploy your Flask application.
And then we have the maintenance and updates. We'll monitor and update regularly for the performance and use the model as needed based on user feedback.
So now moving to the Python code and see how this model can be created.
So here we'll start importing the libraries and module, and we are using Flask, Prequel, and JSONify.
And we will start with app initialization.
We'll initialize a new Flask web application that would be a special variable which gives Python files a unique name to differentiate between them when they are important
into other scripts.
And after that, we'll load the model. So loading a pretend machine learning model from the file system. So this model is assumed to be saved in the same directory as this script.
So the model is loaded in RB mode, which stands for read binary.
And after that, we'll move to API route and prediction function. So we will define an API endpoint at predict that listens for post request.
This is the URL that the front end of the web application will call to send data to the backend.
And after that, we'll start with predicting the function.
And here we have extract features that retrieves data sent into the JSON format from the POST request.
That is request.get underscore JSON and the force we have set it as true here and forcefully formats the request data into JSON
ensuring compatibility.
And then we'll extract the relevant features that is location, size, and amenities from the JSON object and store them in a list as expected by the model.
And after preparing the features, we'll make the prediction, we'll use the loaded model to make a prediction based on the provided feature. And then we have the return prediction method.
Here we will convert the prediction result into JSON format using JSON Ify and send it back to the client, and this will ensure that the response can be easily handled by the client application.
So this was all about the question number 17.
Now moving to the question number 18, that is based on analyzing. And now we'll move to the question number 18 that is based on analyzing geospathical data.
And your question is you are tasked with analyzing geospathical data to help a city improve its public transportation system.
The data includes GPS coordinates of bus stops, ridership numbers, and traffic patterns. What steps would you take to analyze this data?
And can you provide a sample Python code snippet to illustrate how you might visualize bus stop location and ridership?
So you can start answering this question that JUISPAL data analysis can provide critical insights into how effectively a public transportation system serves its
city and guide improvements.
And there's a detailed approach for this, and we can start with data preparation, and in this, we'll do data collection and data cleaning.
And after this step, we'll move to the next step that is exploratory data analysis.
And in this, we'll have statistical summary, we'll generate descriptive statistics, and then we have correlation analysis.
And after moving that, we have geospatial visualization that is mapping bus stop. We'll plot the locations of bus stop on a map to visually assess their distribution across the city.
And after that, we have heat maps that will create ridership data to identify hot sports and areas with potential service gaps.
And after geospatial visualization, we'll move with spatial analysis.
We have proximity analysis that will analyze the proximity of bus stop to key areas like commercial centres or residential areas.
And now moving to the fifth step that is optimization and recommendation.
So we'll have a route optimization that will suggest modifications to route based on traffic patterns and ridership demand
and the policy recommendations that will provide actionable recommendations for improving bus frequencies.
Now moving to the sample Python code where we can define this model and use it accordingly.
And here we will start importing the libraries and modules, and here we'll start with importing geo pandas and matprolib.pyplot.
And after importing, we'll start with data loading.
So we will declare a variable bus underscore stops and load the bus stops data from a shape file. So shapefiles are popular geospatial vector data formats for geographic information system software.
And then we have the ridership that will load ridership data from a CSV file, which includes columns for longitude, latitude, and ridership levels.
And after that, we'll create geodata frame that will convert the ridership data frame into a geodata frame.
And this step involves creating a geometry column from the longitude and latitude columns.
And then we have the plotting one.
Here we will plot the graphs that would be figures and axis and create a figure for the single subplot with the specified size that is 10 x
10 inches.
And then we have city underscore map.plot.
It is assumed that there is a base map of the city loaded as a geodata frame named City Map.
This is plotted first with the light gray color to serve as a background for the other layers.
So this was all about question number 18. Now moving to question number 19 that is based on predictive maintenance using machine learning.
And the question is you are tasked with developing a predictive maintenance system for a manufacturing plant that relies heavily on automated machinery.
So the data available includes machine operational parameters, maintenance history, and failure incidents.
What steps would you take to develop a predictive model and can you provide a sample Python code?
So you can start with predictive maintenance that is essential in manufacturing as it helps prevent equipment failures, reducing downtime and maintenance cost.
And here you have a detailed approach or predictive model for this, starting with data collection and integration.
Then you can do EDA, that is exploratory data analysis, and then we can perform feature engineering and then move to data pre-processing tasks
and then the selection model and training. And after that, we have model evaluation and deployment technique that we can do for the model using appropriate metrics such as precision, recall, and F1
score.
So this was all about question number 19. So now move to question number 20 that is based on personalization using machine learning.
And your question is you are tasked with developing a machine learning model to personalize content recommendations for users on a media streaming platform.
The data available includes user demographic details, viewing history and ratings.
So what steps would you take to build a model for personalized recommendations? And can you provide a sample Python code for that?
So you can start answering this with creating a personalized recommendation system.
This would be essential for engaging users by providing content that is relevant to their interest.
And there will be a systematic approach or personalized content recommendation.
We'll start with data collection and integration, and after that, we'll perform EDA that is explorative data analysis, and then we have feature engineering.
In this we'll interact features and the temporal features.
We'll include time-based features to capture trends and seasonality in viewing behavior.
And then we'll select the model that is by collaborative filtering and hybrid models. And then we'll train the model and validation and implement and monitor them.
Learning objectives.
In this lesson, we are going to explain the concepts of linear algebra, solve a linear system of equations, describe matrix,
forms of matrix and matrix operations, and define vectors and list down its properties.
Introduction to linear algebra.
Linear algebra.
Linear algebra refers to study of linear combinations.
For linear transformations to be carried out, a study of vector spaces, lines, and planes, as well as some mappings
is necessary.
It contains linear functions, vectors, and matrices.
It is an examination of characteristic of linear set transformations, linear equations.
Linear algebra's major goal is to establish systematic techniques for solving systems of linear equations.
A linear equation with $n$ variables can be represented as
$a_1x_1$ plus $a_2x_2 $, plus $a_3x_3$ and so on.
till $a _n x_n$ equals to $b $, where $x_1, x_2, x_3 ,$ and so on. till $x_n$ are the unknown quantities that are to be found.
While a1, a2, a3, and so on, until an are the coefficients.
b here is a constant term.
A linear equation with two variables, x and y is a linear connection between x and y.
The value of one variable often y is determined by the value of the other.
That is x.
The independent variable in this situation is x while the term dependent variable refers to y.
Since it depends on x, let's consider some examples for linear equations.
Linear equations in one variable can be written as 3x plus 5 equals 0, or 3 by 2 of x plus 7 equals to 0,
or 98x equals to 49.
Linear equations in two variables.
Examples can include y plus 7x equals to 3, or 3a plus 2b equals to 5,
6x plus 9, y minus 12 equals to 0.
Linear equations can also be written with 3 variables as x plus y plus z equals to 0.
a minus 3b equals to c.
3x plus 12y equals to half of z,
identifying linear and nonlinear equations.
Linear equations present themselves as a straight line on a graph.
However, nonlinear equations represent themselves as a non-straight line on the graph.
Here, equations like y equals to 8x minus 9
or y plus 3x minus 1 equals to 0 are examples of linear equations.
However, y equals to x square minus 7 is a nonlinear equation, because x is raised to the power 2.
Hence, denoting a nonlinear relationship or a non-straight line relationship between x and y.
Similarly, square root of y plus x equals to 6 or y raised to the power 2 minus x equals to 9
are examples of nonlinear equations as y is raised to the power half and 2 respectively.
Forms of linear equation.
Linear equations can be represented in three forms, a standard form, a slope intercept form, or a point slope form.
Linear equation in standard form.
A linear equation in standard form for a single variable can be represented as a x plus b equals to zero, where a and b are real integers and x is the variable.
While a linear equation in standard form for two variable can be represented as ax plus by equals two c
where ab and c are real integers, while x and y are the variables.
To summarize a linear equation for variables can be written as
ax plus by equals to c where x and y are the variables.
Linear equation in the slope intercept form.
A linear equation slope can be calculated to see how one variable varies in response to a unit change.
In another variable, it is represented as y equals to mx plus b,
where m is the slope, b is the intercept on the y axis and x, and y are the line's distance from the x and the y axis
respectively.
Consider this example.
The lines point at x, y represents the distance from the x and the y-axis respectively,
while the line intercept on the y-axis is at point zero, b.
Linear equation slope.
The slope indicates how steep a line is with respect to y-axis.
When seen from left to right, it indicates whether the line goes up or down.
The slope describes how independent variable has been changed, while the dependent variable is changing.
Types of slope.
There are four types of slopes based on the relationship between the two variables x and y.
The first is the positive slope appear as x increases.
Y is also increasing in a negative slope as x increases.
Y decreases.
If a line is parallel to x-axis, it is a zero slope.
On the other hand, if the line is parallel to y-axis, then the slope is undefined.
Linear equation in point slope form.
A straight line is represented in point slope form by its slope, and a point on the line.
It is represented as y minus y1 equals to m of x minus x1,
where x1 and y1 are the coordinates of the point.
Linear equation forms some examples.
Consider solving the linear equation given as 2x minus 10 divided by 2 equals to 3x minus 1.
First we will clear the fraction.
In this example, we can see only left hand side we have 2x minus 10 divided by 2.
If from the numerator we take 2 as common,
we will be left with 2 times x minus 5 divided by 2, hence x minus 5 on the left hand side.
On the right hand side, we still have 3 times x minus 1.
Now, as a part of next step, we simplify both sides of the equation that has open up the brackets.
When we do that on the right side, we end up getting 3x minus 3 by multiplying 3 to x minus 1.
Solving further, we can write as x equals to 3x plus 2.
Finally, we try to clear the fraction to solve for x.
We can rearrange the equation as x minus 3x equals to 2.
Solving it further, we get minus 2x equals to 2.
And then we solve for x as minus 1.
System of linear equation.
A system of linear equations is a finite collection of linear equations, usually involving the same variables.
It can be represented as a11x1 plus a12x2, and so on equals to b1 A21x1 plus A22X2,
so on equals to B2 and so on.
Here this example is for n variables.
A system of m equations.
A linear system can have unlimited number of solutions, one solution or no solution at all.
In case of a single linear equation, a consistent linear system has a solution while an inconsistent linear system has no solution.
Solving a linear equation.
Solving linear system of equations.
Various methods can be used to solve linear systems of equations, which include graphic method, substitution method,
linear combination or elimination method, or a matrix method.
Graphing method.
Let's try and solve these two linear equations using the graphic method.
The first equation is defined as y equals 0.5x plus 2.
And the second equation is y equals to minus 2x minus 3.
The two equations as we can see are in the slope intercept form.
The first line has a slope of 0.5 and a y-intercept of positive 2, while the second line has a slope of negative 2 and a y
intercept of negative 3.
Let's have a look at these lines through a plot.
Here, the blue line is the first line represented by y equals 0.5x plus 2.
And the red line is represented by y equals to negative 2 of x negative 3.
These two lines intersect at a point at negative 2,1.
Hence we can say that x equals to negative 2 and y equals to 1.
Solving systems of linear equation using substitution.
For substitution we start by putting one of the equations in the form of variable equals to.
We then substitute that variable in the other equation in its place.
Take the other equation to solve.
If there are more than two variables involved, we repeat the process from steps 1 through 3.
Let's consider an example.
Let's consider the equation 3x plus 2y equals to 19 and x plus y equals to 8.
We could begin with any equation and variable.
In this case, let's look at the second equation with variable y.
We start with subtracting x from both sides of x plus y equals to 8.
And we end up getting y equals to 8 minus x.
The first equation still retains its form.
Now we take the value of y that is 8 minus x and substitute in the first equation in place of y.
We end up getting the equation 3x plus 2 times 8 minus x equals to 19.
We further simplify and solve this equation using algebra method to get 3x plus 16 minus 2x equals 290.
We solve this equation further, and we end up getting x plus 16 equals to 19, and finally x equals to 3.
Now we take the value of x and substitute in the new reformed second equation as y equals to 8 minus x.
That gives us y equals to 8 minus 3, hence y equals to 5.
The final answer remains x equals to 3 and y equals to 5.
Solving systems of linear equation using elimination.
In this case, we start by multiplying an equation by a constant anything other than 0.
We then add or subtract an equation onto the other equation.
Let's consider the same example of 3x plus 2 y equals 219 and x plus y equals 8.
We first start by multiplying the second equation by 2,
and we get 2x plus 2, y equals 216.
Now we subtract the second equation from the first equation.
That is 3x minus 2x,
2y minus 2y, and 19 minus 60.
On solving this, we end up getting x equals to 3.
Now using these steps of substitution, we put the value of x in the original second equation, that is x plus y equals to 8,
and achieve a value of y equals to 5.
Hence the answer remains x equals to 3 and y equals to 5.
We can verify the solution by using the graph.
Here again, the blue line represents the point at which 3x plus 2y equals to 19 is true,
while the red line represents the point where x plus y equals to eight is true.
The solution is found at the point where x equals to three
and y equals to five.
This is the point where both lines intersect.
Introduction to matrices
Matrix.
A matrix is rectangular array or table with rows and columns of numbers, symbols, expressions
used to represent a mathematical object or an attribute.
For example, here A is a matrix of two rows and three columns
as two one three minus one, two, and four.
Well, B is a squared matrix with two rows and two columns given as two, one, three, four.
Matrix size.
The matrix size is expressed as M cross n, where m is the number of rows, and n is the number of columns.
A matrix with two rows and three columns can be referred to as two by three matrix or a two cross three matrix,
or a matrix of dimension two cross three.
Notation of a matrix.
A matrix with m rows and n columns can be presented as this.
Here each element will be identified by its row number and column number.
For example, the element over here is in the third row and the first column.
Hence it is identified as a 3 1.
Forms of matrix.
The matrix is termed as a squared matrix.
If n equals to m, that is the number of rows and number of columns are equal.
An element's entry in the matrix of from AI i is located on the diagonal.
Hey is called a diagonal matrix.
If heij equals to zero,
when i is not equal to j,
that is in a square matrix.
Apart from diagonal at all places, we have zero as a value.
Matrix operations.
Addition.
Addition of two matrices is adding their corresponding elements, as in A11 plus B11, A12
plus B12, A21 plus B21,
A22 plus B22, and so on.
Consider the example over here.
We have a matrix A as 22, 32, 11, 16, and matrix B as 13, 8, 13, and 16.
Matrix A is of the order 2 cross 2, and matrix B is also of the same order, 2 cross 2.
Hence the corresponding elements can be quickly added as 22 plus 13,
32 plus 8,
11 plus 13, and 16 plus 16, giving us the result in matrix of 35, 40, 24,
and 32.
Addition rules.
Only matrices with the same size can be added.
That is the two matrices should have the same number of rows and same number of columns.
Matrix addition follows commutative property.
That means A plus B is equal to B plus A.
Subtraction.
Matrix subtraction is the same as matrix addition.
It is subtracting the corresponding values.
Let's consider the same example of matrix A and B.
The result of A minus B can be given as 22 minus 13.
That is A11 minus B11.
32 minus 8.
That is A12-B12, 11 minus 13, A21-B21, and 16-16,
that is A22 minus B22,
giving us result as 9, 24, negative 2, and 0.
Subtraction rules.
Only matrices with the same number of rows and columns can be subtracted.
Matrix subtraction does not follow commutative property.
That means A minus B is not equals to B minus A.
Multiplication.
Matrix multiplication results in what is called as a product matrix.
In matrix multiplication, each row of the first matrix is multiplied to each column of the second matrix.
To compute each of these elements in the matrix, the values are then added.
For example,
consider the matrix A and B.
To get the first element, we will multiply the first row of matrix A to the first column of matrix B,
and then add the individual elements, that is 22 multiply to 13, and 32 multiplied to 13,
and then add them up to get this particular element.
For the second element, we multiply the first row of A to the second column of B,
hence getting 22 multiplied to 8 plus 32 multiplied to 16.
Similarly, we compute all the remaining elements, that is the second row multiplied to the first column,
and added 11 multiplied to 13 plus 16 multiplied to 13.
And the second row now multiplied to the second column, that is 11 multiplied to 8 plus 16 multiplied to 16.
This gives us the resulting matrix as 702, 688, 351, and 344
multiplication rules.
Let us say C equals to AB.
Here C is our product matrix,
which can be computed as summation over A at Ij. Bjk
for a matrix of size ij matrix B of size JK
to calculate the value of each member
in the i cross k matrix of C.
The matrix product AB is defined only when the number of columns in A equals to the number of rows in B.
The matrix product of BA is defined only when the number of columns in B is equals to the number of rows in a
A.B is not always equals to B.A.
Transpose.
A transpose is a matrix form by turning all the rows of a given matrix into the columns and vice versa.
The transpose of a matrix A is denoted as AT.
For example, if the matrix A is 22, 32, 11, and 16, the transpose of A would be 22,
11, 32, and 16.
Here we can see the row has been converted to column.
Inverse, if it is a non-singular square matrix,
there exists N cross N matrix, a minus one known as A's inverse,
that satisfies A dot. A inverse
equals to A inverse.a equals to I,
where I is the identity matrix.
And identity matrix is characterized as a diagonal's one and all other elements are zero.
Also A B equals to B dot A
equals to In
where I N denotes the N cross N identity matrix
special matrix types.
Symmetric matrix, a matrix A is set to be symmetric.
If A is equals to transpose of A, diagonal matrix, A matrix D is diagonal only if Dij
equals to zero.
For all i not equals to J,
identity matrix.
Identity matrix is denoted as ion, where a ion equals to ion dot a equals to a
tensors.
Tensors are arrays with more than two axes.
A tensor can have in dimensions.
AijK is the value in the tensor A at coordinates ij and k.
The principal component analysis PCA,
which is a statistical technique used to reduce the number of dimensions in a given data set while we preserve its variability.
So there are different use cases of PCA in real-time scenarios.
One of the major use cases is in the healthcare domain, so technically known as the spike-triggered covariance analysis.
It uses the principle of PCA in neuroscience to identify the specific properties of a stimulus that increase a neuron's probability of generating an action potential.
So it is using reduction techniques, which is going to be really helpful in detecting the coordinated activities of large neuronal ensembles.
So it is basically used for identifying a neuron from the shape of its action potential.
Then in terms of quantitative finance.
So PCE help us in reducing the dimensionality of a complex problem.
Let's say a fund manager has 200 stocks in his portfolio.
Now to analyze these stocks quantitatively, a stock manager will require a correlational metric of a size 200 by 200,
which makes the problem very complex.
However, if he has to extract 10 principal components, which best represents the variance in the stock price.
This will reduce the complexity of the problem while still explaining the movement of all 200 stocks.
So we use it for analyzing the shape of the yield curve in terms of forecasting the portfolio returns, developing the asset allocation algorithms,
and so on, and it is also widely used in image compression.
So PCA is also used for image compression.
So if we go ahead and use any of the PyCharm IDE, so here we can work with Matplotlib, ImagePyplot, and the NumPy
as NP.
And here, we can also import from sklearn.
And we can import the PCA.
So basically we are trying to print the shape of the image by reading the image.
This is a sample logo.png, which has been placed in the same directory.
We are trying to print the image.
So if we run this particular code,
then we will be able to see the shape of the image.
Return to us first the current shape based on the image which has been deducted, which is 156, 94, and 3.
So what does this mean?
This means image is in the form of 156 rows, and each row containing 194 pixels,
and then having three channels, which is red, green, and blue.
So we had to resize the image so that it is in a format required for PCA input, which is 196 by 3,
which is going to be 582.
So here we can see we have performed a simple operation as image R, where we are using the NumPy library for reshaping the image.
And then we are printing the shape of the image again.
So here we can see 156 and 582 has been returned as a response.
Now running the PCA with 32 principal components, we can use this fit for the image that has been reshaped, and then we are trying to train the transform image.
So, with these 32 components, we are able to express 98.7% of the variance.
So, inverse transforming the PC output and reshaping the visualization can also be done forward.
And that's how PCA is widely used as a part of the medical and the other sciences.
For example, it is used for object detection model for the healthcare domain for the transportation, aviation, and location-based services.
Introduction to vectors.
Objects with both magnitude and direction are called as vectors.
The magnitude of the vector determines its size.
It is represented as a line with an arrow, where the length of the line indicates the vector's magnitude, and the arrow points in the desired direction.
Other names for it include Euclidean vector, geometric vector, spatial vector, or simply vector.
Its length is indicated by the simple double bar V double bar,
and it begins at the original 0,0.
Notation of a vector.
A vector can be represented in a standard form as a equals to a i cap plus bj cap plus c
k cap, where a, b, and c are numeric values.
The unit vectors along the xy z-axis are i, j, and k cap respectively.
Hello and welcome to machine learning tutorial part one.
This is part one of a machine learning series put on by Simply Learn.
My name is Richard Kirshner.
I'm with the Simply Learn team. That's www.simplylearn.com.
Get certified, get ahead.
What's in it for you today?
Well, we'll start off with a brief explanation of why machine learning and what is machine learning, and then we'll get into a few of the types of machine learning.
Machine learning algorithms, linear regression, decision trees, support vector machine, and finally we'll do a use case
where we're going to classify whether recipes of a cupcake or a muffin using the SVM or the support vector machine.
Sounds like a delicious way to explore machine learning.
So why machine learning?
Why do we even care about having these computers come up and be able to do all these new things for us?
Well, because machines can now drive your car for you.
It's still very in the infant stage, but it's just exploding, as we see with uh Google's Waymo and then uh Uberhead their program, which unfortunately crashed.
They know that this is huge. This is going to be the huge industry to change our whole transportation infrastructure.
Machine learning has now used to detect over fifty eye diseases. Do you know how amazing that is to have a computer that double checks for the doctor for things they might miss?
That's just huge in the health industry.
Pretty soon we actually do already have that in some areas where maybe not for eyes, but for other diseases
where they're using the camera on your phone to help pre-diagnose before you go in and see the doctor.
And because the machine can now unlock your phone with your face.
I mean, that's just cool, having it being able to identify your face or your voice and be able to turn stuff on and off for you depending on where you're at and what you need.
Talking about an ultimate automation, the world we live in.
And as we dig in deeper, we have a nice example of Facebook.
As you can see here, they have the Facebook post with Halloween.
Comment yes if you want it.
Order here. Nobody likes spam posts on Facebook that annoy them into interacting with likes, shares, comments, and other actions.
I remember the original ones were all, if you don't click on here, you will have bad luck or some kind of fear factor.
Well, this is a huge thing in a social media when people are getting spammed, and so this tactic, known as engagement bait,
takes advantage of Facebook's newsfeed algorithm by choosing engagement in order to get the greater reach.
Or to eliminate engagement bait, the company reviewed and categorized hundreds of thousands of posts who train a machine learning model that detects different types of engagement bait.
So in this case we have, we're using Facebook, but this is of course across all the different social media.
They have different tools they're building. And the Facebook scroll, Jeff, will be replaced.
Kind of like a virus coming in there and notices that there's a certain setup with Facebook and is able to replace it.
And they have like vote baiting, react baiting, share baiting.
They have all these different these are kind of general titles, but there certainly are a lot of ways of baiting you to go in there and click on something.
So they fed all this. This data was fed into the machine.
And then they have the new post. The new post comes up that takes over part of the Facebook setup. And that's what you're looking at.
You're looking at this new post that's replaced, like a virus has replaced that.
So what Facebook did to eliminate this is they start scanning for keywords and phrases like this and checks the click-through rate.
So it starts looking for people who are clicking through it without even looking at it or clicking through it and it's not something that normally would be clicked through.
Once Facebook has scanned for these keywords and phrases, it is now able to identify the spam coming in.
And this makes your life easier, so you're not getting spammed, it's not like walking through an airport, and in a lot of countries you have like hundreds of people trying to sell you timeshare.
Come join us, sign up for this. It eliminates that annoyingness, so now you can just enjoy your Facebook and your cat pictures, or maybe it's your family pictures. Mine is family.
Certainly people like their cat pictures too.
Another good example is Google's Deep Mind Project, Alpha Go.
A computer program that plays a board game Go has defeated the world's number one Go player, and I hope I say his name right, Keiji.
The ultimate Go Challenge game of three of three was on May 27, 2017. So that's just last year that this happened.
And what makes this so important is that you know Go is just is a game, so it's not like you're driving a car or something in our real world,
but they are using games to learn how to get the machine learning program to learn.
They want it to learn how to learn.
And that is a huge step.
A lot of this is still in its infant stage as far as development, as we saw what happened with the, as I referred to earlier, the Uber cars.
They lost their whole division because they jumped ahead too fast.
So it's still at an infant stage, but boy, is this like the beginning of just an amazing world that is automated in ways we can't even imagine what tomorrow's going to look like.
We've looked at a lot of examples of machine learning, so let's see if we can give a little bit more of a concrete definition.
What is machine learning?
Machine learning is the science of making computers learn and act like humans by feeding data and information without being explicitly programmed.
And we see here we have a nice little diagram where we have our ordinary system.
Your computer, nowadays you can even run a lot of the stuff on a cell phone, because cell phones have advanced so much.
And then with artificial intelligence and machine learning, it now takes the data and it learns from what happened before.
And then it predicts what's going to come next.
And then really the biggest part right now in machine learning that's going on is it improves on that. How do we find a new solution?
So we go from descriptive where it's learning about stuff and understanding how it fits together to predicting what it's going to do to postscripting, coming up with a new solution.
And when we're working on machine learning, there's a number of different diagrams that people have posted for what steps to go through.
A lot of it might be very domain specific. So if you're working on photo identification versus language versus medical or physics, some of these are switched around a little bit
or new things are put in. They're very specific to the domain.
This is kind of a very general diagram.
First, you want to define your objective.
Very important to know what it is you're wanting to predict.
Then you're going to be collecting the data.
So once you've defined an objective, you need to collect the data that matches.
You spend a lot of time in data science collecting data and the next step preparing the data.
You've got to make sure that your data is clean going in.
There's the old saying bad data in, bad answer out, or bad data out.
And then once you've gone through and we've cleaned all this stuff coming in, then you're going to select the algorithm.
Which algorithm are you going to use? You're going to train that algorithm. In this case, I think we're going to be working with SVM, the support vector machine.
Then you have to test the model.
Does this model work?
Is this a valid model for what we're doing?
And then once you've tested it, you want to run your prediction.
You want to run your prediction or your choice or whatever output it's going to come up with.
And then once everything is set and you've done lots of testing, then you want to go ahead and deploy the model.
And remember I said domain specific. This is very general as far as the scope of doing something.
A lot of models you get halfway through and you realize that your data is missing something, and you have to go collect new data because you've run a test in here someplace along the line,
you're saying, hey, I'm not really getting the answers I need.
So there's a lot of things that are domain specific that become part of this model.
This is a very general model, but it's a very good model to start with.
And we do have some basic divisions of what machine learning does that's important to know.
For instance, do you want to predict a category?
Well, if you're categorizing thing, that's classification.
For instance, whether the stock price will increase or decrease. So in other words, I'm looking for a yes-no answer. Is it going up or is it going down?
And in that case, we'd actually say, is it going up? True.
If it's not going up, it's false, meaning it's going down.
This way it's a yes-no, zero, one.
Do you want to predict a quantity?
That's regression.
So remember we just did classification, now we're looking at regression. These are the two major divisions in what data's doing.
For instance, predicting the age of a person based on the height, weight, health, and other factors.
So based on these different factors, you might guess how old a person is.
And then there are a lot of domain specific things. Like, do you want to detect an anomaly?
That's anomaly detection.
This is actually very popular right now.
For instance, you want to detect money withdrawal anomalies. You want to know when someone's making a withdrawal that might not be their own account.
We've actually brought this up because this is really big right now.
If you're predicting the stock, whether to buy stock or not, you want to be able to know if what's going on in the stock market is an anomaly.
Use a different prediction model because something else is going on, you've got to pull out nude information in there.
Or is this just the norm?
I'm going to get my normal return on my money invested.
So being able to detect anomalies is very big in data science these days.
Another question that comes up, which is on what we call untrained data, is do you want to discover structure in unexplored data?
And that's called clustering.
For instance, finding groups of customers with similar behavior given a large database of customer data containing their demographics and past buying records.
And in this case, we might notice that anybody who's wearing certain set of shoes goes shopping at certain stores or whatever it is. They're going to make certain purchases.
By having that information, it helps us to market or group people together so that we can now explore that group and find out what it is we want to market to them if you're in the marketing world.
And that might also work in just about any arena.
You might want to group people together, whether they're based on their different areas and investments and financial background,
whether you're going to give them a loan or not.
Before you even start looking at whether they're a valid customer for the bank, you might want to look at all these different areas and group them together based on unknown data.
So you're not, you don't know what the data is going to tell you, but you want to cluster people together that come together.
Let's take a quick detour for quiz time. Oh, my favorite.
So we're going to have a couple questions here under our quiz time, and we'll be posting the answers in the part two of this tutorial.
So let's go ahead and take a look at these quiz times questions, and hopefully you'll get them all right, and we'll get you thinking about how to process data and what's going on.
Can you tell what's happening in the following cases?
Of course, you're sitting there with your cup of coffee and you have your checkbox and your pen trying to figure out what's your next step in your data science analysis.
So the first one is grouping documents into different categories based on the topic and content of each document.
Very big these days.
But certainly having that automated is a huge thing in today's world.
B. Identifying handwritten digits and images correctly. So we want to know whether uh they're writing an A or capital A, B, C. What are they writing out in their hand digit their handwriting?
C.
Behavior of a website indicating that the site is not working as designed.
D.
Predicting salary of an individual based on his or her years of experience. Wait, HR hiring uh setup there.
So stay tuned for part two. We'll go ahead and answer these questions when we get to the part two of this tutorial.
Or you can just simply write at the bottom and send a note to Simply Learn, and they'll follow up with you on it.
Back to our regular content.
And these last few bring us into the next topic, which is another way of dividing our types of machine learning, and that is with supervised,
unsupervised, and reinforcement learning.
Supervised learning is a method used to enable machines to classify, predict objects, problems, or situations based on labeled data fed to the machine.
And in here you see we have a jumble of data with circles, triangles, and squares. And we label them.
We have what's a circle, what's a triangle, what's a square, and we have our model training, and it trains it. So we know the answer.
Very important, when you're doing supervised learning, you already know the answer to a lot of your information coming in.
So you have a huge group of data coming in, and then you have a new data coming in. So we've trained our model.
The model now knows the difference between a circle, a square, a triangle.
And now that we've trained it, we can send in, in this case, a square and a circle goes in and it predicts that the top one's a square and the next one's a circle.
And you can see that this is uh being able to predict whether someone's gonna default on a loan, because I was talking about banks earlier.
Supervised learning on stock market, whether you're gonna make money or not.
That's always important.
And if you are looking to make a fortune in the stock market, keep in mind it is very difficult to get all the data correct on the stock market.
It is very uh it fluctuates in ways you really hard to predict.
So it's quite a roller coaster ride. If you're running machine learning on the stock market, you start realizing you really have to dig for new data.
So we have supervised learning, and if you have supervised, we should need unsupervised learning.
In unsupervised learning, machine learning model finds the hidden pattern in an unlabeled data.
So in this case, instead of telling it what the circle is and what a triangle is and what a square is, it goes in there, looks at them, and says, for whatever reason, it groups them together.
Maybe it'll group it by the number of corners.
And it notices that a number of them all have three corners, a number of them all have four corners, and a number of them all have no corners.
And it's able to filter those through and group them together.
We talked about that earlier with looking at a group of people who are out shopping.
We want to group them together to find out what they have in common.
And of course, once you understand what people have in common, maybe you have one of them who's a customer at your store, or you have five of them who are customer at your store,
and they have a lot in common with five others who are not customers at your store. How do you market to those five who aren't customers at your store yet?
They fit the demographs of who's going to shop there, and you'd like them to shop at your store, not the one next door.
Of course, this is a simplified version, you can see very easily the difference between a triangle and a circle, which might not be so easy in marketing.
Reinforcement learning.
Reinforcement learning is an important type of machine learning where an agent learns how to behave in an environment by performing actions and seeing the result.
And we have here where the, in this case a baby, it's actually great that they used an infant for this slide, because the reinforcement learning is very much in its infant stages.
But it's also probably the biggest machine learning demand out there right now or in the future, it's going to be coming up over the next few years,
is reinforcement learning and how to make that work for us.
And you can see here where we have our action.
I mean, the action on this one, it goes into the fire. Hopefully the baby didn't it was just a little candle, not a giant fire pit like it looks like here.
When the baby comes out and the new state is the baby is sad and crying because they got burned on the fire.
And then maybe they take another action.
The baby's called the agent, because it's the one taking the actions. And in this case they didn't go into the fire, they went a different direction, and now the baby's happy and laughing and playing.
Reinforcement learning is very easy to understand because that's how, as humans, that's one of the ways we learn.
We learn whether it is, you know, you burn yourself on the stove, don't do that anymore. Don't touch the stove.
In the big picture, being able to have a machine learning program or an AI be able to do this is huge. Because now we're starting to learn how to learn.
That's a big jump in the world of computer and machine learning.
And we're going to go back and just kind of go back over supervised versus unsupervised learning.
Understanding this is huge because this is going to come up in any project you're working on.
We have in supervised learning we have labeled data.
We have direct feedback.
So someone's already gone in there and said, yes, that's a triangle.
No, that's not a triangle.
And then you predict an outcome.
So you have a nice prediction. This is this this new set of data is coming in and we know what it's going to be.
And then with unsupervised training, it's not labeled.
So we really don't know what it is.
There's no feedback.
So we're not telling it whether it's right or wrong. We're not telling it whether it's a triangle or a square. We're not telling it to go left or right.
All we do is we're finding hidden structure in the data, grouping the data together to find out what connects to each other.
And then you can use these together.
So imagine you have an image and you're not sure what you're looking for.
So you go in and you have the unstructured data, find all these things that are connected together.
And then somebody looks at those and labels them.
Now you can take that label data and program something to predict what's in the picture.
So you can see how they go back and forth and you can start connecting all these different tools together to make a bigger picture.
There are many interesting machine learning algorithms. Let's have a look at a few of them.
Hopefully, this gives you a little flavor of what's out there.
And these are some of the most important ones that are currently being used.
We'll take a look at linear regression, decision tree, and the support vector machine.
Let's start with a closer look at linear regression.
Linear regression is perhaps one of the most well-known and well-understood algorithms in statistics and machine learning.
Linear regression is a linear model.
For example, a model that assumes a linear relationship between the input variables x and the single output variable y.
And you'll see this if you remember from your algebra classes, y equals mx plus c.
Imagine we are predicting distance traveled y from speed x.
Our linear regression model representation for this problem would be y equals m times x plus c or distance equals m times speed plus c,
where m is the coefficient and c is the y-intercept. And we're going to look at two different variations of this. First we're going to start with time is constant.
And you can see we have a bicyclist, he's got a safety gear on, thank goodness.
Speed equals ten meters per second.
And so over a certain amount of time, his distance equals thirty-six kilometers.
We have a second bicyclist who's going twice the speed, or twenty meters per second.
And you can guess if he's going twice the speed and time is a constant, then he's going to go twice the distance.
And that's easy to compute. 36 times two, you get seventy-two kilometers. And so if you had the question of how fast would somebody is going three times that speed, or thirty meters per second is,
you can easily compute the distance in our head, we can do that without needing a computer.
But we want to do this for more complicated data.
So it's kind of nice to compare the two, but let's just take a look at that and what that looks like in a graph.
So in a linear regression model, we have our distance to the speed, and we have our m equals the VE slope of the line. And we'll notice that the line has a plus slope.
And as the speed increases, distance also increases, hence the variables have a positive relationship.
And so your speed of the person, which equals y equals mx plus c distance traveled in a fixed interval of time,
and we could very easily compute either following the line or just knowing it's three times ten meters per second, that this is roughly 102 kilometers distance that this third bicyclist has traveled.
One of the key definitions on here is positive relationship.
So the slope of the line is positive, as distance increase, so does speed increase.
Let's take a look at our second example where we put distance as a constant.
So we have speed equals ten meters per second, they have a certain distance to go, and it takes them a hundred seconds to travel that distance.
And we have our second bicyclist who's still doing twenty meters per second.
Since he's going twice the speed, we can guess that he'll cover the distance in about half the time.
50 seconds.
And of course you could probably guess on the third one, a hundred divided by thirty since he's going three times the speed.
You could easily guess that this is thirty-three point three three three seconds time.
We put that into a linear regression model or a graph.
If the distance is assumed to be constant, let's see the relationship between speed and time.
And as time goes up, the amount of speed to go that same distance goes down. So now your m equals a minus VE slope of the line.
As the speed increases, time decreases, hence the variable has a negative relationship.
Again, there's our definition, positive relationship and negative relationship dependent on the slope of the line.
And with a simple formula like this, um and even a significant amount of data, let's uh see what the mathematical implementation of linear regression.
And we'll take this data. So suppose we have this data set where we have xy x equals one, two, three, four, five, standard series, and the y value is three,
two, two, four, three.
When we take that and we go ahead and plot these points on a graph, you can see there's kind of a nice scattering, and you could probably eyeball a line through the middle of it.
But we're going to calculate that exact line for linear regression.
And the first thing we do is we come up here and we have the mean of x i.
And remember mean is basically the average. So we added five plus four plus three plus two plus one and divide by five.
And that simply comes out as three.
And then we'll do the same for y.
We'll go ahead and add up all those numbers and divide by five, and we end up with the mean value of y of i equals two point eight, where the xi
references is an average or means value, and the yi also equals a means value of y.
And when we plot that, you'll see that we can put in the y equals two point eight and the x equals three in there on our graph, and we kind of give it a little different color,
so you could sort it out with the dashed lines on it.
And it's important to note that when we do the linear regression, the linear regression model should go through that dot. Now let's find our regression equation to find the best fit line.
Remember we go ahead and take our y equals mx plus c, so we're looking for m and c.
So to find this equation for our data, we need to find our slope of m and our coefficient of c.
And we have y equals mx plus c or m equals the sum of x minus x average times y
minus y average, or y means and x means, over the sum of x minus x means squared.
That's how we get the slope of the value of the line.
And we can easily do that by creating some columns here. We have x, y.
Computers are really good about iterating through data, and so we can easily compute this and fill in a graph of data.
And in our graph you can easily see that if we have our x value of one, and if you remember the xi or the means value is three,
one minus three equals a negative two, and two minus three equals a negative one, so on and so forth.
And we can easily fill in the column of x minus xi, y minus yi, and then from those we can compute x minus xi
squared and x minus xi times y minus yi.
And you can guess it that the next step is to go ahead and sum the different columns for the answers we need.
So we get a total of ten for our x minus xi squared, and a total of two for x minus xi times y minus yi.
And we plug those in, we get two tenths, which equals point two. So now we know the slope of our line equals point two.
So we can calculate the value of c.
That'd be the next step is we need to know where it crosses the y-axis.
And if you remember I mentioned earlier that the linear regression line has to pass through the means value, the one that we showed earlier.
We can just flip back up there to that graph.
And you can see right here there's our means value, which is three x equals three and y equals two point eight.
And since we know that value, we can simply plug that into our formula, y equals point two x plus c.
So we plug that in, we get two point eight equals point two times three plus c, and you can just solve for c.
So now we know that our coefficient equals two point two.
And once we have all that, we can go ahead and plot our regression line y equals point two times x plus two point two.
And then from this equation, we can compute new values. So let's predict the values of y using x equals 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 and plot the points.
Remember the 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 was our original x values.
So now we're going to see what y thinks they are, not what they actually are.
And when we plug those in, we get uh y of designated with y of p.
You can see that x equals 1 equals 2.4, x equals 2 equals 2.6, and so on and so on.
So we have our y predicted values of what we think it's going to be when we plug those numbers in.
And when we plot the predicted values along with the actual values, we can see the difference.
And this is one of the things that's very important with linear regression in any of these models is to understand the error.
And so we can calculate the error on all of our different values. And you can see over here we plotted x and y and y predict.
And we draw in a little line so you can sort of see what the error looks like there between the different points.
So our goal is to reduce this error. We want to minimize that error value on our linear regression model.
Minimizing the distance.
There are lots of ways to minimize the distance between the line and the data points, like sum of squared errors, sum of absolute errors, root mean square error, etc.
We keep moving this line through the data points to make sure the best fit line has the least square distance between the data points and the regression line.
So to recap with a very simple linear regression model, we first figure out the formula of our line through the middle, and then we slowly adjust the line to minimize the error.
Keep in mind this is a very simple formula.
The math gets, even though the math is very much the same, it gets much more complex as we add in different dimensions.
So this is only two dimensions, y equals mx plus c, but you can take that out to x, z, ijq, all the different features in there,
and they can plot a linear regression model on all of those using the different formulas to minimize the error.
Let's go ahead and take a look at decision trees, a very different way to solve problems than the linear regression model.
Decision tree is a tree-shaped algorithm used to determine a course of action.
Each branch of a tree represents a possible decision, occurrence, or reaction.
We have data which tells us if it is a good day to play golf.
And if we were to open this data up in a general spreadsheet, you can see we have the outlook, whether it's uh rainy, overcast, sunny, temperature,
hot, mild, cool, humidity, windy, and did I like to play golf that day, yes or no?
So we're taking a census.
And certainly I wouldn't want a computer telling me when I should go play golf or not.
But you can imagine if you got up in the night before you're trying to plan your day, and it comes up and says tomorrow would be a good day for golf for you in the morning,
and not a good day in the afternoon, or something like that.
This becomes very beneficial, and we see this in a lot of applications coming out now where it gives you suggestions and lets you know what would what would
fit the match for you for the next day or the next purchase or the next uh whatever, you know, next mail out. In this case, is tomorrow a good day for playing golf based on the weather coming in?
And so we come up and let's uh determine if you should play golf when the day is sunny and windy.
So we found out the forecast tomorrow is gonna be sunny and windy.
And suppose we draw our tree like this. We're gonna have our humidity, and then we have our normal, which is uh if it's if you have a normal humidity, you're gonna go play golf.
And if the humidity is really high, then we look at the outlook. And if the outlook is sunny, overcast, or rainy, it's gonna change what you choose to do.
So if you know that it's a very high humidity and it's sunny, you're probably not gonna play golf because you're gonna be out there miserable,
fighting off the mosquitoes that are out joining you to play golf with you.
Maybe if it's rainy, you probably don't want to play in the rain. But if it's slightly overcast and you get just the right shadow, that's a good day to play golf and be outside out on the green.
Now, in this example, you can probably make your own tree pretty easily because it's a very simple set of data going in.
But the question is, how do you know what to split? Where do you split your data? What if this is much more complicated data where it's not something that you would particularly understand?
Like studying cancer, they take about thirty-six measurements of the cancerous cells, and then each one of those measurements represents some how bulbous it is, how extended it is,
how sharp the edges are.
Something that as a human we would have no understanding of.
So how do we decide how to split that data up? And is that the right decision tree? But so that's the question that's going to come up. Is this the right decision tree?
For that, we should calculate entropy and information gain.
Two important vocabulary words there are the entropy and the information gain.
Entropy.
Entropy is a measure of randomness or impurity in the data set.
Entropy should be low.
So we want the chaos to be as low as possible.
We don't want to look at it and be confused by the images or what's going on there with mixed data.
And the information gain.
It is a measure of decrease in entropy after the data set is split, also known as entropy reduction.
Information gain should be high.
So we want our information that we get out of the split to be as high as possible.
Let's take a look at entropy from the mathematical side.
In this case, we're going to denote entropy as I of p of and n, where p is the probability that you're going to play a game of golf,
and n is the probability where you're not going to play the game of golf.
Now you don't really have to memorize these formulas. There's a few of them out there depending on what you're working with.
But it's important to note that this is where this formula is coming from, so when you see it, you're not lost when you're running your programming,
unless you're building your own decision tree code in the back.
And we simply have a log squared of p over p plus n minus n over p plus n times the log squared of n of p plus n.
But let's break that down and see what actually looks like when we're computing that from the computer script side.
Entropy of a target class of the data set is the whole entropy.
So we have entropy play golf.
And when we look at this, if we go back to the data, you can simply count how many yeses and no in our complete data set for playing golf days.
In our complete set, we find we have five days we did play golf and nine days we did not play golf.
And so our i equals, if you add those together, nine plus five is fourteen.
And so our i equals five over fourteen and nine over fourteen. That's our p and n values that we plug into that formula.
And you can go with uh five over fourteen equals point three six, nine over fourteen equals 0.64.
And when you do the whole equation, you get the minus 0.36 log root squared of 0.36 minus 0.64
log squared root of 0.64.
And we get a set value, we get 0.94.
So we now have a full entropy value for the whole set of data that we're working with.
And we want to make that entropy go down.
And just like we calculated the entropy out for the whole set, we can also calculate entropy for playing golf and the outlook. Is it going to be overcast or rainy or sunny?
And so when we look at the entropy, we have uh p of sunny times e of three of two, and that just comes out how many sunny days yes and how many sunny days
no over the total, which is five. Don't forget to put the we'll divide that five out later on, uh equals p overcast equals four comma zero plus rainy equals two comma three.
And then when you do the whole setup, we have five over fourteen.
Remember I said there was a total of five, five over fourteen times the i of three of two plus four over fourteen times the four comma zero and five
fourteen over i of two three.
And so we can now compute the entropy of just the part it has to do with the forecast, and we get 0.693.
Similarly, we can calculate the entropy of other predictors like temperature, humidity, and wind.
And so we look at the gain outlook. How much are we going to gain from this? Entropy play golf minus entropy play golf outlook.
And we can take the original .94 for the whole set minus the entropy of just the rainy day and temperature,
and we end up with a gain of 0.247.
So this is our information gain. Remember we define entropy and we define information gain. The higher the information gain, the lower the entropy, the better.
The information gain of the other three attributes can be calculated in the same way.
So we have our gain for temperature equals 0.029.
We have our gain for humidity equals 0.152, and our gain for a windy day equals 0.048.
And if you do a quick comparison, you'll see the 0.247 is the greatest gain of information, so that's the split we want.
Now let's build the decision tree. So we have the outlook. Is it going to be sunny, overcast, or rainy? That's our first split because that gives us the most information gain.
And we can continue to go down the tree using the different information gains with the largest information.
We can continue down the nodes of the tree where we choose the attribute with the largest information gain as the root node,
and then continue to split each sub node with the largest information gain that we can compute.
And although it's a little bit of a tongue twister to say all that, you can see that it's a very easy-to-view visual model.
We have our outlook, we split it three different directions.
If the outlook is overcast, we're going to play.
And then we can split those further down if we want. So if the over outlook is sunny, but then it's also windy, if it's windy, we're not going to play. If it's not windy, we'll play.
So we can easily build a nice decision tree to guess what we would like to do tomorrow and give us a nice recommendation for the day.
So we want to know if it's a good day to play golf when it's sunny and windy.
Remember the original question that came out? Tomorrow's weather report is sunny and windy?
You can see by going down the tree we go outlook sunny, outlook windy, we're not going to play golf tomorrow. So our little smartwatch pops up and says, I'm sorry, tomorrow's not a good day for golf.
It's going to be sunny and windy.
And if you're a huge golf fan, you might go, uh-oh, it's not a good day to play golf.
We can go in and watch a golf game at home.
So we'll sit in front of the TV instead of being out playing golf in the wind.
Now that we looked at our decision tree, let's look at the third one of our algorithms we're investigating.
Support vector machine.
Support vector machine is a widely used classification algorithm.
The idea of support vector machine is simple.
The algorithm creates a separation line which divides the classes in the best possible manner.
For example, dog or cat, disease or no disease.
Suppose we have a labeled sample data which tells height and weight of males and females.
A new data point arrives and we want to know whether it's going to be a male or a female.
So we start by drawing a line.
We draw decision lines, but if we consider decision line one, then we will classify the individual as a male.
And if we consider decision line two, then it will be a female.
So you can see this person kind of lies in the middle of the two groups, so it's a little confusing trying to figure out which line they should be under.
We need to know which line divides the classes correctly, but how.
The goal is to choose a hyperplane, and that is one of the key words they use when we talk about support vector machines.
Choose a hyperplane with the greatest possible margin between the decision line and the nearest point within the training set.
So you can see here we have our support vector, we have the two nearest points to it, and we draw a line between those two points.
And the distance margin is the distance between the hyperplane and the nearest data point from either set.
So we actually have a value, and it should be equally distant between the two points that we're comparing it to.
When we draw the hyperplanes, we observe that line one has a maximum distance. So we observe that line one has a maximum distance margin, so we'll classify the new data point correctly.
And our result on this one is going to be that the new data point is MEL.
One of the reasons we call it a hyperplane versus a line is that a lot of times we're not looking at just weight and height.
We might be looking at thirty-six different features or dimensions.
And so when we cut it with a hyperplane, it's more of a three-dimensional cut in the data or multi-dimensional. It cuts the data a certain way.
And each plane continues to cut it down until we get the best fit or match.
Let's understand this with the help of an example.
Problem statement. Always start with a problem statement when you're going to put some code together. We're going to do some coding now.
Classifying muffin and cupcake recipes using support vector machines. So the cupcake versus the muffin.
Let's have a look at our data set.
And we have the different recipes here. We have a muffin recipe that has uh so much flour. I'm not sure what measurement 55 is in, but it has 55 maybe it's ounces.
But uh has a certain amount of flour, certain amount of milk, sugar, butter, egg, baking powder, vanilla, and salt.
And so based on these measurements, we want to guess whether we're making a muffin or a cupcake.
And you can see in this one, we don't have just two features. We don't just have height and weight as we did before between the male and female.
In here we have a number of features.
In fact, in this we're looking at eight different features to guess whether it's a muffin or a cupcake.
What's the difference between a muffin and a cupcake?
Turns out muffins have more flour, while cupcakes have more butter and sugar.
So basically the cupcake's a little bit more of a dessert where the muffins are a little bit more of a fancy bread.
But how do we do that in Python? How do we code that to go through recipes and figure out what the recipe is?
And I really just want to say cupcakes versus muffins, like some big professional wrestling thing.
Before we start in our cupcakes versus muffins, we are going to be working in Python.
There's many versions of Python, many different editors.
That is one of the strengths and weaknesses of Python, is it just has so much stuff attached to it and it's one of the more popular data science programming packages you can use.
In this case, we're going to go ahead and use Anaconda in Jupyter Notebook.
The Anaconda Navigator has all kinds of fun tools. Once you're into the Anaconda Navigator, you can change environments.
I actually have a number of environments on here. We'll be using Python 3.6 environment. So this is in Python version 3.6.
Although it doesn't matter too much which version you use.
I usually try to stay with the 3x because they're current, unless you have a project that's very specifically in version 2x. 2.7, I think, is usually what most people use in the version 2.
And then once we're in our um Jupyter Notebook editor, I can go up and create a new file.
And we'll just jump in here.
In this case we're doing SVM muffin versus cupcake.
And then let's start with our packages for data analysis.
And we almost always use a couple there's a few very standard packages we use.
We use import oops import.
Import
numpy.
That's for number python.
And they usually denote it as np, that's very comma.
That's very common.
And then we're going to import pandas as PD.
And NumPy deals with number arrays. There's a lot of cool things you can do with the NumPy uh setup.
As far as multiplying all the values in an array, in a NumPy array, data array.
Pandas, I can't remember if we're using it actually in this data set. I think we do as an import.
It makes a nice data frame.
And the difference between a data frame and a numpy array is that a data frame is more like your Excel spreadsheet.
You have columns, you have indexes, so you have different ways of referencing it, easily viewing it, and there's additional features you can run on a data frame.
And pandas kind of sits on NumPy, so they you need them both in there.
And then finally we're working with the support vector machine. So from SK Learn, we're going to use the SK Learn model,
import SVM, support vector machine.
And then as a data scientist, you should always try to visualize your data.
Some data obviously is too complicated or doesn't make any sense to the human.
But if it's possible, it's good to take a second look at it so that you can actually see what you're doing.
And for that, we're going to use two packages. We're going to import mapplotlibrary.pyplot as plt.
Again, very common.
And we're going to import c born as SNS. And we'll go ahead and set the font scale in the SNS right in our import line.
That's with this semicolon followed by a line of data.
We're going to set the SNS.
And these are great because the the CBON sits on top of Mapplot Library, just like Panda sits on Numpey.
So it adds a lot more features and uses and control.
We're obviously not going to get into Mapplot Library and CBON, that'd be its own tutorial.
We're really just focusing on the SVM, the support vector machine from sklearn.
And since we're in Jupyter Notebook, uh we have to add a special line in here for our Matplot library.
And that's your percentage sign or amber sign Mapplot Library in line.
Now, if you're doing this in just a straight code project, a lot of times I use like Notepad,
and I'll run it from there.
You don't have to have that line in there, because it'll just pop up as its own window on your computer, depending on how your computer's setup.
Because we're running this in the Jupyter Notebook as a browser setup, this tells it to display all of our graphics right below on the page.
So that's what that line is for.
Remember the first time I ran this, I didn't know that, and I had to go look that up years ago.
It's quite a headache. So Mapplot Library inline is just because we're running this on the web setup.
And we can go ahead and run this, make sure all our modules are in, they're all imported, which is great.
If you don't have them import, you'll need to go ahead and pip, use the PIP or however you do it. There's a lot of other install packages out there, although pip is the most common.
And you have to make sure these are all installed on your Python setup.
The next step, of course, is we've got to look at the data. You can't run a model for predicting data if you don't have actual data.
So to do that, let me go ahead and open this up and take a look.
And we have our uh cupcakes versus muffins, and it's a CSV file or.csv, meaning that it's comma separated variable.
And it's going to open it up in a nice uh spreadsheet for me.
And you can see up here we have the type. We have muffin, muffin, muffin, cupcake, cupcake, cupcake, and then it's broken up into flour, milk, sugar, butter, egg, baking powder, vanilla, and salt.
So what we can do is we can go ahead and look at this data also in our Python.
Let us create a variable recipes equals. We're gonna use our pandas
module.readcsv. Remember it was a comma-separated variable.
And the file name happened to be cupcakes versus muffins. Oops, I got double brackets there.
Do it this way.
There we go.
Cupcakes versus muffins.
Because the program I loaded, or the the place I saved this particular Python program is in the same folder, we can get by with just the file name.
But remember if you're storing it in a different location, you have to also put down the full path on there.
And then because we're in pandas, we're gonna go ahead and you can actually in line you can do this, but let me do the full print. You can just type in recipes.head
in the Jupyter Notebook.
But if you're running in code in a different script, you'd need to go ahead and type out the whole print recipes.head.
And pandas knows is that's gonna do the first five lines of data.
And if we flip back on over to the spreadsheet where we opened up our CSV file,
uh you can see where it starts on line two. This one calls it zero, and then two, three, four, five, six is gonna match.
Go and close that out because we don't need that anymore.
And it always starts at zero.
And these are it automatically indexes it since we didn't tell it to use an index in here. So that's the index number for the left hand side.
And it automatically took the top row as uh labels. So pandas using it to read a CSV is just really slick and fast.
One of the reasons we love our pandas, not just because they're cute and cuddly teddy bears.
And let's go ahead and plot our data.
And I'm not going to plot all of it.
I'm just going to plot the uh sugar and flour.
Now, obviously, you can see where they get really complicated if we have tons of different features.
And so you'll break them up and maybe look at just two of them at a time to see how they connect.
And to plot them, we're going to go ahead and use Corn.
So that's our SNS.
And the command for that is sns.lmplot.
And then the two different variables I'm going to plot is flour and sugar.
Data equals recipes.
The hue equals type.
And this is a lot of fun because it knows that this is pandas coming in.
So this is one of the powerful things about pandas mixed with CBORN in doing
graphing.
And then we're going to use a palette set1.
There's a lot of different sets in there. You can go look them up for CBORN.
We'll do a regular a fit regular equals false, so we're not really trying to fit anything.
And it's a scatter KWS.
A lot of these settings you can look up in Cborne. Half of these you could probably leave off when you run them.
Somebody played with this and found out that these were the best settings for doing a CBORN plot.
And let's go ahead and run that.
And because it does it in line, it just puts it right on the page.
And you can see right here that just based on sugar and flour alone, there's a definite split.
And we use these models because you can actually look at it and say, hey, if I drew a line right between the middle of the blue dots and the red dots,
we'd be able to do an SVM and a hyperplane right there in the middle.
Then the next step is to format or pre
process our data.
And we're going to break that up into two parts.
We need a type
label, and remember we're going to decide whether it's a muffin or a cupcake. Well, a computer doesn't know muffin or cupcake, it knows zero and one.
So what we're going to do is we're going to create a type label.
And from this we'll create a numpy array np where,
and this is where we can do some logic. We take our recipes from our panda, and wherever a type equals muffin, it's going to be zero.
And then if it doesn't equal muffin, which is cupcakes, it's going to be one. So we've created our type label.
This is the answer.
So when we're doing our training model, remember we have to have a training data?
This is what we're going to train it with is that it's zero or one. It's a muffin or it's not.
And then we're going to create our recipe features.
And if you remember correctly, from right up here, the first column is type.
So we really don't need the type column because that's our muffin or cupcake.
And in pandas, we can easily sort that out.
We take our value
recipes.columns, that's a pandas function built into
pandas.values, converting them to values. So it's just the column titles going across the top.
And we don't want the first one.
So what we do is it always starts at zero.
We want one
colon till the end.
And then we want to go ahead and make this a list, and this converts it to a list of strings.
And then we can go ahead and just take a look and see what we're looking at for the features. Make sure it looks right.
Let me go ahead and run that.
And I forgot the S on recipes, so we'll go ahead and add the S in there and then run that.
And we can see we have flour, milk, sugar, butter, egg, baking powder, vanilla, and salt.
And that matches what we have up here.
Right where we printed out everything but the type.
So we have our features and we have our label.
Now the recipe features is just the titles of the columns, and we actually need the ingredients.
And at this point, we have a couple options. One, we could run it over all the ingredients.
And when you're doing this, usually you do. But for our example, we want to limit it so you can easily see what's going on.
Because if we did all the ingredients, we have, you know, that's what, um seven, eight different hyperplanes that would be built into it.
We only want to look at one so you can see what the SVM is doing.
And so we'll take our recipes and we'll do just flour and sugar.
Again, you can replace that with your recipe features and do all of them. But we're going to do just flour and sugar, and we're going to convert that to values.
We don't need to make a list out of it because it's not string values. These are actual
values on there.
And we can go ahead and just print
ingredients, and you can see what that looks like.
And so we have just the amount of flour and sugar, just the two sets of plots.
And just for fun, let's go ahead and take this over here and take our recipe features.
And so if we decided to use all the recipe features, you'll see that it makes a nice column of different data. So it just strips out all the labels and everything. We just have just the values.
But because we want to be able to view this easily in a plot later on, we'll go ahead and take that and just do flour and sugar.
And we'll run that and you'll see it's just the two columns.
So the next step is to go ahead and fit our model.
We'll go ahead and just call it model.
And it's a SVM.
We're using a package called SVC.
In this case, we're going to go ahead and set the kernel equals linear. So it's using a specific setup on there.
And if we go to the reference on their website for the SVM,
you'll see that there's about there's eight of them here.
Three of them are for regression,
three are for classification.
The SVC support vector classification is probably one of the most commonly used.
And then there's also one for detecting outliers, and another one that has to do with something a little bit more specific on the model.
But SVC and SVR are the two most commonly used, standing for support vector classifier and support vector regression.
Remember, regression is an actual value, a float value or whatever you're trying to work on.
And SBC is a classifier, so it's a yes, no, true, false.
But for this, we want to know 0, 1, muffin cupcake.
We go ahead and create our model.
And once we have our model created, we're going to do model.fit. And this is very common, especially in the SKLearn. All their models are followed with the fit command.
And what we put into the fit, what we're training with it, is we're putting in the ingredients, which in this case we limited to just flour and sugar,
and the type label. Is it a muffin or a cupcake?
Now, in more complicated data science series, you'd want to split into, we won't get into that today, we split it into uh training data and test data.
And they even do something where they split it into thirds, where a third is used for where you switch between which one's training and test.
There's all kinds of things that go into that, and it gets very complicated when you get to the higher end.
Not overly complicated, just an extra step, which we're not going to do today because this is a very simple set of data.
And let's go ahead and run this, and now we have our model fit.
And uh I got an error here, so let me fix that real quick. It's capital SVC, it turns out.
I did it lowercase.
Support vector
classifier. There we go. Let's go ahead and run that.
And you'll see it comes up with all this information that it prints out automatically.
These are the defaults of the model.
You notice that we changed the kernel to linear.
And there's our kernel linear on the printout.
And there's other different settings you can mess with.
We're going to just leave that alone for right now for this. We don't really need to mess with any of those.
So, next we're going to dig a little bit into our newly trained model.
And we're going to do this so we can show you on a graph.
And let's go ahead and get the separating.
So we're gonna say uh we're gonna use a w for our variable on here.
We're gonna do model.coefficient underscore zero.
So what the heck is that?
Again, we're digging into the model. So we've already got a prediction and a train.
This is the math behind it that we're looking at right now.
And so
the w is gonna represent two different coefficients. And if you remember we had y equals mx plus c.
So these coefficients are connected to that, but in two-dimensional.
It's a plane.
We don't want to spend too much time on this because you can get lost in the confusion of the math. So if you're a math whiz, this is great.
You can go through here and you'll see that we have a equals minus w of zero over w of one. Remember there's two different values there.
And that's basically the slope that we're generating.
And then we're going to build an xx. What is xx?
We're gonna set it up to a numpy array. There's our np, dot line space.
So we're creating a line
of values between thirty and sixty.
So it just creates a set of numbers for x.
And then if you remember correctly, we have
our formula y equals the slope times x
plus the intercept.
Well, to make this work, we can do this as yy
equals the slope times each value in that array.
That's the neat thing about numpy. So when I do a times xx, which is a whole numpy array of values, it multiplies a across all of them.
And then it takes those same values and we subtract the model intercept. That's your uh remember we had uh mx plus c, so that'd be the c from the formula, y equals mx plus c.
And that's where all these numbers come from.
A little bit confusing because it's digging out of these different arrays.
And then we want to do is we're gonna take this and we're gonna go ahead and plot it.
So plot the parallels to separating hyperplane that pass through the support vectors.
And so we're gonna create b equals a model support vectors.
Pulling our support vectors out there.
Here's our yy, which we now know is a set of data, and we have, uh, we're gonna create yy down, equals a times xx plus b1
minus a times b zero.
and then model support. vector b is gonna be set that to a new value, the minus one setup, and yy up equals a times xx plus b1
minus a times. b zero.
And we can go ahead and just run this to load these variables up.
If you wanted to know a understand a little bit more of what's going on, you can see if we print
yy, let me just run that.
You can see it's an array, it's this is a line.
It's gonna have, in this case, between thirty and sixty, so it's gonna be thirty variables in here.
And the same thing with yy up, yy down.
And we'll we'll plot those in just a minute on a graph so you can see what those look like.
You just go ahead and delete that out of here and run that. So it loads up the variables, nice clean slate.
I'm just gonna copy this from before.
Remember this? Our SNS dot our cborne plot, lm plot, flower, sugar.
And uh I'll just go ahead and run that real quick so you can see what remember what that looks like. It's just a straight graph on there.
And then one of the neat things is because c borne sits on top of pi plot, we can do the pi plot for the line going through.
And that is simply plt dot plot.
And that's our xx and yy, our two corresponding values, xy.
And then somebody played with this to figure out that the line width equals two in the color black would look nice.
So let's go ahead and run this whole thing with the pi plot on there.
And you can see when we do this, it's just doing flour and sugar on here.
Corresponding line between the sugar and the flour and the muffin versus cupcake.
Um, and then we generated the um support vectors, the yy down and yy up.
So let's take a look and see what that looks like.
So we'll do our PL plot,
and again this is all against xx, the f our x value, but this time we have yy
down.
And uh let's do something a little fun with this.
We can put in a k-
that just tells it to make it a dotted line.
And if we're gonna do the down one,
we also want to do the up one.
So here's our yy
up, and when we run that, it adds both sets of line.
And so here's our support, and this is what you expect. You expect these two lines to go through the nearest data point.
So the dashed lines go through the nearest muffin and the nearest cupcake when it's plotting it.
And then your SVM goes right down the middle. So it gives it a nice split in our data, and you can see how easy it is to see, based just on sugar and flour, which one's a muffin or a cupcake.
Let's go ahead and create a function
to predict
muffin or cupcake.
I've got my um recipes I pulled off the um
internet, and I want to see the difference between a
muffin or a cupcake.
And so we need a function to push that through.
And uh we'd create a function with deaf.
And let's call it muffin or cupcake.
Now remember we're just doing flour and sugar today. We're not doing all the ingredients.
And that actually is a pretty good split. You really don't need all the ingredients to know it's flour and sugar.
And let's go ahead and do an if-l statement. So if model predict
is a flour and sugar equals zero.
So we take our model and we do it run a predict. It's very common in sklearn where you have a dot predict, you put the data in, and it's gonna return a value.
In this case, if it equals zero, then print you're looking at a muffin recipe.
Else, if it's not zero, that means it's one, then you're looking at a cupcake recipe.
That's pretty straightforward for
function, or def for definition. DEF is how you do that in Python.
And of course, if you're gonna create a function, you should run something in it.
And so let's run a cupcake and we're gonna send it values fifty and twenty, a muffin or a cupcake, I don't know what it is.
And let's run this and just see what it gives us.
And it says, oh, it's a muffin.
You're looking at a muffin recipe.
So it very easily predicts whether we're looking at a muffin or a cupcake recipe.
Let's plot this.
There we go. Plot this on the graph so we can see what that actually looks like.
And I'm just gonna copy it and paste it from below, where we're plotting all the points in there.
So this is nothing different than what we did before. If I run it, you'll see it has all the points and the lines on there.
And what we want to do is we want to add another point,
and we'll do PLT plot.
And if you remember correctly, we did for our test, we did 50 and 20.
And then somebody went in here and decided we'll do uh YO for yellow, or it's kind of an orange yellow color is going to come out.
Marker size 9.
Those are settings you can play with. Somebody else played with them to uh come up with the right setup so it looks good.
And you can see there it is graphed uh clearly a muffin.
If you'd like to do your own muffin
contender series, you certainly can send a note down below, and the team at Simular will send you over the data they use for the muffin and
cupcake.
And that's true of any of the data.
We didn't actually run a plot on it earlier. We had men versus women.
You can also request that information to run it on your data setup so you can test that out.
So to go back over our setup, we went ahead for our support vector machine code.
We did a predict 40 parts flour, 20 parts sugar.
I think it's different than the one we did, whether it's a muffin or a cupcake.
So we have built a classifier using SVM, which is able to classify if a recipe is of a cupcake or a muff, which wraps up our cupcake versus muffin
model.
So the key takeaway is what is machine learning?
We discussed that with some of the different aspects of machine learning on there.
We went into types of machine learning.
If you remember right, we have supervised, unsupervised, and reinforcement learning.
We discussed regression line or best fit, and we did the building a decision tree and what the logic is behind that.
And finally, we did classification using SVM, support vector machine, and we did the code in there.
Today we are diving into machine learning, the technology behind things like Netflix recommendations, CD, and even the phase unlock of your phone.
Machine learning helps devices get smarter by learning from data and predicting what we might like or need.
And here's why machine learning is huge for your career.
Right now, machine learning jobs are among the fastest growing roles worldwide.
Companies in every industry, tech, healthcare, finance, and more are looking for people with machine learning skills to improve their products,
automate tasks, and make smarter decisions.
Machine learning engineers in the US earn around $112,000 on average, with plenty of room for growth as you gain experience.
So if you want to jump into this exciting field, learning machine learning can open doors to high-paying in-demand jobs.
So in this video, I'll guide you through the ultimate roadmap to master machine learning in 2025, one step at a time.
So let's get started.
So in the first month, start with the foundations of programming.
So programming is a language you'll use to communicate with your computer and bring machine learning algorithms to life.
So this month is all about Python, the language of choice for most machine learning practitioners.
So here's what to focus on.
First, learn Python basics.
Begin with Python's fundamentals like variables, data types, loops, and functions.
So spend time writing small programs daily to get comfortable.
After that, explore the key libraries like NumPy, Pandas, and ScikitLearn.
So NumPy is for numerical operations.
It makes handling large data sets faster and easier.
And pandas is to manipulate and analyze data.
So pandas allow you to filter, sort, and reshape data in a ways.
And then scikit learn is for implementing algorithms in just a few lines of code.
So now you might have heard about R, another language using machine learning.
But don't stress about it now. Python will serve you well, especially as a beginner, because it's simpler and more flexible.
So aim to spend an hour or two each day coding.
By the end of this month, you'll have a solid base to build on.
Now in the second month, get organized with version control and data structures.
So this month is about learning how to organize and manage your code effectively and sharpening your problem solving skills with data structures and algorithms.
So first is version control with Git.
So think of Git as your project history tracker.
So imagine working on a big project and making changes, then realizing something went wrong.
You want to go back to an earlier version, right?
So that's where Git comes in.
And here's what you should practice.
Number one is committing changes.
So save different versions of your work as you progress.
And then branching, which means work on separate features without affecting your main code.
And then comes merging, which means combining changes from different versions once they are ready.
So you have to set up an account on GitHub or GitLab to store your projects online.
So not only will this be super useful, but it'll also start building your portfolio.
Now next is data structures and algorithms.
So think of data structures like tools in a toolkit.
So each one like arrays, stacks, queues, etc., serves a specific purpose.
So here's how to approach them.
Number one, arrays and lists.
Now arrays and lists are for storing data in sequence.
After that, you can get familiar with stacks and queues.
So stacks and queues are for tasks that need order data access.
And then you have sorting and searching algorithms.
So these make your programs more efficient, and that's super important in machine learning where data can get massive.
So the goal here is to build up your problem solving skills, which are key to machine learning success.
So take it slow, practice daily, and you'll see progress.
Now in the third month, learn to access data with SQL.
So in machine learning, a lot of work involves accessing and organizing data from databases.
So SQL, a structured query language, is your ticket to getting the data you need for training ML models.
So here's what you should focus on.
Select and where.
So these commands help you pull specific pieces of data.
And then you can move on to joins.
Joins usually combine data from different tables.
So this is so powerful that you'll use it all the time.
And then comes group by and aggregate functions.
They are great for summarizing data to find patterns.
So spend time working with sample databases you can find online and practice writing queries.
Being comfortable with SQL will save you time when preparing data for your models.
Now after completing the third month, you can move on to mathematics, which is building your analytical mind.
So this month we are tackling the math behind machine learning.
So don't worry, you don't need to be a math genius, but understanding certain concepts will make everything feel less mysterious.
So in this month you have to focus on linear algebra.
So this is the math behind how models see data.
So you can study vectors, matrices, and operations like multiplication.
Next comes calculus.
So you'll use calculus to help your models learn.
So you have to focus on derivatives and gradients, which help minimize errors in your model.
And then you can move on to probability and stylistics.
So understanding probability helps you make sense of data.
So learn about distributions like normal distribution, binormal distribution, and then variance and standard deviation.
So once you have learnt maths, next you'll be moving on to data handling and visualization, which is the heart of machine learning as you all know.
So with math under your belt, it's time to dig into data handling and visualization.
So data preparation is vital because your model is only as good as the data you feed it.
So number one comes data manipulation.
So using pandas and numpy, you'll clean and organize your data.
You might be removing missing values like clean up messy data so it doesn't confuse your model, and then you will learn transforming variables like converting data into formats that work for models.
And then you will move on to encoding categorical data, like changing text data, like female or male, into numbers.
Now, once you're done with data manipulation, next comes data visualization.
So visualization is how you get to see your data before training a model.
So here you have to learn mathplotlib and C bond.
So you can create line charts, histograms, scatter plots, and heat maps.
So this lets you explore patterns and spot outliers.
So understanding these patterns in your data is crucial for building effective models.
Now, in the sixth month, you will be moving on to the machine learning fundamentals.
So now it's time to start building your own models.
So you will focus on two main types of machine learning this month.
Number one comes the supervised learning.
So, this is when you train a model on label data where the outcome is already known.
So, you will work with algorithms like linear regression, which predicts a continuous outcome.
Then you will work with decision trees, which breaks down decisions into a tree structure, and then you have support vector machines under supervised learning, which updates data into classes.
Now, after supervised learning comes unsupervised learning.
So here your model identifies patterns in data without labeled outcomes.
So two popular techniques in unsupervised learning is number one clustering, like K means clustering, which means group similar data points, and then you have dimensionality reduction.
This reduces data complexity by focusing on key features.
So you can use Scikit Learn to try out these algorithms on sample datasets.
So this will give you hands-on experience with model training and you will learn to fine-tune them to get better results.
Now before moving on, if you are interested in advancing your career in the field of AI and machine learning, Simply Learn's postgraduate program, Delivery in collaboration with Purdue
University and IBM, is a perfect opportunity.
This highly ranked program offers a comprehensive curriculum covering essential topics like machine learning, deep learning, NLP, computer vision,
reinforcement learning, generative AI, prompt engineering, and many more.
With hands-on experience to 25 plus projects and access to 20 plus cutting-edge tools, you will gain the skills needed to excel in today's competitive job market.
So join now and elevate your expertise with the backing of Purdue's Academic Excellence and IBM's industry leading insights.
You can find the course link in the description box and pin comments.
Now moving on to the 7th month, you'll be building and training models with advanced libraries.
So by now you have experimented with some basic models.
So let's step it up with advanced tools like TensorFlow and PyTorch.
So these libraries offer more flexibility and power. So TensorFlow and PyTorch, so here you can start with simple models and work your way up.
So these libraries allow for building neural networks, which you will be studying more on the next month.
Now once you have become familiar with TensorFlow and PyTorch, you can move on to model training and evaluation.
So you have to learn to split data into training and testing sets and evaluate models using metrics like accuracy and precision.
So your goal this month should be to get comfortable with these libraries and understand how they handle data and model training behind the scenes.
So once you are done with this, you will be moving on to the eighth month where you'll be dealing with advanced machine learning.
So this month's concept will be number one on ensemble learning, which means combining multiple models to get better predictions.
So here you'll be learning about bagging.
For example, random forests.
Here multiple decision trees make predictions and then you have boosting like ADI boost, XG Boost.
So models learn from each other's mistakes over here.
And after ensembled learning comes deep learning.
So here you explore neural networks which mimic the human brain.
So you'll learn about neural network basics.
So you can start with simple, fully connected networks, and then you can move on to backpropagation and gradient descent.
So these help your model learn and improve.
So you can use TensorFlow or PyTorch to practice building neural networks.
So you can work on projects to reinforce these concepts.
Now moving on, you have to specialize on topics like NLP and computer vision.
So machine learning applications are so powerful, and here you'll get a taste of two major fields, which is NLP or natural language processing.
So here they work with text data for tasks like sentiment analysis and text classification.
So you can start with basic pre-processing like tokenization, stop word removal, and move to building simple NLP models.
After that, you can try out computer vision.
So for image data, you have to learn CNNs, convolutional neural networks.
So these networks analyze visual patterns, making them ideal for image classification.
So you practice with open data sets like text, documents, or images and apply the concepts you will learn to see results in real world applications.
Now in the 10th month, you'll be dealing with model deployment, which is bringing your models to life.
So here you'll be using Flask or Django, so you can use these frameworks to create a web API so users can interact with your model.
For example, build a web app that lets people upload images for classification.
And then you can also try to Docker to package your model and its dependencies so it can run on any machine.
So this is super helpful for deploying models without compatibility issues.
So by the end of this month, you'll be able to show your models to the world.
So moving on to the 11th month, you'll be starting with cloud and production.
So this month you'll learn how to deploy models on the cloud and ensure they perform well in real-world environments.
So you'll be dealing with cloud platforms like AWS, Google Cloud, or Azure.
So you have to learn to deploy models on the cloud for wider accessibility and scalability.
And then comes monitoring and maintenance.
So understand how to track your model's performance over time and update it as needed.
So these skills are essential for maintaining models in production and ensuring they skill reliability.
And finally, you will be creating real-world projects and portfolio building.
So here you have to choose topics that interest you and showcase your skills.
So first you can start with full projects.
So complete projects that go from data cleaning and model building to deployment.
So ideas could be a sentiment analysis tool or an image recognition app.
And then you have to build your portfolio.
So organize and document your projects, host them on GitHub, and create an online portfolio to share with potential employers or collaborators.
So by following this roadmap, you'll be well prepared to handle real-world machine learning challenges and have an impressive portfolio to show for it. Welcome to Machine Learning Tutorial Part 2.
My name is Richard Kirschner with the Simply Learn team.
That is www.simplylearn.com.
Get certified, get ahead.
Today in our second tutorial, we're going to cover K-means and linear regression, along with going over the quiz questions we had during our first tutorial.
What's in it for you?
We're going to cover clustering.
What is clustering?
K-means clustering, which is one of the most common used clustering tools out there, including a flow chart to understand k-mean clustering and how it functions.
And then we'll do an actual Python live demo on clustering of cars based on brands.
Then we're going to cover logistic regression. What is logistic regression?
Logistic regression curve and sigmoid function.
And then we'll do another Python code demo to classify a tumor as malignant or benign based on features.
And let's start with clustering.
Suppose we have a pile of books of different genres.
Now we divide them into different groups like fiction, horror, education, and as we can see from this young lady, she definitely is into heavy horror.
You can just tell by those eyes and the maple Canadian leaf on her shirt.
But we have fiction, horror, and education, and we want to go ahead and divide our books up.
Well, organizing objects into groups based on similarity is clustering.
And in this case, as we're looking at the books, we're talking about clustering things with known categories.
But you can also use it to explore data. So you might not know the categories, you just know that you need to divide it up in some way to conquer the data and to organize it better.
But in this case, uh we're going to be looking at clustering in specific categories.
And let's just take a deeper look at that.
We're going to use k-means clustering.
K-means clustering is probably the most commonly used clustering tool in the machine learning library.
K-Means clustering is an example of unsupervised learning.
If you remember from our previous thing, it is used when you have unlabeled data. So we don't know the answer yet. We have a bunch of data that we want to cluster to different groups.
Define clusters in the data based on feature similarity.
So we've introduced a couple terms here. We've already talked about unsupervised learning and unlabeled data.
So we don't know the answer yet. We're just going to group stuff together and see if we can find an unanswer of how things connect.
We've also introduced feature similarity, features being different features of the data.
Now with books, we can easily see fiction and horror and history books, but a lot of times with data, some of that information isn't so easy to see right when we first look at it.
And so K means is one of those tools where we can start finding things that connect that match with each other.
Suppose we have these data points and want to assign them into a cluster.
Now when I look at these data points, I would probably group them into two clusters just by looking at them. I'd say two of these group of data kind of come together.
But in k-means, we pick k clusters and assign random centroids to clusters, where the k clusters represents two different clusters.
We pick k clusters and sign random centroids to the clusters, then we compute distance from objects to the centroids.
Now we form new clusters based on minimum distances and calculate the centroids.
So we figure out what the best distance is for the centroid, then we move the centroid and recalculate those distances.
Repeat previous two steps iteratively till the cluster centroids stop changing their positions and become static.
Repeat previous two steps iteratively till the cluster centroids stop changing and the positions become static.
Once the clusters become static, then k means clustering algorithm is said to be converged.
And there's another term we see throughout machine learning is converged. That means whatever math we're using to figure out the answer has come to a solution or it's converged on an answer.
Shall we see the flow chart to understand?
Make a little bit more sense by putting it into a nice easy step by step.
So we start, we choose K, we'll look at the elbow method in just a moment.
We assign random centroids to clusters, and sometimes you pick the centroids, because you might look at the data in a graph and say, oh, these are probably the central points.
Then we compute the distance from the objects to the centroids.
We take that and we form new clusters based on minimum distance and calculate their centroids.
Then we compute the distance from objects to the new centroids.
And then we go back and repeat those last two steps. We calculate the distances.
So as we're doing it, it brings into the new centroid, and then we move the centroid around and we figure out what the best which objects are closest to each centroid.
So the objects can switch from one centroid to the other as the centroids are moved around.
And we continue that until it is converged.
Let's see an example of this.
Suppose we have this data set of seven individuals and their score on two topics, A and B.
So here's our subject, in this case referring to the person taking the test.
And then we have subject A where we see what they've scored on their first subject, and we have subject B and we can see what they score on the second subject.
Now let's take two farthest apart points as initial cluster centroids.
Now remember we talked about selecting them randomly, or we can also just put them in different points and pick the furthest one apart so they move together.
Either one works okay, depending on what kind of data you're working on and what you know about it.
So we took the two furthest points, one and one, and five and seven, and now let's take the two farthest apart points as initial cluster centroids.
Each point is then assigned to the closest cluster with respect to the distance from the centroids.
So we take each one of these points in there, we measure that distance, and you can see that if we measured each of those distances,
and you'd use the the uh Pythagorean theorem for a triangle in this case, because you know the x and the y and you can figure out the uh diagonal line from that.
Or you can just take a ruler and put it on your monitor.
That'd be kind of silly, but it would work if you're just eyeballing it.
You can see how they naturally come together in certain areas.
Now we again calculate the centroids of each cluster.
So cluster one and then cluster two, and we look at each individual dot, there's one, two, three, we're in one cluster, uh the centroid then moves over.
It becomes one point eight, comma, two point three. So remember it was at one and one.
Well, the very center of the data we're looking at would put it at the one point roughly two, two, but one point eight and two point three.
And the second one, if we wanted to make the overall mean vector, the average vector of all the different distances to that centroid, we come up with four, comma one
and five, four.
So we've now moved the centroids.
We compare each individual's distance to its own cluster, mean, and to that of the opposite cluster, and we find, build a nice chart on here,
that the as we move that centroid around, we now have a new different kind of clustering of groups, and using Euclidean distance between the points and the mean,
we get the same formula you see a new formula is coming up. So we have our individual dots, distance to the mean, centroid of the cluster, and distance to the mean centroid of the cluster.
Only individual three is nearer to the mean of the opposite cluster, cluster two, than its own cluster one.
And you can see here in the diagram where we've kind of circled that one in the middle.
So when we've moved the cluster the the centroids of the clusters over, one of the points shifted to the other cluster because it's closer to that group of individuals.
Thus, individual three is relocated to cluster two, resulting in a new partition.
And we regenerate all those numbers of how close they are to the different clusters.
For the new clusters, we will find the actual cluster centroids. So now we move the centroids over, and you can see that we've now formed two very distinct clusters on here.
On comparing the distance of each individual's distance to its own cluster mean and to that of the opposite cluster, we find that the data points are stable,
hence we have our final clusters.
Now if you remember I brought up a concept earlier, k mean on the k-means algorithm, choosing the right value of k will help in less number of iterations.
And to find the appropriate number of clusters in a dataset, we use the elbow method.
And within sum of squares, WSS is defined as the sum of the squared distance between each member of the cluster and its centroid.
And so you see what we've done here is we have the number of clusters.
And as you do the same k-means algorithm over the different clusters, and you calculate what that centroid looks like,
and you find the optimal, you can actually find the optimal number of clusters using the elbow of the graph is called as the elbow method.
And in this, we guessed at two just by looking at the data.
But as you can see, the slope, you actually just look for right there where the elbow is in the slope, and you have a clear answer that we want two different to start with k means equals two.
A lot of times people end up computing k-means equals two, three, four, five until they find the value which fits on the elbow joint.
Sometimes you can just look at the data, and if you're really good with that specific domain, remember domain I mentioned that last time, you'll know that that where to pick those numbers
or where to start guessing at what that k-value is.
So let's take this, and we're gonna use a use case using k means clustering to cluster cars into brands using parameters such as horsepower,
cubic inches, make, year, etc.
So we're gonna use the dataset cars data having information about three brands of cars, Toyota, Honda, and Nissan.
We'll go back to my favorite tool, the Anaconda Navigator with the Jupyter Notebook.
And let's go ahead and flip over to our Jupyter Notebook.
And in our Jupyter Notebook, I'm gonna go ahead and just paste the uh basic code that we usually start a lot of these off with.
We're not gonna go too much into this code because we've already discussed NumPy, we've already discussed Mapplot Library and Pandas, NumPy being the number array, pandas
being the pandas data frame, and mapplot for the graphing.
And don't forget uh since if you're using the Jupyter Notebook, you do need the Mapplot library in line so that it plots everything on the screen.
If you're using a different Python editor, then you probably don't need that because it'll have a pop-up window on your computer.
And we'll go ahead and run this just to load our libraries and our setup into here.
The next step is of course to look at our data, which I've already opened up in a spreadsheet.
And you can see here we have the miles per gallon, cylinders, cubic inches, horsepower, weight pounds, how you know how heavy it is, time it takes to get to 60.
My card is probably on this one at about 80 or 90.
What year it is. So this is you can actually see this is kind of older cars, and then the brand Toyota, Honda, Nissan.
So the different cars are coming from all the way from 1971, if we scroll down to uh the 80s. So we have between the 70s and 80s the number of cars that they've put out.
And that's uh we come back here, we're gonna do importing the data. So we'll go ahead and do dataset equals.
And we'll use pandas to read this in, and it's uh from a CSV file.
Remember you can always post this in the comments and request the data files for these.
Either in the comments here on the YouTube video or go to simplylearn.com and request that.
The car CSV, I put it in the same folder as the code that I've stored. So my Python code is stored in the same folder so I don't have to put the full path.
If you store them in different folders, you do have to change this and double check your name variables.
And we'll go ahead and run this, and uh we've chosen dataset arbitrarily because you know it's a dataset we're importing, and we've now imported our cars CSV into the dataset.
As you know, you have to prep the data. So we're going to create the X data. This is the one that we're going to try to figure out what's going on with.
And then there's a number of ways to do this, but we'll do it in a simple loop so you can actually see what's going on. So we'll do 4i nx dot columns.
So we're going to go through each of the columns and a lot of times it's important I'll I'll make lists of the columns and do this because I might remove certain columns,
or there might be columns that I want to be processed differently.
But for this, we can go ahead and take x of i and we want to go fill in a. And that's a pandas command.
But the question is what are we going to fill the missing data with? We definitely don't want to just put in a number that doesn't actually mean something.
And so one of the tricks you can do with this is we can take x of i.
And then in addition to that we want to go ahead and turn this into an integer, because a lot of these are integers. So we'll go ahead and keep it integers. And we add the bracket here.
And a lot of editors will do this. They'll think that you're closing one bracket.
Make sure you get that second bracket in there if it's a double bracket.
That's always something that happens regularly.
So once we have our integer of x of y, this is gonna fill in any missing data with the average.
And I was so busy closing one set of brackets I forgot that the mean is also has brackets in there for the pandas.
So we can see here we're gonna fill in all the data with the average value for that column. So if there's missing data it's in the average of the data it does have.
Then once we've done that, we'll go ahead and loop through it again and just check and see to make sure everything is filled in correctly.
And it will print, and then we take x is null, and this returns a set of the null value or the how many lines are null, and we'll just sum that up
to see what that looks like. And so when I run this, and so with the x, what we want to do is we want to remove the last column because that had the models.
That's what we're trying to see if we can cluster these things and figure out the models.
There is so many different ways to sort the x out. For one, we could take the x and we could go dataset, our variable we're using, and use the iLocation, one of the features that's in pandas.
And we could take that and then take all the rows and all but the last column of the dataset.
And at this time we could do values. We just convert it to values.
So that's one way to do this. And if I let me just put this down here and print X, it's a capital X we chose.
And I run this, you can see it's just the values.
We could also take out the values and it's not gonna return anything because there's no values connected to it.
What I like to do with this is instead of doing the ILocation, which does integers, more common is to come in here and we have our dataset,
and we're gonna do dataset.
or dataset.columns.
And remember that lists all the columns. So if I come in here,
let me just mark that as red, and I print dataset.columns.
You can see that I have my index here. I have my mpg cylinders, everything, including the brand which we don't want.
So the way to get rid of the brand would be to do data columns of everything but the last one, minus one.
So now if I print this, you'll see the brand disappears.
And so I can actually just take dataset columns minus one,
and I'll put it right in here for the columns we're gonna look at.
And uh let's unmark this
and unmark this.
And now if I do an x dot head, I now have a new data frame, and you can see right here we have all the different columns except for the brand at the end of the year.
And it turns out when you start playing with the dataset, you're gonna get an error later on, and it'll say cannot convert string to uh
float value.
And that's because it it for some reason these things the way they recorded them must have been recorded as strings.
So we have a neat feature in here on pandas to convert.
And it is simply convert objects.
And for this we're gonna do convert oops convert underscore
numeric numeric equals true.
And yes, I did have to go look that up. I don't have it memorized, the convert numeric in there. If I'm working with a lot of these things, I remember them.
But um depending on where I'm at, what I'm doing, I usually have to look it up.
And we run that, oops, I must have missed something in here. Let me double check my spelling.
And when I double check my spelling, you'll see I missed the first underscore in the convert objects.
And when I run this, it now has everything converted into a numeric value.
Because that's what we're going to be working with is numeric values down here.
And the next part is that we need to go through the data and eliminate null values.
Most people, when they're doing small amounts working with small data pools, discover afterwards that they have a null value and they have to go back and do this.
So you know be aware, whenever we're formatting this data, things are going to pop up and sometimes you go backwards to fix it.
And that's fine. That's just part of exploring the data and understanding what you have.
And I should have done this earlier, but let me go ahead and increase the size of my window one notch.
There we go.
Easier to see.
So we'll do 4i in working with x dot columns. We'll page through all the columns.
And we want to take x of i and we're going to change that and we're going to alter it.
And so with this, we want to go ahead and fill in x of i.
Pandas has the fill in a
and that just fills in any non-existent missing data.
And we'll put my brackets up, and there's a lot of different ways to fill this data.
If you have a really large data set, some people just void out that data because they've and then look at it later in a separate uh exploration of data.
One of the tricks we can do is we can take our column and we can find the means.
And the means is in their our quotation marks.
So we take the columns, we're going to fill in the the non existing one with the means.
The problem is that returns a decimal float. So some of these aren't decimals.
Certainly we need to be a little careful of doing this, but for this example, we're just going to fill it in with the integer version of this.
Keeps it on par with the other data that isn't a decimal point.
And then what we also want to do is we want to double check.
A lot of times you do this first part first to double check, then you do the fill, and then you do it again just to make sure you did it right.
So we're going to go through and test for missing data.
And one of the re ways you can do that is simply go in here
and take our x of i column.
So it's going to go through the x of i column that says is null.
So it's going to return any any place there's a null value, it actually goes through the all the rows of each column is null, and then we want to go ahead and sum that.
So we take that and we add the sum value, and these are all pandas. So is null is a panda command, and so is sum.
And if we go through that and we go ahead and run it,
and we go ahead and take and run that, you'll see that all the columns have zero null values.
So we've now tested and double checked, and our data's nice and clean, we have no null values, everything is now a number value, we turned it into numeric.
And we've removed the last column in our data.
And at this point, we're actually going to start using the elbow method to find the optimal number of clusters.
So we're now actually getting into the sklearn part.
Uh the k means clustering on here.
I guess we'll go ahead and zoom it up one more knot so you can see what I'm typing in here.
And then from sklearn, we're going to or sklearn
cluster,
we're going to import
k
means.
I always forget to capitalize the k and the m when I do this.
So it's capital K, capital M, K means.
And we'll go and create a um array, WCSS equals we'll make it an empty array.
If you remember from the elbow method from our slide,
within the sums of squares, WSS is defined as the sum of square distance between each member of the cluster and its centroid.
So we're looking at that change in differences as far as a square distance.
And we're going to run this over a number of k mean values.
In fact, let's go for i in range, we'll do eleven of them.
Range zero of eleven.
And the first thing we're going to do is we're going to create the actual
all lowercase.
And so we're going to create this object
from the k-means that we just imported.
And the variable that we want to put into this is in
clusters. And we're going to set that equals to i.
That's the most important one because we're looking at how increasing the number of clusters changes our answer.
There are a lot of settings to the k-means.
Our guys in the back did a great job just kind of playing with some of them.
The most common ones that you see in a lot of stuff is how you init your k-means.
So we have k-means plus plus plus plus.
This is just a tool to let the model itself be smart how it picks its centroids to start with, its initial centroids.
We only want to iterate no more than 300 times. We have a max iteration we put in there.
We have an the nth init, the random state equals zero.
You really don't need to worry too much about these when you're first learning this. As you start digging in deeper, you start finding that these are shortcuts that will speed up the process
as far as the setup. But the big one that we're working with is the in clusters equals i. So we're gonna literally train our k-means eleven times. We're gonna do this process eleven times.
And if you're working with uh big data, you know the first thing you do is you run a small sample of the data so you can test all your stuff on it.
And you can already see the problem that if I'm gonna iterate through a terabyte of data eleven times, and then the k-means itself is iterating through the data multiple times,
that's a heck of a process.
So you've got to be a little careful with this.
A lot of times though, you can find your um elbow, using the elbow method, find your optimal number on a sample of data, especially if you're working with larger data sources.
So we want to go ahead and take our k-means and we're just gonna fit it.
If you're looking at any of the sklearn, very common you fit your model.
If you remember correctly, our variable we're using is the capital X.
And once we fit this value, we go back to the array we made, and we want to go ahead and just appin that value on the end.
And it's not the actual fit we're pinning in there, it's like when it generates it, it generates the value you're looking for is inertia.
So k means.
And
let's get a visual on this.
We'll do our plt plot, and what we're plotting here
is first the x-axis, which is range 011, so that will generate a nice little plot there, and the WCSS
for our y-axis.
It's always nice to give our uh plot a title.
And let's see, we'll just give it the elbow method for the title, and let's give some labels. So let's go ahead and do plt
x label.
And what we'll do, we'll do number of clusters for that, and plt y label.
And for that we can do oops, there we go.
WCSS, since that's what we're doing on the plot on there. And finally we want to go ahead and display our graph, which is simply plt. oops, dot show.
There we go. And because we have it set to inline, it'll appear inline.
Hopefully I didn't make a type error on there.
And you can see we get a very nice graph. You can see a very nice elbow joint there at uh two, and again, right around three and four, and then after that there's not very much.
Now, as a data scientist, if I was looking at this, I would do either three or four, and I'd actually try both of them to see what the uh
output looked like.
And they've already tried this in the back, so we're just going to use three as a setup on here.
And let's go ahead and see what that looks like when we actually use this to show the different kinds of cars.
And so let's go ahead and apply the k-means to the car's dataset.
And basically, we're going to copy the code that we looped through up above, where k-means equals k-means number of clusters, and we're just going to set the number of clusters to three.
Since that's what we're going to look for.
And you could do three and four on this and graph them just to see how they come up differently.
But for this we're just going to set it to three.
Go ahead and create our own variable, yk means, for our answers.
And we're going to set that equal to whoops, I double equal there, to k means.
But we're not going to do a fit. We're going to do a fit predict is the setup you want to use.
And when you're using untrained models, you'll see um a slightly different, because usually you see fit and then you see just the predict.
But we want to both fit and predict the k-means on this.
And that's fit underscore predict, and then our capital X is the data we're working with.
And before we plot this data, we're going to do a little pandas trick. We're going to take our X value and we're going to set X as matrix.
So we're converting this into a nice rows and columns kind of setup, but we want the we're going to have columns equals none, so it's just going to be a matrix of data in here.
And let's go ahead and run that.
A little warning.
You'll see this warnings pop up because things are always being updated.
So there's like minor changes in the versions and future versions.
Instead of matrix, now the it's more common to set it at dot values instead of doing as matrix.
But MASMatrix works just fine for right now.
But let's go ahead and dive in and plot this and see what that looks like.
And before we dive into plotting this data, I always like to take a look and see what I am plotting.
So let's take a look at y k means. I'm just going to print that out down here.
And we see we have an array of answers. We have two, one, zero, two, one, two.
So it's clustering these different rows of data based on the three different spaces it thinks it's going to be.
And then let's go ahead and print x and see what we have for x.
And we'll see that x is an uh array, it's a matrix. So we have our different values in the array.
And what we're going to do, it's very hard to plot all the different values in the array. So we're only going to be looking at the first two, or positions zero and one.
And if you were doing a full presentation in front of the board meeting, you might actually do a little different than and dig a little deeper into the different aspects,
because this is all the different columns we looked at. But we'll only look at columns one and two for this to make it easy.
So let's go ahead and clear this data out of here and let's bring up our plot. And we're going to do a scatter plot here. So PLT, scatter,
and
this looks a little complicated, so let's explain what's going on with this.
We're going to take the x values
and we're only interested in y of k means equals zero, the first cluster.
Okay?
And then we're going to take value zero for the x-axis, and then we're going to do the same thing here.
We're only interested in k means equals zero, but we're going to take the second column. So we're only looking at the first two columns in our answer or in the data.
And then the guys in the back played with this a little bit to make it pretty.
And they discovered that it looks good if it has a size equals 100. That's the size of the dots.
We're going to use red for this one. And when they were looking at the data and what came out, it was definitely the Toyota on this. We're just going to go ahead and label it Toyota.
Again, that's something you'd really have to explore in here as far as playing with those numbers and see what looks good.
We'll go ahead and hit enter in there.
And I'm just going to paste in the next two lines, which is the next two cars.
And this is our NISA and Honda.
And you'll see with our scatter plot we're now looking at where y underscore k means equals one.
And we want the zero column and y k means equals two. Again, we're looking at just the first two columns, zero and one, and each of these rows then corresponds to Nissan and Honda.
And I'll go ahead and hit enter on there.
And uh finally, let's take a look and put the centroids on there.
Again, we're going to do a scatter plot.
And on the centroids, you can just pull that from our k means, the uh model we created, dot cluster centers, and we're gonna just do um
All of them in the first number, and all of them in the second number, which is 0, 1, because you always start with 0 and 1.
And then if we were playing with the size and everything to make it look good, we'll do a size of 300.
We're gonna go make the color yellow, and we'll label them uh it's always good to have some good labels, centroids.
And then we do want to do a title. PLT title.
And pop up there.
PLT title, because you always make want to make your graphs look pretty, and we'll call it clusters of car make.
And one of the features of the plot library is you can add a
legend.
It'll automatically bring in it since we've already labeled the different aspects of the legend with Toyota, Nissan, and Honda.
And finally we want to go ahead and show.
So we can actually see it. And remember it's in line. Uh so if you're using a different editor that's not the Jupyter Notebook, you'll get a pop-up of this.
And you should have a nice set of clusters here.
So we can look at this and we have uh clusters of Honda and green, Toyota and red, Nissan and purple, and you can see where they put the centroids to separate them.
Now, when we're looking at this, we can also plot a lot of other different data on here as far because we only looked at the first two columns.
This is just column one and two, or zero, one as as you label them in computer scripting.
But you can see here we have a nice cluster of car make, and we've able to pull out the data, and you can see how just these two columns form very distinct clusters of data.
So if you were exploring new data, you might take a look and say, well, what makes these different?
Almost going in reverse, you start looking at the data and pulling apart the columns to find out why is the first group set up the way it is.
Maybe you're doing loans and you want to go, well, why is this group not defaulting on their loans, and why is the last group defaulting on their loans?
And why is the middle group 50% defaulting on their bank loans?
And you start finding ways to manipulate the data and pull out the answers you want.
So now that you've seen how to use k-mean for clustering, let's move on to the next topic.
Now let's look into logistic regression.
The logistic regression algorithm is the simplest classification algorithm used for binary or multi-classification problems.
And we can see we have our little girl from Canada who's into horror books is back.
That's actually really scary when you think about that with those big eyes.
In the previous tutorial, we learned about linear regression, dependent and independent variables.
So to brush up, y equals mx plus c, a very basic algebraic function of uh y and x.
The dependent variable is the target class variable we are going to predict.
The independent variables, x1 all the way up to xn, are the features or attributes we're going to use to predict the target class.
We know what a linear regression looks like, but using the graph we cannot divide the outcome into categories.
It's really hard to categorize 1.5, 3.6, 9.8.
Uh for example, a linear regression graph can tell us that with increase in number of hours studied, the marks of a student will increase,
but it will not tell us whether the student will pass or not.
In such cases where we need the output as categorical value, we will use logistic regression.
And for that we're going to use the sigmoid function.
So you can see here we have our marks, 0 to 100, number of hours studied.
That's gonna be what they're comparing it to in this example.
And we usually form a line that says y equals mx plus c.
And when we use the sigmoid function, we have p equals one over one plus e to the minus y.
It generates a sigmoid curve.
And so you can see right here, when you take the uh ln, which is the natural logarithm, I always thought it should be n l, not ln, that's just the inverse of uh
e, your e to the minus y.
And so when we do this we get uh ln of p over one minus p equals m times x plus c.
That's the sigmoid curve function we're looking for.
And we can zoom in on the function, and you'll see that the function as it derives goes to one or to zero, depending on what your x value is.
And the probability if it's greater than 0.5, the value is automatically rounded off to one, indicating that the student will pass.
So if they're doing a certain amount of studying, they will probably pass.
Then you have a threshold value at the point five.
It automatically puts that right in the middle usually.
And your probability if it's less than 0.5, the value rounded off to 0, indicating the student will fail.
So if they're not studying very hard, they're probably going to fail.
This of course is ignoring the outliers of that one student who's just a natural genius and doesn't need any studying to memorize everything.
That's not me, unfortunately. I have to study hard to learn new stuff.
Problem statement.
To classify whether a tumor is malignant or benign.
And this is actually one of my favorite data sets to play with because it has so many features, and when you look at them, you really are hard to understand.
You can't just look at them and know the answer.
So it gives you a chance to kind of dive into what data looks like when you aren't able to understand the specific domain of the data.
But I also want you to remind you that in the domain of medicine, if I told you that my probability was really good at classified things at
say 90% or 95%, and I'm classifying whether you're going to have a malignant or a benign tumor, I'm guessing that you're going to go get it tested anyways.
So you've got to remember the domain we're working with.
So why would you want to do that if you know you're just going to go get a biopsy because you know it's that serious? This is like an all or nothing.
Just referencing the domain, it's important.
It might help the doctor know where to look just by understanding what kind of tumor it is.
So it might help them or aid them in something they missed from before.
So let's go ahead and dive into the code and I'll come back to the domain part of it in just a minute.
So use case, and we're going to do our normal imports here.
We're importing Numbi, Pandas, CBORN, the Matplot Library, and we're going to do Matplotlibrary in line since I'm going to switch over to Anaconda.
So let's go ahead and flip over there and get this started.
So I've opened up a new window in my Anaconda Jupyter Notebook.
And by the way, Jupyter Notebook, uh, you don't have to use Anaconda for the Jupyter Notebook.
I just love the interface and all the tools that Anaconda brings.
So we got our import numpy as in P for our uh NumPy number array. We have our pandas PD.
We're going to bring in Cborn to help us with our graphs as SNS.
So many really nice tools in both CBON and Matplotlibrary.
And we'll do our Matplotlibrary.pyplot as plt, and then of course we want to let it know to do it in line. And let's go ahead and just run that so it's all set up.
And we're just going to call our data data. Not creative today.
Uh equals PD, and this happens to be in a csv file.
So we'll use a pd.read underscore csv, and I happen to name the file or renamed it data for p2.csv.
You can of course um write in the comments below the YouTube and request for the dataset itself or go to the Simply Learn website, and we'll be happy to supply that for you.
And let's just um open up the data before we go any further, and let's just see what it looks like in a spreadsheet.
So when I pop it open in a local spreadsheet, and this is just a CSV file, comma separated variables, we have an ID.
So I guess the um categorize this for reference or what ID which test was done, the diagnosis, M for malignant, B for B9. So there's two different options on there.
And that's what we're going to try to predict is the M and B and test it.
And then we have like the radius mean or average, the texture average, perimeter mean, area mean, smoothness.
I don't know about you, but unless you're a doctor in the field, most of the stuff, I mean you can guess what concave means just by the term concave.
But I really wouldn't know what that means in the measurements they're taking.
So they have all kinds of stuff like how smooth it is, uh the symmetry, and these are all float values. We can just page through them real quick.
And you'll see there's I believe 36 if I remember correctly in this one.
So there's a lot of different values they take, and all these measurements they take when they go in there and they take a look at the different growth, the tumorous growth.
So back in our data, and I put this in the same folder as the code. So I saved this code in that folder.
Obviously, if you have it in a different location, you want to put the full path in there.
And we'll just do um pandas
first five lines of data with the data.head.
And we run that, we can see that we have pretty much what we just looked at. We have an ID, we have a diagnosis.
If we go all the way across, you'll see all the different columns coming across displayed nicely for our data.
And while we're exploring the data, our uh C born, which we referenced as SNS, makes it very easy to go in here and do a joint plot.
You'll notice uh very similar to because it is sitting on top of the plot library.
So the joint plot does a lot of work for us.
And we're just gonna look at the first two columns that we're interested in, the radius mean and the texture mean.
We'll just look at those two columns.
And data equals data.
So that tells it which two columns we're plotting, and then we're gonna use the data that we pulled in. Let's just run that.
And it generates a really nice graph on here.
And there's all kinds of cool things on this graph to look at. I mean we have the texture mean and the radius mean, obviously the axes.
You can also see uh
and uh one of the cool things on here is you can also see the histogram.
They show that for the radius mean.
Where is the most common radius mean come up and where the most common texture is?
That's when we're looking at the text the uh on each growth its average texture and on each radius its average uh radius on there.
It gets a little confusing because we're talking about the individual objects average, and then we can also look over here and see the the histogram showing us the median
or how common each measurement is.
And that's only two columns, so let's dig a little deeper into C-borne.
They also have a heat map.
And if you're not familiar with heat maps, a heat map just means it's in color. That's all that means. Heat map.
I guess the original ones were plotting heat density on something, and so ever since then it's just called a heat map.
And we're gonna take our data and get our corresponding numbers to put that into the heat map, and that's simply data.co r
for that.
That's a pandas expression. So remember we're working in a pandas data frame, so that's one of the cool tools in pandas for our data.
And let's just pull that information into a heat map and see what that looks like.
And you'll see that we're now looking at all the different features.
We have our ID, we have our texture, we have our area, our compactness, concave points.
And if you look down the middle of this chart, diagonal, going from the upper left to bottom right, it's all white.
That's because when you compare texture to texture, they're identical. So they're a hundred percent, or in this case a perfect one in their correspondence.
And you'll see that when you look at say area or right below it, it has almost a black on there when you compare it to texture.
So these have almost no corresponding data. They don't really form a linear graph or something that you can look at and say how connected they are, they're very scattered data.
This is really just a really nice graph to get a quick look at your data.
It doesn't so much change what you do, but it changes verifying.
So when you get an answer or something like that, or you start looking at some of these individual pieces, you might go, hey, that doesn't match.
According to showing our uh heat map, this should not correlate with each other. And if it is, you're gonna have to start asking, well, why? What's going on, what else is coming in there?
But it does show some really cool information on here.
I mean we can see from the ID, there's no real one feature that just says, if you go across the top line,
that lights up. There's no one feature that says, hey, if the area is a certain size, then it's gonna be benign or malignant.
It says there's some that sort of add up. And that's a big hint in the data that we're trying to ID this, whether it's malignant or benign, that's a big hint to us as data scientists to go,
okay, we can't solve this with any one feature.
It's going to be something that includes all the features or many of the different features to come up with a solution for it.
And while we're exploring the data, let's explore one more area and let's look at data.isnull.
We want to check for null values in our data.
If you remember from earlier in this tutorial, we did it a little differently where we added stuff up and summed them up.
You can actually with pandas do it really quickly data.is null and sum it, and it's going to go across all the columns.
So when I run this,
you're going to see all the columns come up with no null data.
So we've just just to rehash these last few steps,
we've done a lot of exploration.
We have looked at the first two columns
and seen how they plot with the C borne with a joint plot which shows both the histogram and the data plotted on the X and Y coordinates.
And obviously, you can do that more in detail
with different columns and see how they plot together.
And then we took and did the Cborne heat map, the SNS dot heat map of the data.
And you can see right here where it did a nice job showing us some bright spots where stuff correlates with each other and forms a very nice combination
or points of scattering points.
And you can also see areas that don't.
And then finally we went ahead and checked the data.
Is the data a null value?
Do we have any missing data in there?
Very important step because it'll crash later on.
If you forget to do this step, it will remind you when you get that nice error code that says null values.
Okay. So not a big deal if you miss it, but it it's no fun having to go back when you're when you're in a huge process and you've missed this step, and now you're ten
steps later and you've got to go remember where you were pulling the data in.
So we need to go ahead and pull out our X and our Y.
So we just put that down here.
And we'll set the X equal to.
And there's a lot of different options here.
Certainly we could do X equals all the columns except for the first two.
Because if you remember the first two is the ID and the diagnosis.
So that certainly would be an option.
But what we're going to do is we're actually going to focus on the worst.
The worst radius, the worst texture, parameter, area, smoothness, compactness, and so on.
One of the reasons to start dividing your data up when you're looking at this information is sometimes the data will be the same data coming in.
So if I have two measurements coming into my model, it might overweigh them.
It might overpower the other measurements because it's measuring it's basically taking that information in twice.
That's a little bit past the scope of this tutorial.
What I want you to take away from this though is that we are dividing the data up into pieces, and our team in the back went ahead and said, hey, let's just look at the worst.
So I'm going to create a an array, and you'll see this array radius worst, texture worst, perimeter worst.
We've just taken the worst of the worst, and I'm just going to put that in my X.
So this X is still a pandas data frame, but it's just those columns.
And our y, if you remember correctly, is going to be, oops, hold on one second.
It's not x, it's data.
There we go. So x equals data, and then it's a list of the different columns, the worst of the worst.
And if we're going to take that, then we have to have our answer for our y for the stuff we know.
And if you remember correctly, we're just going to be looking at
the diagnosis. That's all we care about is what is it diagnosed? Is it uh benign or malignant?
And since it's a single column, we can just do diagnosis. Oh, I forgot to put the brackets around the there we go.
Okay.
So it's just diagnosis on there. And we can also real quickly do like an x dot head if you want to see what that looks like.
And y.head
and run this.
And you'll see um it only does the last one, I forgot about that if you don't do print.
You can see that the the y dot head is just mmm because the first ones are all malignant.
And if I run this, the x.head is just the first five values of radius worst, texture worst, parameter worst, area worst, and so on.
I'll go ahead and take that out.
So moving down to the next step, we've built our two data sets, our answer, and then the features we want to look at.
In data science, it's very important to test your model.
So we do that by splitting the data.
And from SK Learn Model Selection, we're going to import train test splits. So we're going to split it into two groups.
There are so many ways to do this. I noticed in one of the more modern ways they actually split it into three groups, and then you model each group and test it against the other groups.
So you have all kinds of and there's reasons for that, which is past the scope of this, and for this particular example isn't necessary.
For this, we're just going to split it into two groups, one to train our data and one to test our data.
And the sklearn dot model selection, we have train test split.
You could write your own quick code to do this. We just randomly divide the data up into two groups, but they do it for us nicely.
And we actually can almost we can actually do it in one statement with this, where we're going to generate four variables capital X train, capital X
test.
So we have our training data we're going to use to fit the model, and then we need something to test it.
And then we have our Y train, so we're going to train the answer, and then we have our test. So this is the stuff we want to see how good it did on our model.
And we'll go ahead and take our train test split that we just imported.
And we're going to do X and our Y, our two different data that's going in for our split.
And then the guys in the back came up and wanted us to go ahead and use a test size equals 0.3.
That's test underscore size.
Random state, it's always nice to kind of switch a random state around, but not that important.
What this means is that the test size is we're going to take 30% of the data and we're going to put that into our test variables, our y test and our X test.
And we're going to do 70% into the X train and the Y train. So we're going to use 70% of the data to train our model and 30% to test it.
Let's go ahead and run that and load those up.
So now we have all our stuff split up and all our data ready to go.
And now we get to the actual logistics part. We're actually going to do our create our model.
So let's go ahead and bring that in from sklearn. We're going to bring in our linear model and we're going to import logistic regression. That's the actual model we're using.
And this we'll call it logmodel.
Oops, there we go. Model.
And let's just set this equal to our logistic regression that we just imported.
So now we have a variable log model set to that class for us to use.
And with most of the uh models in the sklearn, we just need to go ahead and fix it, fit, do a fit on there,
and we use our X train that we separated out with our Y train.
And let's go ahead and run this. So once we've run this, we'll have a model that fits this data, that 70% of our training data.
And of course it prints this out that tells us all the different variables that you can set on there. There's a lot of different choices you can make.
But for word, we're just going to let all the defaults set.
We don't really need to mess with those on this particular example.
And there's nothing in here that really stands out as super important until you start fine-tuning it. But for what we're doing, the basics will work just fine.
And then let's we need to go ahead and test out our model. Is it working?
So let's create a variable y predict.
And this is going to be equal to our log model.
And we want to do a predict. Again, very standard uh format for the sklearn library is taking your model and doing a predict on it.
And we're going to test y predict against the y test. So we want to know what the model thinks it's going to be. That's what our y predict is.
And with that we want the capital X
test.
So we have our train set and our test set.
And now we're going to do our y predict.
And let's go ahead and run that.
And if we uh print
y predict, let me go ahead and run that.
You'll see it comes up and it
prints a nice array of uh B and M for B9 and Malignant
for all the different test data we put in there.
So it does pretty good. We're not sure exactly how good it does, but we can see that it actually works and is functional.
It was very easy to create.
You'll always discover with our data science that as you explore this, you spend a significant amount of time prepping your data
and making sure your data coming in is good.
There's a saying, good data in, good answers out, bad data in, bad answers out.
That's only half the thing.
That's only half of it.
Selecting your models becomes the next part as far as how good your models are.
And then of course fine tuning it depending on what model you're
using. So we come in here, we want to know how good this came out. So we have our why predict here, logmodel.predict x test.
So, for deciding how good our model is, we're going to go from the sklearn.metrics, we're going to import classification report.
And that just reports how good our model is doing.
And then we're going to feed it the model data. And let's just print this out.
And we'll take our classification report
and we're going to put into there
our test, our actual data.
So this is what we actually know is true.
And our prediction, what our model predicted for that data on the test side.
And let's run that and see what that does.
So when we pull that up, you'll see that we have um a precision for B9 and malignant, B and M.
And we have a precision of ninety-three and ninety-one, a total of ninety-two, so it's kind of the average between these two of ninety-two. There's all kinds of different information on here.
Your F1 score,
your recall, your support coming through on this.
And for this, I'll go ahead and just flip back to our slides that they put together for describing it.
And so here we're going to look at the precision using the classification report. And you see this is the same printout I had up above.
Some of the numbers might be different because it does randomly pick out which data we're using.
So this model is able to predict the type of tumor with 91% accuracy.
So we look back here, it's you will see where we have uh B9 am in England. It actually is 92 coming up here.
But we're looking at about a 92, 91% precision.
And remember I reminded you about domains.
So when we're talking about the domain of a medical domain with a very catastrophic outcome, you know, at 91 or 92% precision, you're still gonna go in there and have somebody do a biopsy on it.
Very different than if you're investing money and there's a 92% chance you're gonna earn 10%
and 8% chance you're gonna lose 8%, you're probably gonna bet the money.
Because at that odds it's pretty good that you'll make some money. And in the long run, if you do that enough, you definitely will make money.
And also with this domain, I've actually seen them use this to identify different forms of cancer.
That's one of the things that they're starting to use these models for.
Because then it helps the doctor know what to investigate.
So that wraps up this section.
We're finally going to go in there and let's discuss the answer to the quiz asked in Machine Learning Tutorial Part 1.
Can you tell what's happening in the following cases?
Grouping documents into different categories based on the topic and content of each document.
This is an example of clustering where k-means clustering can be used to group the documents by topics using bag of words approach.
So if you'd gotten in there that you're looking for clustering, and hopefully you had at least one or two examples like k-means that are used for clustering different things,
then give yourself a two thumbs up.
B.
Identifying handwritten digits and images correctly.
This is an example of classification.
The traditional approach to solving this would be to extract digit-dependent features like curvature of different digits, etc., and then use a classifier like SVM to distinguish between images.
Again, if you got the fact that it's a classification example, give yourself a thumb up.
And if you're able to go, hey, let's use SVM or another model for this, give yourself those two thumbs up on it.
C.
Behavior of a website indicating that the site is not working as designed.
This is an example of anomaly detection.
In this case, the algorithm learns what is normal and what is not normal, usually by observing the logs of the website.
Give yourself a thumbs up if you got that one.
And just for a bonus, can you think of another example of anomaly detection?
One of the ones I use it for my own business is detecting anomalies in stock markets.
Stock markets are very fickled and they behave very erratic.
So finding those erratic areas and then finding ways to track down why they're erratic.
Was something released in social media, was something released you can see where knowing where that anomaly is can help you to figure out what the answer is to it in another area.
D.
Predicting salary of an individual based on his or her years of experience.
This is an example of regression.
This problem can be mathematically defined as a function between independent years of experience and dependent variables, salary of an individual.
And if you guess that this was a regression model, give yourself a thumbs up.
And if you're able to remember that it used between independent and dependent variables and that terms, give yourself two thumbs up.
So to wrap it up, we went over what is t means.
We went through also the chart of choosing your elbow method and assigning a random centroid to the clusters, computing the distance, and then going in there and
figuring out what the minimum centroids is and computing the distance and going through that loop until it gets the perfect centroid.
And we looked into the elbow method to choose for
running our clusters across a number of variables and finding the best location for that.
We did a nice example of clustering cars with c means, even though we only looked at the first two columns to make it simple and easy to graph.
We can easily extrapolate that and look at all the different columns and see how they all fit together.
And we looked at what is a logistic regression.
We discussed the sigmoid function, what is logistic regression, and then we went into an example of classifying tumors with logistics.
I hope you enjoyed part two of machine learning.
So in today's session, we will discuss what RNN model is, moving ahead.
We will see why we should use RNN.
After that, we will see how does RNN work, recurrent neural network.
After covering these topics, we will move forward and see types of RNN, recurrent neural network, and applications of RNN.
At the end, we will do a hands-off live demo of sentiment analysis using RNN.
So before starting, let us have a simple question to brush our knowledge. So, question is what are the applications of RNN? Okay, NLP,
time series, image captioning, and all of the above.
Please answer in the comment section below and we will update the correct answer in the pinned comments or you can pause this video, give it a thought, and answer in the comment section.
Before we move on to the programming part, let's discuss what RNN is and proceed further for the same. So, what is RNN? Recurrent neural network.
So RNN work on the principle of saving output on a particular layer and feeding this back to the input in order to predict the output of the layer.
This is how we can convert a feed neural network into a recurrent neural network, RNN.
The node in different layers of neural network are compressed to form a single layer of recurrent neural network.
A, B, and C are the parameters of neural network.
Now that you understand what RNN is, let's look at the way why RNN.
Okay. So why RNN?
RNN were created because there are few issues in the feed for a neural network. Cannot handle the sequential data, considers only the current input, cannot memorize previous input.
Okay, so the solution of these issues is RNN.
An RNN can handle sequential data accepting the current input data and previously received input data. So RNN can memorize previous input due to their internal memory.
So moving forward, let's see how RNN networks work.
Okay, so the input layer X takes an input to the neural network and process it and passes it into the middle layer.
The middle layer H can consist of multiple hidden layers, each with its own activation function and weight and biases.
If you have a neural network where the various parameters of different hidden layers are not affected by the previous layer, that is the neural network
does not have the memory, then you can use RNN.
So the RNN will standardize the different activation function and weights and biases so that each hidden layer has the same parameter.
Then instead of creating multiple hidden layers, it will create one N loop over it as many times it has required. So moving forward, let's see types of RNN.
So there are four types of RNN
one to one,
one to many, many to many, and many to one.
So let's see one to one RNN.
So this type of neural network is known as the vanilla neural network that is used for general machine learning problems, which has a single input and a single output.
Now see
one to many RNN.
This type of neural network has a single input and multiple outputs.
An example of this is an image captioning.
Now let's see many to one RNN.
This RNN takes a sequence of input and generates a single output.
Sentiment analysis is a good example of this kind of neural network where a given sentence can be classified as expressing positive or negative sentiment.
And the last one is many to many RNN.
This RNN takes a sequence of inputs and generates a sequence of output.
Machine translation is the one of the examples.
So moving forward, let's see application of recurrent neural network.
First one is
image captioning.
RNNs are used to caption an image by analyzing the activities present.
The second one is time series prediction.
Any time series problem like predicting the prices of stocks in a particular month can be solved using RNN.
And the third one is natural language processing.
Text mining and sentiment analysis can be carried out using RNN or NLP, natural language processing.
The fourth one is machine translation.
Given an input in one language, RNNs can be used to translate the input into different languages as output. So now let's move to the programming part.
First we will import some libraries, major libraries for the first we will import for the data frame.
So I will write import
panda
spd.
The second one is import
numpy as np.
So pandas is a software library written for the Python programming language for data manipulation and analysis.
In particular, it offers a data structure and operations for manipulating numerical tables and the time series.
And this numpy.
So for plotting, we will import some libraries like C bond
as
This is nothing just a short form of we don't have to write again and again C bond C bond. We can write SNS.
So then, another one: from
word _cloud,
import
word
_cloud.lib;
dot
by plot
as plt.
Okay, so cbon is a library that uses matplotlib underneath to plot graphs.
It will be used to visualize random distribution.
And the word cloud is a visual representation
of words.
Cloud creators are used to highlight popular words and phrases based on frequency and relevance.
They provide you with quick and simple visual insights that can lead to more in-depth analysis.
And this matplotlib.
Matplotlib is a plotting library for the Python programming language and its numerical mathematical
extension number.
It provides an object-oriented API for embedding plots into applications using general purpose UI.
Okay, like
Tinker, X Python, QT or GTK.
So let's import some
NLTK
Nagal Language Toolkit.
So
I will write import
NLTK.
Okay.
From
NLTK.
And
from NLTK.
NLTK.
The natural language toolkit, or more commonly, NLTK, is a suite of libraries and programs for symbolic and statical natural language processing for English
written and Python programming language.
And this is stop words.
Stop words are words that are so common they are basically ignored by typical tokenizers.
And this word tokenize is a function in Python that splits a given sentence into words using the analytical library.
Okay, so let's import some scikit learn
library.
So for that I will write from sklearn
dot model
selection
import
train
test.
Okay.
Then from
SQLarn
dot feature
extraction,
dot text import
vectorizer.
And then from
sk learn dot
matrices
matrix
import
confusion metric
classification.
Okay.
So SIGETLEARN is a free source software machine learning library for Python programming language.
It features various classification, regression, and clustering algorithms, including support vector machine learning, logistic regression, and many others, like
random forest classifier,
and this train test split method is used to split our data into train and test set.
First, we need to divide our data into features like X and Y labels.
And this TFID vectorizer converts a collection of raw documents into a matrix of TF or IDF features, the fast text
or what to vectorize or what embedding Python implementation.
And this confusion matrix. A confusion matrix is a table that is used to define the performance of a classification algorithm.
Okay,
then we'll import some libraries like from
SKL
dot
linear model
importistic
regression
from
symbol
random
forest classifier.
Okay.
Then from
asky learn dot
nabase
Burnoli.
Okay.
So everything is correct.
You will see while running.
So logistic regression estimate the probability of an event occurring, such as voted or didn't vote, based on a given dataset of the independent variable.
Sorry, linear support vector machine SVC is an algorithm that attempts to find a hyperplane to maximize the distance
between classified samples.
And this random forest classifier creates a set of decision trees from a randomly selected subset of the training set.
And this Bernoulli and Vernolly name base is a part of the name base family. It is based on Bernoulli distribution and accept only binary values that is zero or one.
So let's import some tensor flow. So import
tensor flow,
compad, dot v2
and
import
tensor flow
data sets
as tfts.
So TensorFlow is a free and open source library for machine learning and artificial intelligence across a range of tasks, but has a particular focus on training and inference of deep neural networks.
Okay, let's import
warnings.
So everything is basic, just let's see the pickle. Pickle is a Python is primarily used in serializing and deserializing a Python object structure.
Okay, let's run it.
Let's see how many error
can come.
After that, we will load the data set and uh we will go through data visualization.
Okay, word cloud cannot import name word cloud. Okay, C C will be capital here.
Okay,
it's still loading here.
Let's see.
Okay, so loading is done.
So now let's load the data set. So we'll write data equals to pd dot
seat
underscore csv.
Data set name
data data
test.
So
you can find this data set on the description box below.
Perhaps you pocket come over
to the. okay.
seems fine.
Let me change this first
is using RNN.
So
here I will write data person
data dot sample
data.
Okay.
So let me like brief uh tell you that what we are going to okay.
Let me brief you like what we will do in this uh sentiment analysis using RNM.
So in this demo, like you will see uh text processing on Twitter dataset, and after that we will perform different machine learning algorithms on the data such as logistic reaction,
random forest classifier, SPC name base to classify positive and negative new data.
After that, I will also build uh RNN recurrent neural network, which is the best fit for such textual sentiment analysis.
Okay, since it's a sequential data set, which is requirement for the RNN network.
So let's dive into.
So now
we will see the data, data visualization, data set details target like the polarity of the tweets, zero negative, okay, then the date,
like date of the tweet, and the polarity and the user that what tweeted, then the text.
Okay, so I will write print
data set
shape
data,
comma, shape.
Okay,
wait, let me first do like this, yeah.
So there are twenty,
or you can say two like rows and six number of columns.
Okay, so it is a huge data.
I will you can find this data set from the description box below.
So here let's see the data,
and why I use head, head is used for like
for showing
top ten rows of the dataset.
If you will use tail instead of head, it will show the last 10 rows of the dataset.
Okay, here polarity zero, zero means negative and four means positive.
Okay, like you can consider zero one.
This is ID, date, then query, then user, then the text.
Okay, so
here I will do data
polarity.
Okay,
these are the zero four, okay. Uniqueness zero means negative and the four means positive.
Yeah, replacing the value four as one for the ease of understanding. What I said to you, you can consider as zero, one, so data,
polarity,
four to one
and data.
Now you can see 01010110.
Okay.
So if you will write only head, it will show the top five rows only.
So now let's use one Python function describe
data dot.
Right.
So as you can see here, count is two like,
and the mean of the particular row is this,
and the ID is this standard deviation, minimum value, the 25%, the 50%, and the 75%, and the maximum.
Okay.
So let's see the number of positive versus negative tag the sentence.
So here I will write positives
versus data
polarity.
Theta dot polarity
one
then negatives
data
polarity.
Total
length of
the data is
dot format
data,
dot shape.
Now I will print
the total length, the negative and the positives.
Okay, so number of
positive.
Okay.
So
I will copy
this and paste it here.
And here I will do the changes for the negatives.
Okay, now let's see.
So here polarity is not defined.
So
you as you can see the total length of the data is two lakh, and the number of positive sentences is
like one lakh forty-six.
Number of negatives, okay, spelling is
the number of negative text sentences ninety-nine thousand nine hundred and fifty-four.
Okay, so now we have a brief data.
So now let's get a word count per of text.
So for this,
I will write
count
ten words,
length of
first dot split.
And now let's plot about count distribution for both positive and negative.
So I will create a bar plot. So for that, I will add it
but
data and
text
dot apply
but count.
Okay.
Then I will write P positive equals to data
and
count
data dot polarity
is equals to one.
So
let me copy this only.
Okay, then
PLT. dot figure
and figure size
to
twelve, comma six,
then P L T
L T. dot
forty five
then P L T. dot X level
word count;
PLT. dot Y level
and frequency
will write
G Paso
PRT. dot
comma N
color
equals
alpha
equals to zero point. five
positive.
Then let's make a legend also.
Location should be
right
walls,
data word ground priority goes to
Okay. my bad.
So, as you can see, the positive and the negatives.
Okay.
So these are the like word count distribution for both positive and negative.
So now let's uh what we can do, we can do the get like get the common words in training data set
for the training data set.
So, for that, I will do:
from
collections
import
Counter.
All
words
pursue,
and for
I have
an
test
data
text
to line.
dot,
split,
or word
and
words
if length of
word
than
two,
all
words. dot append
word.
dot
lower
here. I can write counter
all words
dot most
common, then I need twenty.
So as you can see, these are the most common words used like in every sentence.
The and you for have that I am but just like this out over all.
So
these are the most common words, like it used the is used like 64,000 times, and like this, your is used for
eight thousand times,
something like that.
So now we will do some data pro data processing.
Okay,
now let's do the data processing.
So,
live
and s.
Dot
count plot
data
polarity.
These are the uh negatives and is positives.
I guess
that is why it's not looking
so much of different, like there's a slight
46 different, so that is why it's looking almost the same.
Okay,
so now removing the unnecessary columns like query, user word count,
data, dot drop,
date
query
and word count.
Okay.
It will be true.
So here I will write data
words on this okay, my bad.
So here, I will write: data dot drop
ID
command access
one;
then, data dot head
the data.
See we have only the two the polarity and the text.
Okay.
So
now uh let's see the null values.
So data
dot.
Okay.
So now converting Panda's object to a string type.
For that we have to write
text
pursuit data
type
yeah.
So now, download the stop words. NLTK
download.
words,
words
also set
stop
words
in English.
These are some you know, stop words.
So moving forward, let's download
an L ticket dot
download.
Okay.
So
the pre-processing steps taken are like lowercasting. Each text is converted to lowercase, then remover of URLs will do this.
We will do so. Okay. Links starting with STP or STTPS or WW are replaced by like
commas and removing usernames, removing short words, removing stop words, like lematization is the process
will do of con for the converting a word to its base.
Okay.
So for that,
what I will do,
I'll just copy the whole code for you.
Will explain you one by one what I've done.
Okay.
So this is the course for the URL pattern for removing all the ww https and http type of thing,
and removing
them.
Then I have used pattern for the lower casting, removing all the URL.
Okay,
then removing all the usernames like at the red and removing punctuations and stop words.
Okay, like this.
So now, what we have to do: data
processed
tweets
and data
text,
or apply
lambda
acts,
process
and tweets
and print
text
preprocessing
time.
and it will be completed.
The text pre-processing is done.
Okay.
As you can see, the text put pre-processing is done.
So now let's check
data.
As
you can see, see the at the rate and these slices are gone.
Okay.
So now the text is pre-processed.
So now what we will do, we will analyze the data.
So now we are going to analyze the pre-processed data to get an understanding of it. We will plot word clouds for positive and negative tweets from our data set and see which words occurs the most.
Okay, first we will uh create for the negative words or negative tweets. You can see so I will add pld dot figure
and figure size.
Fifteen, comma, fifteen.
Okay.
Then Bird Cloud Cosmo
Bird
Cloud
Max Words
cost to
two thousand, comma.
Right equals to
sixteen hundred,
comma,
height was to
eight hundred,
and rate
dot join the data.
dot polarity.
Then I will write here polarity.
Okay, what equals zero
again
processed tweets.
Then, here
I have to write:
PLT dot show,
may show
Cher
pollution,
bilinear.
Perhaps you forget the comma here.
So
two thousand
then comma width
dot generate.
Okay, what I can do.
Let me run now.
Let's see.
Hope this time it will work.
As you can see, this is
okay, like today I am and work, don't wish, day, need, much.
These are the most negative tweets.
Okay, words from negative tweets you can say.
Right?
So let's see the positive tweets.
Okay.
So the thing will be the same.
Let me copy,
paste it here. So for this, I will do
one.
Take a little bit of time
to come.
Still loading.
Like as you can see, hate can't.
Okay.
Sorry,
these are the negative words.
Okay, still loading.
So let's wait for like a few seconds.
Now you can see the positive words like love, okay. Good,
lol,
and awesome, something like that.
Okay, so these are some
positive words.
So now let's do the vectorization and splitting the data, like storing into input variable process to its to X and output variable polarity to Y.
Okay, we'll do that.
So, X equals to data
process
tweets,
values,
and y equals to
data
reality
dot
values.
Okay.
Now I will write print
text.shape
print
y dot shape.
Okay, cool. So now what we will do, we will convert text to word frequency vectors.
Okay, t a tf to idf. So this is an acronym that stands for term frequency to inverse document frequency, which are the components of the resulting scores
assigned to each word.
Okay, so term frequency this summarizes how often a given in word appears within a document and inverse document frequency this downscales
word that appears a lot across documents.
Okay, so now here we will convert a collection of raw documents to a matrix of TF to IDF features.
Okay, then I will write,
enter
t IDF riser
and sublinear
X, because
print
number of features,
comma, length,
feature names.
So number of feature words are like one seven zero three to one.
Okay, now we will do like
now let's rent the shape.
So the previous data is divided into two sets of data training data and the testing data.
So data set upon which the model would be trained on contains 80% data.
The test data is the data set upon which model would be tested again contains 20% of data.
So for that, I will write extrain,
test,
come of a train,
come of
train
test,
speed.
Random
state
was one zero one.
So
what I will do, I will do the you know, print the shape of X train, Y train, X text, Y test. Like how many columns are there? Rows, not column exactly, the rows are there.
Okay,
so I will paste there.
So see
X train, like this is a total was like two lakh.
Okay, so one lakh sixty thousand in training, as we discussed earlier, like 80% in training and 20%
in testing.
Okay,
so now let's do the model building,
okay.
Model evaluating functions.
So now let's make a model,
okay.
And first I will do I will write and then I will explain you the whole.
Okay.
So here what I did it uh this will tell you the accuracy of the model of training data and the testing data.
Okay, then we will predict the values for test data set and the evaluation for the data set, then we will compute and plot the confusion matrix,
okay. The both the categories negative positives, okay. Group name will be true, negative, and the false positive. Okay,
so
is nothing that's let's run it.
So now what we will do? We will do first for the logistic regression.
So here I will write LG goes to
logistic
regression.
Okay, then history
goes to Lg dot fit
X train,
comma
Y train.
Okay, then model
evaluate
LG.
Now let's see.
This is for the logistic regression.
Okay,
as you can see, the accuracy of the training data is 83%, the testing data is 77%.
so this is the concluding matrix, the predictive value, like these are the categories.
Now let's see for the linear SVM.
For that, I will write SVM
equals two
linear
SVC
and SVM
dot fit,
drain,
comma, white drain
and model
evaluate
SVM.
Okay,
and after that we will do for random forest and the naive base.
Okay, then we will start with the RNN.
So as you can see, the accuracy of training data is very pretty good. 93% and logic is 83%,
and the testing is less than
regression model. Let's see
for the random forest. So I will write here
Rf equals to
random forest
specifier
centimeters
equals to twenty.
Then
RF dot
strain,
comma,
y, drain,
and model
evaluate.
After this we will do for the neighbors
and after that we will move on to the our main model RNN recurrent neural networks.
It's still loading.
So
as you can see the confusion matrix
So training data accuracy is 75% very less. So now let's see the last model nay base.
Okay.
So N B equals to
know Li
N B,
N B dot fit
white train,
then model
evaluate.
So nay base training eighty-six seventy-six.
So as far
linear SCC has the best
test training uh accuracy, you can say, and the best
testing accuracy is 7676.45 77. See logistics variation.
So now let's move to the our main model RN.
So what is RNN?
Recurrent neural network at the start,
are the state-of-the-art algorithm for sequential data and are used by Apple CD and Google search voice.
It is the first algorithm that remembers its input due to an internal memory, which makes it perfectly suited for machine learning problems that involve sequential data.
And that is one more thing: embedding layer.
Embedding layer is one of the available layers in Keras.
This is mainly used in natural language processing related applications such as language modeling.
Embedding can also be used with other tasks that involve neural networks.
While dealing with NLP problems, we can use pre-trained word embeddings such as glow.
Alternatively, we can also train our own embeddings using Keras embedding layer.
You
can check it out, were introduced by SkyMeter.
These have widely been used for speech recognition, language processing, sentiment analysis, and text protection.
If you are going deep into LSTM, we should first understand the need of LSTM, which can be explained by the drawback of practical use of RNN.
So let's start with RNA.
Okay.
So here I will import in some libraries.
So after that, I will write import
Keras
version
two point one one zero. Okay, fine.
So now let's
end.
Test, comma
why train
why test?
To train
test
with
tweets, comma, data, dot polarity,
dot
values,
and
test
size,
plus two zero point two.
Test size zero point two means
like eighty and twenty percent
thing,
eighty two training and then
twenty percent to
testing.
Okay,
then
let's
the model evaluation.
Okay.
So I will these are Relu, Sigmo, and all the you know the layers.
So now this epok it will run till five thousand. Like
count will go till five thousand.
Okay, see the five thousand and it will go to one to ten, so it will take time. So I will get back to you after this completing this. Okay.
Now, as you can see, uh the box
ran successfully.
Okay,
so what should I do?
But I will give some space here.
Oh, now we will see the positive and negative outcome.
Okay, this is something like testing.
Okay, we will test, we will predict,
we will give one uh a sentence and then we will predict
it is coming right or wrong. The accuracy is giving a right or wrong.
Okay, so here I will write
sequence
request to
tokenizer.
Dot
text
to
sequences.
Then I will write this
data science
article
this
worst.
Okay.
So here I will write test equals to pad
sequences,
and here I will write sequence,
comma
max length
equals to
max length.
Then I will write here: prediction equals to
write model.
then we'll write model twelve
to dot predict,
then test.
Okay.
If prediction
is greater than zero point five means fifty percent,
then
it should print
positive.
Okay.
Negative.
Okay, let me run this.
Okay, sequential object is no
okay. Spell let's take
The negative because it is the word burst,
it is showing correct now. Check from the RNN model. So model equals to KS dot models
dot load
models.
Here we will load RNN model RN underscore model
dot sg
f file.
It is pretend model.
Okay, pretend Rnn model.
So sequence
tokenizer
dot text
to sequences.
Then
I will write here this
ML
course
is test.
Okay.
Underscore sequences
sequence
underscore length.
Okay, then prediction
equals to model
dot predict,
then test
if prediction is greater than zero point five,
print
positive.
Means fifty percent, more than fifty percent.
Else,
print negative
attribute load models
positive, because this ML course is best,
so there is no negative word.
Okay.
So what we will do now, we will do model saving, loading and prediction.
so for that, uh, I will write import
pickle
by pursuit, open
vectorizer
and
w.
here I will write pickle
dot dump,
dump
vector file vector.
Okay.
So like this, I have to write for nay base, logistic deviation, S VM and random forest.
So
what I will do?
Okay, let's run this.
Okay.
So
now what we have to do, we have to predict using saved model.
Okay.
What we will do here? We will load model first and we will predict.
So
first I will write the function name load
models
and we will load the vectorizer. So, file equals to
open
vectorizer,
dot pickle
rb
vectorizer
load
file;
that file dot close.
Now I am loading the logistic regression model.
So for that, we have to write: open
B
LG equals to
pickle
road
that file dot close
dungeon.
Okay.
Yeah.
So now we will predict the sentiment. So for that I will write DF
predict
riser
text.
Okay.
So here we will predict the sentiment. So, for that
process
underscore text
equals to
process
underscore
sentiments
for
sentiment in
text
and
data
characterizer.
Dot
transformations,
understand
then sentiment
to model.
Dot predict.
here I will make a list of text with sentiment. So for that I will add data equals to M DRA
then for
text
prediction
and zip
text comma sentiment
data.
Okay
and we will convert the list into Pantas data frame.
So for that, I will add df equals to
td dot data frame
comma columns
pursue
text,
comma
sentiment.
Then D F equals two D F dot
replace
comma, one
negative
comma
positive.
So at last I will write here Fosto.
Then here we will load in the model vectorizer,
comma, LG plus two
load.
Here we text to classify like what should be in the list.
So
text question.
Here I will like I love machine.
Johnny
P, and so
here, DF equation
predict
retrizer,
comma text,
then print
df, not
head.
I love machine learning positive. Bug is so active, positive. John I feel so good, negative.
Okay, there is
and
yeah, see now it's coming okay.
This is how you can do the sentiment analysis using uh RNM model. Here we have loaded RNN model, so it is showing right. So let's do them as poses,
right here
at
why
negative.
Okay.
RNN model is working so right.
Today we are going to explore K nearest neighbors or KNN, which is one of the most popular algorithms in data science.
Python is a powerful tool for data science, and KNN is great for classifying data by predicting the category of sample base on its closest neighbor.
This algorithm is used in many fields like healthcare, finance, and agriculture, helping us make decisions based on data.
The best part, it is really easy to use. You just need to pick a number for K and choose a distance function to compare data points.
However, KNN has its downsides. It doesn't work well with the large dataset and it requires proper scaling of the data to get accurate results.
In this video, we will show you how KNN works with real dataset.
The IRS dataset will walk you through simple Python code and demonstrate how to find the best key value to maximize your model's accuracy. So stay tuned to see KNN in action.
So welcome to the demo part. So I am here using Google Colab. So you can use any of your favorite ID like Jupyter Notebook, IntelliJ, Visual Code Studio, anything.
Okay, so let me rename this file as KNN classification.
Okay, cool. So let me tell you that KNN can be used for the classification regression predictive problems. So Knn falls in the supervised learning family of algorithms.
Okay, so we will measure the distance, uh, between the k neighbors, and the first step will be we'll choose the number of k of neighbors.
Then, uh, we'll take the k nearest neighbors of the new data point according to your distance metric, and the step three will be:
our among these k neighbors count the number of data points of each category, okay. Step four, we will assign the new data points to the category where you counted the most neighbors.
Okay, so let's start first.
Let's import some library. Import
numpy
as
np, and let's import
pandas as pd. So everyone knows what is numpy and the pandas.
Okay, so numpy is the library for the python programming language adding support for, uh, you know, large multi-dimensional arrays, okay, along with the large collection of, uh,
what to say, uh, high-level mathematical functions.
And whereas pandas is a software library written for the Python programming language for the data manipulation and analysis, uh, all the data frames
and, uh, data structures it offers for the manipulating numerical tables, okay, and the time series you can see.
So, moving forward, uh we'll import uh our data set. So you can download the dataset from the description box below.
Okay, data set
equals to pd.read underscore csv.
The data name is iris.csv.
Okay, this is how you read uh your data in Python.
Okay, yeah, data set is loaded, so dataset dot shape
shape okay, yeah. So data set dot shape is used for how many numbers of uh rows and columns present in your dataset, okay. 150 rows and six columns.
So let me tell you brief about data set this IDS data set. So iris data set includes three iris species with uh 50 samples each, as well as uh some properties about each flower.
So one flower species is uh linearly separable from the other two, you can say, but the other two are not linearly separable from each other,
okay. And this shape I told you, we can get a quick idea of how many instances of rows and columns are present in our dataset.
So let's see our dataset dataset dot
head.
So head is used for uh you know by you can see top five rows of your dataset using head,
and if you will use tail you uh instead of head, you can see the last five rows of your dataset.
Cool, okay. So columns are ID, sepal length, sepal width, petal length, petal width, and the species.
Cool. Then moving forward, let's describe our data sets. So these are the basic uh basic functions, okay.
Of Python, you can say
so. Data set dot described. What describes do is it will give you count of all the rows, mean value, standard deviation value, minimum value.
What is the 25% okay of all the uh values in the particular row?
What is the 50%?
What is the 75%? What is the maximum? Maximum is 150. You can say okay, and 25% of 150 is 38.25.
This okay, of all the columns.
If it is normal, uh you know corrector, so it won't give you any data.
Okay, cool. Yeah, so moving forward, uh, let's now take a look at the number of instances row belong to each classes.
Okay, so we will write data set dot
group by
species dot
size, okay.
Uh species S is capital, that's why it's showing the error.
Yeah, so you can see iris satosa are 50, iris versical are 50, and virginica is 50.
Okay, and the data type is integer.
Cool. So, as we can see, data set contains six columns like ID, sepal length, sepal width, and petal length, petal width, and species.
The actual features are described by columns one to four, the last columns labels or samples.
Okay, so firstly we need to split data into two arrays like x features and y labels.
So, how we will do this by writing code like feature underscore columns equals to
sample length, sample width, petal length, petal width.
Just remember you are writing correct name, okay. Then x equals to dataset
feature underscore
columns,
okay.
Dot
values,
then
y equals to
dataset
species.
Dot values.
Cool, then let me run it.
So, this is uh how we can split the data set okay into two areas x and the y.
Okay, in X there are feature columns, these four columns are there, and in y species column is there, okay. And what is the species column? This Satosha, Volgenica, and all this.
Cool.
Then now we will do label encoding.
So, as you can see, labels are categorical, uh, knamers classifier does not accept the string labels, so we need to use label encoder to transform them into numbers,
okay. Then iris satosa correspond to zero, iris voci color uh correspond to one, and iris virginica correspond to two.
Okay, zero, one, two.
Cool. So, how can I from
sklearn dot preprocessing
import
label
encoder?
Okay, so what we'll do label encoder transform them into numbers. Okay, so I will write Ali equals to
label encoder.
Okay, my bad.
Label encoder okay, then y equals to ally fit dot transform y.
Okay, so now I will run it, yeah, correct. So splitting data set into training set and the test set now.
Okay, so now we'll split data set into training set and test set to check later on whether or not a classifier works correctly or not.
Okay, so here I will write from sklearn dot
not cross.
I will write here sklearn dot model selection.
Import
import train trust split.
So, what is train trust split?
Train test split is a model validation procedure that reveals how your model performs on your new data.
Okay, and what is X train, XS, Y train, Y test in Python? Okay, let me first write it and then I will let you know. Okay, then I will write here
X train, comma, X test,
comma, Y train, comma, Y test.
Okay, question
train
test
split then X, comma Y,
comma test size 0.2 and the random system.
Okay, okay, some error came.
Okay, underscore model section.
Yeah, cool.
So what is X train, X test, Y train, Y test? Okay, so X train and Y train sets are used for training and fitting the model.
Okay, so the X test and the Y test are the set used for testing the model and it's predicting the right outputs
label.
Okay, so here you can see test size is 0.2 means 80% is for testing.
Oh sorry, 80% is for training and 20% is for testing for the new data.
Cool, yeah.
So now we will see some let's do some data visualization.
Okay, so here I will write import
matplotlib
dot pyplot
as plt,
then import
c bond as sns.
Then here I will write person matplotlib
inline. So what is matplotlib?
Matplotlib is a plotting library for the python programming language and its numerical mathematic extension.
Okay, so numpy, it provides an object API for embedding plots into application using generating purpose GUI toolkits like Kinter
and uh Python Qt or GTK.
Okay, whereas Cbon, Cbon is a library for making statical graph in Python;
it builds on the top of Matplotlib and integrates closely with Pandas data structure.
Okay, Cbon helps us to explore and understand the data.
Okay, so I will run it here. I will write from
pandas.plotting,
import
parallel
coordinates,
then PLT dot
figure.
figure size should be
fifteen, comma ten,
okay.
Then parallel coordinates,
okay, then dataset dot drop.
I don't need ID,
comma, X's is one
okay, then comma species.
Then plt dot
title and let Lords plot, okay?
And
you can give some font size equals to twenty,
then font
width
equals to
... okay, let's say bold, only bold.
Then plt dot x level,
then
features,
comma
font size plus to fifteen.
Then plt
dot y level, then I'll write here features
values,
comma font size
to fifteen.
Okay, then plt dot legend,
then l octo.
one
comma
I will already have frame on
equals to true comma. shadow equals to true comma. face color
equals to white
(T should be capital
), and comma edge color
equals to
okay. plt dot, show.
Okay. some error is there: plt, dot figure size.
Okay, spelling mistake.
Okay, one more error: plt dot legend Okay, face color.
Okay, some spelling mistake. So yeah, let me make it pre-out put in full screen. Yeah, so parallel coordinates is a plotting technique for plotting, you know, uh, multivariate data.
So it allows one to see clusters in the data and to estimate other stat visually.
So using parallel coordinate points, uh, you know, are represented as the connected line segments, as you can see.
Okay. And each vertical line represents one attribute, and one set of connected line segments represent one data point.
Okay.
And points that, uh, tend to cluster will appear closer together.
Okay. So this, uh, this color is iris satusa, and this is iris versicolar, and this one is iris
vaginica, as you can see in the legend.
Okay, cool.
So moving forward, let's create another graph.
Andrew curves. Okay. So here I will write: from
pandas dot plotting import scatter.
No, it's, uh, plotting import.
Andrew curves,
okay. Then plt
dot figure it's AI based so it's giving me suggestions, suggestions, suggestions. Okay, some sometimes suggestions are good but not always.
Yeah, let's carry on. Figure size is 15, comma 10,
then entry
Curves,
then I will add dataset dot drop id access species and plt and recurves plot. Okay, fine.
Okay,
let me add:
we don't need x label and all. Let me add legend, plt .dot (legend
), then same l _oc equals to one,
then
proposition size.
Then I will write here: size
is 15
of frame on equals to two,
comma shadow equals to true.
So this is, uh, truly based upon you if you want to add legend or not, or you can skip.
If you want to skip, you can skip.
Okay, face color equals to white then.
H
color equals to black.
Okay, then plt dot show
Yeah, so no error is there. So let me first view output in full screen.
Okay, so Andrew curves, these are the Android curves. Okay, the ... you can see the graph in the curve.
So Andrew curve allow one to plot the multivariate data as a large number of curves, so that are created using the attributes of samples, okay,
as coefficient for Fourier series. Okay, so by coloring these curves differently for each class, it is possible to visualize data clustering.
So curves. Belongs, belonging to samples of the same class will usually be closer together and they form large structure.
Okay, as you can see here, and this is the legend why we are setting the four colors should be white and yeah, and the edge
color should be black.
Okay, and frame on shadow should be there. You can see the shadow, okay, like this. If you want to skip, you can skip this part, legend part, part legend part, okay.
But uh, like it's good to have, it's good practice to have this cool.
So let's create one small pair plot. Okay, so I will write here: plt, dot
figure.
Then I will write sns, dot pairplot.
then I will write dataset,
dot drop,
We'll drop again. id, we don't need.
x is is one.
Then I will write u equals to
species
size equals to three,
then markers equals to
oh sd.
Yeah, cool. Then plt dot shoe It's running.
Yeah, so first let me make it to full screen.
Yeah, so here pairwise is useful uh when you want to visualize the distribution of the variable or the relationship between the multiple variables
separately within subsets of your data set, okay?
So here, uh, this blue one is uh satosa versicolor and the virginica.
Okay, so these are some uh graphs you can say, or here you can see sepal length.
Okay, so green one is virginica and versicolor are almost having the same sepal length.
Okay, and here are the different types of graphs.
Okay, if you don't want to uh let's say, if you don't know how to read this graph, you can use this graph or you can use
this graph;
either you can use this graph.
Okay, that's the power pair pairwise plots you can say. And the sepal uh width centimeter. Okay, satusa no, okay, virginic and vertical.
Again, having almost same sample width, okay? And here as well, okay. This satusa is in different form, okay?
Yeah, so we'll uh create one small uh pair of uh one small graph, then we'll move forward, okay? Uh, I will write here plt dot so now we are creating box plot figure.
Okay, then dataset dot drop,
then again id, comma, access should be one
dot box plot.
Okay, then figure size. I chose this. Yeah, let's run it.
Yeah, again, see this is the box plot petal and same petal width, sepal and sepal width.
Okay, according to width, it is showing like from this to this width, we have the verci color, and from this to this width,
this length. Sorry, sepal length. We have uh uh that virginica lies here, iris virginica, and from here to here, iris setosa lies okay.
The sepal length cool, and like you can use 3D models, you can use different types of charts. Okay, I did four and four are enough to uh read the data set, okay.
So now we will do uh some KN classification. Okay, we will make prediction and we will see the accuracy of our dataset.
Okay, so now what I will do, I will write here from
sklearn
dot
neighbors
import
k neighbors, okay.
Write from
sklearn dot
neighbors
import
k neighbor
classifier.
Okay,
then I will write here: from
sklearn dot
matrix
import,
confusion,
matrix, comma, accuracy, accuracy, score.
Okay, then I will write from
sklearn.
Score okay.
So here what we I did uh we are fitting the classifier to the training set and the loading the libraries basically, okay. Then we'll initiate a learning model k equals to through three.
Okay, so here I will write classifier.
Let me give one space classifier equals to
neighbors classifier
and
neighbors equals to three.
Okay, then fitting the model I will write here classifier dot
fit
x train,
comma, y train
okay. Then uh now we will predicting the test uh test set results. Okay, so y prediction equals to
classifier dot
predict
x test cool okay. From okay, spelling mistake.
Okay,
okay.
Yeah, I guess fine now.
So now let's evaluate the prediction. So here I will uh build the confusion matrix.
Okay, so here I will add CM confusion matrix equals to confusion underscore matrix uh
Y test, comma, Y prediction.
Okay, then here I will add CM. Okay, so what is confusion matrix basically?
So I confusion matrix uh you know is a table that shows how well a model performs by comparing its prediction to the actual values,
okay. So what it shows a confusion uh dismatrice displays the number of correct and incorrect prediction of each class in models,
which either it can give you true positive, true negative, false positive, false negative, either it can give you zero or one.
Okay, so yeah, moving forward, let's calculate the model accuracy. This is the main part. If the model accuracy is low, it means uh your analysis of you know classification is not good.
Okay, so accuracy it should be more than 80 at least.
Accuracy.
Equals to
accuracy underscore score
white test,
comma y prediction into hundred, otherwise it will give me in points. So I will write print
canon model accuracy
is
oh I will write plus str
I will round it okay accuracy.
I will add the percent. So why I wrote this accuracy to round so I don't want after points, I need only two numbers. Okay, I don't want like 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 10 like this.
Okay, I need only like 80.20, like this.
Cool.
Let's run it.
See uh KN model accuracy is 96.67, that's why I wrote two here, and the percent should be
so 96, which is very, very, very good.
Okay, so this is how you can find uh the accuracy. So now let's find the optimal number of neighbors in k.
Okay, basically finding the best k.
So we will uh use uh using cross-validation parameter okay. Tuning so first I will create the list of k for kn okay. So here I will write k underscore list
equals to list
range
one, comma fifty, comma two.
Here I am I will create the list of C V score.
Okay, so here I will write C V
scores
okay, okay. I have to give the brackets, yeah.
So we'll here perform the tenfold uh cross validation.
Okay, I will explain you what is cross-validation, don't worry. So first, let me write 4k
n k list.
kn equals to
k neighbor classifier.
and here I will add n neighbor
neighbors equals to k.
then scores
equals to cross
value, score
kn, then x train,
comma, y train.
okay, comma. I will write here clause validation equals to 10
comma scoring equals to I will write here accuracy.
Okay,
and then here cv underscores course dot append
to scores dot me.
Okay, so now yeah, let me run it okay.
Some error came okay. The error is the scoring parameter,
yeah.
Why because here accuracy you can see, and I did the spelling mistake.
Okay, so now what is cross-validation? Of course, cross-validation uh you know determine the accuracy of your machine learning model by partioning the data into two different groups,
okay. Called training set and testing set. You can see trains test and the testing set, okay. Excel y so they the data is randomly separated into a certain number of groups or subsets called folds.
Okay, you can see the 10 folds we have wrote. Each fold contains about the same amount of okay, and there is one more thing validation.
So, validation is a technique for assessing the accuracy of the model on data set.
Okay, and this cross-validation we did on new dataset.
Cool.
So now let's find the best K.
Okay.
So here I will write best
K equals to K
list.
Okay. Before that, I will write one thing.
I will write here.
MSE was changing to misclassification error. Okay. So equals to one's X
for X in for X in
C V scores.
Okay. At least I will write MSE dot
index
minimum
MSE.
I will use this bracket, square bracket.
Okay. So then, I will write: "print.
the best
optimal
number of
neighbors is person T
person
best underscore K.
Okay, let's run it.
See the best optimal number of neighbors. Okay, and
neighbors is nine. Okay. So in the K nearest neighbor Kn algorithms, okay. So K represent the number of neighbors that are considered when classifying a query point.
Okay.
See the if we'll classify this particular point, you will get the six.
Okay, one, two, three, four, five, six.
Okay.
And uh let me show you if you will classify this portion only, so you will get one, two, three, four, five, six points, like this.
So the best optimal number of neighbor is nine.
What is Python?
Python is a high-level object-oriented programming language developed by Guido Van Rosum in 1989 and was first released in 1991.
Python is often called a batteries included language due to its comprehensive standard library.
A fun fact about Python is that the name Python was actually taken from the popular BBC comedy show of that time, Monty Python's Flying Circus.
Now, let's look at the top features of Python.
First, so Python has a simple structure and a clearly defined syntax.
This allows the learners to pick up the language quickly so it is easy to learn and use.
Python can run on different operating systems such as Windows, Linux, and Mac, making it a portable language.
It enables programmers to develop the software for several competing platforms by writing a program only once.
Third, Python is freely available at the official website.
Since it is open source, this means that source code is also available to the public.
Now Python uses an object-oriented approach that encapsulates code within objects.
Python provides a collection of libraries for various tasks such as machine learning, web development and data analysis.
And finally, in Python, you don't need to assign the data type of the variable.
When you assign some value to the variable, it automatically allocates the memory to the variable at runtime.
So,
Python programming language is used to develop desktop applications and build web applications too.
It is popularly used in the field of data science, machine learning, and artificial intelligence to analyze data, build predictive models, and make business decisions.
Python is also widely used in game development.
Now, let's see some of the popular Python frameworks and libraries.
Python can be used for web development using frameworks like Zango, Flask, Pyramid, and CherryPy.
You can build graphical user interfaces using libraries and frameworks such as tkinter or justkinter.
You can also use PygtK, PyQt or PYJS or Python JavaScript.
Python is also used to perform machine learning tasks using libraries such as TensorFlow, PyTorch, ScikitLearn, Macplotlib, and SciPy.
You can also perform mathematical computations using NumPy and Pandas.
Now let's look at the best IDEs that you can use to write programs in Python and perform specific tasks.
So we have Jupyter Notebook, which is part of the Anaconda distribution that is widely used these days.
Even for our demo in this video, we'll be using Jupyter Notebook. I'll show you in a while.
Then we have the visual code editor from Microsoft.
This is also one of the preferred
IDEs by learners and companies.
Then we also have the popular text editor called Sublime Text Editor.
Then we also have PyCharm followed by Python IDLE and Spider as our top IDEs.
Now let's look at the top companies that are using Python in our day-to-day work.
So we have Google, Quora, Facebook, even Netflix, Spotify, and Instagram.
Now there are other top product-based, service-based and startups that also use Python programming.
So what really is Python programming language?
Python is an object-oriented, high-level programming language that supports built-in data structures and dynamic semantics.
It supports multiple programming paradigms such as structured, object-oriented, and functional programming.
Python is often described as batteries-included language because it has a comprehensive collection of standard libraries.
Python supports different modules and packages which allows program modularity and code reuse.
Python was developed by Guido Van Rosum and its implementation started in December 1989.
Python 1.0 version was released in the year 1994.
Python 2.0 came out in October 2000, while Python 3.0 was released in December 2008.
Now that you have got an understanding of the Python programming language, let's now look at the top 10 reasons why you should learn Python.
So at number 10, we have ease of use.
One of the most common reasons to like Python is that it is quite easy to learn and code.
It provides a simple syntax that improves readability and makes it easier to understand.
So developers can create any desktop or machine-based application using this language.
Python is very versatile and is instrumental in artificial intelligence and machine learning.
We will talk about this later in the session.
Compared to Java or C C, it has fewer lines of codes.
In the example here, we are printing a hello world program in Java.
As you can see,
if you have to write a program in Java, you first have to declare the class name along with its scope.
Next, using curly braces, you need to pass the main method along with its arguments.
And then using system.out.println method, you can print hello world.
That's quite a tedious task, isn't it?
The same task of printing hello world can be done using just one line of code in Python as shown here.
You can write the print function and pass whatever you want to display inside the brackets, and that will print the output.
It is so simple.
That is why Python is considered as a high-level language and it's open source.
You can just download it from the website and start using it.
At 9, we have Active Community.
You need a community to learn new technology, and friends are your best asset when it comes to learning a programming language.
Python has large community support.
It has an extensive and active community to assist engineers, developers, analysts, and data scientists with expert support in case of programming errors or issues with the software.
You can just go ahead and put your queries in the community forum.
The community members will address your queries in real quick time.
Communities like Stack Overflow also bring many Python experts together to help learners.
Python Enhancement Proposals or PEP is where the proposals and the improvements are announced.
Also, there are a set of recommendations or core values called the Zen of Python written by Tim Peters that represents the guiding principles for Python development.
Up next at 8, we have portable and extensible.
Multiple cross-language operations can be performed effectively because Python is portable and extensible in nature.
For example, if the users have a Python code written on Windows and they want to execute on a Mac operating system or Linux operating system or Solaris,
they can easily do it without any amendment.
They can also run this code on any platform flawlessly and without any interrupt.
Due to its extensibility feature, you can integrate other programming languages such as Java, .NET, C and C codes with Python.
The components of other programming languages can be used with Python and thus it can be used to make a cross-platform suitable application too.
So it is a really good feature that Python provides.
The next reason to learn Python is testing frameworks.
Python supports several built-in flawless testing tools and frameworks that help in debugging and speeding of workflows.
Some of the tools and frameworks supported by Python are PyTest, Selenium, and Splinter.
This is the reason for which every tester tries to use Python-based tools and frameworks to test any application or code or to validate it in an easier manner.
PyTest is the most recommended testing framework for functional, integrational, and unit testing.
You can run Selenium test scripts using Python programming language to automate various tasks, and Splinter is an open source tool for testing web applications using Python.
It lets you automate browser actions such as visiting URLs and interacting with their items.
At number six, we have libraries and packages.
Another reason why Python has become so popular in the industry these days is that it has a massive collection of libraries and packages that make your task simple and easy.
It has a range of libraries, packages, frameworks, and modules for data manipulation, statistical calculation, web development, machine learning, and data science.
Python programmers have developed tons of free and open source libraries that you can use.
You can find many of them via Python package index, the repository of Python software.
Python provides the default package called PIP.
Anaconda is a third party Python ecosystem.
Other examples include NumPy, SciPy, and Django.
Then we have scripting and automation.
Python is not just a programming language.
It can also be used for writing scripts for automating tasks and workflows without human intervention.
The code can be written in the form of scripts and executed later.
Further, it is interpreted by the machine and checked for errors at runtime.
The machine is used to read and interpret the code.
Once the developer checks the code, it can further run or be used several times without any interruption.
This allows you to automate a set of certain tasks within a program or the same code can be used with other applications as well.
At number 4, we have web development.
Another reason to learn Python is that it makes the web development process so much easier.
It provides a wide collection of frameworks that make it easier for developers to develop web applications.
Some of the examples are Django, Flask, Pyramid, TurboGears, CherryPy, etc.
These frameworks are written in Python, which makes the code a lot faster and stable.
The task which used to take hours in PHP can be finished in minutes using Python.
Python is also used for web scraping.
Django offers many elements of intricate programs such as template design, management panel, signing in, signing up,
signing out, URL routing, etc.
Once the user establishes the framework, all these features become ready to use.
Flask is a microwave framework written in Python.
Of all the components that are part of this module, they are all ready to execute in the server context.
Pinterest and LinkedIn use Flask.
Pyramid offers more attributes than Flask.
It will assist users with URL routing and authentication support.
Turbo Gears is a highly recommended and scalable framework that supports features such as authentication, caching, identification,
management of sessions, and pluggable applications.
Up next at number three,
we have machine learning.
The growth of machine learning has been phenomenal in the last five years and it's rapidly changing the world around us.
Python is one of the most preferred programming languages for machine learning because of its simple syntax and support for several machine learning libraries.
Using different libraries and functions in Python, the system can learn and train itself from past data.
Once the system is trained, it can then learn to adjust itself to new inputs.
Finally, it can make predictions and perform human-like tasks automatically.
At number two, we have data science.
Machine learning and data science go hand in hand.
Python is robust, scalable, and provides extensible visualization and graphics options.
Hence, it is widely used in data science.
Python has libraries such as NumPy for numerical computation of data, pandas for operations to manipulate data on numerical tables and time series.
It also provides SymPy for symbolic computation and SciPy for technical and scientific computations.
It has another library called PyBrain, which is sought for Python-based reinforcement learning, artificial intelligence, and neural network library.
And finally, it provides PyTorch and TensorFlow for deep learning.
Finally, coming to the most important and the top reason to learn Python, which is career opportunities and salary.
Python language provides a variety of job opportunities and promises a high growth graph with huge salary prospects.
It is being used by most of the tech giants.
Industry leaders using Python are Amazon, Google, Facebook, IBM, NASA, Netflix, and YouTube.
Next, you can see the Google Trends.
But I have considered three programming languages Python, Java, and C.
I have compared them for the past 12 months.
You can see it clearly on your screens that Python has become a frontrunner in terms of popularity and web search volume.
It means people are interested in Python, they want to learn it and use it in their work.
You can also check for the YouTube search.
There also you will find that Python Programming Language is the most searched language on YouTube.
Now on your screens, you can see the report of PYPL, which is popularity of programming language index.
It is created by analyzing how often language tutorials are searched on Google.
It is a leading indicator.
The raw data comes from Google Trends.
The bar graph depicts that Python is the most popular and widely used programming language across the globe, followed by Java, then JavaScript and C.
The popularity of programming language index can help you decide which language to study or which one to use in a new software project.
The next graph shows the popularity of Python and Java over the years, starting from 2004 till the current period, which is 2020.
Worldwide, Python is the most popular language.
Python grew the most in the last 5 years by 19.4%, and Java lost the most by minus 7.2%.
Now let's talk about the different career opportunities and the job roles that you can get into if you learn Python language.
First, you can become a Python developer
where you will be asked to write and test codes, debug programs, and integrate applications with third-party web services.
Second, you can become a web developer.
Here, you will be responsible for writing server-side web application logic.
Python web developers usually develop back-end components, connect the application with third-party services,
and support the front-end developers by integrating their work with the Python application.
You can also become a data analyst if you know Python.
As a data analyst, you have to gather data from multiple sources using scripts, analyze that data, develop and implement databases
and data collection systems.
You can become a data scientist.
As a data scientist, you need to understand the challenges in business and come up with the best solutions using modern tools and techniques to analyze,
visualize, and build prediction models to make business decisions.
Lastly, you can be a machine learning engineer where you can develop intelligent machines that can learn from vast volumes of data and apply knowledge without human intervention.
So there's a lot of scopes if you learn Python.
But before we move on, let's understand first what is Jupyter Notebook.
So, guys, as you can see all over here, that Jupyter Notebook is a popular open source tool that basically allows you to create and share documents
which contains codes, equations, you can have visualizations also.
Basically, it is used for data analysis, machine learning, and scientific research, which makes it a very essential tool for developers like data scientists and researchers alike.
Now, before installing Jupyter Notebook, I request you that you have Python installed in your system.
So the requirement should be Python 3.6 or greater.
So now let us officially navigate to the Python's website.
So guys, as you can see all over here, so on python.org, if I click on download Python, so we're gonna see that all over here,
download Python 3.1 to 5.
So as I already told you that the requirement of Python should be greater than 3.6.
So just you can click all over here and you can see the download had started.
So, guys, as you can see all over here that we have installed the Python.
Now let us open the file.
So you can see the given software is going to install on this directory.
Okay, so just click all over here.
So guys, as you can see all over here, the Python installation of 3.125 is in progress.
Let's wait for some time till it gets installed.
So as you can see, guys, all over here that we have successfully installed our Python.
Now let us open our terminal and let us check whether Python is correctly installed.
So we are going to type
Python
slash version.
So as you can see all over here, we have successfully installed our Python.
So guys, that was our prerequisite.
Now there are two ways to install Jupyter Notebook.
The first one can be pip.
Okay, pip is a package manager or using Anucandor distribution.
So let us see with PIP first.
So guys, pip is a package manager which is used to install and manage software packages, libraries written in Python.
So you can see all over here that the Python with version greater than 3.6 have default pip installed in them.
Okay, so we can use pip command to install our Jupyter notebook.
So guys, as you can see all over here, we have come to the official documentation of jupyter.org and it is saying that installing JupyterLab with pip command.
So what you can do, guys, you can just copy all over here, you can go right all over here and click on this.
Now as you can see all over here, it has started downloading the Jupyter Lab.
So guys, we are going to install our Jupyter lab with the pip command.
So this is the official documentation of Jupyter Notebook.
Okay, and just all you have to do is copy this and type on your terminal.
So as you can see all over here, it has started downloading the packages which is required to download the Jupyter Notebook.
Let us wait for some time.
Okay, guys, so we have successfully completed this step.
Now let us move on to our next step.
So as you can see all over here,
so we have installed, okay.
Then what we have to do, then you can type this, you can launch the Jupyter lab with this command on the terminal.
Now let us wait.
So as you can see all over here, guys, we have successfully installed our Jupyter notebook.
So you can go all over here and just create a new notebook, and you can also choose your kernel and you can start working on your Jupyter notebook.
Suppose I'll show you one snippet.
So 3 plus 5, let us try to run this notebook.
So as you can see, it is giving us the 8 as answer.
So it is following the Python syntax, and in this way, we have successfully installed our Jupyter notebook using the pip command.
So now, as you can also see all over here, you can also install Jupyter Notebook with this command, pip install notebook, and then you can just open it.
This is also another alternative.
Similarly, you can install with Viala also.
Same command and just open the Viala.
Now, if you are using any other operating system like Mac OS or Linux, then you can install by Brew install JupyterLab.
So home brew will be the package manager for Mac OS and Linux.
So I hope so you are pretty clear with how to install Jupyter Notebook with the PEP command.
Now I have downloaded Anacondas from this official website.
So as you can see all over here, this is the official website of Anaconda.
Okay.
Now just type your email and you can just download it.
So similarly, as you can see, after installing, I'm going to launch my installer and let us click next.
Okay.
Let us click agree.
And let us install this on the given directory.
Let us wait for some time till the installation gets complete.
So guys, as you can see all over here, we have completed our installation of AnoConna.
You can say we have successfully installed our enough.
Now it has opened our Anaconda navigator.
So it does open.
So as you can see all over here, just right-click on this and our Anucanda navigator will be opened.
So as you can see all over here, this is our Anucanda navigator and it is loading the packages.
And for us to install the Jupyter notebook, so as you can see all over here, just click on launch.
So guys, if you click on launch, it is going to open our Jupyter notebook.
So as you can see all over here, it is saying launching the Jupyter Notebook.
And it is hosted on localhost 8889.
So this is our hosted Jupyter Notebook.
And similarly, you can create a new notebook all over here.
And in this way, you can start working.
LLMs.
If you ever wondered how machine learning can now understand and generate human-like text, you are in the right place.
From chat boards like ChatGPT to AI assistant that power search engines.
LLMs are transforming how we interact with technology.
One of the most exciting advancements in this space is Google Gemini or OpenAI ChatGPT.
A cutting-edge large language model designed to push the boundaries of what AI can achieve.
In this video, we will explore what LLMs are, how they work, and why models like Gemini are critical for the future of AI.
Google Gemini is part of a new wave of AI models that are smarter, faster, and more efficient.
It is designed to understand context better, offer more accurate responses, and integrate deeply into service like Google Search and Google Assistant,
providing more human-like interactions.
So we will break down the science behind LLMs, including their massive training data set, transformer architecture, and how models like Gemini use deep learning innovation to change industries.
Plus, we will compare Google Gemini to other popular LLMs such as OpenAI Chat GPT models, showing how each of these technologies is used to power chatbots,
virtual assistants, and other AI-driven applications.
By the end of this video, you will have a clear understanding of how large language models like Gemini work, their key features, and what they mean for their future AI.
Don't forget to like, subscribe, and hit the bell icon to never miss any update from Simply Learn. So, what are the large language models?
Large language models like ChatGPT 4, Generative Pre-Trained, Transformer 4, O, and Google Gemini are sophisticated AI systems designed to comprehend and generate human-like text.
These models are built using deep learning techniques and are trained on vast datasets collected from the internet.
They leverage self-attention mechanisms to analyze the relationship between words or tokens allowing them to capture context and produce coherent relevant responses.
LLMs have significant applications, including powering virtual assistants, chat boards, content creation, language translation, and supporting research and decision making.
Their ability to generate fluent and contextually appropriate text has advanced natural language processing and improved human-computer interaction.
So now let's see what are large language models used for.
Large language models are utilized in scenarios with limited or no domain specific data available for training.
These scenarios include both few short and zero short training approaches, which rely on the model's strong inductive bias and its capability to derive meaningful
representation from a small amount of data.
Or even no data at all. So now let's see how our large language models are trained.
Large language models typically undergo pre-training on a board, all encompassing data set that shares statical similarities with the dataset
specific to the target task.
The objective of pre-training is to enable the model to require high level features that can later be applied during the fine-tuning phase for specific tasks.
So there are some training processes of LLM which involves several steps. The first one is text pre-processing.
The textual data is transformed into a numerical representation that the LLM model can effectively process.
This conversion may be involved techniques like tokenization and coding and creating input sequences. The second one is random parameter initialization.
The model's parameters are initialized randomly before the training process begins. The third one is input numerical data.
The numerical representation of the text data is fed into the model of processing.
The model's architecture, typically based on transformers, allows it to capture the conceptual relationship between the words or tokens in the next.
The fourth one is loss function calculation. A loss function calculation measures the discrepancy between the model's prediction and the actual next word or token in a syntax.
The LLM model aims to minimize this loss during training.
The fifth one is parameter optimization. The model's parameters are adjusted through optimization technique.
This involves calculating gradient and updating the parameters accordingly, gradually improving the model's performance. The last one is iterative training.
The training process is repeated over multiple alterations or epochs until the model's output achieves a satisfactory level of accuracy on that given task or dataset.
By following this training process, large language models learn to capture linguistic patterns, understand context, and generate coherent responses,
enabling them to excel at various language-related tasks.
The next topic is how do large language models work?
So, large language models leverage deep neural networks to generate output based on patterns learned from the training data.
Typically, a large language model adopts a transformer architecture which enables the model to identify relationship between words in a sentence irrespective of their position in the sequence.
In contrast to RNNs that rely on recurrence to capture token relationship, transform a neural network, employ self-attention as their primary mechanism.
Self-attention calculates attention scores that determine the importance of each token with respect to the other token in the text sequence,
facilitating the modeling of intricate relationships within the data.
Next, let's see application of large language models. Large language models have a wide range of applications across various domains.
So here are some notable applications. The first one is natural language processing NLP.
Large language models are used to improve natural language understanding tasks such as sentiment analysis, named entity recognition, text classification,
and language modeling.
The second one is chatbot and virtual assistant.
Large language models power conversational agents, chatbots, and virtual assistant, providing more interactive and human-like user interaction.
The third one is machine translation.
Large language models have been used for automatic language translation, enabling text translation between different languages with improved accuracy.
The fourth one is sentiment analysis.
LLMs can analyze and classify the sentiment or emotion expressed in a piece of text, which is valuable for market research, brand monitoring, and social media analysis.
The fifth one is content recommendation.
These models can be employed to provide personalized content recommendations, enhancing user experience and engagement on platforms such as news websites or streaming services.
So these applications highlight the potential impact of large language models in various domains for improving language understanding automation.
So hello guys, welcome to this demo part of this video.
So here what I will do, I will go to new Python Python 3 file.
Data
analysis.
Basically, we will so we have one
dataset file of
roller coaster basically.
So we will be using then, and you can download that file from the description box below from the below link drive link.
Okay, so we will be doing some small basic functions
using Python and later on we will uh make some good charts.
Okay, we will remove duplicates and all, we will do all that
thing.
We'll do data preparation, we'll do feature engineering, okay.
And uh we'll remove the duplicates, we'll check for the duplicates, we'll make charts like histogram,
kd plots, box plot, and like many more similar to that, like heat map. We'll make scatter plot group by comparison. Okay, we all do that, right?
So just stick with me and you can
write side along with me your discourse, okay.
Okay, so let's start with importing
pandas first.
I guess everyone knows what is pandas and numpy.
Fine
as np, then I will import
numpy
as np.
Why this is np and pd?
Sorry, my bad pd is here because I don't want to write again and again this pandas, this numpy. So basically, I can write this a small version, okay.
Yeah, so if you guys don't know what is panda, so panda is a very popular library for working with data.
Okay, it's
goal is to be the most powerful and flexible open source tool. Okay, so it has these that code.
So data frames are the center of pandas,
and what is data frame? A data frame is structured like a table or a spreadsheet, okay. The rows and the columns, okay. Whereas numpy numpy is an open source Python library again
that facilitates uh you know efficient numerical operation on large quantities of data.
Okay, so there are many functions in numpy as well.
Those we can use in the pond as data frame.
Got it?
So we'll import one more
dot pyplot
dot file lab okay, as
PLT.
Okay, there is one more library matplotlib for plotting the graph, and
and there is one more import
c1
as SNS.
So, what is C1? C1 is again the Python data visualization library based on matplotlib.
Okay, it provides a high level interface for drawing attractive and informative statical unographs.
Okay, then I will write here plt.style
dot use
will write ggplot.
Got it ggplot.
Fine.
So yeah,
let me run it.
So, what is ggplot? So, ggplot is an again this is an open source data visualization package for historical programming.
Okay, so yeah,
uh, you can say or a journal scheme for data visualization which breaks up graph into you know semantic components such as scales and layers.
Okay, mapload leap dot py.
Okay, it's pylab.
P okay, yeah.
So now
we will import our data set.
Df df means data frame. You can write any word of your choice, then pd again pandas.read underscore csv
use for readings CSV file.
Okay, Excel files.
Got it.
Then here I will write my
this
coaster.csv.
Okay, I'm not writing any path because my this uh
dataset is here itself.
Coaster coaster C coast.
This is coaster.csv okay.
If you have your data set in another location as in like in C drive, D drive or whatever, okay. You can give that path.
Okay, let me run it.
Yeah,
so now we will do some data understanding.
Okay, we'll see uh data frame shape, head and tail, data types, and describe like small small function we will use
df.shape
so we have 1087 rows and 56 columns in our dataset,
okay.
Then we will see df.hat
five.
So df.head means it will give me top five rows of my data set.
Okay, you can see one, two, three, four, five.
Okay, five rows and fifty-six columns here 56 columns, but we have one zero eight seven
rows. Okay, so we have cluster name, length, speed, location, status, opening, date, type, this, this, this, this.
Okay,
we will do
uh you know, we'll make some graphs using this these columns, okay.
And there is one more df.tail
again, last five rows. So df.tale gives you the lice last five rows.
See one zero eight six one zero eight five. Okay,
and if you want to see
full data, it is here,
okay. 021086, fine.
Yeah, so we have one more df.columns to check
all the columns.
See cluster name, land, speed, location, status, opening date, type, and these are all my columns names. Fine.
So we have one more data types.
Actually, we have like many data types, but let me show you some important ones, or you can say some of the basics ones, okay.
So df dot d types, d types means data types, cluster name is object type, length object, and inversion is float.
Okay,
we'll check inversion.
Where is the inversion?
Yeah, float type.
Okay,
then everything is object, and year introduces int numeric one and let it float.
so basically we have three types float, int, and object.
Okay,
then what do we do?
Let's just quickly check this.
Describe.
Okay,
so what is the count of this inversion 932?
Okay, it won't include any, you know, what is it?
Empty cells.
Okay, it won't count empty cells, right?
Mean of this particular table, then standard deviation, then mean, minimum value 25 percent, 70 percent, 75 percent, and max.
It will describe you all this,
okay.
And there is one more df.info to get the info.
See
question name 1087 value non-null object, then length 953 non null.
Okay, like this.
Yeah, so now moving forward, what we will do? We will do data preparation, okay.
What comes in data preparation, like dropping irrelevant columns and rows which we don't want, okay.
Then second thing is identifying duplicates, columns, then third is renaming columns.
Then we'll do some feature creations,
right?
So if you want to drop a column,
okay, how you can drop?
So you have to write just df.drop.
First, I will give here has tag data
reparation.
Okay, yeah.
So how you can drop a column?
Okay, df.drop,
then here I will write
opening
date
comma access equals to one.
Okay.
Opening okay, access parties wrong.
Instead of this,
maybe what is the opening date?
Okay, always capital here.
Instead of this, you can use double equals two.
Okay, access is not defined.
My bad.
So what you have to do, you have to keep this here, and you have to put it here. Yeah,
okay. Access is not defined.
Yeah,
fine.
Okay.
So as you can see here,
first I will show you this question name, length, speed, location, status, and opening date is here.
Fine.
So if you will go here,
question name, length, speed, location, status, nothing opening date is there.
Right.
So this is how you can drop a table.
Fine.
For a while, I'm making this as a comment.
Maybe in future or upcoming, you know, uh making graph.
I'll leave this.
Okay, so yeah, so I will write here: DF equals to
DF
cluster name,
comma, location,
then comma
status.
Then here I will write, manufacture
fine,
then again, comma.
then I will give here
ear
introduced,
then
comma,
latitude.
Wait, I will tell you why I'm doing this, then longitude, latitude, longitude.
then
I will give you
type in
okay.
then
opening
date,
clean
fine.
Then speed into
meter per hour to slide
speed into hour,
and comma what else
than
height
into foot
inversion,
clean,
comma,
G force,
clean.
dot copy.
Yeah.
So here I will write okay
type in
okay, one more mistake is here.
Fine.
So now, what I will do,
I will write here: opening
date
clean equals to
Pd. two
dot date time,
DF
opening
date,
clean find.
So what is does this pd.2 datetime do?
Okay, so it converts argument to data time date time.
Okay, so this function you know you can say converts a scalar array like or series or data frame dictionary like to a pandas
date time object okay.
So now let's rename the columns.
Okay.
Then two, you know, for better things.
equals to df .dot (rename
columns equals to
poster
name
). Then
poster
name,
comma,
here
introduced.
Then
here
introduced, okay.
Opening date clean to
open
up date,
okay.
Then I'll write a speed
in the interval r,
then I will write
caps
speed and so
interval r,
got it.
Then
height
into foot,
I will write it as,
okay, should be kept.
So why I'm writing this?
Because this is a very good practice as a professional way.
Or no, as a data analyst or as a business analyst, whatever. You are working on machine learning projects or whatever the thing, this is a good practice.
Okay?
So inversions,
inversions
clean.
Then it should be like
inversions,
then
g force
clean,
fine.
Let me run it.
Okay, now let's check the column.
Yeah, so now you can say our column name is changed.
Fine,
so I will write this an a
dot
sum.
So, what does this is na dot sum do so is an a function returns a boolean value of, you know, true if the value is n an
and the false otherwise, and the sum function returns the sum of the true values which equals to the number of n n values in the column.
So here we have 0 and n here, same this status 213 here, 217, 5
high foot is 916. Okay, so now what we will do?
We will write here
df.
dot
location
df dot
duplicate
I told you in starting
we'll
duplicate it, okay?
So question name location status manual, okay? It's duplicate it now,
okay?
So now what we will do? I will check duplicates for the question name. So you can write df dot co l o g, l o c, then df,
df dot
duplicate it.
and subset equals to
poster
name,
then dot hat.
Okay.
head of five.
Now everyone know right what do
what this hat does?
Okay,
yeah.
So here you can see so these are duplicate
okay of the question
name, right?
Why because you can just check the type in word
and all fine.
So now, checking with an example, duplicate. let's check df.query,
(costa _name
="crystal "). custom
crystal.
and now you will get beach
cyclone.
Okay, I took this crystal beach cyclone,
fine,
then run it.
So now you can see 39 and 43 are the same.
Okay, everything is same.
So this one is duplicate.
So now what I will do? I will write here let me give some space here df.columns,
then I will write here df question df.
Then df.
Question name,
then
location,
opening
date,
okay.
Dot
reset
index,
then drop that,
okay.
So
now what we will do? We will do some feature understanding.
Okay.
So now we will do some feature understanding.
So in this we will plot some feature distribution like histogram kd box plot.
Okay, for that I will write a df
er introduced.
Okay,
then I will write value
counts.
So now what I will do?
Let's create
bar chart.
Okay.
Ax equals to DF
year
introduced dot
value
counts.
Okay, then dot
head ten max I need,
then dot plot kind equals to I need bar,
then title is topped.
I write what, what, what, what should we give? Top ten
years
clusters introduced.
Okay,
then
I will write here ex
dot
set
x level,
then I will write here years
introduced.
Okay,
then I will write here ax dot
set y level,
then
count.
Okay, let me run it.
Okay, unexpected corrector after line continuation.
Okay,
we can remove this as we go;
unexpected, intended.
Now let me run it.
Yeah,
so this is our bar
plot. Okay,
so this is how you can create bar plot
using your data.
Okay, so
a bar plot is you know one of the most common types of graphics in this data visualization or ED.
It shows the relationship between a numerical and the categorical variable.
Okay, so each entity of this category variable is represented as a bar.
Got it?
So now let's do some more.
So what uh let's make a historogram class
okay,
histogram.
So for that, I will write
ax equals to df
speed
r.
then plot
kind
equals to
store gram,
then comma.
I'll write bins here.
Okay, pins equals to twenty,
then
title
equals to coaster
speed
metapol,
then
axet
text level,
yes, speed
meter, per hour.
Okay, forgot to give this
okay, yeah.
So histogram displays numerical data by grouping data into bins of equal width.
So here each bin is plotted as a bar whose height corresponds to how many data points are in that bin.
So bins you can say are also sometimes called the intervals or classes or buckets.
Basically,
it's the same.
So here for this, this much is the bin.
For this, this much is a bin.
So this is like that.
Okay.
So now let's create kd plot.
So for that, it's very simple.
ax equals df.
then I can write speed in meter power r.
then plot
kind
equals to kd,
comma, then title.
I can write anything coaster
speed
then ax.
Okay, meet the bar.
Yeah.
So kd, what does kd mean?
A kernel density estimate.
This plot is a method of you know uh visualizing the distribution of observation in a data set analogs to a histogram.
So kd represents the data using a continuous probability density curve in one or more dimension,
okay?
In one or more dimension that curve.
Fine.
So now let's do some feature relationship.
So in this we will make scatter plot, heat map correlation, and pair plot, okay, or we can also do some group by comparison.
Fine.
So now let's first make
scatter plot.
Okay, so df dot plot
kind
was to
scatter, comma,
x equals to
speed meter parallel,
comma, y equals to
height in foot,
fine.
Then comma, let's skip the title equals to coastal speed
versus
uh height
fine then PLD dot show.
Okay, some error is there.
Speed meter bar.
Okay.
Okay, s should be capital and should be capital.
Yeah.
So this is scatter plot speed versus height.
This is speed versus height.
Okay.
If the
I can see here height is directly proportional to speed, somewhat because if you can see the 350s speed is then
120 kilometer per hour. No, it's not like that.
Okay, fine.
So scatter plot identifies the possible relationship between change observed in two different sets of variables.
Here the variables are height and the speed.
Okay, it provides a visual and the aesthetical uh you know means to test the strength of relationship between two variables.
Fine.
Now let's okay, now let's make one more to give you a better idea.
Okay, with legend.
Now I will show you bit sns, dot
scatter,
plot, then x equals to
speed.
inter R,
comma. y equals to
height into foot
feet.
whatever you can say, then hue will be there.
then here
introduced.
okay.
Then, data equals to df,
then ax equals to set title,
set title, then
coaster,
speed. what is
height,
then plt, dot show.
Yeah,
so now you can see.
So this color, you know the light color. I will let me zoom it.
Okay, so this color we have some here which are introduced in 90s, okay, and this color which are introduced in 1925, and this color
which are introduced in 2000.
Okay,
so we you can see like this as well.
So now let's make pair plot,
okay.
It's look amazing.
So let me write sns dot
dot
pair plot.
then tf, comma
variable is equals to
I need year. introduce.
then
speed
meter per r,
comma,
as should be kept on height.
foot.
Just remember the spelling, okay?
Case sensitive inversion,
inversions, comma, g force,
okay, comma, hue. I will put what what what what what okay I will put type
mean
find that plt.shoc
let me run it. Okay, some error is there
here introduced
why it will be carabito
that's same here.
See, that's why I'm saying, just remember the proper spelling.
Again, some
error, sorry, my bad. Inversions?
Now let me run it.
Okay, again, some errors.
What inversions?
Okay, let me check here while renaming
inversions only.
Okay, fine.
Inversions there.
Paste input, nothing changes.
Let me check again.
Okay, some error is there
Wait,
so yeah, you can see it's running fine.
So after this, what I will do?
So, what is the pair plot? So, pair plot function allows the user to get you know then an access grid via which each numerical variable is stored in the data is shared across the x and the y
in the structured column.
So this is how the you know type in wood, other
and steel.
This red one is wood, other
are the blue one and the purple other
steel one.
Okay,
the different different formats.
Okay, now let's create the last graph which is
a heat map.
Okay.
so let me write: df
correlation.
df
here
introduced
speed
foot
drawing.
So
this is correlation values of all the things, right?
So now let's write SNS dot
heat map and tf underscore,
comma, and not will be true.
Okay.
Now let me run it.
Yeah, so to create heat map in Python, so you can use this, okay. See born library for this heat map.
So this function takes a data frame, you know, as an input and generates a heat map
type of things as the output.
Okay, so this is how you can perform EDA using any data set, or you can show your data or insights with a beautiful representation
using graphs and all, like this.
Fine.
Web scraping is a powerful technique that allows you to automatically extract data from websites, turning the vast amount of information available online
into something you can easily analyze and use, whether you are gathering data for research, building a data set for machine learning projects,
or just curious about how websites work behind the scenes.
Web scrapping is an essential skill to have in your toolkit.
On the other hand, Python is one of the most popular programming languages for web scripting, thanks to its simplicity and the wealth of liabilities available.
In this video, we will explore how to use Python to script data from websites.
And we will dive into practical examples using Python liabilities like request and beautiful soap to fetch and parts of web content.
But it's not just about the code.
Web scrapping comes with its own set of challenges and ethical considerations.
We will talk about how to script responsibly, respecting the rules set by websites and ensuring that your scrapping activity don't negatively impact the sites you are collecting data from.
So by the end of this video, you will have a solid understanding of how to start scrapping data from the web using Python.
Whether you are new to programming or looking to add web scripting to your skill set, this video will give you the knowledge and tools you need to get started.
So let's jump in and see how Python can help you unlock the full potential of the web.
So without any further ado, let's get started.
So here I am using this Google Collab for the web scrapping.
Okay, you can use your own like Jupyter Notebook, Visual Code Studio, anything.
Okay, so here I'll write scrapping
using Python.
Okay, then here first, you have to install some libraries, like,
you know, uh, request,
and you have to install beautiful. so,
and you have to install that.
you know, on dust because we will create one data frame and we will save it.
Then we will check our data.
Okay.
And you can install some basic Python levels like NumPy and all that.
Okay. So here first I will import
request.
Okay.
Then I will write from BS4
import
beautiful
soap.
Okay.
Then I will write import
pandas
as PD.
Fine.
Then now what I will do. Okay, let's see what is this request and all the things. So request is an HTTP client library for the Python programming language.
So request is one of the most you know downloaded Python libraries.
Okay, with like more like over 2000, not exactly 2000, sorry, 200 or 300 million monthly download.
Okay, so what it does is it maps the STT protocol onto Python's object-oriented semantics.
And here beautiful soup. So
beautiful soup is a Python package for you know parsing the STML and XML documents, including those with you know malphone markup.
It creates a parsery for documents that can be you know used to extract data STML from HTML, which is useful for web
scraping.
Let's be telling it here.
Our second step will be
define the URL and the headers.
Okay, URL and the headers.
So URL.
Okay, from where you want to set your data.
So I will write here singly learn,
then this okay. Let's open this PMP certification.
Okay, let's cut it.
Yeah, so here I will write this
and headers
to
these are the headers, okay.
So like in which you know device or you are working on, which browser you are working on.
So these are for the headers.
So now what I will do, I will send a get request to the simplic page, okay, to this URL.
For that, you know, right?
Let me write this sending
get request.
Okay, here write response
requests
dot
get
then you added
comma headers
to headers.
Okay, let me run it.
Okay, working fine.
So now uh
let's check if the request is successful or not for that. If
the sponsor dot status code, plus two equals two questions equals two hundred,
then
so
was true.
we need it for. so,
okay.
Then
response
dot
content
comma
STML
dot parser.
Okay.
Here
so here I will write codes
titles.
Why?
Because here I am you know initializing the list to store our
titles or whatever the things are, okay, basically the data.
Okay, why I'm writing course here? Because this is again course page.
That's right.
Nothing else.
Okay, here I will give the empty list.
So now we will find all course titles based on the actual HTML structure. What is HTML structure?
You have to go to the page, right-click,
then inspect.
Okay, according to this HTML structure means
what is the class name, what is the you know this PMP certification is which heading, H1 adding, H2 adding, which heading it is.
Okay, so let's see
which heading it is okay.
Always this PMP certification training H1 adding.
Okay, just remember H1 adding.
So here I will write for
course in so
dot
find
or
H one.
Okay.
Then title
costume course text
dot strip.
Okay.
Then here I'm write course
titles
dot
append
title.
Okay.
Now what I will do? I will check
if any data was extracted before it not.
Okay. I will write if
course
titles.
Here I will create a data frame df what so pd.data
frame.
In this I will write course title, it will be our
you know uh that
column name.
So for I will write it course zeta.
Okay,
then
course
titles.
Okay,
then here I will write df
dot to
then uh just create simply learn.csv.
Okay, so our data will be saving this simply learn.csv.
Okay, csv
fine.
Here, what I will do? I will write index equation, false
print,
". print "data is saved in csv.
simply. learn
dot csv
Fine.
so here I will write
else,
print
"web, page,
". Okay.
let me write.
find
to
retrieve the
web page.
Okay, that's it.
Let me run it.
Okay, here:
if response story studies code
sponsor Object has no attribute stata code Okay,
outdate title.
Some minor spelling mistakes are there.
Okay, dear doctor.
Sorry, sorry, my bad.
Again.
Okay, sorry.
D will be kept alive.
Yeah. So now you can see data is saved in simply learn.csv. So what I will do? I will write data equals to everyone know how to read csv in python.read underscore csv.
What was a file name?
Simplylearn.csv.
Okay, if I copy paste, run it,
and find data.
Okay.
Pmp certification training.
Data is fetched.
Okay.
Here you can see H1 we gave, and that's why PMP certification training came.
Let's take what's in H2.
Okay, in H2, there is leading premier PMI partner. Something is there.
Okay, I will change here.
Okay.
Fine.
See leading premier PMI. Okay, let me make it bigger.
Yeah.
So now you can see
course data we mentioned.
So
if you will see this H1 didn't come.
Why? Because we have mentioned H2.
That's why. So these all are the H2.
Okay.
So what is this? I don't know.
This is a time series graph. This is Google tool, I think.
Okay, so this is how you can literally retrieve your data from any website.
Okay. Just remember that some websites don't give you access to their, you know, for the scrapping, just like Amazon don't give. So you have to use at that time API.
And this is not ethical also to use someone's data.
Okay?
Without asking or whatever you guys are. Welcome to the Neural Network tutorial.
My name is Richard Kirshner. I'm with the Simply Learn team.
What's in it for you?
Well, today we're going to cover what is a neural network.
What can neural networks do?
How does a neural network work?
Types of neural networks. And then we're going to jump into a use case to classify between the photos of dogs and cats.
And we'll do that on the caras with the TensorFlow in the back. But it's a Python script, so that's always my favorite part is when we dive into the actual script.
So what is a neural network?
So hi guys. I heard you want to know what a neural network is. Here we have uh looks like he just went shopping at a red tag sale. My robot's back.
So, as a matter of fact, you have been using neural network on a daily basis. In today's world, it's just amazing how much we use our new technology. We're not even aware of it.
When you ask your mobile assistant to perform a search for you, you know, like saying your Google or Siri or whoever you use, Amazon Web, self-driving cars,
so that's the newest thing coming out. They're just now trying to make those legal in different states in the US and around the world.
Even in the UK, they now have uh self-driving cars going up and down the street. It's pretty amazing. These are all neural network driven. Computer games use it.
A lot of computer games are driven by neural networks in the back end as part of the game system and how it adjusts to the players.
And it's also used in processing the map images on your phone.
So every time you do a navigation someplace and it opens it up, they now use neural networks to help you find the quickest way to get there.
Neural network.
A neural network is a system or hardware that is designed to operate like a human brain.
In today's development, this is so important to understand because we don't have anything else to compare it to.
I'm sure someday in the future the computer will redefine, or the neural network or the AI, artificial intelligence, will redefine what these mean.
But as far as we can today's world and today's commercial development, we have to compare it to what humans do.
So it's we want to compare how it operates to a human brain and how it solves problems like a human does.
What can a neural network do? And really, we're just gonna dive in deeper to what we just covered and look at other examples.
So what can a neural network do? Well, let's list out the things neural networks can do for you.
Translate text.
Boy, we got Google Translate and Microsoft has their own translate. They have some really cool they actually have an earpiece that's supposed to start translating as you talk.
What a cool technology, what a cool time to live. Identify faces. Can you imagine all the uses for facial identification?
In the case of our uh sample or our code that we're gonna look at later, we'll be identifying dogs and cats, so not quite as detailed as uh understanding whose face belongs to who.
I I'm waiting for the Google glasses to come out so I can see who's who when they identify faces as I'm walking around, have a little name tag over them. Not out there yet, but boy, we are close.
We can identify the faces and they have all kinds of technologies to bring that information back to us. Recognize speech goes along with the translate text.
So now as you're talking into your assistant, it can use that to do commands, turn lights on. All kinds of things you can do with recognizing speech.
Read handwritten text. They're starting to translate all these old text documents that they've had in storage.
Instead of doing it individually where somebody's going through each text by themselves in a room, you can picture like an old Raiders of the Lost Arc theme where he's in the back, you know,
archaeologist studying the text. Now it's fed into a computer, they take a picture.
They even use neural networks to take a scroll that is so messed up that they can't undo the scroll and they x-ray it,
and then they use that x-ray to translate the text off of it without ever opening the scroll.
I mean, just way cool stuff they're starting to do with all this. And of course, control robots.
What would be in a neural network without bringing in the robots? And we have our own favorite robot in the middle who goes to our red tag cell and goes shopping for us.
So, you know, these are just a few of the wonderful things that neural networks are being applied to. It's such an infant stage technology. What a wonderful time to jump in.
And there are a lot of other things it goes into. I mean, we could spend just forever talking about all the different applications from business to whatever you can even imagine.
They're now applying neural networks to help us understand.
So now that we talked a little bit about all the cool things you can do with a neural network, let's dive in and say how does a neural network work?
So now we've come far enough to understand how neural network works. Let's go ahead and walk through this in a nice graphical representation.
They usually describe a neural network as having different layers. And you'll see that we've identified a green layer, an orange layer, and a red layer.
The green layer is the input.
So you have your data coming in. It picks up the input signals and passes them to the next layer. The next layer does all kinds of calculations and feature extraction. It's called the hidden layer.
A lot of times there's more than one hidden layer.
We're only showing one in this uh picture, but we'll show you how it looks like in a more detail in a little bit.
And then finally we have an output layer.
This layer delivers the final result.
So the only two things we see is the input layer and the output layer.
Now let's make use of this neural network and see how it works.
Wonder how traffic cameras identify vehicles registration plate on the road to detect speeding vehicles and those breaking the law?
They got me going through a red light the other day. Well, last month. That's like the horrible thing.
They send you this picture of you and all your information because they pulled it up off of your license plate and your picture. I shouldn't have gone through the red light.
So here we are, and we have an image of a car, and you can see the license plates on there. So let's consider the image of this vehicle and find out what's on the number plate.
The picture itself is 28 by 28 pixels, and the image is fed as an input to identify the registration plate.
Each neuron has a number called activation that represents the grayscale value of the corresponding pixel range. And we range it from zero to one, one for a white pixel and zero for a black pixel.
And you can see down here we have an example where one of the pixels is registered as like 0.82, meaning it's probably pretty dark. Each neuron is lit up when its activation is close to one.
So as we get closer to black on white, we can really start seeing the details in there. And you can see again the pixel shows us one up there. It's like part of the car. And so it lights up.
So pixels in the form of arrays are fed to the input layer.
And so we see here the pixel of a car image fed as an input. And you're going to see that the input layer, which is green, is one dimension, while our image is two dimension.
Now, when we look at our setup that we're programming in Python, it has a cool feature that automatically does the work for us.
If you're working with an older neural network pattern package, you then convert each one of those rows so it's all one array. So you'd have like row one and then just tack row two onto the end.
You can almost feed the image directly into some of these neural networks.
The key is though, is that if you're using a 28 by 28 and you get a picture of this 30 by 30, shrink the 30 by 30 down to fit the 28 by 28.
So you can't increase a number of input, in this case green dots. It's very important to remember when you're working on neural networks. And let's name the inputs x1, x2, x3 respectively.
So each one of those represents one of the pixels coming in. And the input layer passes it to the hidden layer.
And you can see here we now have two hidden layers in this image, in the orange, and each one of those pixels connects to each one of those hidden layers.
And the interconnections are assigned weights at random. So there gets these random weights that come through. If x1 lights up, then it's going to be x1 times this weight going into the hidden layer.
And we sum those weights. The weights are multiplied with the input signal, and a bias is added to all of them.
So as you can see here, we have x1 comes in and it actually goes to all the different hidden layer nodes, or in this case uh whatever you want to call them, network setup,
the orange dots.
And so you take the value of x1, you multiply it by the weight for the next hidden layer.
So x1 goes to hidden layer 1, x1 goes to hidden layer 2, x1 goes to hidden layer 1, node 2, hidden layer 1, node 3, and so on.
And the bias, a lot of times they just put the bias in as like another green dot or another orange dot.
And they give the bias a value 1, and then all the weights go in from the bias into the next node. So the bias can change. We always just remember that you need to have that bias in there.
There's things that can be done with it. Generally, most of the packages out there control that for you, so you don't have to worry about figuring out what the bias is.
But if you ever dive deep into neural networks, you've got to remember there's a bias, or the answer won't come out correctly.
The weighted sum of the input is fed as an input to the activation function to decide which nodes to fire.
And for feature extraction, as a signal flows within the hidden layers, the weighted sum of inputs is calculated and is fed to the activation function in each layer to decide which nodes to fire.
So here's our feature extraction of the number plate. And you can see these are still hidden nodes in the middle.
And this becomes important. We're going to take a little detour here and look at the activation function.
So we're going to dive just a little bit into the math. So you can start to understand where some of the games go on when you're playing with neural networks and you're programming.
So let's look at the different activation functions. Before we move ahead, here's our friendly red tag shopping robot. And so one is a sigmoid function.
And the sigmoid function, which is one over one plus e to the minus x, takes the x value and you can see where it generates almost a zero and almost a one
with a very small area in the middle where it crosses over. And we can use that value to feed into another function.
So if it's really uncertain, it might have a point one or point two or point three, but for the most part it's going to be really close to one and really close to this case zero, zero to one.
The threshold function. So if you don't want to worry about the uncertainty in the middle, you just say, oh, if x is greater than or equal to zero, if not, then uh x is zero.
So it's either zero or one. Really straightforward, there's no in between in the middle.
And then you have the what they call the RELU relue function, and you can see here where it puts out the value, but then it says, well, if it's over one,
it's going to be one. And if it's uh less than zero, it's zero.
So it kind of just dead ends it on those two ends, but allows all the values in the middle. And again, this like the sigmoid function allows that information to go to the next level.
So it might be important to know if it's a point one or a minus point one.
The next hidden layer might pick that up and say, oh, this piece of information is uncertain, or this value has a very low certainty to it.
And then the hyperbolic tangent function. And you can see here it's a one minus e to the minus two x over one plus e to the minus two x.
And it's very much along the same theme, a little bit different in here in that it goes between minus one and one.
So you'll see some of these they go zero to one, but this one goes minus one to one.
And if it's less than zero, it's you know it doesn't fire, and if it's over zero, it fires, and it also still puts out a value.
So you still have a value that you can get off of that, just like you can with the sigmoid function and the relue function, very similar in use.
And I believe the originally it used to be everything was done in the sigmoid function. That was the most uh commonly used. And now they just kind of use more of the relue function.
The reason is one, it processes faster.
Because you already have the value and you don't have to add another compute the one over one plus e to the minus x for each hidden node.
And the data coming off works pretty good as far as putting it into the next level if you want to know just how close it is to zero. How close is it not to functioning?
You know, is it minus 0.1, minus 0.2? Usually they're float values, you get like minus point, you know, minus 0.00138 or something.
So you know, important information, but the relue is most commonly used these days as far as the setup we're using. But you'll also see the sigmoid function very commonly used also.
Now that you know what an activation function is, let's get back to the neural network.
So finally the model would predict the outcome of applying a suitable activation function to the output layer.
So we go in here, we look at this, and we have the optical character recognition, OCR, is used on the images to convert it into a text in order to identify what's written on the plate.
And as it comes out, you'll see the red node, and the red node might actually represent just a letter A. So there's usually a lot of outputs when you're doing text identification.
We're not going to show that on here. But you might have it even in the order, might be what order the license plate's in.
So you might have A, B, C, D, E, F, G, you know, the alphabet plus the numbers, and you might have the one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten
places.
So it's a very large array that comes out. It's not a small amount of uh, you know, we show three dots coming in, eight hidden layer nodes, you know, two sets of four. We just show one red coming out.
A lot of times this is uh you know, twenty-eight times twenty-eight. If you did thirty times thirty, that's you know, nine hundred nodes.
So twenty-eight is a little bit less than that, uh, just on the input.
And so you can imagine the hidden layer is just as big, each hidden layer is just as big, if not bigger, then the output is gonna be there's so many digits, you know,
it's a lot, there's it's a huge amount of input and output. But we're only showing you just you know, it's it'd be hard to show in one picture.
And so it comes up, and this is what it finally gets out on the output is it identifies a number on the plate. And in this case we have 08-d dash zero three eight five eight.
Error in the output is backpropagated through the network, and weights are adjusted to minimize the error rate. This is calculated by a cost function.
When we're training our data, this is what's used. And we'll look at that in the code when we do the data training.
So we have stuff we know the answer to, and then we put the information through, and it says, yes, that was correct, or no, because remember we randomly set all the weights to begin with.
And if it's wrong, we take that error. How far off are you? You know, are you off by is it if it was like minus one, you're just a little bit off.
If it's like minus 300 was your output, remember when we're looking at those different options, you know, hyperbolic or whatever, and we're looking at the REL, the REL could
doesn't have a limit on top or bottom. It actually just generates a number. So if it's way off, you're gonna have to adjust those weights a lot.
But if it's pretty close, you might adjust the weights just a little bit.
And you keep adjusting the weights until they fit all the different training models you put in.
So you might have 500 training models, and those weights will adjust using the back propagation.
It sends the error backward.
The output is compared with the original result, and multiple iterations are done to get the maximum accuracy.
So not only does it look at each one, but it goes through it and just keeps cycling through these the data and making small changes in the network until it gets the right answers.
With every iteration, the weights at every interconnection are adjusted based on the error.
We're not going to dive into that math because it is a differential equation, and it gets a little complicated.
But I will talk a little bit about some of the different options they have when we look at the code.
So we've explored a neural network.
Let's look at the different types of artificial neural networks. And this is like the biggest area growing is how these all come together. Let's see the different types of neural network.
And again, we're comparing this to human learning.
So here's a human brain. I feel sorry for that poor guy.
So we have a feed for forward neural network.
Simplest form of a they call it an ANN, a neural network. Data travels only in one direction, input to output.
This is what we just looked at.
So as the data comes in, all the weights are added, it goes to the hidden layer, all the weights are added, it goes to the next hidden layer, all the weights are added, and it goes to the output.
The only time you use the reverse propagation is to train it.
So when you actually use it, it's very fast.
When you're training it, it takes a while because it has to iterate through all your training data. And you start getting into big data because you can train these with a huge amount of data.
The more data you put in, the better train they get.
The applications, vision and speech recognition, actually they're pretty much everything we talked about. A lot of almost all of them use this form of neural network at some level.
Radio basis function, neural network. This model classifies the data point based on its distance from a center point.
What that means is that you might not have training data, so you want to group things together and you create central points and it looks for all the things,
you know, some of these things are just like the other. If you've ever watched the Sesame Street as a kid, that dates me.
So it brings things together, and this is a great way if you don't have the right training model, you can start finding things that are connected you might not have noticed before.
Applications, power restoration systems.
They try to figure out what's connected, and then based on that, they can fix the problem if you have a huge power system.
Cahonan's self-organizing neural network. Vectors of random dimensions are input to discrete map comprised of neurons.
So they basically find a way to draw, and they call them, they say dimensions or vectors, or planes, because they actually chop the data in one dimension,
two dimension, three dimension, four, five, six. They keep adding dimensions and finding ways to separate the data and connect different data pieces together.
Applications used to recognize patterns in data, like in medical analysis.
The hidden layer saves its output to be used for future prediction. Recurrent neural networks. So the hidden layers remember its output from last time and that becomes part of its new input.
You might use that, especially in robotics or flying a drone.
You want to know what your last change was and how fast it was going to help predict what your next change you need to make is to get to where the drone wants to go.
Applications, text-to-speech, conversation model. So you know I talked about drones, but you know, just identifying on Lexus or Google Assistant or any of these, they're starting to add in.
I'd like to play a song on my Pandora, and I'd like it to be at volume 90%. So you now can add different things in there and it connects them together.
The input features are taken in batches like a filter.
This allows a network to remember an image in parts.
Convolution, neural network.
Today's world in photo identification and taking apart photos and trying to, you know, have you ever seen that on Google where you have five people together?
This is the kind of thing separates all those people so then it can do a face recognition on each person. Applications used in signal and image processing.
In this case, I use facial images or Google picture images as one of the options.
Modular neural network.
It has a collection of different neural networks working together to get the output.
So wow, we just went through all these different types of neural networks. And the final one is to put multiple neural networks together.
I mentioned that a little bit when we separated people in a larger photo and individuals in the photo, and then do the facial recognition on each person.
So one network is used to separate them, and the next network is then used to figure out who they are and do the facial recognition. Applications still undergoing research. This is a cutting edge.
You hear the term pipeline, and there's actual in Python code and in almost all the different neural network setups out there, they now have a pipeline feature usually.
And it just means you take the data from one neural network and maybe another neural network, or you put it into the next neural network,
and then you take three or four other neural networks and feed them into another one. So how we connect the neural networks is really just cutting edge, and it's so experimental.
I mean it's almost creative in its nature. There's not really a science to it because each specific domain has different things it's looking at.
So if you're in the banking domain, it's going to be different than the medical domain, then the automatic car domain.
And suddenly figuring out how those all fit together is just a lot of fun and really cool. So we have our types of artificial neural network.
We have our feed forward neural network, we have a radial basis function neural network, we have our Kohenan self-organizing neural network, recurrent neural network,
convolution neural network, and modular neural network where it brings them all together.
And uh no the colors on the brain do not match what your brain actually does, but they do bring it out that most of these were developed by understanding how humans learn.
And as we understand more and more of how humans learn, we can build something in the computer industry to mimic that, to reflect that.
And that's how these were developed.
So exciting part, use case, problem statement. So this is where we jump in. This is my favorite part. Let's use the system to identify between a cat and a dog.
If you remember correctly, I said we're gonna do some Python code, and uh you can see over here I my hair is kind of sticking up over the computer,
a cup of coffee on one side, and then a little bit of old school, a pencil and a pen on the other side. Yeah, most people now take notes. I I love the stickies on the computer, that's great.
That's that is my computer. I have sticky notes on my computer in different colors. So not too far from uh today's programmer.
So the problem is is we want to classify photos of cats and dogs using a neural network.
And you can see over here we have quite a variety of dogs in the pictures and cats, and you know, just sorting out it is a cat is pretty amazing.
And why would anybody want to even know the difference between a cat and a dog?
Okay, you know why? Well, I have a cat door.
It'd be kind of fun that instead of it identifying, instead of having like a little collar with a magnet on it, which is what my cat has, the door would be able to see,
oh, that's the cat, that's our cat coming in. Oh, that's the dog. We have a dog too. That's the dog I want to let in. Maybe I don't want to let this other animal in because it's a raccoon.
So you can see where you could take this one step further and actually apply this. You could actually start a little startup company idea, a self-identifying door.
So this use case will be implemented on Python. I am actually in Python 3.6.
It's always nice to tell people the version of Python because that does affect sometimes which modules you load and everything. And we're gonna start by importing the required packages.
I told you we're gonna do this in Karas. So we're gonna import from Karas models a sequential from the Karas Layers, conversion 2D or C O N V 2D, Max Pooling 2D,
Flatten, and Dents.
And we'll talk about what each one of these do in just a second. But before we do that, let's talk a little bit about the environment we're gonna work in.
And uh, you know, in fact, let me go ahead and open a uh the website, Karas' website, so we can learn a little bit more about Carras.
So here we are on the Karas website, and it's uh K-E-R-A-S.io.
That's the official website for Karas. And the first thing you'll notice is that Caras runs on top of either TensorFlow, C N T K, and I think it's pronounced Thano or Thano.
What's important on here is that TensorFlow, and the same is true for all these, but TensorFlow is probably one of the most widely used currently packages out there with the Caras.
And of course, you know, tomorrow this is all gonna change. It's all gonna disappear and they'll have something new out there.
So make sure when you're learning this code that you understand what's going on, and also know the code.
I mean, look when you look at the code, it's not as complicated once you understand what's going on. The code itself is pretty straightforward.
And the reason we like Carras, and the reason that people are jumping on it right now and it's such a big deal, is if we come down here, let me just scroll down a little bit.
They talk about user friendliness, modularity, easy extensibility, work with Python. Python's a big one because a lot of people in data science now use Python.
Although you can actually access caras other ways. Is if we continue down here is layers.
And this is where it gets really cool.
When we're working with Caras, you just add layers on. Remember those hidden layers we were talking about? And we talked about the RELU activation.
You can see right here, let me just up that a little bit in size. There we go. That's big. I can add in an RELU layer, and then I can add in a softmax layer, the next instance.
We didn't talk about softmax. So you can do each layer separate. Now if I'm working in some of the other kits I use, I take that and I have one setup and then I feed the output into the next one.
This one I can just add hidden layer after hidden layer with the different information in it, which makes it very powerful and very fast to spin up and try different setups
and see how they work with the data you're working on. And we'll dig a little bit deeper in here.
And a lot of this is very much the same, so when we get to that part, I'll point that out to you also.
Now, just a quick side note, I'm using Anaconda with Python in it, and I went ahead and created my own package, and I called it the Caras Python 3.6
because I'm in Python 3.6. Anaconda's cool that way. You can create different environments real easily.
If you're doing a lot of different experimenting with these different packages, probably want to create your own environment in there.
And the first thing is you can see right here, there's a lot of dependencies. A lot of these you should recognize by now if you've done any of these videos.
If not, kudos for you for jumping in today. Pip install numpy, scipy, the sci kit learn.
Pillow and h5py are both needed for the TensorFlow and then putting the caras on there. And then you'll see here, uh and pip is just a standard installer that you use with Python.
You'll see here that we did pip install tensorflow. Since we're going to do caras on top of TensorFlow.
And then pip install, and I went ahead and used the GitHub. So Git plus Git. And you'll see here GitHub.com.
This is one of their releases, one of the most current release on there that goes on top of TensorFlow. And you can look up these instructions pretty much anywhere. This is for doing it on Anaconda.
Certainly you'd want to install these if you're doing it in an Ubuntu server setup.
You'd you'd want to get, I don't think you need the H5PY on Ubuntu, but you do need the rest in there because they are dependencies in there. And it's pretty straightforward.
And that's actually in some of the instructions they have on their website. So you don't have to necessarily go through this. Just remember their website on there.
And then when I'm under my uh Anaconda navigator, which I like, you'll see where I have environments, and on the bottom I created a new environment and I called it CrossPython 36.
Just to separate everything. You can say I have Python 30.5 and Python 3.6. I used to have a bunch of other ones, but it kind of cleaned house recently.
And of course, once I go in here, I can launch my Jupyter notebook, making sure I'm using the right environment that I just set up.
This of course opens up my um in this case I'm using uh Google Chrome.
And in here I could go and just create a new document in here. And this is all in your um browser window when you use the Anaconda. Do you have to use Anaconda in Jupyter Notebook?
No.
You can use any kind of Python editor, whatever setup you're comfortable with and whatever you're doing in there.
So let's go ahead and go in here and paste the code in.
And we're importing a number of different settings in here. We have import sequential, that's under the models, because that's the model we're going to use as far as our neural network.
And then we have layers and we have conversion 2D, max pooling 2D, flatten, dense. And you can actually just kind of guess at what these do. We're talking, we're working in a 2D photograph.
And if you remember correctly, I talked about how the actual input layer is a single array. It's not in two dimensions, it's one dimension.
All these do is these are tools to help flatten the image. So it takes a two-dimensional image and then it creates its own proper setup. You don't have to worry about any of that.
You don't have to do anything special with the photograph. You let the Karas do it.
We're going to run this, and you'll see right here they have some stuff that is going to be depreciated and changed because that's what it does. Everything's being changed as we go.
You don't have to worry about that too much. If you have warnings, if you run it a second time, the warning will disappear.
And this is just imported these packages for us to use.
Jupiter's nice about this that you can do each thing step by step. And I'll go ahead and also zoom in there. A little control plus. That's one of the nice things about being in a browser environment.
So here we are back, another sip of coffee. If you're familiar with my other videos, you notice I'm always sipping coffee. I always have a in my case latte next to me, an espresso.
So the next step is to go ahead and initialize, we're going to call it the CNN or Classifier Neural Network.
And the reason we call it a classifier is because it's going to classify it between two things. It's going to be cat or dog. So when you're doing classification, you're picking specific objects.
You're specific it's a true or false. Yes, no, it is something or it's not.
So first thing we're going to create our classifier and it's going to equal sequential.
So their sequential setup is the classifier. That's the actual model we're using. That's the neural network. So we call it a classifier. And uh the next step.
is to add in our convolution. And let me just do a uh let me shrink that down in size so you can see the whole line.
And let's talk a little bit about what's going on here.
I have my classifier and I add something. What am I adding? Well I'm adding my first layer.
This first layer we're adding in is probably the one that takes the most work to make sure you have it set correct.
And the reason I say that is this is your actual input. And we're gonna jump here to the part that says input shape equals 64 by 64 by 3.
What does that mean? Well that means that our picture's coming in and there's these pictures remember we had like the picture of the car was 128 by 128 pixels.
Well this one is 64 by 64 pixels and each pixel has three values.
That's where these numbers come from.
And it is so important that this matches I mentioned a little bit that if you have like a larger picture you have to reformat it to fit this shape.
If it comes in as something larger there's no input notes there's no input neural network there that will handle that extra space. So you have to reshape your data to fit in here.
Now the first layer is the most important because after that Carras knows what your shape is coming in here and it knows what's coming out.
And so that really sets the stage. Most important thing is that input shape matches your data coming in. And you'll get a lot of errors if it doesn't.
You'll go through there and picture number 55 doesn't match it correctly. And guess what it does? It usually gives you an error.
And then the activation if you remember we talked about the different activations on here we're using the RELU model.
Like I said that is the most commonly used now because one it's fast doesn't have the added calculations in it.
It just says here's the value coming out based on the weights and the value going in and from there you know it's uh it's if it's over one
then it's good or over zero it's good. If it's under zero then it's considered not active. And then we have this conversion 2D.
What the heck is conversion 2D?
I'm not going to go into too much detail in this because this has a couple of things it's doing in here. A little bit more in-depth than we're ready to cover in this tutorial.
But this is used to convert from the photo because we have 64 by 64 by 3 and we're just converting it to two dimensional kind of setup.
So it's very aware that this is a photograph and that different pieces are next to each other.
And then we're going to add in a second convolutional layer. That's what the C O N V stands for 2D.
So it's these are hidden layers. So we have our input layer and our two hidden layers and they are two dimensional because we're dealing with a two dimensional photograph.
And you'll see down here that on the last one we add a max pooling 2D and we put a pool size equals two two.
And so what this is is that as you get to the end of these layers one of the things you always want to think of is what they call mapping and then reducing wonderful terminology from the big data.
We're mapping this data through all these layers and now we want to reduce it to only two sets.
In this case it's already in two sets because it's a 2D photograph but we had you know two dimensions by we actually have sixty four by sixty four by three.
So now we're just getting it down to a two by two just the two dimension two dimensional instead of having the third dimension of colors. And we'll go ahead and run these.
And this is where you start playing because maybe you'll add a different layer in here to do something else to see how it works and see what your output is.
That's what makes Karas so nice is I can with just a couple flips of code put in a whole new layer that does a whole new processing and see whether that improves my run or makes it worse.
And finally we're going to do the final setup which is to flatten classifier add a flatten setup and then we're going to also add a layer a dense layer
and then we're going to add in another dense layer and then we're going to build it. We're going to compile this whole thing together.
So let's flip over and see what that looks like. And we've even numbered them for you so we're going to do the flattening and flatten is exactly what it sounds like.
We've been working in a two dimensional array of picture which actually is in three dimensions because of the pixels.
The pixels have a a whole nother dimension to it of three different values and we've kind of resized those down to two by two but now we're just going to flatten it.
I don't want to have multiple dimensions being worked on by Tensor and by Karras. I want just a single array So it's flattened out.
And then step four, full connection. So we add in our final two layers. And you could actually do all kinds of things with this.
You could actually leave out this uh some of these layers and play with them. You do need to flatten it.
That's very important.
Then we want to use the dents. Again, we're taking this and we're taking whatever came into it.
So once we take all those different the two dimensions or three dimensions as they are, and we flatten it to one dimension, we want to take that and we're gonna pull it into units of 128.
They got that. You're gonna say, where did they get twenty hundred and twenty-eight from? You could actually play with that number and get all kinds of weird results.
But in this case, we took the 64 plus 64 is 128.
You could probably even do this with 64 or 32. Usually you want to keep it in the same multiple, whatever the data shape you're already using is in.
And we're using the activation, the R-E-L-U, just like we did before. And then we finally filter all that into a single output.
And it has how many units? One. Why? Because we want to know whether true or false. It's either a dog or a cat.
You could say one is dog, zero is cat, or maybe you're a cat lover and it's one is cat and zero is dog. And if you love both dogs and cats, you're gonna have to choose.
And then we use the sigmoid activation. If you remember from before, we had the RELU, and there's also the sigmoid. Sigmoid just makes it clear it's yes or no.
We don't want a any kind of in-between number coming out. And we'll go ahead and run this, and you'll see it's still all in setup. And then finally we want to go ahead and compile.
And let's put the compiling our classifier neural network.
And we're going to use the optimizer atom. And I hinted at this just a little bit before.
Where does Atom come in? Where does an optimizer come in?
Well, the optimizer is the reverse propagation. When we're training it, it goes all the way through and says error, and then how does it readjust those weights? There are a number of them.
Atom is the most commonly used, and it works best on large data.
Most people stick with the atom because when they're testing on smaller data, see if their model is going to go through and get all their errors out before they run it on larger data sets.
They're going to run it on atom anyway, so they just leave it on atom, most commonly used. But there are some other ones out there.
You should be aware of that that you might try them if you're stuck in a bind or you might blur that in the future. But usually atom is just fine on there. And then you have two more settings.
You have loss and metrics.
We're not going to dig too much into loss or metrics. These are things you really have to explore corros because there are so many choices. This is how it computes the error.
There's so many different ways to on your back propagation and your training. So we're using the atom model, but you can compute the error by standard deviation, standard deviation squared.
They use binary crossentropy. I'd have to look that up to even know what that is. There's so many of these.
A lot of times you just start with the ones that look correct that are most commonly used, and then you have to go read the Carras site and actually see what these different losses and metrics
and what different options they have. So we're not going to get too much into them other than to reference you over to the Caras website to explore them deeper.
But we are going to go ahead and run them.
And now we've set up our classifier. So we have an object classifier. And if you go back up here, you'll see that we've added in step one, we added in our layer for the input.
We added a layer that comes in there and uses the RELU for activation. And then it pulls the data.
So this is even though these are two layers, the actual neural network layer is up here, and then it uses this to pull the data into a two by two.
So into a two-dimensional array from a three-dimensional array with the colors.
Then we flatten it. So there's our adder flatten, and then we add another dense, what they call dense layer. This dense layer goes in there and it downsizes it to 128. It reduces it.
So you can look at this as uh we're mapping all this data down the two dimensional setup, and then we flatten it. So we map it to a flattened map, and then we take it and reduce it down to 128.
And we use the R E L U again.
And then finally we reduce that down to just a single output.
And we use the sigmoid to do that.
To figure out whether it's yes, no, true, false, in this case cat or dog.
And then finally, once we put all these layers together, we compile them.
That's what we've done here.
And we've compiled them as far as how it trains to use these settings for the training, back propagation.
So if you remember, we talked about training our setup.
And when we go into this, you'll see that we have two data sets. We have one called the training set and the testing set.
And that's very standard in any data processing, is you need to have that's pretty common in any data processing is you need to have a certain amount of data to train it.
And then you gotta know whether it works or not. Is it any good?
And that's why you have a separate set of data for testing it. Where you already know the answer, but you don't want to use that as part of the training set.
So in here we jump into part two, fitting the classifier neural network to the images.
And then from Carros, let me just zoom in there. I always love that about working with Jupyter Notebooks you can really see.
We're gonna come in here, we do the cross pre-processing an image, and we import image data generator. So nice of Carross. It's such a high-end product right now going out.
And since images are so common, they already have all this stuff to help us process the data, which is great.
And so we come in here, we do train data gen, and we're gonna create our object for helping us train it for reshaping the data so that it's gonna work with our setup.
And we use an image data generator, and we're gonna rescale it.
And you'll see here we have one point, which tells us it's a float value on the rescale over 255.
Where does 255 come from? Well, that's the scale in the colors of the pictures we're using.
They are value from zero to two fifty-five.
So we want to divide it by two fifty-five and it'll generate a number between zero and one.
They have shear range and zoom range, horizontal flip equals true. And this of course has to do with if the photos are different shapes and sizes. Like I said, it's a wonderful package.
You really need to dig in deep to see all the different options you have for setting up your images. For right now, though, we're gonna just stick with some basic stuff here.
And let me go ahead and run this code. And again, it doesn't really do anything because we're still setting up the pre-processing. Let's take a look at this next set of code.
And this one is just huge. We're creating the training set.
So the training set is gonna go in here and it's gonna use our train data gen we just created, dot flow from directory. It's gonna access, in this case, the path, data set training set.
That's a folder.
So it's gonna pull all the images out of that folder.
Now I'm actually running this in the folder that the data sets in.
So if you're doing the same setup and you load your data in there and you're doing this, make sure wherever your Jupyter Notebook is saving things to that you create this path,
or you can do the complete path if you need to, you know, C colon slash, etc.
And the target size, the batch size, and class mode is binary.
So the class is we're switching everything to a binary value.
Batch size, what the heck is batch size? Well that's how many pictures we're going to batch through the training each time.
And the target size, 64 by 64.
A little confusing, but you can see right here that this is just a general training, and you can go in there and look at all the different settings for your training set.
And of course, with different data, we're doing pictures, there's all kinds of different settings depending on what you're working with.
Let's go ahead and run that and see what happens.
And you'll see that it found 800 images belonging to one classes.
So we have 800 images in the training set.
And if we're gonna do this with uh the training set, we also have to format the pictures in the test set.
Now we're not actually doing any predictions, we're not actually programming the model yet.
All we're doing is preparing the data. So we're gonna prepare a training set and the test set. So any changes we make to the training set at this point also have to be made to the test set.
So we've done this thing, we've done a train data generator, we've done our training set, and then we also have, remember our test set of data.
So I'm gonna do the same thing with that. I'm gonna create a test data gen, and we're gonna do this image data generator. We're gonna rescale one over two fifty-five.
We don't need the other settings, just the single setting for the test data gen. And we're gonna create our test set.
We're gonna do the same thing we did with the test set, except that we're pulling it from the test set folder.
And we'll run that.
And you'll see in our test set we found 2,000 images.
That's about right. We're using 20% of the images as test and 80% to train it. And then finally we've set up all our data.
We've set up all our layers, which is where all the work is is uh cleaning up that data and making sure it's going in there correctly, and we are actually going to fit it.
We're going to train our data set.
And let's see what that looks like.
And here we go, let's put the information in here, and let's just take a quick look at what we're looking at with our fit generator.
We have our classifier dot fit generator.
That's our back propagation.
So the information goes through forward with a picture, and it says, oh, you're either right or you're wrong, and then the error goes backward and reprograms all those weights.
So we're training our neural network. And uh of course we're using the training set. Remember we created the training set up here, and then we're going steps per epoch.
So it's eight thousand steps. Epic means that that's how many times we go through all the pictures.
So we're gonna rerun each of the pictures and we're gonna go through the whole data set twenty-five times. But we're gonna look at each picture during each epoch 8,000 times.
So we're really programming the heck out of this and going back over it.
And then they have validation data equals test set. So we have our um training set, and then we're gonna have our test set to validate it.
So we're gonna do this all in one shot, and we're gonna look at that and they're gonna do 200 steps for each validation.
And we'll see what that looks like in just a minute.
Let's go ahead and run our training here.
And we're gonna fit our data.
And as it goes, this says Epic 1 of 25, you start realizing that this is gonna take a while.
On my older computer, it takes about forty-five minutes. I have a dual processor. Yeah, we're processing uh 10,000 photos. That's not a small amount of photographs to process.
So if you're on your laptop, you know which I am, that's gonna take a while. So let's go ahead and uh go get our cup of coffee and a sip and come back and see what this looks like.
So I'm back.
You didn't know I was gone. That was actually uh a lengthy pause there. I made a couple changes, and let's discuss those changes real quick and why I made them.
So the first thing I'm gonna do is I'm gonna go up here and insert a cell above, and let's paste the original code back in there.
And you'll see that the original thing was steps per epic 8,000, 25 epics, and validation steps 2000.
And I changed these to 4,000 epics or 4,000 steps per epic, 10 epics, and uh just 10 validation steps. And this will cause problems if you're doing this as a commercial release.
But for demo purposes, this should work.
And if you remember, our steps per epic, that's how many photos we're gonna process. In fact, let me go ahead and get my drawing pen out.
And uh let's just highlight that right here. Well, we have 8,000 pictures we're going through. So for each epic, I'm gonna change this to 4,000. I'm gonna cut that in half.
So it's gonna randomly pick 4,000 pictures each time it goes through an epic. And the epic is how many processes. So this is 25, and I'm just gonna cut that to 10.
So instead of doing 25 runs through 8,000 photos each, which you can do the math of 25 times 8,000, I'm only gonna do 10 through 4,000.
So I'm gonna run this 40,000 times through the processes.
And the next thing I noticed you'll you'll want to notice is that I also changed the validation step.
And this would cause some major problems in releasing, because I dropped it all the way down to 10.
What the validation step does is it says we have 2,000 photos in our trainings or in our testing set.
And we're gonna use that for validation. Well, I'm only gonna use a random ten of those to validate. So not really the best settings, but let me show you why we did that.
Let's scroll down here just a little bit.
And let's look at the output here and see what that what's going on there.
So I've got my drawing tool back on, and you'll see here it lists a run.
So each time it goes through an epic, it's going to do 4,000 steps. And this is where the 4,000 comes in. So that's where we have. We have epic one of 10, 4,000 steps.
So it's randomly picking half the pictures in the file and going through them. And then we're going to look at this number right here. That is for the whole epic, and that's 2411 seconds.
And if you remember correctly, you divide that by 60, you get minutes. If you divide that by 60, you get hours. Or you can just divide the whole thing by 60 times 60, which is 3600.
If 3600 is an hour, this is roughly 45 minutes right here.
And that's 45 minutes to process half the pictures. So if I was doing all the pictures, we're talking an hour and a half per epic times 36. Or no, 25. They had 25 up above.
25. So that's roughly a couple days.
A couple days of processing. Well, for this demo, we don't want to do that. I don't want to come back the next day. Plus, my computer did a reboot in the middle of the night.
So we look at this and we say, okay, let's we're just testing this out. My computer that I'm running this on is a dual core processor, uh, runs 0.9 gigahertz per second.
For a laptop, you know, it was good about four years ago, but for running something like this it's probably a little slow. So we cut the times down, and the last one was validation.
We're only validating it on a random ten photos. And this comes into effect because you're gonna see down here where we have accuracy, value loss, value accuracy, and loss.
Those are very important numbers to look at.
So the 10 means I'm only validating across ten pictures. That is where here we have value, this is ACC is for accuracy, value loss, we're not gonna worry about that too much, and accuracy.
Now accuracy is while it's running, it's putting these two numbers together. That's what accuracy is. And value accuracy is at the end of the epic. What's our accuracy at the end of the epic?
What is it looking at? In this tutorial, we're not gonna go so deep, but these numbers are really important when you start talking about these two numbers reflect bias.
That is really important.
We'll just put that up there. And bias is a little bit beyond this tutorial, but the short of it is if this accuracy, which is being our validation per step, is going down
and the value accuracy continues to go up, that means there's a bias.
That means I'm memorizing the photos I'm looking at.
I'm not actually looking for what makes a dog a dog, what makes a cat a cat.
I'm just memorizing them. And so the more this discrepancy grows, the bigger the bias is. And that is really the beauty of the caras neural network.
It is a lot of built-in features like this that make that really easy to track. So let's go ahead and take a look at the next set of code.
So here we are into part three.
We're gonna make a new prediction, and so we're gonna bring in a couple tools for that, and then we have to process the image coming in and find out whether it's an actual dog or cat.
We can actually use this to identify it.
And of course, the final step of part three is to print prediction.
We'll go ahead and combine these, and of course you can see me there adding a more sticky nose to my computer screen, hidden behind the screen, and uh you know,
last one was don't forget to feed the cat and the dog.
So let's go ahead and take a look at that and see what that looks like in code and put that in our Jupyter notebook. Alright, and let's paste that in here.
And we'll start by importing NumPy SNP. Numpy is a very common package. I pretty much import it on any Python project I'm working on. Another one I use regularly is pandas.
They're just ways of organizing the data. And then np is usually the standard in most machine learning tools as the return for the data array.
Although, you know, you can use a standard data array from Python. And we have cross, pre-processing, import image.
This should all look familiar because we're gonna take a test image and we're gonna set that equal to in this case cat or dog one, as you can see over here.
And you know what, let me get my drawing tool back on.
So let's take a look at this. We have our test image we're loading, and in here we have test image one, and this one hasn't data hasn't seen this one at all, so this is all new.
Oh, let me shrink the screen down. Let me start that over.
So here we have my test image, and we went ahead and the cross processing has this nice image setup. So we're going to load the image and we're going to alter it to a 64 by 64 print.
So right off the bat we're gonna cross is nice that way, it automatically sets it up for us so we don't have to redo all our images and find a way to reset those.
And then we use all those to set the image to an array. So again, we're all in pre processing the data, just like we pre processed before with our uh test information and our training data.
And then we use the numpy.
Here's our numpy.
That's uh from our um right up here import numpy as in p. Expand the dimensions test image axes equal zero. So it puts it into a single array.
And then finally, all that work, all that pre-processing, and all we do is we run the result.
We click on here and we go result equals classifier predict test image, and then we find out well what is a test image. And let's just take a quick look and just see what that is.
And you can see when I ran it, it comes up dog, and if we look at those images, there it is, cat or dog, image number one.
That looks like a nice floppy-eared lab.
Friendly with his tongue hanging out. It's either that or a very floppy-eared cat. I'm not sure which. But according to our software, it says it's a dog.
And uh we have a second picture over here. Let's just see what happens when we run the second picture. We can go up here and change this uh from dog image one to two.
We'll run that, and it comes down here and says cat. You can see me highlighting it down there as cat. So our process works. We are able to label a dog a dog and a cat a cat just from the pictures.
There we go, cleared my drawing tool. And the last thing I want you to notice, when we come back up here to when I ran it, you'll see that it has an accuracy of one and the value accuracy of one.
Well, the value accuracy is the important one, because the value accuracy is what it actually runs on the test data. Remember I'm only testing it on I'm only validating it on a random ten photos.
And those ten photos just happen to come up one.
Now, when they ran this on the server, it actually came up about 86%.
This is why cutting these numbers down so far for a commercial release is bad.
So you want to make sure you're a little careful of that when you're testing your stuff that you change these numbers back when you run it on a more enterprise computer
other than your old laptop that you're just practicing on or messing with.
And we come down here and again, you know, we had the validation of cat.
And so we have successfully built a neural network that could distinguish between photos of a cat and a dog.
Imagine all the other things you could distinguish. Imagine all the different industries you could dive into with that, just being able to understand those two different sort of pictures.
What about mosquitoes?
Could you find the mosquitoes that bite versus the mosquitoes that are friendly?
It turns out the mosquitoes that bite us are only four percent of the mosquito population, if even that, maybe two percent.
There's all kinds of industries that use this, and there's so many industries that are just now realizing how powerful these tools are.
Just in the photos alone, there is a myriad of industries sprouting up.
And I said it before, I'll say it again. What an exciting time to live in with these tools and that we get to play with. So, key takeaways. Well, we covered what is a neural network.
We use all kinds of processing, the map images on your phone. We've talked about things that a neural network can do.
Translate text, identify faces, all the way to control robots, you know, lots of exciting things. How does a neural network work?
So we discussed that with the different layers, going from the picture to the input layer, to the hidden layers and their weights to the final output layer.
We also talked about how it does the math in computing the output as uh yes or no, categorically true false.
We discussed types of artificial neural networks, a lot of vocabulary there from the feed forward neural network, which is the most commonly used.
That's the one the neural network we used is a feed forward neural network that does backward propagation to train. And there's a lot of other ones out there.
There's the radial biases, the Kohenan self-organizing, recurrent neural network, convolution neural network, modular neural network.
The big one was modular because it incorporates pieces of all the other ones, so that whatever you're working on now is a huge conglomerate of multiple networks. Just all cutting edge.
All of it's new. People even working on it don't even know where it's going. Again, very exciting times. And finally, we dug through my favorite part.
You can see with my uh latte on one side, my old school pens and pencil, and all my sticky notes working away. That's not actually me, by the way. You probably guessed that.
And we walked through and actually did a cat and dog photo, a simple cat and dog photo, and you could see where some of the problems are in processing large amounts of photographs and data,
where that starts to become going from a single machine on my laptop with this, you know.
lower amount of resources all the way to big data.
How if you're processing hundreds and thousands of these photos, this now needs to be set up on an enterprise machine or even on a cluster of computers. Again, significantly past the scope of this.
The neat part about it though is once you write this code, MOSA's code, they now have tools that you can almost take the same ideas, if not the actual code,
and push it right on to a cluster computation.
So really cool times for this. Python. My name is Richard Kirschner with the Simply Learn team. That's www.simplylearn.com. Get certified, get ahead.
Although deep learning has been around for a while, it is just in its infant stages of development as far as exploding on the market.
I mean it is right now they're building robots with it. Deep learning is used to train robots to perform human tasks.
Music composition deep neural nets can be used to produce music by making computers learn the patterns involved in composing music.
Image colorization. Neural network recognizes objects and uses information from the images to color them. Machine translation.
Given a word phrase or a sentence in one language neural networks automatically translate them into another language. Google Translate is one such popular machine translator you may have come across.
And you'll notice in here we didn't show any examples of straight numbers like projective cells in a business, tracking your favorite stock.
You can certainly do those with machine languages but this is the next level.
Save that for your regression models, your linear regression where you're actually processing and crunching just straight numbers.
With machine learning and deep learning we're going to a whole new level as far as what we can figure out on the computer.
What's in it for you?
We're going to cover what is deep learning. We're going to take a look at the biological versus artificial intelligence.
What is neural network activation function in your neural network and the cost function and how do neural networks work?
How do neural networks learn? So there's a little you'll see a switch right there. We just went from how are they working in the math in the background to exactly how are they learning.
We'll be implementing the neural network we'll do a gradient descent deep learning platforms and we'll give an introduction to TensorFlow and implementation in TensorFlow.
That's Google's platform that they open sourced recently and it's probably one of the most cutting edges in deep learning.
And even it is still in the infant stage which is one of the reasons they released it to open source. What is deep learning?
Deep learning is a subfield of machine learning that deals with algorithms inspired by the structure and function of the brain.
And you can see we have a nice picture here we have artificial intelligence which is kind of the big bubble that encompasses all these different things we're talking about.
This is ability of machine to imitate intelligent human behavior. And in there we have machine learning application of AI that allows a system to automatically learn and improve from experience.
And if you looked at any of our other videos you'll know that machine learning covers a lot.
So deep learning is a subcategory of that but don't forget machine learning has all kinds of other tools that people use to do very basic descriptive and predictive
and postscriptive analytics. And then you have deep learning application of machine learning that uses complex algorithms and deep neural nets to train a model.
Let's take a look at the biological neuron versus the artificial neuron. Now remember in the human brain and this is true for most animals there are a lot of different neurons going on.
So this is the very basic one.
I mean there's hundreds of different cells involved.
So when we talk about neural networks this is why I say it's in a very infant stage they're really basing it on just the most basic thing that we're able to figure out
going on in the neural networks. And you can see right here we have dendrites fetch information from an adjacent neurons and pass them on as inputs.
So you have your data coming in and your data going out.
Any computer model should be looking at that what's coming in what's going out. The data is fed as an input to the neuron.
So when we look at the artificial neuron you can see we have our inputs they come in each one is specially weighted into the neuron and then the neuron has an output.
The cell nucleus processes the information received from the dendrites and the neuron processes the information provided as inputs. Axons are the cables over which the information is transmitted.
And the information is transferred over weighted channels. So you can look at that I mentioned weights briefly but to alter the data coming in.
So those weights are what causes different information coming in to be weighted differently and processed differently.
And the synapses receive the information from the axons and transmit it to the adjacent neurons that's in your biological model and then when we look at the artificial neuron
the output is a final value predicted by the artificial neuron.
So as we dig deeper into looking at the theory behind the neural network and we kind of flip back and forth between these because there's two huge aspects of it.
One is from the outside, what are you seeing? And what's going on from the inside so you can find to do what you need to do and give the best results you can. And we start off with uh what do we feed?
We feed an unlabeled image to a machine which identifies it without any human intervention. And so you can see here we have a circle that comes in at 784 pixels, and it comes in by 28 by 28.
And you can see how it colors in the um the circle on there. And we put a triangle in, the triangle in also comes in as 28 by 28, and it has 784 pixels.
So you'll see between these two, both of them are 784 pixels. This machine is intelligent enough to differentiate between the various shapes.
So that's what we want to use our neural network to do, is to say, hey, this is a circle, this is a triangle. That's more of a categorical.
You can also do a regression model where you're actually putting out a float value or a numerical value.
We'll be looking at the truefalse or the categorical model mostly, because that's where you usually start at.
The difference, there is no real difference when you as far as the way the internal functioning goes, when you start flipping between them, other than well, we'll talk about that in just a minute.
So you can actually go between the two quite easily. And the neural network provides this capability. So we're going to use this capability to look between those two.
One of the things I want you to note in here is that we're looking at 784 pixels. We're looking at 784 inputs.
That's very different than stock with a high low or last year's cells based on date, where we're looking at just a couple of numbers and they're very clear their
numbers, they're very clear what they are, which is something you'd put into a machine learning linear regression model.
This is a step up from that in that we're looking at complex patterns and how do you figure those complex patterns out.
So a neural network is a system modeled on the human brain.
And we looked at that comparing the two, let's go ahead and look deeper into the neural network itself. We have our inputs coming in.
So the inputs are fed to a neuron that processes the data and gives us an output.
Input and output. This is the most basic structure of a neural network known as a perceptron.
So if you see the term perceptron, that's what we're talking about. We're talking about this single node that has inputs and an output. However, neural networks are usually much more complex.
Let's start with visualizing a neural network as a black box. And I always love that symbol. It's a black box. It's kind of magical. We have our inputs coming in and we want certain outputs.
The box takes inputs, processes them, and gives an output.
Let's have a look at what happens within this box.
You can see me there in my uh secret agent getup. I got my hidden hood and everything. I guess I'm part of the uh black skull or something like that group.
Uh so let's take a look at what happens within this magic box.
And remember we're skipping back and forth between the theory of what's going on in the box, which you have to know how to fine-tune and how to build, versus looking at it from the outside.
We're programming this box and we have an input and an output to the box as a whole. Within the box exists a network that is a core of deep learning.
And you can see here we're showing uh one layer, and we have our grid coming in.
The network consists of layers of neurons.
Each neuron is associated with a number called the bias. And you can think of the bias uh if you overly simplify this and we're doing a linear regression model.
This is your y-intercept in your Euclidean geometry. You have to have something that offsets it, and so you always have a bias in these cells.
Neurons of each layer transmit information to neurons of the next layer over channels. And so you can see each of our layers going through from left to right.
These channels are associated with numbers called weights.
These weights, along with the biases, determine the information that is passed over from the neuron to neuron.
So just like the bias is your y-intercept in Euclidean geometry, you could look at the an in one weight. Remember this is very complicated, so we're not looking at just one weight.
You can look at the weight as your slope of the line. Or if you're doing x equals uh my plus c, it'd be the m value. Neurons of each layer transmit information to neurons of the next layer.
And you can see here is a light up going across into the final layer, and then to the output.
And in this case, the output is gonna be either uh a square in this one, or it might light up the other one, which is a circle. The output layer emits a predicted output.
So in this case we're looking at a classification, uh true false. Is it a circle? Is it a triangle? Is it a square?
Let's now go deeper what happens within the neuron.
So we're gonna dig deeper and start getting a little bit closer to some of the math. Don't worry, you don't have to be a calculus expert or know your differential equations.
Even though this is one giant differential equation, you don't need to understand those to understand what's going on.
Within each neuron, the following operations are performed.
The product of each input and the weight of the channel it's passed over is found.
This is simply addition. We're going to sum up the weight times the output from the previous channel, and plus the bias. Sum of the weighted products is computed. This is called the weighted sum.
Bias unique to the neuron is added to the weighted sum. The final sum is then subjected to the particular function. And we'll discuss those that particular function.
That part is really important because those functions have a huge impact on how well your model performs under different conditions. The final sum is then subjected to a particular function.
This is the activation function. So if you ever hear the term activation function, that's what we're talking about. What activates this cell and what doesn't?
As we dig deeper into activation function, an activation function takes the weighted sum of the input as its input, adds a bias, and provides an output.
And a lot of times you'll actually see one formula for the sum of the weight the weighted sum and the bias. You'll just see that as a single line of everything added together.
And here we've broken it apart because it makes it clear that this bias is not computed the same as the weighted sums. Here are the most popular types of activation function.
And I always find these interesting because at one point I was sitting at a table with a gentleman who was finishing his PhD.
He was in his last year, and he said he went through all this stuff and he ended up just trying the four different activation functions on this particular problem he was working on.
So knowing the math behind it doesn't necessarily mean you're going to know it right away.
So even somebody who might have a PhD and be doing the calculations on this comes back out of it and ends up just trying the different uh activation functions to see what's going to make a difference.
And a lot of times that's a final step.
That's the kind of thing where you built your whole model, you've come back, and you're like, wait a minute, can I do a better deal with a sigmoid function or the threshold or the rectifier?
Knowing what they're doing is important, so you can explain it to somebody else. And again, you probably do this on a small set of data.
If you're working with big data, uh you don't want to take down the full server farm just to test out your three different series.
You take a small portion of that data, test it, and then you put it through to the big data.
So let's take a look at this. We have the sigmoid function, and it's used for models where we have to predict the probability as an output. It exists between zero and one.
And you'll see that's true of all of our activation functions we're working with. Either the cell's on or off, it's true or false.
And there might be a little variation in there, which as an output could be used to compute uncertainty in your solution.
So if you're getting a 0.7 with this activation function, it might be, well, I'm not sure if that's really a square, or I'm not sure that's really a triangle.
And that might be a flag for it to be looked at by a human observer, at least in today's models where we're at right now.
And you can see here where we have the formula simply equals 1 over 1 plus e to the minus x, where x is your value coming in,
and it's gonna give you a result that looks very similar to the graph on there, which is somewhere between 0 and 1.
Um and right in the middle, you can see that there's a huge uh kind of you can go through all the different values and uncertainties involved.
So the sigmoid function is probably the default on most of them.
Uh the next one is the threshold function. It is a threshold-based activation function. If x value is greater than a certain value, the function is activated and fired, else not.
Pretty straightforward. Yes, no, true, false. Um I don't want to test for improbabilities, I just want a straight answer.
I don't want to know if there's a partial value on there. It either is true or it's false. And the rectifier function, it is the most widely used activation function. I would debate that.
Um rectifier is pretty common one, although I see that the sigmoid function is used to be the basic one, but it's up there.
The rectifier function is very commonly used because the output of x if x is positive and zero otherwise.
And you can see here again, just like um uh it's it's either you kind of get a value going up there. So max of x of zero. So it's you it's again it's like the threshold function. Yes, no, true, false.
Uh it's either zero or it's uh some kind of progressive value. And then we have the rectifier function.
I would argue with this, because the sigmoid function used to be the most common one, but with the rectifier function,
uh it now says it is the most commonly used or widely used activation function and gives an output of x if x is positive and zero otherwise.
This is kind of nice because it now says absolutely not or it gives you a value of probability. Now when I say a value of probability, be very careful there.
I'm not saying that it's gonna tell you this is a 75% chance of being a circle.
I'm gonna tell you that it says, hey, if this says point one, it probably needs to be looked at, or point two, or point three. It's gonna depend on your data as to what that value means.
In general, that just means it's flagging it that if it's not a one, then chances are it needs to be looked at by a person and re-evaluated. And there's a hyperbolic tangent function.
This function is similar to sigmoid function, is bound to a range of minus one to one. So you can see there's our one minus e to the minus two x and one plus over one plus e to the minus two x.
Again, it's very similar to the sigmoid function. The bonus of the uh hyperbolic function is you have that variable coming through the middle.
So again, you can look at it and you have a little bit more weight as far as you can process that down the line.
That's a little bit more advanced than than what we're looking at right now, and a lot of times it's not even necessary in a lot of our different uh uses for these activation functions.
Now we looked at activation functions, and I kind of said those are a little bit like a black box, because even if you know all the math,
a lot of times you end up just playing with them to find out what works.
and it also depends on what model you're working with, whether you need a flat yes, no, true, false, or you need to have something in the middle that says, "Hey.
this isn't quite a one .". you might need to process this with the human intervention. And you could look at that uh one example would be self-driving cars.
You don't want a car to be yes, no, I'm gonna go through the the light. You want it to be like, okay, if it's uh almost yes, maybe we stop and have human intervention so we don't get an accident.
Cost function is something you can really see and measure and is very important.
The cost value is the difference between the neural net's predicted output and the actual output from a set of labeled training data.
So we have our group of data that's a square circle, and since we're looking at geometrical shapes, we've had somebody already labeled that data.
They've already said this is a triangle, this is a square.
And so if this is coming up and it's giving us and it's saying a square is a triangle, and it's saying a triangle is a circle, the output is wrong.
And so that output can then be measured in the versus the actual output, and that's the cost. Uh, you might also hear this as error, because that's the error value being returned. How far off is it?
And what we're looking for is the least cost or the least error value, and it's obtained by making adjustments to the weights and biases iteratively throughout the training process.
And this this is called back propagation. And we're going to look in that a little deeper as we look into an example.
It's really hard to see when you're just looking at arrows without actual numbers and where that flow is coming from. But you can look at this as here's our inputs.
They put out a prediction, the prediction comes out and says, hey, we've already labeled this data because we're in training mode and the training data is off. This is the cost.
Can we send that error or that cost back and adjust those weights? And we do it in very small increments across large amounts of data so that those weights minimize that cost or that error.
But what happens within these neurons? So let's look at a little example of this. Kind of helps if you have some kind of visual.
Let's build a neural network that predicts bike prices based on a few of its features. And we'll see here we have our CC, our mileage, and our ABS, and these are our three input layers.
And then we have the bike price and the output layer. Now it doesn't do us very good to just uh Pump it in from the beginning and pump it out.
And to be honest, I would use a machine learning linear regression model on this, since these are just straight numbers.
But because we want a simple example, we're going to put this through and show you as a neural network what that looks like. And we've got to put a hidden layer in there.
The hidden layer helps in improving the output accuracy. And you could look at this as a bunch of ORs.
So it might say, hey, when we compare these three values on the first hidden layer neuron, we're looking at one set of features. And then we might weight them in the second one.
So these are a bunch of different ores, kind of how the math comes out and behind the scenes. And then they go out, of course, to the bike price or the output layer.
And each of the connections have a weight assigned with it.
And you'll see here we have a mileage CC with the weight one and weight two going into our first neuron. And you'd also have your ABS going in there.
And so X1 times weight one plus X2 times weight two plus the bias of one. And step two is our activation, the activation function coming in there. When does this fire?
And the neuron takes a subset of the inputs and processes it.
And then we go through, we do that with the second hidden layer neuron and the third one and so on. So you process each layer in order going forward.
Now, when I told you this is in its infant stage, they now have neurons that fire into the same layer or back a layer, so that you now have a time series,
and there's all kinds of wild things that they're experimenting with on these layers. This basic setup has been around since the mid-90s.
It's only now because of our technology that it's open to almost everybody to play with it. And that's why I say this is in an infant stage in development.
Is this basic math is here, but what we can do with it is amazing, and what they're actually doing with all these different things is amazing.
And so we're just at the beginning of how to use all these different tools in our deep learning and our neural networks.
And so once we have our hidden layer computed, the information reaching the neurons in the hidden layer is subjected to the respective activation function.
And so each one of these fires an activation output, uh, and then those are each weighted to the final output layer.
So the processed information is now sent to the output layer, once again over weighted channels.
And you could look at this as each one of these is um I always look at this as like a group of people.
They're all looking at the bulletin board, and the first person says, this is what I project sells for the company, and the second person and the third and so on,
and then their perspectives are weighted based on their expertise.
So your accountant might have a very high weight where the um maybe your janitor has a very low weight because their expertise is not in accounting. And then that goes into the output layer.
And once in the output layer, it goes uh the output, which is the predicted value, is compared against the original value.
So now we have our output layer, and since we have like already a list of uh bikes with their the different setups and what their value is, we can now generate an error from this.
The cost function determines the error in prediction and reports it back to the neural network.
So this is the cost, this is how far off it is, this is your error coming back. And as you can see, this is uh back propagation going on.
So now our error is going in reverse because we know we're not completely correct on this particular channel.
The weights are adjusted in order to reduce the error. So each time we go back, we are changing those weights to reduce that error, and we change them in small increments.
You don't want to fit one input. Remember, you might have a data pool with a terabyte of data.
You don't want to solve for the first set of data that comes in, and that'd be the main solution because everything else will be off. This is going to confuse you.
That's also called a bias. So we have the bias in the cell where we're adding a value, the kind of like the y intercept, and we have a bias of the whole.
Neural network, which means that it's weighted towards one set of answers. So we want to make small changes in these weights so we don't create a bias.
And the weights are adjusted in order to reduce the error or the cost. The network is now trained using the new weights.
Once again, the cost is determined and back propagation is continued until the cost cannot be reduced any further. So let's go ahead and plug in values and see how our neural network works.
So here we come in here, and initially our channels are assigned with random weights.
This is important because if you assign them all with the same weight, you might be able to reproduce it, but it turns out that if I put all my weights as one or all my weights as zero,
it takes longer to train. Where if you have random weights, they already have like a little bit of adjustment and ores built in, and that will give us a better answer and train faster.
Our first neuron takes a value of mileage and CC as inputs. So here comes our computation, whatever those inputs are, and we do that again with the second neuron with those values coming in.
You can see here we have weight three and so on, and then our third neuron coming down, and of course our fourth neuron. So we're adding all these different values coming in here in our hidden layer.
The process value from each neuron is sent to the output layer over weighted channels. So again, here's our weights coming in, and we have n1, n2, n3, and n4.
Once again, the values are subjected to the activation function, and a single value is emitted as the output.
On comparing the predicted value to the actual value, we clearly see that our network requires training.
So here we have it that our bike price uh we put out we thought it was worth uh 2,000 on our random weights, and the bike actually was 4,000 on there.
Guessing that's not US dollars, because that'd be a very expensive bike, but maybe it is. There's some $2,000, $4,000 bikes out there. The cost function is calculated and back propagation takes place.
And this is pretty simple. You can look at that as our um we're subtracting one value from the other, we square it, and then we take half of that.
And that is propagated back up, and each layer generates its own errors. Let's go back one because you have your predicted y and your actual y.
That goes back to the first layer. And then based on the value of the cost function, certain weights are changed.
So when we look at the next layer, that error is not the original uh 4000 minus two thousand squared divided by two. This error is based on the error of each cell generated.
How far off is that cell as far as its weights? We're not going to show you, it's actually a very complicated differential equation, and you can probably write it out if you wanted to.
You just write out each formula that goes into the next level and you add them all together, and you can write it out all the way through. Computers make it so you don't have to.
And our neural network is considered trained when the value for the cost function is minimum. So when we get our error way down or as low as we can, that's when our neural network is trained.
And they're, I mean, just recently they've come up with all kinds of different means for measuring that particular value.
A little bit beyond the scope of today's neural network, but you can actually you can actually see it, you know, how far do you do this until the neural network doesn't need to be trained anymore?
And you can overtrain a neural network. Now the tools that we're looking at automatically let you know when to stop, which is really nice.
And that is just, like I said, we're at the beginning stages in neural networks, and it's just really cool what they can do now and how much of it's automated
and how much of it is experimental right now.
Let's take a look at gradient descent. But what approach do we take to minimize the cost function?
So here we have uh nice error thing coming in. This is our cost or our error. Uh let's start with plotting the cost function against the predicted value.
And so you can see they fed in multiple y's and these are the errors coming in and the cost of each of these inputs and changes going on.
Note we start at a random point on the curve.
So usually you put in, you know, you pick up your data and you randomly pick where to start in your data.
A lot of times you just run it from the beginning, because you're going through so much data, it's not that big of a deal, but you start with one point going in.
So your forward propagation goes through, you're gonna go ahead and find your cost or your error. It points out on the curve, and you can see how we're plotting it right here.
Since the gradient at this point is positive, we may move right. So we're gonna move a little bit to the right on here. And this time the gradient is negative, we move a little bit to the left.
Eventually we try out the point where the gradient is zero. This is the least value of cost. Function.
You have to be a little careful with this because this particular I mean they make it look nice and simple in this graph. Sometimes these curves look like stair steps.
And so there is global minimums, and then there is local. There might be a local point where the gradient is zero, but it's not the global one.
So it might be way off to the left where it just happens to step down a little bit and you think you're in the right gradient.
And with that we have all the right weights, and we can say our network is trained.
So here we have just some major, these are some of the big names out there right now in development for deep learning platforms. TensorFlow, which we'll actually do an example in in a minute.
Deep Learning4J, which is in the Java platform.
So if you're a Java programmer, uh by the way, as TensorFlow is accessed, most people are using Python to access it, but it is a system that's kind of separate from a lot of the programming languages,
which makes it a lot more flexible as far as used. Deep Learning4j is Java based. And then Cross is just exploding right now. And this is interesting.
It actually can sit on top of TensorFlow and it can also do its own thing.
So if you're studying deep learning or getting into it, you'll want to know the basics of TensorFlow, but you also are going to want to know the upper level of Karas sitting on top of TensorFlow.
We're just looking at TensorFlow today, though, in our example. And there's also Torch on there. There's a bunch more that we didn't list on here.
Even SKLearn or the side package in Python has a neural network you can program, a very basic one.
And it is the same basic one that you could do in TensorFlow if you stripped everything out of it. And then TensorFlow has a lot of tools they've added in, and so has Karas.
But we're gonna be looking specifically at TensorFlow in our example. And TensorFlow is an open source tool used to define and run computations on what they call tensors. Very common language now.
So you more and more we see the term tensor as being a standard in the uh deep learning language. And this was originally developed by Google. So let's dig a little bit bigger in there.
What are tensors? Tensors are just another name for arrays. So a tensor of dimension five. You can see here we have A, B, K, M, Q, whatever. So it's an array coming in.
And the tensor of dimension five, four, more like a picture.
Very common to see that in a picture. You can also see a tensor even more detailed in a picture as we go to the next one. Tensor of Dimension 333. This is 3D space.
You might have a picture that also has colors, that might be the third dimension. You might have four dimensions because you have both your grid and your different color channels and your Z plot.
You can see where you can now process a very high-level set of data coming in, whether it's as an image or features. They could be features that have nothing to do with images.
So there's a lot of stuff you can do now with the tensors coming in.
This is where the term TensorFlow comes from.
So we have um right now that TensorFlow is the most popular library in deep learning. And I did mention Karas now works with TensorFlow, so there's a lot of stuff you can do between the two.
Uh, it's an open source software library developed by Google. Uh so they hit a roadblock and they realized, hey, this is an infant stage technology.
You know, we thought it was going to be the next greatest thing and we were going to have a hole on it, but it's really infant as far as how it's applied and what we can do with it.
Let's open source it so everybody can work on it. Uh let's take it to the next level. And that's really what open source does to a lot of these uh packages when they release them.
And you can run on either a CPU or a GPU.
So when we look at the details, if you have your graphic processing units, um what's nice about those is they run a lot faster.
The downside is you have to play with them a little bit to get them up and running, and it's a hardware upgrade.
When we run it, I'll be running it in the CPU mode. I have played with it in my GPU on my personal computer.
You know, it does increase the processing, uh, but I did run into some version problems with my Python and stuff like that.
And when I did finally work it out, I went back to the CPU because it didn't increase my speed enough for what I was working on.
But in a larger group, you might be able to put that on. If you're working with a larger stack of computers, you might want to run it in the GPU.
You can create a data flow graphs that have nodes and edges. So there's our edges coming in. We didn't talk about edges, but that's a very up and coming way of looking at.
Your analytical data is how do different nodes connect? What do those edges look like in between them? And it's used for machine learning applications such as neural networks.
It is mostly a neural network, but they have all kinds of tools which sit on top of our basic neural network. They have new stuff evolving into the TensorFlow library.
So it's very much uh just exploding.
Great time to jump into TensorFlow because there's all kinds of cool things we're doing with it and all kinds of cool applications you can now use uh TensorFlow for.
So let's take a look at uh implementation in TensorFlow. And we're going to build a neural network to identify handwritten digits using the uh uh MNIST database or the MNIST database.
And that stands for Modified National Institute of Standards and Technology Database.
It has a collection of 70,000 handwritten digits, and the digit labels identify each of the digits from zero to nine.
This is a cool example because it's simple enough that you could actually run this through some basic machine learning categorizing algorithms and train them,
and you'll get about the same answer because again it's it's simple grid.
The digits on the grid don't have a huge amount of variation like you would say an automated driving car looking at the environment.
So you could still do this with a lot of your um different linear models and stuff like that. You can solve this, and you'll get about the same answer.
When I ran a comparison between TensorFlow and between some basic uh regression models or category models in machine learning, they came up pretty even as far as their output.
Uh so this is kind of where we start to see the complexity of something coming in, uh, in this case a tensor, you know, or a grid of uh information,
where the deep learning model does as good as the regular models.
And when you get past this kind of complexity in features, suddenly the neural networks come up with better answers, better solutions, and a better build.
And that's why there's such a move into neural networks, is we live in a complicated world, and it's just really cool we can do with this.
So the handwritten digits from the um NIST database, they come in, the data set is used to train the machine, a new image of a digit is fed,
and the digit is identified. Um if you've looked at any of our other machine learning tools where we're doing training uh where we train our uh model to fit and then you test it out,
this will look pretty familiar. Uh and there is some tools out there for say untrained categorizing, uh, where it's just looking for features that fit together.
So there are tools that don't need that training. But this is where uh when we're talking about neural networks, we do need to train them, and this is what we're looking at.
So for this, I'm gonna use the Anaconda Navigator just because it's a very nice visual tool.
You might be in PyCharm or one of your other IDEs for editing Python, because we are looking at Python TensorFlow.
And under Anaconda, we have the notebook, which is something we use pretty regularly, and they have the Jupyter Lab. The Jupyter Lab is the Jupyter Notebook, but with tabs and a few new features.
So we'll be using the Jupyter Lab today. And under the environment, you'll want to go ahead and and uh if you haven't yet, uh you'll see that I have a number of different setups in here.
Right now I have the Python version 3.6 and the TensorFlow. In this case I have TensorFlow 1.12. If we scroll down, you can see that. Uh here we go, TensorFlow and it's version 1.12.
And uh in here, if you haven't yet, you'll need to install those and go in and just open our terminal.
And uh if you've never used the Anaconda or if you're in your other thing, you might have something simple like pip. Conda is what I use for my install, and you can simply do conda install tensorflow.
And that should bring in the most current version.
Now, when I installed this a few months ago, Python version, I'm not gonna run this because I already have it installed on here, Python version 3.7,
the newest one out, still had a couple glitches with the TensorFlow. I believe they've fixed it as of writing of this, but um, I'm gonna stick with 3.6 just so I don't get any surprises on there.
So this is Python version 3.6 with TensorFlow 1.12 on here.
And if you haven't installed it yet, uh you also want to install Numpy for this example, that's NumbersPython or uh NUMPY at you can just simply run an install on there.
Keep in mind if you're in Anaconda uh and you've created one of these environments specific to this, keep with conda if you're gonna use conda. If you're gonna use pip, keep with pip.
Don't install one package with pip and one under conda because that's how they track those version numbers and how they fit together, and you can end up with a problem.
They don't pip doesn't see conda and vice versa.
Uh so just keep that in mind when you're running your installs. We'll go ahead and open up JupyterLab and we're gonna launch that.
So here's my Jupyter Lab. One of the really cool features of JupyterLab is you have tabs now, so you can open up multiple uh notebooks.
This is nice because I have my notes I'm working on and then our actual window we're looking in.
And we'll go ahead and zoom in a little bit here. There we go. So you have a nice, uh hopefully easy to see fonts. And then we'll go ahead and do a simple or get our imports out of the way.
Um and so we're gonna import our TensorFlow as TF. Uh that's pretty much a standard for TensorFlow, NumPy, our numbers Python as PY, and we'll import our matplotlibrary as
PLT. Again, these are very common. So if you see TF or PY or PLT, this is the standard that most people use.
Do you have to? No.
You could just do import numpy instead of doing as py. And then from tensorflow dot examples dot tutorials, this is always nice because they actually include
data set we're going to play with. So we're going to import input data. So there's our data coming in. That's all we're doing is uh telling it this is where it's coming from.
And if we're gonna tell where it's coming from, we need to go ahead and create a variable with that information in it. And we'll just call this uh MNIST NIST or minst.
You know, I don't really know how they pronounce that. I should probably look that up. It's a very common data set to use. And there's our input data, and we're gonna read data sets.
And this is um, if you look at this, we imported input data from our TensorFlow, and so this is a TensorFlow read statement for their tutorials.
So this isn't like some special Python setup, this is just their setup. It makes it easy to pull it in. So once we get into their data sets, we need to go ahead and tell it what kind of data set.
And again, this is what we brought in, but it's gonna be the NINST data. And this part is very important. One hot
equals true.
This means that instead of importing a value from zero to nine, we evaluate the data set, it's gonna bring it in as one
hot. Whenever you see one hot encoder, we're flattening that out and we have true false for zero, true false for one, true false for two.
So our output, if you remember from our output uh from the slide we did earlier, uh in this case I grabbed the one for bike price, doesn't really matter which one we use. This has one output.
So we have our bike price. On this, we're gonna have instead of one output, we're gonna have ten outputs representing each of the digits in there. And this code really isn't gonna show us anything.
It's good to see what we're actually looking at. So um let's go ahead and do a figure ax equals, go into our plot library, subplots, ten, comma, ten,
and that is, if you remember we talked about tensor, tensor being data coming in. This is a ten by ten grid or a hundred pixels on there.
And if we're gonna display it, uh let's go do k zero for i in range ten, just a simple loop through on the data. Let's do what is it, uh, for j in range ten. So I actually misquoted that.
10 uh 10 by 10 is not the actual size of the pixels. Uh the actual pixels are gonna be uh when we look at the shapes, and we'll get into that in just a second here.
We'll take a quick look at uh shape on there. Uh turns out they're uh what are they are I believe twenty eight by twenty-eight.
Uh so let's take a look at that. And we're just gonna plot these.
What are we looking at? What are we working with?
As a data scientist, you should always be looking back at your data and seeing what it looks like and get that human perspective because you just never know.
You know, the the computer might put something out that looks makes no sense, and uh at that point you want to go back and reevaluate what you did. Uh so we're gonna go ahead and plot.
We're gonna plot ten digit, you know, ten of the digits by ten of the digits, and here's our ax. We'll create the IJ on our subplots, and we're gonna do an image show.
We're gonna look at the training image for images of K.
And then we want to reshape this. We're going to reshape this. And we're going to reshape this 28 by 28.
That's how I knew I had it wrong, is because I looked down my notes and I was like, oh no, that says 28, it's not 10 by 10.
And I should know that already because I've done enough messing with this data set that I should remember. But it's 28 by 28. And the aspect we're going to do is auto.
And this is all, if you look at this, here's our variable NIST. The NIST is coming from dataset. So this is all part of the TF TensorFlow learning or examples tutorial in there.
And then we'll go ahead and do uh K plus equals one. So we just keep paging through our different um images. And let's see what that looks like. Let's go ahead and do a plot show.
Uh and we'll go ahead and run this so we can take a look and see what we have here.
And so we have a nice plot here, and you can just see that we have uh some random numbers showing up in each one of these little subplots.
If you're wanting a copy of this code, put a note down in the YouTube video and let us know, or come visit us at www.simplylearn.com
and we'll send you out a copy of what we're working on and get a copy of that for your uh own setup. Uh so now we've taken a look, we can just see we have our here's our pictures that are coming on.
We've plotted them so we have an idea of what we're looking at. Let's go ahead and uh print, let's look at the shape of the features.
Uh so when we have this, we have our uh NIST train images, and we'll do the shape on there. Let's take a look and just see what we're looking at uh as far as uh our count and everything.
And so you can see here we have uh 55,000, that's basically how many images we have, and this by 784.
And in this data set, there's also our labels. So let's take a look at that. We have our NIST train labels shape. Let's take a look and see what that looks like.
Uh and there we have 10 because there's 10 digits. So we brought in that's our output we're looking at.
And so we have there we go, 55,000, they match, they should match, because you should have equal numbers in both of those. You know, here's our data in and here's our answer.
If you remember, this is uh a bunch of zeros and with one each each one will be zero, zero, zero, one would be what, letter four or something like that.
So let's take a look at what our one hot encoding did for the first observation. And this is when we're exploring data, you really want to dig in there and just see what the heck am I looking at.
So we're gonna look at the labels, and this would be the first label that comes up. And we'll go ahead and run this.
And we look at that, you can see this is what I'm talking about. Zero, zero, our one is zero, two is zero, three is zero, four is zero, five is zero, six is zero, seven equals one.
So our very first label is a seven, but our very first label comes up that it's a seven.
And so we don't have like zero through nine, we have a bunch of zeros and just the one to mark it as a seven on here.
So now we've kind of left a quick look at the data, and in here you might ask some questions like what is seven eighty-four? 24 times 24.
Remember that's the size of our grid on there, or our tensor coming in. So 784 is a setup on there. And we've gone through all this viewing the data.
We'll go ahead and start looking at our tensor flow. So let's take our X variable. This is going to be our training set. We'll do a placeholder, and then we're gonna have these come in as float.
Now, if I remember correctly, they're actually, you know, uh zero or one for the values, because they're either uh but we have them coming in as a float value,
and we have a little bit of a shape coming in here, and there's our 784. Uh so we let it know that this is what's what our input is for our tensor flow. And this is our training set.
So we'll just put a label on there to help us uh track that train set, and then w. And with W we'll go ahead and do TF variables, and we'll do this as uh zeros.
Variables, TF zeros, and we'll set this as 784 by 10, 10 being the output, 784 being our number of uh variables in,
and this is our weights. Remember we have a bias in there too. And I'll go back over this in just a second as we see how that fits together in our tensor flow.
And we'll do this one um with our variables. Again, we have ten, so we're gonna do the bias. We do it the same kind of format and setup on here, and so we'll do that as TF0s of ten.
So we'll just create an array of 10 there, and this is our bias.
So with these three lines, um, and there's actually they're coming out with the eager execution, which would bypass some of what we're doing.
But this is important to understand is the first thing you have to do with TensorFlow is we have to allocate a space for the variables.
And our TF placeholder and our TF variable with our weights and our biases, this actually hasn't done anything yet. So all it is is placeholders, that's why it's okay to use zeros.
Um you could have just as easily used ones or anything else and it wouldn't matter. The next stage is to go ahead and set up some of the functions going on.
But before we do that, just note that this hasn't done anything. Even if I execute it, all it's done is created placeholders until we do the final initialization.
And so we need to go ahead and set up we'll do y equals tf.nn.softmax. And the code for this is tf.matmole xw plus b. And this is our uh sum.
Let's just put a note here so we can keep track of what's going on. We're finding weighted sum of inputs plus the bias. Uh so there's our plus b the bias.
And then we need to go ahead, keep um, let's do y underscore, and again another placeholder. And this one we'll set uh it's actually we'll put in as tf placeholder on here. Tf placeholder float non10.
There's our uh one hot encoder going on there. So our 10 values coming out. And we'll do a cross entropy on here. And this is gonna be minus tf reduce sum. And we'll do y.
Here's our y underscore, which is remember we have your y output and your actual output. Uh so this will be our y underscore times the tf log of y.
And then finally, um before we do the actual initialization of all our variables, we'll set up our train step. This equals our gradient descent optimizer. Very important.
Remember we looked at that chart on our um uh slides, and so we've set up all these formulas, and here's our gradient descent optimizer, and as it keeps looking, it keeps looking for that zero value.
That's what we're doing with that particular formula.
So let's take a look and see what we're doing here. We just put together all of our pieces for tensor flow. And you know, the devil's in the um details.
We have here our training set coming in, we have to put a placeholder on there, we have our uh variables with their weights, we have our biases coming out, and then we put in our uh the weighted
sum.
So here's uh summising our summation here. Then we have our uh y variable output. So there's our y um how it works, and then of course the actual um output on there.
And then we have our cross entropy coming in, and that's our minus tf dot reduce sum, the y times the tf log of y.
And then the training step, gradient descent optimizer.
And we're using a 0.01 in this, and we're gonna minimize cross entropy. So we're gonna let it do all the work.
So once we've set up all of these different layers, we've allocated for them, we need to go ahead and initialize them. So we're gonna do an init tf initialize, and it's gonna be all variables.
Uh, one of the cool things is they're in the process of doing away with this. So all these steps would be bundled into one instead of having to add placeholders.
You initialize them in the same process going on. And then finally, everything in TensorFlow is based on your session.
Now, this is changing that there's other options to be able to run this, but we want to go ahead and do uh session.
There's our TF, there's a TF session, and then we want to go ahead and do session run. And what are we gonna run? Well, we did initialization of all our variables.
Uh so this is what we're running, and this is where actually once we do this, we actually create our TensorFlow object. So this whole piece of code right here is our TensorFlow object.
We have our input coming in with our weighted variables coming in, our softmax for our metmal going out. How does it add it together for our y value? Uh and then we have the actual.
Uh float value coming out, checking on our um all the way down. So you can see all the different stages going through that we're setting up.
Um and this is one of the reasons that a lot of people like TensorFlow is because you can designate all these different pieces one step at a time.
This is also one of the reasons people don't like TensorFlow, is because you have to designate all the different layers coming down.
And there's a lot of steps being made right now to minimize this, to make it either easier to uh automate it or to allow you to do more complicated things.
And all those steps are still at play, so it's worth looking into the more advanced version of what's going on with Karas on top of TensorFlow.
It's also important to understand what's going on at these individual levels if you're gonna play with them.
It's important to understand, hey, what's going on with the um uh finding the weighted sum of the inputs plus the bias, because there's other ways to do that.
There's all kinds of other tools in there now. But this is the basic setup that you want to do on a TensorFlow coming in. And we want to go ahead and just run and init our TensorFlow.
So let's go ahead and do that. Let's run this. We do get a warning here because uh there's a move to use global variables. This is one of the changes they're making.
But it does as far as this example, it's not gonna make a difference because we're doing once we initialize it.
This is initializing our variables, and again, these are only placeholders up here until we initialize them.
And I would highly suggest put a note down there or or go over to simply learn.com and let them know and have them uh email you a copy of the code so you can actually play with this code right here.
Because this is the body of what's going on in TensorFlow. This is the build in neural networks.
And then once we've done that, now comes kind of the fun part is we need to go ahead and train it.
Uh so we've created our TensorFlow.
We've created our uh network. And now we need to go ahead and train it.
Uh so let's put together that training code and let's just do uh for i in range uh 1000, 0 to 1000.
So we're just gonna look at uh the first 1000 in our training. And the way we pull that data from our mints train, next batch of 100.
Uh so you look at this, we're gonna be doing groups of 100, and then there's gonna go through a thousand of them.
This is very important that TensorFlow builds this in. This is one of the downsides of doing sklearn or one of the older packages, is they don't let you batch groups in.
Uh they wanted to have it all up front, and then you have to build your own batch programs right now. Uh, this lets us go ahead and do that, and you can see here we have batch x of s, batch y of s.
So there's our x and our y. You can look at this as our training of x and our train of y or the data in and the answer in. Uh and then we simply do our session run.
Uh so here's our session that we've created. We're gonna run it, and we want to do the train step.
Remember, we initialized our train step up here and our TF, and so there's our train step feed, it's a dictionary. Dictionary coming in, which we're gonna create right here.
Uh is X is our batch, X of our sample, comma, and our Y underscore is gonna be our batch of our Y
sample. Uh and so this goes through and we've now hit the run button and we've trained our session. We've trained this setup on here.
And once we've trained it, then we need to go ahead and find out how good our accuracy was and actually start running some predictions through there.
Uh so we'll go ahead and create a correct prediction.
And this is where our tf.equal, we'll use our argmax y of one and tf argmax of y of underscore of one to help us get the correct predictions on there.
And then we want to use that to feed into an accuracy.
And so our accuracy is gonna be tf reduce uh mean. And we'll take that and we'll do um a cast. And this is the correct prediction that we're sending in there.
Let's go ahead and print this out so we can see where we're looking at. So what are we printing out? Uh we need to do a session around. This session around is going to be on the accuracy.
Where did accuracy come from? This is our we're casting our TF on there with the correct predictions on that. So here's our accuracy.
This is going to be our
images.
There is going to be our
labels. Let me just double check and make sure I have it typed in there correctly. There we go. And let's go ahead and run that and see what comes up.
And we end up with a point nine one six five for our accuracy. Which means our trained neural network does a pretty good job letting us know what these different symbols are.
I'm guessing that a seven and a three and a four, uh something that is human we kind of take for granted. I even have trouble reading that symbol.
So I don't know if I would be able to like the first one. I would sit there for a long time figuring out that's a seven versus a two. That could have easily been a two to me.
We can now create this nice neural network that does all kinds of cool things.
Do you know, friends, that according to the lending statistics, the demand for AI and ML specialist is projected to surge by 40% between 2023 to
2027?
And on an average, an ML engineer is expected to earn around $133 and $336 per year.
So if you are an aspiring ML engineer and thinking about what innovative projects you can show in your portfolio, then your wait is over.
Because in this video, I'll be covering eight amazing ML projects that you can showcase in your resume.
So, guys, let's start first with a beginner level project.
And the first project that we are going to encounter is home value prediction.
So, guys, this project aims to develop a predictive model to estimate the value of residential properties.
The model will analyze various features such as location, square, footage, number of bedrooms and bathrooms, age of the property,
and other relevant factors.
By leveraging historical property data, the model will be able to provide accurate home value predictions, which can be useful for real estate agents,
buyers, and sellers.
So, guys, the programming language that we are going to use all over here will be Python, and machine learning libraries that we will be using will be ScikitLearn, TensorFlow,
Kiras, and for data handling libraries we have Pandas, NumPy, and for visualization, we have to use Matplotlab and CBON.
Now, what will be the approach for this one, guys?
So, guys, the first one that we have a data collection.
So, here, what is going to happen, guys? So, first you have to collect the historical property data from the sources like Zillow Retailer.com.
You can also get database from the public real estate databases like Kaggle datasets where you have Zillow home value prediction.
Ensure that the dataset includes features like location, where you have latitude-longitude, square footage, number of rooms, ear build, property type, and previous sales.
The next step that comes is data cleaning.
You have to handle the missing values by using imputation techniques or removing incomplete records, removing outliers that may skew the model's prediction,
normalize or standardize the data to ensure consistency.
The third one that we have is feature engineering.
You have to create new features such as proximity to schools, crime rates, and access to the public transportation.
Encode categorial variables, example property type, location using techniques like one-hot encoding. Generate interaction features that capture relationship between existing features.
The fourth one that we have is model selection.
Use regression models like linear regression, random forest, gradient boosting, neural networks.
Experiment with different models to identify the best performing one.
Now, in the next phase, all you have to do, guys, is model training and evaluation.
Split the data set into training and test sets.
Train the model on a training set and evaluate their performance on the testing set using metrics like RSME, which means root means squared error.
You can use cross-validation to ensure the model's robustness and avoid overfitting.
The sixth one that we have always hyperparameter tuning.
You can optimize the model's hyperparameter using techniques such as grid search or random search to improve accuracy.
And if you're looking forward to deploy your model, then you can develop a web interface using Flask or Django to allow users to input property features and get predictions.
You can deploy the model on the cloud platform like AWS for scalability.
Now, if we talk about the complexity level of this, we all know that it is a beginner level project.
Now let us move on to the one more set that is music genre, classification, and generation.
So, guys, this is also one of the most beginner level projects.
This project aims to develop a system that can classify music tracks into different genres and generate new music composition within specified genres.
The goal is to build a model that analyzes audio features to categorize music and uses deep learning techniques to create new music.
This project introduces advanced concepts of audio processing, deep learning, and generative models.
So, guys, what will be used in this? So we'll have programming language that will be Python.
For audio processing, we'll be using Librosa.
For machine learning libraries, we'll be using TensorFlow, Kiras, PyTorch.
For data handling libraries, we'll be using Pandas, NumPy.
For visualization, we'll be using Matplotlet, Cbon.
For the dataset, guys, you can use GDZAN Music Genre dataset or you can get it from Free Music Archive.
So, guys, in the first phase, we are going to have data collection.
You can opt datasets containing music tracks and their corresponding genre from the sources, from GDZAN Music Genre dataset and the free music
archive.
Ensure that a dataset includes diverse genre and substantial number of tracks per genre.
Next, we'll go for data pre-processing.
Use library Librosa to load and pre-process audio files, including feature extractions such as mill frequency, sepstral coefficients,
chroma features, and spectral contrast.
You can normalize the extracted features to ensure consistent input for the given models.
Now, if you talk about feature engineering guys, you can extract additional features from the audio files such as tempo, beat, zero crossing rate, etc.
Create a feature matrix that represents the extracted audio features.
Then go for the model selection.
Use conventional neural network or recurrent neural networks for the music genre classification.
Split the dataset into training and testing dataset.
Now, if we talk about model training and evaluation, guys, then you can train the selected classification model on the training set.
Evaluate the model's performance on the testing set using metrics like accuracy, precision, recall, and FN score.
Use confusion matrices to understand the classification performance across different genres.
Now, if you talk about model selection and training for the music generation, what you will do, guys, you can use the generative adversarial networks or recurrent neural networks such as LSTM,
long short-term memory for music generation. Train the generative model on the dataset to create new music sequences.
Next, we have model training and evaluation.
You can train the generative model on sequences of audio features, you can evaluate the generated music by listening tests and by objective metrics like inception score or frichet audio distance.
If I talk about hyperparameter tuning guides, you can optimize the model. You can use the hyperparameters using techniques like grid search or random search to improve performance.
If I talk about deployment, guys, we can deploy these models on cloud platforms like AWS.
Now let us move on to our next project.
So, guys, the complexity of this project is at the Bignal level.
Now let us move to the intermediate level projects.
Next project that we have all over here is sentiment analysis of Twitter data.
This project aims to develop a sentiment analysis model that can classify to its at positive, negative, or neutral.
The goal is to analyze public sentiment on various topics or events using natural language techniques.
So, guys, what will be used all over here?
So in this, we will have programming language like Python, okay, NLP libraries, NLTK Spacey.
For machine learning libraries, we can use ScikitLearn, TensorFlow, Kiras for data handling libraries, we have Pandas, NumPy.
For visualization, we have Matplotlib, Cbon, and we can use the API Twitter for data collection.
Now, how are you going to work on it, guys?
So, guys, if I talk about the data collection, use a Twitter API to collect tweets based on specific hashtags like keywords or topics.
Extract relevant fields like tweet text, user information, timestamp, etc.
Then if I talk about data preprocessing guys, clean the tweet text by removing special characters, links, mentions, hashtags, and stop words.
Tokenize the text and perform lemization or stemming to reduce the words to their base form.
Next, if you talk about feature engineering guys, you convert the clean text data into numerical representation using TFIDF, bag of words, or word
embedding.
Now if I talk about model selection, guys, you can choose the classification algorithms such as logistic regression, nape bias, or LSTM.
Split the dataset into training and testing dataset.
Now, if I talk about model training and evaluation, then you can train the selected model on the training set.
Evaluate the model's performance on the testing set using metrics like accuracy, precision, recall, and FN score. Use cross-validation to ensure the model's robustness.
If I talk about hyperparameter tuning, guys, you can optimize the model's hyperparameters using grid search or random search to improve the performance.
For deployment, which can be optional, you can deploy your model on AWS for real-time sentiment analysis.
So if I talk about the complexity level, guys, its complexity is intermediate.
So guys, our next project is customer segmentation using K-Mains clustering.
This project aims to segment customers into distinct groups based on their purchasing behavior and demographic information.
The objective is to understand customer segments and tailor marketing strategies accordingly.
So guys, what programming languages we'll be using?
So basically, we'll be using Python.
For machine learning libraries, we will have ScikitLearn.
For data handling libraries, we'll have Pandas, NumPy. For visualization libraries, we'll have Matplotlab, CBON, and the dataset source will be e-commerce transaction data.
How are we going to work on this one?
For data collection, we can obtain a data set of e-commerce transactions that include customer demographics, purchase history, and product information.
Next, we'll have data pre-processing.
For data pre-processing, we are going to do the cleaning of the data by handling the missing values and outliers.
Then for feature engineering, we are going to create features like total purchase amount, purchase frequency, and recency of the purchases.
Then we are going to proceed for the model selection.
We can use k-means clustering to segment the customers into distinct groups.
We can determine the optimal number of clusters using methods like elbow methods or Silhout score.
Now, if I talk about model training and evaluation, you can train the K-means model on the process dataset.
You can evaluate the quality of clusters by analyzing intra-cluster and intercluster distances.
Next, we have the evaluation. You can visualize the clusters using techniques like PCA, principal component analysis, TSNE, etc.
Next, we have the hyperparameter tuning.
Now you can tune this model and interpret the characteristics of each segment.
You can develop a target marketing strategy for each segment based on unique behavior and preferences.
Now deployment is optional. You can develop a dashboard using Flask or Django to visualize customer segments and track marketing campaigns.
So, guys, if I talk about the complexity of this project, so this is an intermediate level project.
So, guys, for dataset, you can use the Kaggles customer segmentation dataset, which is available at the Kaggles platform.
Now, the third intermediate level project that we have all over here is building a chatbot with Rasa.
This project aims to build an intelligent chatbot using RASA framework.
The chatbot will be capable of understanding user queries and providing appropriate responses, making it useful for customer support, personal assistance, or information retrieval.
What languages are we going to use? So it will be Python-based.
We'll have the NLP libraries like Rasa, NLTKs, PIC.
For machine learning libraries, we are going to have ScikitLearn, TensorFlow, Kira's, etc.
For data handling libraries, we are going to use Pandas, NumPy.
So guys, this was what we are going to do it.
And how you can work on this one? By collecting the data, collect the conversation data and FAQs from the target domain.
Annotate the data to create training examples for the chatbot.
Next comes is data pre-processing.
Clean the text data by removing special characters and normalizing the text.
You can tokenize and limitize the text to prepare for a training.
The third one we have the modules training.
You can use Rasa's NLU's component to train a model for intent recognition and entity extraction.
You can define the dialog management policies to handle different conversation flows.
Next, guys, you can perform the feature engineering and integration.
You can integrate the Rasa's NLU and core components to build complete chatbot.
You can connect the chatbot to messaging platforms like Facebook, Messenger, etc.
For model selection and testing, what you can do, guys, you can test this chatbot with various inputs to ensure that it handles the scenarios appropriately.
And you can also select the right model using this.
Now, if I talk about model training, guys, what do you have to do? You have to collect the user feedback and conversational logs to continuously work on training the model.
Next, similarly, you have to retrain the model periodically with the new data to see how it is working. So that will be your evaluation.
Now for the hyperparameter tuning, what are you going to do, guys?
You have to check in those scenarios where it is able to tune up with those scenarios where it can handle the input appropriately.
And next is deployment. So guys, for deploying it, you can use AWS.
So guys, for a dataset, you can use RASAS open source.
So that's a very good dataset for you to proceed.
So guys, if you talk about the difficulty of this project, this is an intermediate level project.
Now let us move on to the advanced level projects.
For advanced level projects, the first one that comes up to my mind is movie similarity from plot summaries.
Now, this project aims to develop a system that can find out recommended movies similar to a given movie based on their plot summaries.
By analyzing the textual content of the movie, plot summaries, the model will identify similarities and suggests movies with similar themes, storylines, or genres.
This project introduces Begner's to natural language processing, text similarly measures, and recommendation systems.
What languages we are going to use, guys? We'll be using Python, NLP libraries like NLTK, Spacey, Machine Learning Libraries like ScikitLearn, data handling libraries like Pandas,
NumPy, Visualization, we can use NumPy, and dataset source will be IMDB or Kegel.
So guys, this process is also involving the data collection.
Then you have to go for data cleaning, then feature engineering, next, model selection.
So similar process as I have discussed in other projects. So you have to also go through the same one.
Next, what do you have to do, guys?
Similarly, what do you have to do? You have to train the model, then evaluate the model, then hypertune it, and finally proceed for the deployment.
So this is the overall process of this project.
Try to research on the website a lot, like how you can extract it.
So, guys, you can use Kegel or Towards Data Science to research more about this project.
Now, guys, if I talk about the difficulty of this project, then this is an advanced level project.
Now, let us move on to the next one that we have all over here.
That is the image segmentation project for brain tumor prognosis.
This is a very, very amazing project, and definitely you can put up on your portfolio.
Basically, guys, this project aims to develop an image segmentation model to identify and de-alineate brain tumors from MNI scans.
The goal is to accurately segment the tumor regions which can aid in prognosis, treatment, planning, surgical interventions.
This project introduces intermediate level concepts of computer visions, deep learning, and medical image analysis.
So, guys, what we'll be using all over here?
For programming languages, we can use Python. For deep learning libraries, we can use TensorFlow, Kiras, PyTorch. For image processing libraries, we can use OpenCV, Scikit Image.
For data handling libraries, we can use Pandas, NumPy.
For visualization, we can use Matplotlab Cbon.
Now, if I talk about what is the process of developing this project, the first step will be the same data collection.
So next step, you have to go for data pre-processing.
Third step, you have to do the model selection where you can use CNN models for image segmentation tasks.
Then you go for model selection.
Moving ahead, you're going to have the model training and evaluation.
You have to split the dataset into training and validation and testing datasets.
Next, proceed for the evaluation phase.
Okay. Evaluate the model with certain metrics. So here I can give you certain ideas like you can use dice coefficient, intersection over union, or accuracy.
Then go for hyperparameter tuning where you have to optimize the model's hyperparameters.
You can use grid search or random search as we have discussed, and finally, you can deploy this model on AWS.
Now, guys, we have come to the final project.
This is also a very amazing project, guys.
So, guys, the complexity level of this project is advanced level.
Now, let us move on to our final project, that is the impact of climate change on birds.
This is a very, very amazing project, and definitely you can add it on your resume.
This project aims to analyze the impact of climate change on the bird population and migration patterns.
By examining various climatic factors and their correlation with bird species data, the project seeks to predict how climate change might affect bird behavior and distribution.
This project will introduce you some advanced level concepts like time series analysis, environmental data modeling, etc.
So, guys, what programming languages we'll be using? For data analysis, you can see we'll have pandas, numpy. For machine learning libraries, we are going to have scikit-learn, tensor flow.
For visualization, we are going to have MatplotLab Plotly.
For geospatial, we are going to have GeoPandas, Folium.
For radar service, we're going to have public data sets on bird observation and climate data sources from eBird.
Now, what will the process flow for this one, guys?
First, you have to proceed for data collection, gather bird observation from the data like eBird, which provides extensive record of bird sightings.
Okay. And for climate data, you can collect it from NOAA, including temperature, precipitation, and other relevant climatic factors over the time.
And similar next process will be the data pre-processing, then you have to proceed for feature engineering, then you have to go for model selection.
Okay.
Moving ahead, you have to go for model training, then evaluation, then hypoparameter tuning, and finally, you have to deploy the model.
So research about this project, see what models you are going to use. Suppose I can give you a hint about this. You can use time series analysis models like Arima or ML models.
You can also use random forest or gradient boosting for predicting impact on the bird population.
So, guys, use Google exhaustively to research about this project.
This is also a very amazing project, and it's going to give you a lot of ideas.
Now, if I talk about the complexity level of this, it is an advanced level project.
Welcome to Deep Learning Interview Questions.
My name is Richard Kirschner with the Simply Learn team. That's www.simplylearn.com.
Get certified, get ahead.
Today we're going to help you prepare for interview questions dealing with deep learning.
And we're going to go from the very basics of neural networks and deep learning into some of the more commonly used models
so that you can have an understanding of what kind of questions are going to come up and what you need to know in interview questions.
We'll start with a very general concept of what is deep learning.
This is where we take large volumes of data, in this case on cats and dogs or whatever. A lot of times you use a training setup to train your model.
Remember it's kind of like a magic black box going on there. Then we use that to extract features or extract information, and in this case, classify the image of a cat and a dog.
So the primary takeaway we're talking about deep learning is it learns from large volumes of structured and even unstructured data and uses complex algorithms to train neural networks.
It also performs complex operations to extract hidden patterns and features.
And if we're going to discuss deep learning in this very simplified overview, then we also have to go over what is a neural network.
This is a common image you'll see of a drawing of a forward propagation neural network. And it's it's a human brain inspired system which replicate the way humans learn.
So this is inspired how our own neurons and our brain fire, but at a much simplified level.
Obviously, it's not ready to take over the human population and be our leader yet, not for many years. It's very much in its infant stage. But it's inspired by how our brains work.
And they use a lot of other inspirations. You can study brains of moths and other animals that they've used to figure out how to improve these neural networks.
The most common one consists of three layers of network, and this is generally how you view these networks, is you have an input, you have a hidden layer, and an output.
And the neural network is broken up into many pieces, but when we focus just on the neural network, it's always on the hidden layers that we're making all the adjustments
and figuring out how to best set up those hidden layers for their functions to both train faster and to function better. When we look at this, of course, we have our input, hidden, and output.
Each layer contains neurons called as nodes that perform various operations.
And you can see here we have the list of the nodes, we have both our input nodes and our output nodes, and then our hidden layer nodes.
And it's used in deep learning algorithm like CNN, RNN, GAN, etc.
We'll address some of these models a little closer, at least the most common models, as we go down the list and we study the deep learning and the neural network framework.
Let's start with what is a multi layer percepitron, or MLP, a lot of time is referred to. And you'll see these abbreviations.
I'll be honest, I have to write them down on a piece of paper and go through them because I never remember what they all mean, even though I play with them all the time.
What is a multilayer percipitron?
Well, if you look at the image on the right, it's very similar to what we just looked at. You have your input layer, your hidden layer, and your output layer. And that's exactly what this is.
It has the same structure of a single layer percipiton with one or more hidden layers, except the input layer.
Each node in the other layers uses a nonlinear activation function.
What that means is your input layer is your data coming in, and then your activation function is based upon all those nodes and weights being added together, and then it has the output.
MLP uses supervised learning method called backpropagation for training the model.
Very key word there is backpropagation. Single layer percepitron can classify only linear separable classes with binary output, zero, one, but the MLP can classify nonlinear classes.
So let's break this down just a little bit the multi-layer percipitron with an input layer and a hidden layer and an output layer.
As you see that it comes in there, it has adds up all the numbers and weights, depending on how your setup is, that then goes to the next layer,
that then goes to the next hidden layer if you have multiple hidden layers, and finally to the output layer.
The back propagation takes the error that it sees. So whatever the output is, it says, hey, this has an error to it, it's wrong. And then sends that error backwards from where it came from.
And there's a lot of different functions used to train this based on that error and how that error goes backwards in the nodes.
So forward is you get your answers, backward is for training.
You see this every day. Even my Google Pixel phone has this. They train the neural network, which takes a lot more data to train than it does to use.
And then they load up that neural network into, in this case, I have a Pixel 2, which actually has a built-in neural network for processing pictures.
And so it's just the forward propagation I use when it processes my photos. But when they were training it, it used the back propagation to train it with the errors they had.
We'll be coming back to different models that are used.
For right now, though, multi-layer percepitron MLP.
Put that down as your vocabulary word. And of course, backpropagation.
What is data normalization and why do we need it? This is so important. We spend so much time in normalizing our data and getting our data clean and setting it up.
So when we talk about data, there's a pre-processing step to standardize the data.
So whatever we have coming in, we don't want it to be a you know one gigabyte file here, a two gigabyte picture here, and a three-kilobyte text there.
Even as a human, I can't process those all in the same group. I have to reformat them in some way that loops them together so that the standardized format.
We use this data normalization and in pre-processing to reduce it and eliminate data redundancy.
A lot of times the data comes in and you end up with two of the same images or the same information in different formats.
Then we want to rescale values to fit into a particular range for achieving better convergence. What this means is with most neural networks they form a bias.
We've seen this in recently in attacks on neural networks where they light up one pixel or one piece of the view and it skews the whole answer.
So suddenly because one pixel is really bright, uh it doesn't know what to do.
Well, when we start rescaling it, we put all the values between say minus one and one, and we change them and refit them to those values, it helps get rid of that bias,
helps fix for some of those problems. And then finally we restructure the data and improve the integrity. We want to make sure that we're not missing values or we don't have partial data coming in.
One way to look at this is uh bad data in, bad data out. So we want clean data in and you want good answers coming out.
One of the most basic models used is a Boltzmann machine. So let's address what is a Boltzmann machine. And if you know, we just did the MLP multi-layer perceptron.
So now we're going to come into almost a simplified version of that.
And in this we have our visible input layer and we have our hidden layer. The Boltzmann machines are almost always shallow.
They're usually just two-layer neural nets that make stochastic decisions whether a neuron should be on or off. True, false. Yes, no.
First layer is the visible layer, and second layer is the hidden layer.
Nodes are connected to each other across layers, but no two nodes of the same layer are connected. Hence it is also known as restricted Boltzmann machine.
Now that we've covered a basic MLP or multi layer perceptron, and we've gone over the Boltzmann machine, also known as the restricted Boltzmann machine,
let's talk a little bit about activation formulas. And this is a huge topic that can get really complicated, but it also is automated, so it's very simple.
So you have both a complicated and a simple at the same time.
So what is the role of activation functions in a neural network? Activation function decides whether a neuron should be fired or not.
That's the most basic one. And that actually changes a little bit because it's either whether fired or not, in this case activation function, or what value should come out when it's fired.
But in these models we're looking at just the Boltzmann restricted layers.
So this is what causes them to fire. Either they don't or they do. It's a yes or no, true, false, all or nothing.
It accepts a weighted sum of the inputs, the bias as input to any activation function.
So whatever activation function is, it needs to have the sum of the weights times the input. So each input, if you remember on that model, and let's just go back to that model real quick.
And then you always have to add a bias.
And you can look at the bias if you remember from your Euclidean geometry, you draw a straight line.
The formula for that line has a y coordinate at the end.
It's always um cx plus m or something like that, where m is where it crosses the y coordinates if you're doing a straight line.
With these weights, it's very similar, but a lot of times we just add it in as its own weight.
We take it as a node of a one value coming in, and then we compute its new weight, and that's how we compute that bias, just like we compute all the other weights coming in.
The node which gets fires depends on the y value, and then we have a step function. And the step function, this is where, remember I said it's going to get complicated and simple all at the same time.
We have a lot of different step functions. We have the sigmoid function, we have just a standard step function, we have the um RayLu, it's pronounced like Ray, the ray from the sun
and lu, like a name. So RayLu function.
And we have the tangent h function. And if you look at these, they all have something similar. They all either force it to be um one value or the other.
They force it to be in the case of the first three a zero or one, and in the last one, it's either a minus one or a one. And you can usually convert that to a zero, one, yes, no, true, false.
And on this, one of the most common ones is the step function itself, because there is no middle value. There is no um uh discrepancy that says, well, I'm not quite sure.
But as you get into different models, probably the most commonly used used to be the sigmoid was most commonly used, but I see the RayLu used more often.
Really, depending on what you're doing, you just have to play with these and find out which one works best, depending on the data and your output.
The reason to have a non-zero one answer or something kind of in the middle is when you're looking at this and it's coming out, you can actually process that
middle ground as part of the answer into another neural network. So it might be that the RayLu function says, hey, this is only a 0.6, not a 1.
And uh, even though the one is what's going into the next neural network or the next hidden layer as an input, the 0.6
value might also be going in there to let you know, hey, this is not a straight up one or straight up zero, it's someplace in the middle. This is a little uncertain what's coming out here.
So it's a very powerful tool. But in the basic neural network, you usually just use the step function. It's yes or no.
Let's take a um a big step back and take a uh kind of an overview.
The next function is what is a cost function that we're gonna cover.
This is so important because this is your end result that you're gonna do over and over again and use to decide whether the model is working or not, whether you need to try a different step function,
whether you need to try a different activation, whether you need to try a fully different model used.
Uh so what is the cost function?
Cost function is a measure to evaluate how good your model's performance is.
It is also referred as loss or error used to compute the error of the output layer during backpropagation. There's our backpropagation where we're training our model. That's one of our key words.
Mean squared error is an example of a popular cost function. And so here we have the cost function c equals half of y minus y predicted. Um and then you square that.
So the first thing is um, you know, real quick, if you haven't done statistics, this is not a percentage. It's not a percentage of how accurate it is, it's just a measurement of the error.
And we take that error if we're training it, and we push that error backwards through the neural network, and we use that through the different training functions,
depending on what model you're using, to train the neural network. So when you deploy the network, you're usually done training it, because it takes a lot of computational force to train it.
Um this is a very simple model. And so you deploy the trained one, uh, but we want to know how your error is. And so how do we do that? Well, you split your data.
Part of your data is for training and part of your data is for testing, and then we can also test the error on there. So that's very important. And then we're gonna go one more step on this.
We gotta look at both the local and the global setup. It might work great to test your data on what you have on your computer, but that's different than in the field.
So when we're talking about all these different tests and the error test as far as your loss, you don't you want to make sure that you're in a closed environment when you do initial testing,
but you also want to open that up and make sure you follow up with the testing on the larger scale of data because it will change. It might not fit the larger scale.
There might be something in there in the way you brought the data in specifically, or the data group you used, or any of those could cause an error.
So it's very important to remember that we're looking at both the local and the global context of our error.
And just one other side note on the lot of the newer models of neural networks, by comparing the error we get on the data, our training data,
with a portion of the test data, we can actually figure out how good the model is, whether it's overfitted or not. We'll go into that a little bit more as we go into some of the different models.
So we have our output, we're able to figure out the error on it based on the square means usually, although there's other uh functions used. So we want to talk about what is gradient descent.
Another vocabulary word. Gradient descent is an optimation algorithm to minimize the cost function or to minimize the error.
Aim is to find the local or global minima of a function.
Determine the direction the model should take to reduce the error. So as we're looking at this, we have our uh squared error that we just figured out, the cot based on the cost function.
It says how bad is my model fitting the data I just put through it. And then we want to reduce that error.
So how do you figure out what direction to do that in? Well, it could be that you're looking at just that line of that line of data coming in, so that would be a local minima.
We want to know the error of that particular setup coming in. And then you have your global, your global minima. We want to minimize it based on the overall data we're putting through it.
And with this, we can figure out the global minimum cost. We want to take all those local minimum costs of each piece of data coming in and figure out the global one.
How are we going to adjust this model to fit all the data?
We don't want it to be biased just on three or four lines of data coming in. We want it to kind of extrapolate a general answer for all the data coming in.
This, of course, uh we mentioned it briefly about backpropagation. This is where it really comes in handy is training our model. Neural network technique to minimize the cost function.
It helps to improve the performance of the network, backpropagates the error, and updates the weights to reduce the error.
So as you can see here is a very nice depiction of a backpropagation. We have our predicted why coming out, and then we have, since it's a training set, we already know the answer.
And the answer comes back and based on case of the square means was one of the functions we looked at. One of the activation functions based on cost function.
That cost function then, depending on what you choose for your backpropagation method, and there's a number of them, will change the weights.
It will change the weight going to each of the one of those nodes in the hidden layer.
And then based upon the error that's still being carried back, it'll change the weights going to the next hidden layer. And then it computes an error level on that and sends that back up.
And you're going to say, well, if it computes the error into the first hidden layer and fixes it, why would it stop there?
Well, remember, we don't want to create a biased neural network. So we only make small adjustments on these weights. We don't make a big adjustment that changes everything right off the bat.
So no matter how far back you go, you're always going to have a small amount of error, and that's still going to continue to go all the way back up the hidden layers.
For right now, focus on the back propagation is taking that error and moving it backwards on the neural network to change the weights and help program it so that it'll have the correct answers.
So far, we've been talking about forward propagation neural networks. Everything goes forwards, goes left to right.
But let's take a little detour and let's see what is the difference between a feed forward neural network and a recurrent neural network.
Now this is in the function, not when we're training it using the back propagation.
So you've got new information coming in and you want to get the answer, and there's a couple different networks out there,
and we want to know we have a feed forward neural network and we have a new vocabulary term, recurrent neural network.
A feed forward neural network, signals travel in one direction from input to output. No feedback loops, considers only the current input, cannot memorize previous inputs.
One example of one of these feedforward neural networks, and we've covered a number of them, but one of the ones that has a big highlight nowadays is the CNN,
a convolutional neural network. TensorFlow, the one put out by Google, is probably most known for their CNN, where the information goes forward.
It uh first takes a picture, splits it apart, goes through the individual pixels on the picture, so it picks up a different reading, then calculates based on that,
goes into a regular feedforward neural network, and then gives your categorization on there.
Now we're not covering the CNN today, but we do have a video out that you can look up on YouTube, put out by Simply Learn, the convolutional neural network. Wonderful tutorial.
Check that out and learn a lot more about the convolutional neural network.
But you do need to know that the CNN is a forward propagation neural network only.
So it's only moving in one direction. So we want to look at a recurrent neural network. Signals travel in both directions, making it a looped network.
Considers the current input along with the previous received inputs for generating the output of a layer, has the ability to memorize past data due to its internal memory.
And you can see they have a nice uh image here. We have our input, and for some reason they always do the recurrent neural network in reverse from bottom up in the images.
Kind of a standard, although I'm not sure why. Your X goes into your hidden layer, and your hidden layer, the answer for part of the answer from that it generates, feeds back into the hidden layer.
So now you have an input of both X and part of the hidden layer, and then that feeds into your output.
Now, if we go back to the forward, let me just go back a slide, and we're looking at uh our forward propagation network.
One of the tricks you can do to use just a forward propagation network is if you're in a what they call a time sequence, that's a good uh term to remember,
or a time series. Meaning that it's sequential data. Each term comes after the other. You can trick this by creating your input nodes as with the history.
So if you know that uh you have values one, five, and seven going in, and you know what the output is from one what those outputs are, you can expand the input to include the history input.
That's one of the ways to trick a forward propagation network into looking at that. But when you do it with the recurrent neural network, you let the hidden layer do that for you.
It sends that data and reprocesses it back into itself.
What are some of the applications of recurrent neural network?
The RNN can be used for sentiment analysis and text mining.
Getting up early in the morning is good for health. And it's a positive sentiment.
One of the catches you really want to look at this when you're looking at the language is that I could switch this around and totally negate the meaning of what I'm doing,
so it'd no longer be positive. So when you're looking at a sentence, knowing the order of the words is as important as the meaning of the words.
You can't just count how many good words there are versus bad words to get some positive sentiment. You now have to know what they're addressing.
And there's lots of other different uses. Uh kids are playing football or soccer as we call it in the US. RN can help you caption an image.
So based on previous information coming in, it refeeds that back in and you have an image setter.
And then time series problems like predicting the prices of stocks in a month or quarter or sell a product can be solved using an RNN. And this is a really good example.
You have whatever your stocks were doing earlier this month will have a huge effect of what they're doing today if you're investing.
So having an RNN model, a recurrent neural network feeding into itself what was happening previously allows it to take that model and program in that whole series without having to put in the whole
a month at a time of data.
You can only put in one day at a time, but if you keep them in order, it will look back and say, oh, this because of what happened yesterday, I need some information from that,
and I'm going to use that to help predict today's and so on and so on.
We're going to go back to our activation functions. Remember I told you RayLu is one of the most common functions used? Uh so let's talk a little bit more about RayLu and also Softmax.
Softmax is an activation function that generates the output between 0 and 1.
It divides each output such that the total sum of the outputs is equal to 1. It is often used in the output layers. Softmax L of the n equals e to L on the N over the absolute value of E to the L.
So what does this function mean? I mean, what is actually going on here? So we have our uh output nodes, and our output nodes are giving us uh let's say they gave us 1.2, 0.9, and 0.4.
As a human being, I look at that and I say, well, the greatest value is 1.2.
So whatever category that is, if you have three different categories, maybe you're not just doing if it's a cat or it's a dog or um, oh let's say it's a cow. We had cats and dogs earlier.
Why the cats and dogs are hanging out with a cow, I don't know. But we have a value, and it might say 1.2 is a cat, 0.9 is a dog, and 0.4 is a cow.
Uh for some reason it thinks that there's a chance of it being any one of these three items, and that's how it comes out of the output layer.
Well, as a human, I can look at 1.2 and say this is definitely what it is. It's definitely a cat or whatever it is.
Maybe it's looking at different kinds of cars, might be a better whether it's a car, truck, or a motorcycle.
Maybe that'd be a better example.
Well, from a computer standpoint, that might be a little confusing because they're just numbers waving at us. And so with the softmax, we want all those numbers to always add up to one.
So when I add three numbers together, I want the final output to be one on there.
And so it goes through this formula, changes each of these numbers, in this case it changes them to 0.46, 0.34, and 0.20. They all add up to one.
And that's a lot easier to register because it's very set. It's a set output. It's never going to be more than one, it's never going to be less than zero.
And so you can see here that there's probably a pretty high chance that it's the first one. So you're as a human being, we have no problem knowing that.
But this output can then also go into say another input. So it might be an automated car that's picking up images, and it says that image in front of us is probably a big truck.
We should deal with it like it's a big truck. It's probably not a motorcycle, um, or whatever those categories are.
That's the softmax part of it. But now we have the RELU. Well, what's where's the RELU coming from? Well, the RELU is what's generating the 1.2 and the 0.9 and the 0.4.
And so if you remember, our RELU stands for rectified linear unit and is the most widely used activation function.
We looked at a number of different activation functions, including tangent H, the step function.
I remember I said the step function is really used if that's what your actual output is, because then you know it's a zero or one.
But the RayLue, if you have that as your output, you now have a discrepancy in there. And if that's going into another neural network or another process, having that discrepancy is really important.
And it gives an output of x if x is positive and zero otherwise. So it says my x value is going to be somewhere between zero or one.
And then the uh usually unless it's really uncertain, the output's usually a one or zero.
And then you have that little piece of uncertainty there that you can send forward to another network or you can look at to know that there's uncertainty involved.
And is often used in the hidden layers. This is what's coming out of the hidden layers into the output layer usually.
Or as we reference the uh convolution uh neural network, the CNN, which you'd have to go to another video to review. The RayLue is the most common used for convolutional part of that network.
It has a bunch of little pieces that are very simplified looking at all the different images or different sections of the map, and uh the RayLue works really good for that.
Like I said, there's other formulas used, but that this is the most common one, and you'll see that in the hidden layers going maybe between one layer and the next layer.
So just a quick recap, we have our soft max, which means that if you have uh numerous categories, only one of them is going to be picked,
but you also want to have some value attached to it, how well it picked it. And you put that between zero and one, so it's very uh standardized. So we have our softmax.
We looked at that, let's go back one. We looked at that here where it transforms in numbers.
And then we have our RayLue function, which takes the information and the summation and puts it between a zero and a one, where it's either clearly a zero
or depending on how confident our model is, it'll go between the zero and one value. What are hyperparameters? Wow, this is a great interview question. Hyperparameters.
When you are doing neural networks, this is what you're playing with most of the time once you've gotten the data formatted correctly.
A hyperparameter is a parameter whose value is set before the learning process begins, determines how a network is trained and the structure of the network.
This includes things like the number of hidden units, how many hidden layers are you gonna have, and how many nodes in each layer? Learning rate.
Learning rate is usually multiplied once you've figured out the error and how much you want to change the weights.
We talked about, or I mentioned it early, just briefly, you don't want to just make a huge change, otherwise you're gonna have a biased model.
So you only take some little incremental changes, and that's what the learning rate is, is those small incremental changes.
Epics, how many times are you gonna go through all the data in your training set? So one epic is one trip through all the data.
And there's a lot of other things depending on which model you're working with and which programming script you're working with.
Like the Python SKLearn package will have it slightly different than say Google's TensorFlow package, which will be a little bit different than the Spark machine learning package.
So these are just some examples of the hyperparameters.
And so you see in here we have a nice image of our data coming in and we train our model, then we do a comparison to see how good our model is, and then we go back and we say,
hey, this this model's pretty good, but it's biased.
So then we send it back and we change our hyperparameters to see if we can get an unbiased model, or we can have a better prediction on it that matches our data closer.
What will happen if learning rate is set too low or too high? We have a nice couple graphs here.
We just have one over here that says a learning rate set too low, and you can see that it slowly works its way down the curve. And on the right, you can see a learning rate set too high.
It's just bouncing back and forth. When your learning rate is too low, that's what we studied it two slides ago, they asked what the learning rate was.
Training of the model will progress very slowly as we are making very tiny updates to the weights. We'll take many updates before reaching the minimum point.
So I just mentioned epic going through all the data. You might have to go through all the data a thousand times instead of five hundred times for it to train.
Learning rate too high causes undesirable divergent behavior to the loss function due to drastic updates and weights. At times it may fail to converge or even diverge.
So if you have your learning rate set too high and it's training too quickly, maybe you'll get lucky and it trains after one epic run,
but a lot of times it might never be able to train because the weights are changing too fast. They they flip back and forth too easy.
And you see down here we've introduced uh two new terms, converge and diverge.
Uh converge means that our model has reached a point where it's able to give a fairly good answer for all the data we put in. All those weights have adjusted and it's minimized the error.
Diverge means that the data is so chaotic that it can never manage to train to that data. The data's just too chaotic for it to train.
So we have two new words there, converge and diverge are important to know also. What is dropout and batch normalization?
Dropout is a technique of dropping out hidden and visible units of a network randomly to prevent overfitting of data.
It doubles the number of iterations needed to converge the network. So here we have our standard neural network, and then after applying dropout. Now it doesn't mean we actually delete the node.
The node is still there, and we're still going to use that node. What it means is that we're only going to work with a few of the nodes.
A lot of times, I think the most common one right now used is 20%. Uh so you'll drop out 20% of the nodes when you do your training, you reverse propagate your data.
And then you'll randomly pick another 20 nodes the next time you go through an epic data training.
So each time you go through one epic, you will randomly pick 20 of those nodes not to mess with. And this allows for less overfitting of the data.
So by randomly doing this, you create some, I guess it just kind of pulls some nodes off to the sides and says we're going to handle the data later on so we don't overfit.
Batch normalization is the technique to improve the performance and stability of neural network.
The idea is to normalize the inputs in every layer so that they have mean output and activation of zero and standard deviation of one. This question covers a lot of different things, which is great.
It's a great interview question because it pulls in that you have to understand what the mean value is. So a mean output activation of zero, that means our average activation is zero.
So when you normalize it, remember we're usually we're going between minus one and one on a lot of these.
It's a very standard setup, so you have to be very aware that this is your mean output activation of zero. And then we have our standard deviation of one.
So we want to keep our error down to just a one value. The benefits of this doing a batch normalization is it provides regularization, it trains faster, higher learning rates,
and weights are easier to initialize. What is the difference between batch gradient descent and stochastic gradient descent?
Batch gradient descent. Batch gradient computes the gradient using the entire data set. It takes time to converge because the volume of data is huge and weights update slowly.
So you can look at the batches. A lot of times if you're using big data, batch the data in, but you still go through a full epic. You still go through all the data on there.
So batch gradient descent means you're going to use it to fit all the data and look for a convergence there. Stochastic gradient descent.
Stochastic gradient computes the gradient using a single sample. It converges much faster than batch gradient because it updates weight more frequently.
Explain overfitting and underfitting and how to combat them.
Overfitting happens when a model learns the details and noise in the training data to the degree that it adversely impacts the execution of the model on the new
information. It is more likely to occur with nonlinear models that have more flexibility when learning a target function.
An example of this would be if you're looking at, say, cars and trucks and motorcycles, it might only recognize trucks that have a certain box-like shape.
It might not be able to notice a flatbed truck unless it's only a specific kind of flatbed truck or only Ford trucks, because that's what it saw on the training set.
This means that your model performs great on your train data and great on maybe a small test amount of data.
But when you go to use it in the real world, it leaves out a lot and start and is not very functional outside of your small area, your small laboratory data coming in.
Underfitting, doing the opposite when you underfit your data, underfitting alludes to a model that is neither well trained on training data nor can generalize to new information.
Usually happens when there is less and improper data to train a model. As a per performance and accuracy.
So if you're using underfitted data and you generate a model and you distribute that in a commercial zone,
you'll have a lot of people unhappy with you because it's not going to give them very good answers.
So we've explained overfitting and underfitting, so now we want to ask how to combat them. Combating overfitting and underfitting.
Resampling the data to estimate the model accuracy, K-fold cross-validation.
Having a validation data set to evaluate the model.
So when we do the resampling, we're randomly going to be picking out data, and we'll run it a few times to see how that works, depending on our random data and how we
sample the data to generate our model.
And then we want to go ahead and validate the data set by having our training data and then keeping some data on the side, testing data to validate it.
How are weights initialized in a network?
Initializing all weights to zero. All the weights are set to zero. This makes your model similar to a linear model.
So if you have linear data coming in, doing a basic setup like that might work. All the neurons in every layer perform the same operation given the same output and making the deep net useless.
Right there is a key word. It's going to be useless if you initialize everything to zero.
At that point, be looking into some other machine learning tools. Initializing all weights randomly. Here the weights are assigned randomly by initializing them very close to zero.
It gives better accuracy to the model since every neuron performs different computations. And here we have the weights are set randomly.
We have our input layer, the hidden layers, and the output layer. And w equals NP random random n. Layer size L layer size L minus one.
This is the most commonly used, is to randomly generate your weights. What are the different layers in CNN? Convolutional neural network.
First is the convolutional layer that performs a convolutional operation.
We have our other video out if you want to explore that more so and go into detail exactly how the C the convolutional layer works in the CNN as far as creating a number of smaller
picture windows that go over the data.
The second step is as a RAILU layer. RELU brings nonlinearity to the network and converts all the negative pixels to zero.
Output is rectified feature map.
So it goes into a mapping feature there. Pooling layer. Pooling is a down sampling operation that reduces the dimensionality of the feature map.
So we have all our RELU layer, which is pulling all these little maps out of our convolutional layer.
It's taking that picture and little creating little tiny neural networks to look at different parts of the picture.
Then we need to pull it together, and then finally the fully connected layer.
So we flatten our pooling layer out and we have a fully connected layer recognizes and classifies the objects in the image.
And that's actually your forward propagation, reverse propagation training model, usually. I mean there's a number of different models out there, of course.
What is pooling in CNN and how does it work?
Pooling used to reduce the spatial dimensions of a CNN performs down sampling operation to reduce the dimensionality, creates a pooled feature map by sliding a filter matrix over the input matrix.
I mentioned that briefly on the previous slide. It's important to know that you have, if you see here they have a rectified feature map.
And so each one of those colors, like the yellow color, that might be one of the smaller little neural network using the RayLu.
You'll look at, it'll just kind of go over the main picture and look at all the different areas on the main picture.
So you might step one, two, three, four spaces. And then you have another one that's also looking at features. And it has a two seven eight five. Each one of those is a map.
So it might be the first one, might be a map looking for cat ears, and the second one looking for human eyes.
When it does this, you then have this rectified feature map looking at these different features.
And the max pooling with a two by two filters and a stride of two. Stride means instead of skipping every pixel, you're gonna go every two pixels. You take the maximum values.
And you can see over here, we look at a pooled feature map, one of the features says, hey, I had a max value of eight. So somewhere in here we saw a human eye labeled as eight. Pretty high label.
And maybe seven was a human hand, and maybe four was cat whiskers, or something that we thought might be cat whiskers. Four is kind of a low number in this particular case compared to the other ones.
So you have your full pool feature map. You can see the process here is we have our stepping.
We look for the max value, and then we create a pool feature map of the maxed values. How does a LSTM network work? And that's long short-term memory.
So the first thing to know is that an LSTMS are a special kind of recurrent neural network capable of learning long-term dependencies.
Remembering information for long periods of time is their default behavior.
We did look at the RNN briefly, talked about how the hidden layer feeds back into itself with the LSTM as a much more complicated feedback.
And you can see here we have the hidden layer of T minus 1 and the hidden layer, that's what the H stands for, hidden layer of T, and the formula is going in.
As we can see here, we have the hidden layers.
We have T minus 1 and then H of T, where T stands for time. So this is a series. Remember working with series and we want to remember the past.
And you can see you have your X your input of T, and that might be a frame in a video.
As the frame comes in, they usually use in this one the tangent h activation formula, but you also see that it goes through a couple other formulas,
the omega formula.
And so when it combines these, that then goes into the next layer, your next hidden layer.
That then goes into the data that's submitted to the next input. So you have your x of t plus one.
So when you have that coming in, then you have your h value that's coming forward from the last process.
And depending on how many of these omega structures you put in there, depends on how long term the memory gets. So it's important to remember this is more for your long-term recurrent neural networks.
The three steps in an LSTM. Step one decides what to forget and what to remember.
Step two, selectively update cell state values.
So based on what we want to remember and forget, we want to update those cell values, and then decides what part of the current state make it to the output.
So now we have to also have an output on there.
What are vanishing and exploding gradients? This is a great question that affects all our neural networks.
While training an RNN, your slope can become either too small or too large, and this makes the training difficult.
When the slope is too small, the problem is known as vanishing gradient.
So our slope, we have our change in X and our change in Y. When the slope decreases gradually to a very small value, sometimes negative, and makes training difficult.
When the slope tends to grow exponentially instead of decaying, this problem is called exploding gradient. The slope grows exponentially. You can see a nice graph of that here.
Issues in gradient problem, long training time, poor performance, and low accuracy. What is the difference between epic, batch, and iteration in deep learning?
Epic.
An epic represents one iteration over the entire data set.
So that's everything you're going to go ahead and put into that training model.
Batch.
We cannot pass the entire data set into the neural network at once. So we divide the data set into a number of batches. And then iteration.
If we have 10,000 images as data and a batch size of 200, then the epic should run 10,000 times over 200. So that means we have our total number over the 200 equals 50 iterations.
So in each epic, we're running over all the data set, we're going to have 50 iterations. And each of those iterations includes a batch of 200 images in this case.
Why TensorFlow is the most preferred library in deep learning? Well, first, TensorFlow provides both C and Python APIs that makes it easier to work on.
Has a faster compilation time than other deep learning libraries like Carras and Torch.
TensorFlow supports both CPU's and GPU's computing devices.
So right now TensorFlow is at the top of the market because it's so easy to use for both programmer side and for hardware side and for the speed of getting something up and running.
What do you mean by tensor and tensorflow?
Tensor is a mathematical object represented as arrays of higher dimension. These arrays of data with different dimensions and ranks that are fed as input to the neural network are called tensors.
And you can see here we have a tensor of dimensions 5, 4. So it's a two-dimensional tensor coming in.
You can look at an image like this that each one of those pixels is a different value if it's a black and white. So it might be zero and ones, and then each one represents a black and white image.
In a color photo, you might either find a different value system or you might have a tensor value that has the xy coordinates as we see here, plus the colors.
So you might have three more different dimensions for the three different images, the red, the blue, and the yellow coming in.
And even as you go from one layer or one tensor to the next, these layers might change. We might flatten them, might bring in numerous.
In the case of the convergence neural network, we have all those smaller different mappings of features that come in.
So each one of those layers coming through is a tensor if it has multiple dimensions coming in and weights attached to it. What are the programming elements in TensorFlow? Well we have our constants.
Constants are parameters whose value does not change. To define a constant, we use tf.constant command. Example, a equals tf.constant 2.0, tf float 32. So it's a tensor float value of 32.
B equals tf constant 3.0, print ab.
If we did a print of ab, we'd have um tf.constant and then of course uh b is that instance of it.
Variables. Variables allow us to add new trainable parameters to graph.
To divine a variable, we use tf.variable command and initialize them before running the graph in session.
Example, w equals tf variable point three d type tf float32, or b equals a tf variable minus three, comma d type float32. Placeholders.
Placeholders allow us to feed data to a tensor flow model from outside a model.
It permits a value to be assigned later. To define a placeholder, we use tf placeholder command. Example, a equals tf placeholder, b equals a times two.
With the tf session as S E S S result equals session run b comma feed dictionary equals a three point zero print result.
So we have a nice example there of a placeholder.
Session. A session is run to evaluate the nodes. This is called as the tensor flow runtime.
So for example, you have A equals TF constant 2.0, B equals TF constant 4.0, C equals A plus B.
And at this point you'd go ahead and create a session equals TF session, and then you could evaluate the tensor C, print session run C. That would input C as an input into your session.
What do you understand by a computational graph? Everything in TensorFlow is based on creating a computational graph.
It has a network of nodes where each node performs an operation. Nodes represent mathematical operation and edges represent tensors.
Since data flows in a form of a graph, it is also called a data flow graph. And we have a nice visual of this graph or graphic image of a computational graph.
And you can see here we have our input nodes, our add multiply nodes, and our multiply node at the end, and then we have the edges where the data flows. So we have from A going to C, A going to D.
You can see we have a two flowing, a four flowing. Explain generative adversarial network along with an example.
Suppose there is a wine shop that purchases wine from dealers, which they will resell later. So we have our dealer going to the wine, our shop owner that then sells it for a profit.
But there are some malfactor dealers who sell fake wine. In this case, the shop owner should be able to distinguish between fake and authentic wine.
The forger will try the different techniques to sell fake wine and make sure certain techniques go past the shop owner's check. So here's our forger, fake wine, shop owner.
The shop owner would probably get some feedback from the wine experts that some of the wine is not original. The owner would have to improve how he determines whether a wine is fake or authentic.
Goal of forger, to create wines that are indistinguishable from the authentic ones. Goal of shop owner, to accurately tell if the wine is real or not.
There are two main components of generative adversarial network.
And we'll refer it to as a noise vector coming in, where we have our forger who's going to generate fake wine, and then we have our real authentic wine,
and of course our shop owner who has to figure out whether it's real or fake.
The generator is a CNN that keeps producing images that are closer in appearance to the real images, while the discriminator tries to determine the difference between real and fake images.
The ultimate aim is to make the discriminator learn to identify real and fake images. What is an autoencoder?
The network is trained to reconstruct its input. So it is a neural network that has three layers. Here the input neurons are equal to the output neuron.
The network's target outside the same as the input and uses dimensionality reduction to restructure the input.
Input image comes in, we have our latency-based representation, and then it goes back about reconstructing the image.
It works by compressing the input to a latency-based representation and then reconstructing the output from this representation. What is bugging and boosting?
Bagging and boosting are ensemble techniques where the idea is to train multiple models using the same learning algorithm and then take a call.
So we have in here where we're bugging, we take a data set and we split it. We're going to have our training data and our test data, very standard thing to do.
Then we're going to randomly select data into the bags and train your model separately. So we might have bag one, model one, bag two, model two, bag three, model three, and so on.
In boosting, the emphasis is to select the data points which give wrong output in order to improve the accuracy.
So in boosting, we have our data set. Again, we split it to test data and train data. And we'll take bag one and we'll train the model.
Data points with wrong predictions then go into bag two, and we then train that model and repeat. Now, without further delay, let's get started with our Python exploratory data analysis.
But before getting started with the demonstration, let's have a brief understanding of exactly what is exploratory analysis.
Is this anything different from regular data analysis?
Yeah, that's exactly what we're going to discuss.
Now, types of data analysis.
So basically there are two different types of data analysis initial data analysis and exploratory data analysis.
Now what is initial data analysis and what is exploratory data analysis?
Let's understand a little briefing about these both.
First, let's get started with initial data analysis.
So what exactly do you mean by initial data analysis?
So data can be in any form.
It can be an Excel file, it can be a SQL file, it can be a PDF, it can be an XML, it can be even a website.
Whatever it is, it is data. If you have some information in this which can be used to extract some valuable information, then it is data.
So initial data analysis is a process of inspecting the data and screening the data that takes place after data collection and before statistical analysis.
So before you conduct any statistical formulas and analysis on the data and squeeze the data to extract some valuable insights,
the process which you perform is called as initial data analysis.
Like taking the data from the source, cleaning the data, transforming the data into a readable format, and using that readable data to build some basic charts,
what exactly is happening with this particular company, brand, or anything.
Let's say I give you some data from the company, then you get some insights of it, how many number of traffic you received, how many number of orders you received,
how what's the sale that you made in a specific month, specific quarter, or specific year, and what was the profit.
So basic information which you convert from the data and create a dashboard, right?
That is called as initial data analysis.
So a step beyond initial data analysis is known as the exploratory data analysis.
This is where you perform some statistics and probability and predict the future, right?
So let's dive deep and learn what exactly is exploratory data analysis.
So a simple definition for exploratory data analysis is as follows.
Exploratory data analysis is a key step in data analysis process that helps you identify patterns, outliners, and relationships between variables
before making assumptions.
It is not like you just create a dashboard out of the initial data analysis and you can predict the future.
No, it's not like that.
You might have to last, you might have to go through some permutations and combinations, you might have to check the seasons, you might have to check the possibilities,
right?
During some particular seasons in the year, let's say it's Christmas, then you can expect some good sales.
Let's say it's some festival, it's some special occasion, you can expect some good sales on the product, right?
And maybe a part of the year, maybe a part of 10 years, a decade, right? In a certain period of time, there might be some reason due to which the sales of a certain product were high.
So you to make sure that your assumptions, to make sure that your projection of the sales is 100% accurate or at least 90 to 95%
accurate, then you might have to go through the exploratory data analysis where you make use of statistics in your data analysis.
Now, there are certain steps that you might have to follow while going through exploratory data analysis.
So, following are the steps.
So, a first few steps might be slightly relevant to initial data analysis, like connecting data, cleaning it, transforming it, and loading it.
After that, you will import certain libraries from Python.
And after that, you read the data.
What exactly you have in your data, the number of columns, the number of rows, and if there are any null values, if there are any uh entries which are invalid, you might have to check that,
read that, and you might have to check for duplicate entries.
It is possible that one entry might have been entered by two different people, right?
There might be a duplication, so you might have to eliminate those duplications.
You might have to check for some missing values, you might have to calculate the total number of missing values from the data set and try to eliminate them from the calculation during your exploratory
analysis.
Followed by that, you have to do some model engineering.
Followed by that, you might have to do some feature engineering, creating features, and then you will get started with exploratory data analysis, and the at the end,
you will generate a projection or a prediction or give your assumption that this might happen in the future.
and you might have to take action to avoid it, or you might have to take action to improvise it.
Right? So, this is how the steps in exploratory data analysis take part.
Now let's proceed and start with our demo on Python's exploratory data analysis, and in this session, we will be using the use case that we discussed before,
which happens to be the student's performance dataset.
So, in this particular dataset, we will be having some columns based on physical activity.
the distance from home, parental education, the subjects, the marks they have scored in the previous exam, the marks that they have scored in the previous exam,
and if they have any disabilities, if they are having any resources that they require to write the exams, right?
So a few parameters, the important parameters that we will be discussing in this session, and followed by that, we will project the future that
how they will, you know, improve in their exams. and if there is a problem, and if there is a solution to it, then we can implement that solution and help students to gain better marks in their exam.
So that's the overall use case for this demonstration. Now let's get started with a Jupyter notebook.
Now we are on a Jupyter notebook.
Now let's get started. So I would like to have a title for my notebook.
So I'll write an HTML code for that.
So HTML code,
and I have uh three apostrophes,
and here I would like to write something in H1, so I want my title to be in H1.
So
style will be
background color.
So we let's uh proceed with the simply dance background which will be dark blue usually.
And I also want to have the font, let's let me give the font size as 30.
And in the next line I'd like to have border
radius, I can give the border radius as twenty pixels
and adding
to be sixteen pixels.
Text alignment I'd like to keep it center.
There you go.
Let's code the let's close the H1 now. Let's code the uh background color or border color.
So
B style.
So what we can do is we can basically have this uh code here, and what we will do is we will reuse this particular code segment
because we will be having multiple HTML codes in this particular uh workbook which will explain the results of the uh analysis that we are doing.
So the way we just run the code, and after that, we will be getting some visualizations, and I will be writing some textual content in XT in
HTML page so that it will be easier for the people to understand what's what exactly is happening here, right?
So the color will be light blue, and now comes the text.
We will close this, and here we will write the text as
"Python,
Exploratory
Data Analysis
,". and we will
break here
a student performance.
and here we will close the
H1.
and lastly, we will display this in HTML code. So basically, we missed this library, so we will be importing from iPython display import HTML to display this particular code.
So without this particular library, we cannot display any HTML codes in our notebook.
So we will quickly run that and we have a title over here.
Now let's proceed with the next part.
Now we will uh use some libraries like cat boost and light bgm.
So for that we might have to install these libraries.
So we will be using pip install. here,
pip, install, cat, boost
and control enter to run this particular code segment. or you can also use run, and it's installed.
and after that, we will also install
light. bgm,
sorry, not bgm.
So it's already installed.
Now we will start importing the libraries that we need.
So we will be needing numpy, panda, cbon, mapplotlib, and we will also import another special library which is for ignoring warnings.
So we will import warnings and after that from we will be importing that warnings from iPython display import clear output, and after that we will
uh tell the Jupyter notebook to import if there are any warnings. So that code will be warning.filter warnings, and in the uh brackets we will write ignore.
So uh the basic libraries which we will be needing are as follows import
numpy
as np.
Let's quickly copy this and proceed.
Enter.
And now we will be needing pandas as pd.
And now we will be needing c bond
as sns,
and we will also use matplotlib dot pyplot.
As PLT,
and after that, we will import warnings
from
IPython .dot _display,
import
clear
_output
.dot _filter _warnings,
ignore.
Now we'll just quickly run this query run and now we will proceed with feature engineering.
So you can use a hashtag to ignore that particular line from execution for Jupyter Notebook.
And here, we will be importing import RE
from
sklearn .dot .impute, import
simple impute
from sklearn .dot .model.
_selection,
import
k _fold.
There you go.
Now let's quickly run this query.
Now we will proceed with modeling and model evaluation.
Once we are done with this, then we will directly import the data into our notebook.
So for modeling the data, we will again use a hash code so that this particular line will not execute.
And import some libraries: L I G T GBM
as
L GP from Lite GBM, library,
import
LGBM regressor
from cat boost, import
cat boost regressor.
There you go. Let's quickly run this command.
There you go.
Now lastly, we have one more task before importing the data that is model evaluation. Once that is done, we can proceed with the importing the data.
There you go, let's quickly run it.
And now so far, so good. We have done the basic library imports, and feature engineering is done, modeling is done, and model evaluation is also done.
Now we can begin with importing the data.
So we let's also add
the HTML code where we have done this importing.
So here I will try to add another segment and I will import the HTML code here, which displays a similar HTML format which explains what exactly is happening here.
Just a moment.
I have the code ready. I'll just paste it here.
There you go. Let's quickly run this so that we have a HTML code here, a page here which explains what exactly is happening here.
So we are importing libraries and also student data.
Now let's import the student data. So that let's write the query.
So we are importing the data as data frame, and after that, we will write pandas readcsv.
Right, and here we will add the location of the file.
Right.
So the file is located in my downloads section.
So let's quickly copy that location and paste it here.
So this is the location of my file. Let's quickly run it.
So there might be some error.
It's okay. We can resolve it. So in such scenarios, you don't have to worry. Either you can add an R, but even if that doesn't work, you might have to change.
Uh in this case it worked, but in case if it doesn't work, what you can do is uh you can eliminate uh the R and you can just change this from uh
forward slash to backslash.
This will also help. So this could be worth it.
So this can also work. So these are the situations where you can use this now. Let's proceed with some more uh interesting facts. Let's try to understand what's going on with our uh dataset, right?
So what you can do is now the data is stored in df variable as a data frame.
So what you can do is read this particular data df dot shape so that you can understand what's the uh what's happening with this data,
right? So it can tell you that there are uh 600 and sorry, 6607 rows and 20 columns.
Now let's add another query part and here you can uh try to see the head right what head means basically head means uh the column headers.
So what you can do is just write df.head
and run.
Now you have the column headers and couple of sample columns.
Well, sorry, couple of sample rows.
Now let's proceed with uh checking the duplicates and identifying the total number of duplicate entries in this particular dataset.
So you can write down df dot
duplicated
dots
and you will get the number of duplicates present in this particular file.
So we have zero duplicate entries.
Now let's see if there are any null uh elements in this particular data frame.
So df.
is null
dots sum.
So these are all functions control enter.
There you go.
So in the column teacher quality, there are 78 null entries, and in parental educational level, there are 90 null entries, and distance from home there are uh
67 null entries.
Now, what we can do is uh from the okay, so from DF shape, we can add a new cell here and we can write a
HTML code so that the viewer can understand that we are trying to understand our data.
So let's write a quick code for that.
So let's not waste much time in just writing the HTML code. So I've got that HTML code written in a notepad already.
So I'll just paste it over here and let's quickly run it so that we have uh HTML visibility here.
So this was supposed to be the result, so we will add it here.
So what we will do is quickly edit this particular content, we'll just quickly copy this code and paste it over here.
Change the content from importing libraries to
reading
student data, and we will cut this code from here and we will paste it in here.
So that it gives you give us some information. Let's also run this particular code segment so that we have trading student data. There you go.
Now the next part of this session will be about creating a target variable.
So overall target of this particular data analysis is about exam score, right?
So we can name our target variable as exam score and let's understand the distribution of this particular exam score with
the variables we have.
Now let's write down plot dot figure.
Figure size should be around 15 comma nine
equals to let's add a bracket here 15 comma 9
or let's keep it as 6. 9 would be a little bigger.
Now enter.
Now we will use c bound library here, sns.count plot
x is equals to data frame clean the target.
Okay, uh before clean the target, we might have to run a few more.
Okay, we did not perform data cleaning so far, right?
So let's proceed with data cleaning so far. So we found some empty entries, right? Null entries, and we also found some. So here we have 299 rows which have missing values.
So we will have to remove that.
For that, uh we might have to create a new column which has to be named as not
assigned, right? df data frame not assigned, which is equals to df dot dropNA.
So we will be dropping the null values here, it's a function, and here let's print the values print df
dot df underscore hyper underscore na dot shape.
So how many number of rows and columns we have, right?
And after that, let's also try to eliminate the null values as well.
is null so we don't have basically we don't have null values, but we have uh some illegal entries maybe some
there you go.
Now let's quickly run this query.
So there you go. So the new data is about 678 comma 20.
So there is some okay. We did uh some mistake here.
So we are supposed to add it as null nun.
Now quickly run this so we should not get any errors this time.
There you go, no errors so far so good.
Now let's describe the new dataset dfna dot describe.
So these are the new columns and rows that we have,
and we have uh mean, standard variation, standard deviation, minimum, maximum.
So the scores are split into 25%, 50%, and 75%, which could be based on hours studied, which could be based on attendance,
sleep hours, previous course, tutoring sessions, everything.
So minimum sleep hours, maximum sleep hours, 25% of that, 50% of that, 75% of that.
So that is supposed to be the uh describe.
Now, what we will do is we have a target variable which is exam score, right?
Now we will do some changes to it.
We already know in an exam there will be a threshold value, it can be 25 marks per exam, it can be 50 marks per exam,
and it can be 100 marks per exam, right?
In our situation, let's consider the threshold value is 100 marks, right?
If there is a situation where marks is entered in a wrong way, right? It can be if they add if they wanted to add 11, but by mistake, if they added another one, right?
Triple one, it's not a right entry, right?
So we will try to eliminate those kind of data.
So we will create a new data frame here, which is data frame cleaned is equal to data frame underscore not
null. So it we have eliminated the null values df underscore na.
Now we will add our target variable which is exam score,
should be so let's come out of this, and here we will add it as should be less than or equal to 100,
but not more than 100.
Let's use square brackets
here. We also the format is square brackets actually. Actually,
now enter and
We will describe this particular
data set
instead of the FNA. We will copy paste this here.
Now let's run this.
Okay, exam score is not identified.
Let's quickly check the error and resolve it.
Yeah.
So we missed out to add colons here.
It's okay, not a problem.
So this was supposed to be how it is. Now let's run this and we will have the answer over here. So we have the output.
Now let's check the uh head of this particular thing dataset. So we can make use of the same code here and paste it right here.
And instead of describe, let's write head so that we have the header of uh this particular dataset. So we have our study and everything normal.
And we will categorize the data, right?
So we will make use of three columns: our study, attendance, and previous course.
and uh after that, we will also make use of other columns in this particular dataset, which happens to be the parental involvement, access to resources,
sleep hours, tutoring, sessions, etc.
And now, our target will be the exam score that we created over here.
right?
This exam score will be our target, and using this particular exam score target, we will categorize the data.
Okay, we will categorize the data in terms of uh let's say uh first class, uh second class, and uh
pass or something like that, right?
So if if a student is uh scoring below 64 and that is a separate category, if the score student is scoring equals to or above 65, that is a different category,
and if this uh student is scoring beyond 70, that's a different category.
And uh before we proceed with that, let's try to add a HTML code before this particular data set so that we have
an understanding of what exactly happened here.
So I let's uh let's I'll just quickly copy paste this particular code here.
So we will run it, and now next we will describe check the data type column separate and everything, and we will yeah create data type category variables.
Right now, so far so good.
Now we will create the categories.
So num call
equals to
hours study
comma
attendance.
So let's quickly add the data,
previous exam scores.
Just a minute, let's quickly add the columns. Let me take a while.
There you go, I have added the columns. So we are considering three different columns uh our study attendance and previous course for num call and for cat call.
We are considering the other columns apart from the first three, and our target value is
exam score. Let's quickly run this. There you go, and now we will try to build some visualizations, and before that, let's try to uh add
some data from in HTML.
Let's try to create a okay. What we can do is simply copy this particular HTML file here.
We can take this
and add it here so that we will understand what exactly is happening next.
And in place of reading student data, we will write data visualization for student data.
And we will keep the colors same dark blue background, and the color for data visualization will be light blue and student data will be orange.
Let's quickly run and there we have it.
Now our target variable is exam score, right?
Now we will compare this particular target variable with three other parameters.
So our parameters will be the following as we discussed uh creating the segregation in dataset, right?
So first will be distribution of target variable with other parameters.
So we will create another HTML file for that right here.
Just a minute while I paste the code for HTML.
Quickly run this.
There you go.
So distribution of target variable exam score against some parameters.
Now we will write the plot for that.figure.
So we are going to consider the size equals to 15,6
big size.
Is equals to 15 comma six, the same one that we considered before, and we will be using c1 sns dot
countplot
open bracket is a function x is equals to df
clean okay. Uh what we can do is just quickly take the column name so that we don't create any mistakes here, and we will paste it over here
instead of DF.
There you go, of target.
So our target is exam score.
Come up and we will use the palette as green,
and the plot title will be distribution of target variable exam score.
We can copy this, okay.
Just a minute before that PLD dot title
should be let's use double quotes now. Copy this and paste it here.
I think semicolons went off. Okay, not a problem.
It's right here.
Let's add a dot as a full stop and the next line.
If you need, you can add the full stop. If not, you can ignore
plt .dot _grid =True,
which
equals to major,
comma
axis is equal to y,
comma line _style equals to.
so I want lines to be hyphen -hyphen in this way. I want the lines
and comma line width uh let's say 0.5 or 0.7. Let's go with 0.7
line width
equals to 0.9 mm.
There you go. Now let's quickly run this query.
There you go, done.
And we have the first visualization.
So here you can see, there are some students which are scoring 58, 59, and you can see maximum number of students are already scoring good marks,
which is under 65, and uh, sorry, which is under 70 and above 65.
and there is a good number of students, uh, which are also scoring uh above, 65 as well. right?
So sorry, 70 70 as well. So we have no less than or equal to 70, 71, and highest scorer in some situations there is also 100.
If you can see there is slight growth here, there are a few students, stoppers maybe, which have already scored 100 as well.
Now we have the list here. Now we what we need to do is we need to segregate that is part one, which is less than or equal to 64, which falls under 65,
and another category which falls in between 65 to 70 and above 70.
So we need to categorize these three uh data and segregate them as bottom 65, top, which is above 70, and mid between 70 to 65.
Right now, before that, if you want to add an HTML document uh sorry, segment here which explains about the distribution of target,
you can also do that.
It's already added here now.
Let's continue.
But in case if you want to uh add uh some data which explains that we are trying to segregate, you can also do that.
I would like to do that.
Let's quickly uh add that HTML code here.
So, what this particular code will do is it will tell the percentage of students which are scoring less than 65, number of students uh percentage of students
uh scoring in between 65 and 70, and the percent of students which are scoring beyond 70.
Right, let's run this, and here we have the result.
Bottom 21.81% scores under 64, while 24% scores over 70 and 50% are in between 65 to 69.
Right now, let's uh continue with the segregation part of the data.
So for segregation, we will create three different variables a, b, c.
So, first a is equal to length of df cleaned. So let's copy the
column name, sorry, data frame name, length of df cleaned inside the square brackets. We'll again add df cleaned of target variable which is exam score.
Let's also add single quotes here.
Who are scoring in between or less than? Let's start with less than or equal to 64.
We will not consider 65, we'll consider 64 divided by len of tf cleaned target variable
exam score single quotes into 100.
Which will give us the percentage.
Now similarly, let's just copy and paste this three more times for B and C.
So here instead of minus we're supposed to add equals to,
and another one, so here equals to, and instead of A, I will write B and the last one is C, and instead of 64,
we will add 70 here for top, and here we will make some changes.
It should be greater than or equal to
65. So this is the third category a, b, c, and
then we will proceed with printing the files.
So print
the bottom
for the first one, which is f of
a,
is to dot to f,
and we will add the percentage symbol over here are under
64.
Now we can copy paste this same here and we can change the variables.
So here we will be adding the under over 70,
lastly in between the ones in between
65 and 70.
There you go.
Here we will change the values from A to B and here A to C.
There you go, and we can quickly run this query.
So it's not 70, it was supposed to be 69.
There you go.
So we forgot to mention this particular one.
Now let's run this.
There you go. So we have 21%
of people who are scoring under 64, 24% over 70, and 53% are in between average.
So I think the school is focusing on improving this particular percentage, reducing this particular percentage and increasing this particular percentage,
and try to eliminate if possible this particular one which are under 64.
So that is the overall motto, I guess.
Now, so far so good. Let's now try to remove infinite values from HTML.
Right? So before that, let's add this particular HTML code here. So which explains what we are trying to do.
So we will first implement the code that prevents warning about infinite values during data visualization.
And now let's add the code which will try to eliminate the infinite values. Let's copy this particular data frame cleaned
data frame name here.
Now dfcleaned dot replace
square brackets
np dot
info
comma
minus np
dot info out of these square brackets. dot np dot na
non n values, we are trying to eliminate n a values;
in place of those values, you can write True.
And after that, we will try to eliminate the null.
So if it is null
dot sum, give me the total number of null values after this, right?
So let's try to execute that. There you go.
So all the null entries have been removed here.
Now let's see the distribution of numerical values here.
So before that, let's add the HTML code for that.
So let's quickly run this.
So distribution of numerical values.
So we will be considering these three parameters.
So if you go back
here, you can see our studied attendance and previous course.
So we will be considering these three values or these three columns and check the distribution of these variables against
the exam score.
So uh is it making any um you know kind of variation if the uh attendance is high?
If if the attendance is high, is the exam score high?
And uh apart from that, we have if our studies is high, is the uh mark score is high, and if the previous scores are high,
is there a chance to get better scores in this particular exam?
So, what we are trying to do is we are trying to see if there is any direct involvement of number of study hours and number of uh days attended and number of uh
or the number of marks they received in the previous course, and we'll try to build a visualization on that front.
So let's go and build that. So we'll try the try to write the core here
figure access
equals to PLT
dot
subplots. So we will be having three different plots here since we are considering three different categories,
and the fixed size should be
equal to twelve comma four.
There you go.
Now,
is equals to access dot variable
for idx
comma call
in enumerate
call,
and we will try to import the c bound library. here.
We will try to create histoplots here, histograms here,
histoplot.
So line style we will be selecting this one
and the comma
line width will be zero point seven.
There you go.
Next will be access
IDX.
So for this we will be uh setting the title as distribution of columns.
So the columns will be the three uh ones attendance hours studied, and uh what was the third one that we considered
previous course, right?
So instead of mentioning them specifically, what we can do is we can just write columns here, C O L and close.
There you go.
And lastly,
plt.ite
and show the plot.
There you go. Let's quickly run this query.
Run and now we will be having the visualizations here.
So you can directly see the involvement of these three parameters here.
If they are trying to help, if the number of hours are increased, then you can see if there is a better improvement in scores, if the attendance is increased, if there is a better
moment in scores, or if the previous scores are helping, then you can find it out how it is.
There you go.
Now we can write a result here in the form of HTML page, and if we run this, it will give you the result.
The breaks or gaps in the our study variable may be due to the respondents answering appropriately.
The variables attendance and previous scores which exhibit a uniform distribution have a normal impact on exam scores variable, which is a target variable.
Now let's proceed with another part of this session, which will be about the relationship between the numerical values and the target variables.
Now we will copy-paste the same code and make some minute changes to it.
So the only change that we did to it is we are trying to build a scatter plot.
So we will be getting a scatter plot here, but before that, let's try to add another column here and try to add an HTML code which explains why we are doing it.
There you go.
A scatter plot. So basically, these two are one and the same.
Here we use some column graphs. So here we did the same using the scatter plot, which will help for a better understanding.
Now we will try to build some correlations.
So basically, a list is called correlation is created containing the names of the columns for which you want to calculate the correlation.
So here in our situation it is the DF.coR, which is a data frame, and it is created by selecting only these columns for DFclean
data frame, effectively created a new data frame containing only the specified columns.
Now the second one, which is the CORR, which is a calculate correlation.
So this method computes the correlation matrix for selected columns, which is in DFCORR.
The 1 indicates perfect positive correlation, minus 1 indicates the perfect negative correlation, and 0 indicates no correlation.
And lastly, the setup of plot.
This line sets up the figure size of the plot.
In this particular situation, we are choosing 5 and 4.
Right now, let's quickly try to execute this query and see the answer.
And we will also add the HTML code for this so that we have a better understanding for this.
So we will be adding that HTML
box here, which will explain what exactly happened here.
So this is our plot and this is the correlation.
Now let's try to add that HTML code right here.
The result of this particular data visualization will be maintained here.
So the hour study and attendance shows a positive correlationship with the target variable, which is exam sour.
However, previous course appears to have no or little relationship with the target variable.
Right now, let's continue with our next part of this session.
So now we will try to identify the relationship between studies,
hours, and attendance and extracurricular curricular scores.
So we have other
columns to consider, which is extracurricular activities.
So there is a belief that extracurricular activities will also help students to study better.
So we will find if there is a relation between the target variable and these extracurricular activities, attendance and study hours.
Now let's quickly add the code here.
Now let's quickly execute the code.
Now we have the visualization which explains the relationship between the number of hours studied, extracurricular activities, etc.
So here it is.
And now let's add an HTML code which explains about this result.
I think this particular code is supposed to be added here.
So this uh is the resultant column here.
Now here it explains about the influences that it performs.
So the extra collective activities, parental income, and extra things that influence the scores.
And there you go.
Now let us also consider other columns, right?
The other parameters like resources are available or not, parental education and other things which also might have influenced the exam scores of students.
So for that, let's add an HTML code so that we have an HTML page here which explains what is the next procedure that we are following, right?
Now let's add the query here.
So here we are considering the other parameters like family income, peer influence, motivation level, gender, parental involvement, parental educational level, and extracurricular activities.
And we are considering them against the target variable, which is exam score.
And now let's execute this query.
There you go. Now we have generated a graph which explains about this particular parameters against the target variable.
And now let's add the HTML page here which explains about these results.
Let's quickly run it.
And there you go.
So when certain factors affect Q1 and Q2, but not Q2, it can be understood that individual has overcome challenges through personal effort, right?
So if government policies and corporate social contributors are focused on addressing these aspects, it seems that we could create a dynamic country with
greater social mobility and open opportunities for all, right?
So if extracurricular activities can outweigh the influence of other variables in academic performance, then we should foster that kind of an environment, right?
So this is how uh you can get extract some statistical analysis on this particular dataset.
Now let's quickly rename this uh Python
EDA
students
performance.
And you can quickly
say it.
Hello everyone.
In this session, we will cover all the important supervised and unsupervised learning algorithms that are widely used with hands-on demonstrations in Python.
Our instructors with rich experience in machine learning will take us through this course.
But before we begin, make sure to subscribe to the Simply Learn channel and hit the bell icon to never miss an update.
So we will start by understanding the basics of machine learning from a short animated video, followed by the difference between supervised and unsupervised learning.
We will then jump into learning the various algorithms from scratch.
So we will understand linear regression, logistic regression, decision tree, and random forest.
We'll then look at support vector machines and k-nearest neighbor algorithm with a hands-on demonstration in Python.
Finally, we'll get an idea about unsupervised learning algorithms such as k means clustering and principal component analysis.
We will conclude this session with regularization in machine learning.
So let's get started.
We know humans learn from their past experiences and machines follow instructions given by humans.
But what if humans can train the machines to learn from their past data and do what humans can do and much faster? Well, that's called machine learning.
But it's a lot more than just learning, it's also about understanding and reasoning. So today we will learn about the basics of machine learning. So that's Paul. He loves listening to new songs.
He either likes them or dislikes them. Paul decides this on the basis of the song's tempo, genre, intensity, and the gender of voice. For simplicity, let's just use tempo and intensity for now.
So here, tempo is on the x-axis ranging from relaxed to fast, whereas intensity is on the y axis ranging from light to soaring.
We see that Paul likes the song with fast tempo and soaring intensity, while he dislikes the song with relaxed tempo
and light intensity. So now we know Paul's choices. Let's say Paul listens to a new song. Let's name it as song A. Song A has fast tempo and a soaring intensity. So it lies somewhere here.
Looking at the data, can you guess whether Paul will like the song or not? Correct. So Paul likes this song.
By looking at Paul's past choices, we were able to classify the unknown song very easily, right? Let's say Now, Paul listens to a new song. Let's label it as song B.
So song B lies somewhere here with medium tempo and medium intensity. Neither relaxed nor fast, neither light nor soaring. Now can you guess whether Paul likes it or not?
Not able to guess whether Paul will like it or dislike it? Are the choices unclear? Correct. We could easily classify song A.
But when the choice became complicated, as in the case of song B, yes, and that's where machine learning comes in. Let's see how.
In the same example, for song B, if you draw a circle around the song B, we see that there are four votes for like, whereas one vote for dislike.
If we go for the majority votes, we can say that Paul will definitely like the song. That's all. This was a basic machine learning algorithm also. It's called K nearest neighbours.
So this is just a small example in one of the many machine learning algorithms. Quite easy, right? Believe me, it is. But what happens when the choices become complicated? As in the case of song B.
That's when machine learning comes in. It learns the data, builds a prediction model, and when the new data point comes in, it can easily predict for it.
More the data, better the model, higher will be the accuracy. There are many ways in which the machine learns. It could be either supervised learning, unsupervised learning, or reinforcement learning.
Let's first quickly understand supervised learning. Suppose your friend gives you 1 million coins of three different currencies, say 1 rupee, 1 euro, and 1 dirham. Each coin has different weights.
For example, a coin of 1 rupee weighs 3 grams, 1 euro weighs 7 grams, and 1 dirham weighs 4 grams. Your model will predict the currency of the coin.
Here, your weight becomes the feature of coins, while currency becomes their label. When you feed this data to the machine learning model, it learns which feature is associated with which label.
For example, it will learn that if a coin is of 3 grams, it will be a 1 rupee coin. Let's give a new coin to the machine.
On the basis of the weight of the new coin, your model will predict the currency. Hence, supervised learning uses labeled data to train the model.
Here the machine knew the features of the object and also the labels associated with those features. On this note, let's move to unsupervised learning and see the difference.
Suppose you have a cricket dataset of various players with their respective scores and the wickets taken.
When we feed this data set to the machine, the machine identifies the pattern of player performance. So it plots this data with the respective wickets on the x-axis while runs on the y axis.
While looking at the data, you will clearly see that there are two clusters.
The one cluster are the players who scored high runs and took less wickets, while the other cluster is of the players who scored less runs but took many wickets.
So here we interpret these two clusters as batsmen and bowlers. The important point to note here is that there were no labels of batsmen and bowlers.
Hence, the learning with unlabeled data is unsupervised learning. So we saw supervised learning where the data was labeled and the unsupervised learning where the data was unlabeled.
And then there is reinforcement learning, which is reward-based learning. Or we can say that it works on the principle of feedback.
Here, let's say you provide the system with an image of a dog and ask it to identify it. The system identifies it as a cat.
So you give a negative feedback to the machine saying that it's a dog's image.
The machine will learn from the feedback and finally, if it comes across any other image of a dog, it will be able to classify it correctly. That is reinforcement learning.
To generalize machine learning model, let's see a flowchart. Input is given to a machine learning model, which then gives the output according to the algorithm applied.
If it's right, we take the output as our final result. Else we provide feedback to the training model and ask it to predict until it learns.
I hope you've understood supervised and unsupervised learning. So let's have a quick quiz. You have to determine whether the given scenarios uses supervised or unsupervised learning. Simple, right?
Scenario 1. Facebook recognizes your friend in a picture from an album of tagged photographs. Scenario 2. Netflix recommends new movies based on someone's past movie choices.
Scenario 3 Analyzing bank data for suspicious transactions and flagging the fraud transactions. Think wisely and comment below your answers.
Moving on, don't you sometimes wonder how is machine learning possible in today's era? That's because today we have humongous data available.
Everybody is online, either making a transaction or just surfing the internet, and that's generating a huge amount of data every minute. And that data, my friend, is the key to analysis.
Also, the memory handling capabilities of computers have largely increased, which helps them to process such a huge amount of data at hand without any delay.
And yes, computers now have great computational powers. So there are a lot of applications of machine learning out there.
To name a few, machine learning is used in healthcare where diagnostics are predicted for doctor's review.
The sentiment analysis that the tech giants are doing on social media is another interesting application of machine learning, fraud detection in the finance sector,
and also to predict customer journal in the e-commerce sector. While booking a gap, you must have encountered search pricing often where it says the fare of your trip has been updated.
Continue booking. Yes please, I'm getting late for office.
Well, that's an interesting machine learning model which is used by global taxi giant Uber and others, where they have differential pricing in real time based on demand,
the number of cars available, bad weather, rush hour, etc. So they use the search pricing model to ensure that those who need a cab can get one.
Also, it uses predictive modeling to predict where the demand will be high, with the goal that drivers can take care of the demand and search pricing can be minimized. Great.
Hey Siri, can you remind me to book a cab at 6 pm today? Okay, I'll remind you. Thanks. No problem.
Comment below some interesting everyday examples around you, where machines are learning and doing amazing jobs.
Hi guys, this is Apexha from Simply Learn, and we are going to talk about the two types of machine learning, supervised and unsupervised learning.
Their types and applications.
But before we talk about them, let's quickly understand what is machine learning.
These days applications use artificial intelligence in machine learning to optimize speech recognition.
I usually ask Siri things I want to know, like hey Siri, how far is the nearest subway?
So whenever we ask something to Siri, a powerful speech recognition kicks off and converts the audio into its corresponding textual form,
which is then sent to the Apple servers for further processing.
Then neural language processing algorithms are run to understand the user's intent.
And then finally, Siri tells you the answer.
Well, this is what machine learning is all about.
Making the machines learn and act like humans by feeding them with data and information without being explicitly programmed.
As we saw in the previous example, when the data comes in, machines immediately start analyzing the data and eventually gets trained on it and learns it.
Now, when a new data point comes in, a machine accurately makes predictions and decisions based on the past data.
Now that you know what is machine learning, let's talk about supervised and unsupervised learning.
Supervised learning, as the name suggests, works under supervision, that is, it's a learning in which machine is trained with data which is well labeled
and then it predicts with the help of the labeled dataset.
But what is a labeled dataset?
Data for which you already know the target answer is called a labeled data.
Like I show you an image and tell you that it's a dog, then it's a label data.
While if I show you an image without telling you what exactly it is, then it's an unlabeled data.
Now let's say we have images which are labeled as spoon or knife.
We then feed it to the machine, which analyzes and learns the association of these images with its labels based on its features such as shape,
size, sharpness, etc.
But now, when a new image is fed to the machine without any label.
with the help of the past data, the machine is able to predict accurately and tell that it's a spoon.
Hence in supervised machine learning, the algorithm teaches the model how to learn from the label example that we provide.
So supervised learning can be further divided into classification and regression.
It is a classification problem when the output variable is categoric, such as red or blue, disease or no disease, male or female.
Whereas it's a regression problem when the output variable is a real or continuous value.
For example, salary based on work experience, weight based on height. So it creates a predictive model showing trends and data.
So now if I say will I get a salary raise or not, that's classification.
But if I say how much salary raise will I get, that is regression.
Now let's understand classification with the help of an example.
In order to predict whether an email is a spam or not, first we need to teach our machine what a spam mail looks like.
This is done based on a lot of spam filters, like firstly reviewing the content of the email, then review the email header and search if it contains any falsified information.
This is done based on some keywords like free, lottery, price claim, etc.
Then, general blacklist filters to stop emails that come from already blacklisted, known spammers and etc.
So. all these filters score the email, which is known as spam score.
The lower the total spam score of the email, it is more likely that the email will land in subscribers inboxes.
So based on the content, labels and spam score of the new incoming mail, the algorithm decides whether it should land in
inbox or the spam folder.
Now let's quickly understand regression.
So let's say we have two variables, that is temperature and humidity, where temperature is the independent variable and humidity is the dependent variable,
such that as the temperature increases, humidity decreases.
Hence, they are correlated.
When we feed this data to a regression model, it will understand the relationship between these two variables and how one variable depends on the other.
After the machine is trained, it can easily predict the humidity based on the given temperature.
Well, that was about regression.
Now let's see some real life applications where supervised learning is used.
So supervised learning is used in risk assessment to assess risk in financial services or in insurance domain to minimize the risk portfolio of the companies.
Image classification.
Facebook recognizes your friend in a picture from an album of tag photos.
So image classification is one of the key use cases of demonstrating supervised machine learning algorithms.
Obviously, a lot more goes into all these, like convolutional neural networks, etc.
Fraud detection, whether the transactions made by the user are authentic or not.
And visual recognition, the ability of a machine learning model to identify objects, places, people, and actions and images.
Now let's quickly talk about unsupervised learning.
In unsupervised learning, there is no supervision, that is, no training will be given to the machine allowing it to act on the data which is not labeled.
Hence, machine tries to identify patterns and gives the response.
Let's take a similar example as before.
But this time we do not tell the machine whether it's a spoon or a knife.
The machine identifies patterns from the given set and groups them based on their patterns, similarities, etc.
Again, unsupervised learning can be further grouped into clustering and association.
Clustering is basically where the machine forms groups based on the behavior of the data.
Secondly, association.
It is a rule-based machine learning to discover interesting relations between variables in large datasets.
For example, which customer made similar product purchases is clustering, whereas association is which products were purchased together.
Now, let's understand clustering with the help of an example.
To reduce their churn rate, a telecom company studies the behavior of the customers based on average call duration and internet usage and observes that while some customers'
call duration is quite high, others have heavy internet usage.
The customers are grouped based on their observed behavior and a strategy is adopted to minimize churn rate and maximize profit via suitable promotions and campaigns.
As you can see in the chart on the right hand side, customers in group A use more data and also have high call duration.
Group B customers are heavy internet users, while group C customers have high call duration.
So Group B will be given more data benefit plans, while group C will be given cheaper call rates to buy their loyalty.
So this was the example of clustering.
Now let's understand association with another example.
Let's say customer 1 goes to a supermarket and buys these products, say bread, milk, fruits, wheat.
Then customer 2 goes and buys bread, milk, rice and butter.
Now, when customer 3 goes and buys bread, it is highly likely that he will also buy milk.
Hence, relationship is established based on customer behavior and recommendations are made.
Now let's look at some real life applications of unsupervised learning.
Market basket analysis is a machine learning model based on the algorithm that if you buy a certain group of items, you are less or more likely to buy another group of items.
Semantic clustering.
Semantically similar words share similar context.
People post their queries on websites in their own ways.
Semantic clustering groups all responses in a cluster with same meaning to ensure that the customer finds the information they want quickly and easily.
It plays an important role in information retrieval, good browsing experience and comprehension.
Delivery store optimization.
Machine learning models are used to predict the demand and keep up with the supply.
Also, to open stores where demand is more and optimizing routes for more efficient deliveries according to past data and behavior.
We can also use unsupervised machine learning models to identify accident prone areas based on the intensity of those accidents and the area in order to introduce safety measures.
By now I hope you've understood supervised and unsupervised learning.
For a quick recap, let's see a few differences between the two.
The most fundamental difference is that supervised learning uses known and labeled data and unsupervised learning uses unlabeled data as their input.
Secondly, supervised learning follows a feedback mechanism, while unsupervised learning does not.
Also, the most commonly used algorithms in supervised learning are decision tree, logistic regression, support vector machine, etc.
And in unsupervised learning, there k-means clustering, hierarchical clustering, a priori algorithm, and many more. Welcome to linear regression.
My name is Richard Kirschner. I'm with Simply Learn.
Let's look at an example of a common use for linear regression.
Profit estimation of a company.
If I was going to invest in a company, I would like to know how much money I could expect to make.
So we'll take a look at a venture capitalist firm and try to understand which companies they should invest in.
So we'll take the idea that we need to decide the companies to invest in.
We need to predict the profit the company makes, and we're going to do it based on the company's expenses, and even just a specific expense.
In this case, we have our company, we have the different expenses, so we have our RD, which is your research and development, we have our marketing,
we might have the location, we might have what kind of administration it's going through. Based on all this different information, we would like to calculate the profit.
Now in actuality, there's usually about 23 to 27 different markers that they look at if they're a heavy-duty investor.
We're only going to take a look at one basic one.
We're going to come in and for simplicity, let's consider a single variable RD and find out which companies to invest in based on that.
So we take our RD and we're plotting the profit based on the RD expenditure, how much money they put into the research and development, and then we look at the profit that goes with that.
We can predict a line to estimate the profit. So we can draw a line right through the data.
And when you look at that, you can see how much they invest in the RD as a good marker as to how much profit they're going to have.
We can also note that companies spending more on RD make good profit.
So let's invest in the ones that spend a higher rate in their RD. What's in it for you?
First, we'll have an introduction to machine learning, followed by machine learning algorithms. These will be specific to linear regression and where it fits into the larger model.
Then we'll take a look at applications of linear regression, understanding linear regression, and multiple linear regression.
Finally, we'll roll up our sleeves and do a little programming in use case profit estimation of companies.
Let's go ahead and jump in.
Let's start with our introduction to machine learning, along with some machine learning algorithms and where that fits in with linear regression.
Let's look at another example of machine learning.
Based on the amount of rainfall, how much would be the crop yield?
So here we have our crops, we have our rainfall, and we want to know how much we're going to get from our crops this year. So we're going to introduce two variables, independent and dependent.
The independent variable is a variable whose value does not change by the effect of other variables and is used to manipulate the dependent variable.
It is often denoted as x. In our example, rainfall is the independent variable.
This is a wonderful example because you can easily see that we can't control the rain, but the rain does control the crop.
So when we talk about the independent variable controlling a dependent variable, let's define dependent variable as a variable whose value change when there
is any manipulation in the values of the independent variables.
It is often denoted as y. And you can see here our crop yield is dependent variable, and it is dependent on the amount of rainfall received.
Now that we've taken a look at a real life example, let's go a little bit into the theory and some definitions on machine learning and see how that fits together with linear regression.
Numerical and categorical values.
Let's take our data coming in, and this is kind of random data from any kind of project.
We want to divide it up into numerical and categorical.
So numerical is numbers, age, salary, height, where categorical would be a description, the color,
a dog's breed, gender.
Categorical is limited to very specific items where numerical is a range of information.
Now that you've seen the difference between numerical and categorical data, let's take a look at some different machine learning definitions.
When we look at our different machine learning algorithms, we can divide them into three areas supervised, unsupervised, reinforcement.
We're only going to look at supervised today.
Unsupervised means we don't have the answers and we're just grouping things.
Reinforcement is where we give positive and negative feedback to our algorithm to program it, and it doesn't have the information until after the fact.
But today we're just looking at supervised because that's where linear regression fits in.
In supervised data, we have our data already there and our answers for a group, and then we use that to program our model and come up with an answer.
The two most common uses for that is through the regression and classification.
Now we're doing linear regression, so we're just going to focus on the regression side.
And in the regression, we have simple linear regression, we have multiple linear regression, and we have polynomial linear regression.
Now on these three, simple linear regression is the examples we've looked at so far where we have a lot of data and we draw a straight line through it.
Multiple linear regression means we have multiple variables. Remember where we had the rainfall and the crops?
We might add additional variables in there like how much food do we give our crops?
When do we harvest them?
Those would be additional information added into our model. And that's why it'd be multiple linear regression.
And finally we have polynomial linear regression. That is, instead of drawing a line, we can draw a curved line through it.
Now that you see where regression model fits into the machine learning algorithms, and we're specifically looking at linear regression,
let's go ahead and take a look at applications for linear regression.
Let's look at a few applications of linear regression.
Economic growth, used to determine the economic growth of a country or a state in the coming quarter, can also be used to predict the GDP of a country.
Product price can be used to predict what would be the price of a product in the future.
We can guess whether it's going to go up or down or should I buy today.
Housing sales to estimate the number of houses a builder would sell and what price in the coming months.
Score predictions. Cricket fever to predict the number of runs a player would score in the coming matches based on the previous performance.
I'm sure you can figure out other applications you could use linear regression for. So let's jump in and let's understand linear regression and dig into the theory.
Understanding linear regression.
Linear regression is the statistical model used to predict the relationship between independent and dependent variables by examining two factors.
The first important one is which variables in particular are significant predictors of the outcome variable.
And the second one that we need to look at closely is how significant is the regression line to make predictions with the highest possible accuracy.
If it's inaccurate, we can't use it.
So it's very important we find out the most accurate line we can get.
Since linear regression is based on drawing a line through data, We're going to jump back and take a look at some Euclidean geometry.
The simplest form of a simple linear regression equation with one dependent and one independent variable is represented by y equals m
times x plus c.
And if you look at our model here, we plotted two points on here, x1 and y1, x2 and y2.
y being the dependent variable, remember that from before, and x being the independent variable.
So y depends on whatever x is.
m in this case is the slope of the line where m equals the difference in the y2 minus y1 and x2
minus x1.
And finally we have c which is the coefficient of the line, or where happens to cross the zero axes.
Let's go back and look at an example we used earlier of linear regression.
We're going to go back to plotting the amount of crop yield based on the amount of rainfall.
And here we have our rainfall.
Remember we cannot change rainfall, and we have our crop yield, which is dependent on the rainfall.
So we have our independent and our dependent variables.
We're going to take this and draw a line through it as best we can through the middle of the data.
And then we look at that, we put the red point on the y-axis is the amount of crop yield you can expect for the amount of rainfall represented by the green dot.
So if we have an idea what the rainfall is for this year and what's going on, then we can guess how good our crops are going to be.
And we've created a nice line right through the middle to give us a nice mathematical formula.
Let's take a look and see what the math looks like behind this.
Let's look at the intuition behind the regression line.
Now, before we dive into the math and the formulas that go behind this and what's going on behind the scenes,
I want you to note that when we get into the case study and we actually apply some Python script, that this math that you're going to see here is already done automatically for you.
You don't have to have it memorized.
It is, however, good to have an idea what's going on, so if people reference the different terms, you'll know what they're talking about.
Let's consider a sample data set with five rows and find out how to draw the regression line.
We're only going to do five rows because if we did like the rainfall with hundreds of points of data, that would be very hard to see what's going on with the mathematics.
So we'll go ahead and create our own two sets of data.
And we have our independent variable x and our dependent variable y.
And when x was one, we got y equals two.
When x was uh two, y was four, and so on and so on.
If we go ahead and plot this data on a graph, we can see how it forms a nice line through the middle.
You can see where it's kind of grouped going upwards to the right.
The next thing we want to know is what the means is of each of the data coming in, the x and the y.
The means doesn't mean anything other than the average.
So we add up all the numbers and divide by the total. So one plus two plus three plus four plus five over five equals three.
And the same for y, we get four.
If we go ahead and plot the means on the graph, we'll see we get three, four, which draws a nice line down the middle.
A good estimate.
Here we're gonna dig deeper into the math behind the regression line.
Now remember before I said you don't have to have all these formulas memorized or fully understand them, even though we're gonna go into a little more detail of how it works.
And if you're not a math whiz and you don't know if you've never seen the sigma character before, which looks a little bit like an e that's opened up,
that just means summation.
That's all that is.
So when you see the sigma character, it just means we're adding everything in that row.
And for computers this is great, because as a programmer, you can easily iterate through each of the xy points and create all the information you need.
So in the top half you can see where we've broken that down into pieces, and as it goes through the first two points, it computes the squared value of x, the squared value of y,
and x times y.
And then it takes all of x and adds them up, all of y adds them up, all of x squared adds them up, and so on and so on, and you can see we have the sum of equal to 15,
the sum is equal to 20, all the way up to x times y where the sum equals 66.
This all comes from our formula for calculating a straight line where y equals the slope times x plus the coefficient c.
So we go down below and we're going to compute more like the averages of these, and we're going to explain exactly what that is in just a minute and where that information comes from
is called the square means error.
But we'll go into that in detail in a few minutes. All you need to do is look at the formula and see how we've gone about computing it line by line instead of trying to have a huge.
set of numbers pushed into it.
And down here you'll see where the slope m equals, and in the top part if you read through the brackets, you have the number of data points times the sum
of x times y, which we computed one line at a time there, and that's just the 66.
And take all that and you subtract it from the sum of x times the sum of y.
And those have both been computed. So you have 15 times 20.
And on the bottom we have the number of lines times the sum of x squared, easily computed as eighty six for the sum, minus,
I'll take all that and subtract, the sum of x squared.
And we end up, as we come across with our formula, you can plug in all those numbers, which is very easy to do on the computer.
You don't have to do the math on a piece of paper or calculator, and you'll get a slope of 0.6.
And you'll get your c coefficient.
If you continue to follow through that formula, you'll see it comes out as equal to 2.2.
Continuing deeper into what's going behind the scenes, let's find out the predicted values of y for corresponding values of x using the linear equation where m equals 0.6
and c equals 2.2.
We're going to take these values and we're going to go ahead and plot them.
We're going to predict them so y equals 0.6 times or x equals 1 plus 2 point two equals 2 point eight, so on and so on.
And here the blue points represent the actual y values and the brown points represent the predicted y values based on the model we created.
The distance between the actual and predicted values is known as residuals or errors.
The best fit line should have the least sum of squares of these errors, also known as e square.
If we put these into a nice chart where you can see x and you can see y, what we actual values were, and you can see y predict it, you can easily see where we take y minus y
predict it and we get an answer. What is the difference between those two?
And if we square that, y minus y prediction squared, we can then sum those squared values.
That's where we get the 0.64 plus the 0.36 plus 1 all the way down until we have a summation equals 2.4.
So the sum of squared errors for this regression line is 2.4.
We check this error for each line and conclude the best fit line having the least e square value.
In a nice graphical representation we can see here where we keep moving this line through the data points to make sure the best fit line has the least squared distance between the data points
and the regression line.
Now we only looked at the most commonly used formula for minimizing the distance.
There are lots of ways to minimize the distance between the line and the data points. like sum of squared errors, sum of absolute errors, root mean square error, etc.
What you want to take away from this is: whatever formula is being used.
you can easily using a computer programming and iterating through the data calculate the different parts of it.
That way these complicated formulas you see with the different summations and absolute values are easily computed one piece at a time.
Up until this point we've only been looking at two values x and y. Well in the real world it's very rare that you only have two values when you're figuring out a solution.
So let's move on to the next topic multiple linear regression. Let's take a brief look at what happens when you have multiple inputs.
So in multiple linear regression we have uh well we'll start with the simple linear regression where we had y equals m plus x plus c and we're trying to find the value of y.
Now with multiple linear regression we have multiple variables coming in.
So instead of having just x we have x1 x2 x3 and instead of having just one slope each variable has its own slope attached to it.
As you can see here we have m1 m2 m3 and we still just have the single coefficient.
So when you're dealing with multiple linear regression you basically take your single linear regression and you spread it out.
So you have y equals m1 times x1 plus m2 times x2 so on all the way to m to the nth x to the nth
and then you add your coefficient on there. Implementation of linear regression. Now we get into my favorite part.
Let's understand how multiple linear regression works by implementing it in Python.
If you remember before we were looking at a company and just based on its RD trying to figure out its profit we're going to start looking at the expenditure of the company
we're going to go back to that and we're going to predict its profit.
But instead of predicting it just on the RD we're going to look at other factors like administration costs, marketing costs, and so on.
And from there we're going to see if we can figure out what the profit of that company is going to be.
To start our coding we're going to begin by importing some basic libraries.
And we're going to be looking through the data before we do any kind of linear regression.
We're going to take a look at the data to see what we're playing with Then we'll go ahead and format the data to the format we need to be able to run it in the linear regression model.
And then from there we'll go ahead and solve it and just see how valid our solution is.
So let's start with importing the basic libraries.
Now I'm going to be doing this in Anaconda Jupyter Notebook, a very popular IDE.
I enjoy it because it's such a visual to look at and so easy to use.
Just any IDE for Python will work just fine for this.
So break out your favorite Python IDE.
So here we are in our Jupyter Notebook.
Let me go ahead and paste our first piece of code in there.
And let's walk through what libraries we're importing. First, we're going to import NUMPy as NP, and then I want you to skip one line and look at import pandas as PD.
These are very common tools that you need with most of your linear regression.
The NUMPY, which stands for number python, is usually denoted as np, and you have to almost have that for your SK Learn Toolbox. So you always import that right off the beginning.
Pandas, although you don't have to have it for your sklearn libraries, it does such a wonderful job of importing data, setting it up into a data frame so we can manipulate it rather easily.
And it has a lot of tools also in addition to that. So we usually like to use the pandas when we can, and I'll show you what that looks like.
The other three lines are for us to get a visual of this data and take a look at it.
So we're going to import mapplotlibrary.pyplot as plt and then cborn as sns.
cborn works with the mapplot library.
So you have to always import mapplot library and then cborn sits on top of it.
And we'll take a look at what that looks like.
You could use any of your own plotting libraries you want. There's all kinds of ways to look at the data.
These are just very common ones, and the cborne is so easy to use that it just looks beautiful. It's a nice representation that you can actually take and show somebody.
And the final line is the Ambersigned Mapplot Library inline.
That is only because I'm doing an inline IDE.
My interface in the Anaconda Jupyter Notebook requires I put that in there, or you're not going to see the graph when it comes up.
Let's go ahead and run this. It's not going to be that interesting because we're just setting up variables.
In fact, it's not going to do anything that we can see, but it is importing these different libraries and setup.
The next step is load the data set and extract independent and dependent variables.
Now, here in the slide you'll see companies equals pd.readcsv and it has a long line there with the file at the end, 1000 companies.csv.
You're going to have to change this to fit whatever setup you have.
And the file itself you can request.
Just go down to the commentary below this video and put a note in there, and Simply Learn will try to get in contact with you and supply you with that file so you can try this coding yourself.
So we're going to add this code in here, and we're going to see that I have companies equals pd.reader underscore csv.
And I've changed this path to match my computer, c colon slash simply learn slash 1000 underscore companies.csv.
And then below there we're going to set the X equals to companies under the ILocation.
And because this is companies is a PD dataset, I can use this nice notation that says take every row, that's what the colon, the first colon is,
comma, except for the last column.
That's what the second part is, where we have a colon minus one, and we want the values set into there.
So x is no longer a data set, a pandas data set. But we can easily extract the data from our pandas data set with this notation.
And then y we're going to set equal to the last row.
Well, the question is going to be what are we actually looking at?
So let's go ahead and take a look at that.
And we're going to look at the companies.head, which lists the first five rows of data.
And I'll open up the file in just a second so you can see where that's coming from.
But let's look at the data in here as far as the way the pandas sees it. When I hit run, you'll see it breaks it out into a nice setup.
This is what pandas, one of the things pandas is really good about, is it looks just like an Excel spreadsheet.
You have your rows. And remember, when we're programming, we always start with zero. We don't start with one.
So it shows the first five rows.
01234 and then it shows your different columns R and D spend, administration, marketing spend, state,
profit.
It even notes that the top are column names.
It was never told that, but Pandas is able to recognize a lot of things that they're not the same as the data rows.
Why don't we go ahead and open this file up in a CSV so you can actually see the raw data?
So here I've opened it up as a text editor, and you can see at the top we have RND spend, comma, administration, comma, marketing, spin, comma,
state, comma, profit, carriage return.
I don't know about you, but I'd go crazy trying to read files like this.
That's why we use the pandas.
You could also open this up in an Excel and it would separate it since it is a comma separated variable file.
But we don't want to look at this one, we want to look at something we can read rather easily. So let's flip back and take a look at that top part, the first five rows.
Now, as nice as this format is where I can see the data, to me it doesn't mean a whole lot.
Maybe you're an expert in business and investments and you understand what $165,349.20
compared to the administration cost of $136,897.80, so on so on, helps to create the profit of $192,261.83.
That makes no sense to me whatsoever.
No pun intended.
So let's flip back here and take a look at our next set of code where we're gonna graph it so we can get a better understanding of our data and what it means.
So at this point, we're gonna use a single line of code to get a lot of information so we can see where we're going with this.
Let's go ahead and paste that into our uh notebook and see what we got going.
And so we have the visualization, and again we're using SNS, which is pandas.
As you can see, we imported the mapplot library.py plot as plt, which then the cborne uses.
And we imported the cborne as SNS.
And then that final line of code helps us show this in our inline coding.
Without this, it wouldn't display, and you can display it to a file and other means.
And that's the mapplot library inline with the amber sign at the beginning.
So here we come down to the single line of code.
Cborne is great because it actually recognizes the panda data frame.
So I can just take the companies.core for coordinates, and I can put that right into the Cborne.
And when we run this, we get this beautiful plot.
And let's just take a look at what this plot means.
If you look at this plot on mine, the colors are probably a little bit more purplish and blue than the original one.
Uh we have the columns and the rows. We have R and D spending, we have administration, we have marketing spending and profit.
And if you cross-index any two of these, since we're interested in profit, if you cross-index profit with profit, it's gonna show up, if you look at the scale on the right,
way up in the dark.
Why? Because those are the same data, they have an exact correspondence.
So RD spending is gonna be the same as RD spending, and the same thing with administration costs.
So right down the middle, you get this dark row or dark um diagonal row that shows that this is the highest corresponding data
that's exactly the same.
And as it becomes lighter, there's less connections between the data.
So we can see with profit, obviously profit is the same as profit, and next it has a very high correlation with RD spending, which we looked at earlier,
and it has a slightly less connection to marketing spending, and even less to how much money we put into the administration.
So now that we have a nice look at the data, let's go ahead and dig in and create some actual useful linear regression models so that we can predict values and have a better profit.
Now that we've taken a look at the visualization of this data, we're gonna move on to the next step.
Instead of just having a pretty picture, we need to generate some hard data, some hard values.
So let's see what that looks like.
We're gonna set up our linear regression model in two steps.
The first one is we need to prepare some of our data so it fits correctly.
And let's go ahead and paste this code into our Jupyter Notebook.
And what we're bringing in is we're gonna bring in the SKLearn pre-processing where we're gonna import the label encoder and the one hot encoder.
To use the label encoder, we're gonna create a variable called label encoder and set it equal to capital L label, capital E encoder.
This creates a class that we can reuse for transferring the labels back and forth.
Now about now you should ask what labels are we talking about?
Let's go take a look at the data we processed before and see what I'm talking about here.
If you remember when we did the companies.
We have column zero, which is RD spending, column one, which is administration.
Column two, which is marketing spending, and column three is state, and you'll see under state we have New York, California, Florida.
Now, to do a linear regression model, it doesn't know how to process New York, it knows how to process a number.
So the first thing we're gonna do is we're gonna change that New York, California, and Florida, and we're gonna change those to numbers. That's what this line of code does here.
X equals, and then it has the colon, comma three in brackets.
The first part, the colon comma, means that we're gonna look at all the different rows. So we're gonna keep them all together. But the only row we're gonna edit is the third row.
And in there we're gonna take the label coder and we're gonna fit and transform the X, also the third row. So we're gonna take that third row, we're gonna set it equal to a transformation.
And that transformation basically tells it that instead of having a uh New York, it has a zero or a one or a two.
And then finally we need to do a one hot encoder, which equals one hot encoder categorical features equals three.
And then we take the X and we go ahead and do that equal to one hot encoder fit transform X to array.
This final transformation preps our data for us so it's completely set the way we need it as just a row of numbers.
Even though it's not in here, let's go ahead and print x and just take a look at what this data is doing.
You'll see you have an array of arrays, and then each array is a row of numbers.
And if I go ahead and just do row zero, you'll see I have a nice organized row of numbers that the computer now understands.
We'll go ahead and take this out there because it doesn't mean a whole lot to us, it's just a row of numbers.
Next, on setting up our data, we have avoiding dummy variable trap.
This is very important.
Why?
Because the computer has automatically transformed our header into the setup, and it's automatically transformed all these different variables.
So when we did the encoder, the encoder created two columns. And what we need to do is just have the one because it has both the variable and the name.
That's what this piece of code does here.
Let's go ahead and paste this in here, and we have x equals x colon, comma, one colon.
All this is doing is removing that one extra column we put in there when we did our one hot encoder and our label encoding.
Let's go ahead and run that.
And now we get to create our linear regression model.
And let's see what that looks like here. And we're going to do that in two steps.
The first step is going to be in splitting the data.
Now, whenever we create a predictive model of data, we always want to split it up so we have a training set and we have a testing set.
That's very important. Otherwise, we'd be very unethical without testing it to see how good our fit is.
And then we'll go ahead and create our multiple linear regression model and train it and set it up.
Let's go ahead and paste this next piece of code in here. And I'll go ahead and shrink it down a size or two so it all fits on one line.
So from the sklearn module selection, we're going to import train test split.
And you'll see that we've created four completely different variables. We have capital X train, capital X test, smaller case y train, smaller case y test.
That is the standard way that they usually reference these when we're doing different models.
Usually you see that a capital X, and you see the train and the test and the lowercase y.
What this is, is X is our data going in.
That's our R and D spin, our administration, our marketing. And then Y, which we're training, is the answer. That's the profit. Because we want to know the profit of an unknown entity.
So that's what we're going to shoot for in this tutorial.
The next part, train test split.
We take X and we take Y.
We've already created those. X has the columns with the data in it, and Y has a column with profit in it. And then we're going to set the test size equals 0.2.
That basically means 20%. So 20% of the rows are going to be tested. We're going to just put them off to the side.
So since we're using a thousand lines of data, that means that 200 of those lines we're going to hold off to the side to test for later.
And then the random state equals zero. We're going to randomize which ones it picks to hold off to the side.
We'll go ahead and run this.
It's not overly exciting because it's setting up our variables.
But the next step is, the next step we actually create our linear regression model.
Now that we got to the linear regression model, we get that next piece of the puzzle.
Let's go ahead and put that code in there and walk through it.
So here we go. We're going to paste it in there.
And let's go ahead and since this is a shorter line of code, let's zoom up there so we can get a good look.
And we have from the sklearn.linear underscore model, we're going to import linear regression.
Now I don't know if you recall from earlier when we were doing all the math. Let's go ahead and flip back there and take a look at that.
Do you remember this where we had this long formula on the bottom when we were doing all this summization?
And then we also looked at uh setting it up with the different lines, and then we also looked all the way down to multiple linear regression where we're adding all those formulas together.
All of that is wrapped up in this one section.
So what's going on here is I'm going to create a variable called regressor.
And the regressor equals the linear regression. That's a linear regression model that has all that math built in.
So we don't have to have it all memorized or have to compute it individually.
And then we do the regressor.fit.
In this case we do X train and Y train because we're using the training data, X being the data in and Y being profit, what we're looking at.
And this does all that math for us.
So within one click and one line, we've created the whole linear regression model.
And we fit the data to the linear regression model.
And you can see that when I run the regressor, it gives an output linear regression, it says copy x equals true, fit intercept equals true, in jobs equal one,
normalize equals false.
It's just giving you some general information on what's going on with that regressor model.
Now that we've created our linear regression model, let's go ahead and use it.
And if you remember, we kept a bunch of data aside.
So we're going to do a y predict variable and we're going to put in the x test.
And let's see what that looks like.
Scroll up a little bit, paste that in here.
Predicting the test set results.
So here we have y predict equals regressor.predict x test going in, and this gives us y predict.
Now because I'm in Jupyter inline, I can just put the variable up there.
And when I hit the run button, it'll print that array out.
I could have just as easily done print y predict.
So if you're in a different IDE that's not an inline setup like the Jupyter Notebook, you can do it this way, print y predict.
And you'll see that for the 200 different test variables we kept off to the side, it's going to produce 200 answers.
This is what it says the profit are for those 200 predictions.
But let's don't stop there. Let's keep going and take a couple look. We're going to take just a short detail here and calculating the coefficients and the intercepts.
This gives us a quick flash at what's going on behind the line.
We're going to take a short detour here and we're going to be calculating the coefficient and intercepts.
So you can see what those look like.
What's really nice about our regressor we created is it already has the coefficients for us. And we can simply just print regressor.coefficient underscore.
When I run this, you'll see our coefficients here.
And if we can do the regressor coefficient, we can also do the regressor intercept.
And let's run that and take a look at that.
This all came from the multiple regression model.
And we'll flip over so you can remember where this is going into and where it's coming from.
You can see the formula down here where y equals m1 times x1 plus m2 times x2 and so on and so on plus c the coefficient.
So these variables fit right into this formula.
y equals slope 1 times column 1 variable plus slope 2 times column 2 variable all the way to the m into the n and x to the n plus c the coefficient.
Or in this case you have minus 8.89 to the power of 2, et cetera, et cetera, times the first column and the second column and the third column.
And then our intercept is the minus 103009 point.
Boy, it gets kind of complicated when you look at it.
This is why we don't do this by hand anymore. This is why we have the computer to make these calculations easy to understand and calculate.
Now I told you that was a short detour, and we're coming towards the end of our script.
As you remember from the beginning, I said if we're going to divide this information, we have to make sure it's a valid model, that this model works and understand how good it works.
So calculating the R squared value.
That's what we're going to use to predict how good our prediction is. And let's take a look at what that looks like in code.
And so we're going to use this from sklearn.metrics. We're going to import R2 score.
That's the R squared value.
We're looking at the error. So in the R2 score, we take our y test versus our y predict.
Y test is the actual values we're testing. That was the one that was given to us that we know are true.
The y predict of those 200 values is what we think it was true.
And when we go ahead and run this, we see we get a 0.9352.
That's the R2 score.
Now, it's not exactly a straight percentage.
So it's not saying it's 93% correct.
But you do want that in the upper 90s, oh and higher, shows that this is a very valid prediction based on the R2 score.
And if R squared value of 0.91, or 92 as we got on our model, because remember it does have a random generation involved, this proves the model is a good model.
Which means success!
Yay!
We successfully trained our model with certain predictors and estimated the profit of the companies using linear regression.
What is logistic regression? Let's say we have to build a predictive model or a machine learning model to predict whether the passengers of the Titanic ship have survived or not, the shipwreck.
So how do we do that?
So we use logistic regression to build a model for this.
How do we use logistic regression?
So we have the information about the passengers, their ID, whether they have survived or not, their class and name, and so on and so forth.
And we use this information where we already know whether the person has survived or not.
That is the labeled information, and we help the system to train based on this information with based on this labeled data. This is known as labeled data.
And during the process of building the module, we probably will remove some of the non-essential parameters or attributes here.
We only take those attributes which are really required to make these predictions, and once we train the model, we run new data through it whereby the model
will predict whether the passenger has survived or not. Alright, what is logistic regression?
As I mentioned earlier, logistic regression is an algorithm for performing binary classification.
So let's take an example and see how this works.
Let's say your car has not been serviced for quite a few years, and now you want to find out if it is going to break down in the near future.
So this is like a classification problem, find out whether your car will break down or not.
So, how are we going to perform this classification?
So here's how it looks.
If we plot the information along the X and Y axis, X is the number of years since the last service was performed, and Y
is the probability of your car breaking down.
And let's say this information was this data rather was collected from several car users.
It's not just your car but several car users. So that is our labeled data.
So the data has been collected and for for the number of years and when the car broke down and what was the probability. And that has been plotted along X and Y axis.
So this provides an idea, or from this graph, we can find out whether your car will break down or not. We'll see how.
So first of all, the probability can go from 0 to 1. As you all aware, probability can be between 0 and 1.
And as we can imagine, it is intuitive as well, as the number of years are on the lower side, maybe 1 year,
2 years, or 3 years till after the service, the chances of your car breaking down are very limited, right?
So for example, chances of your car breaking down or the probability of your car breaking down within two years of your last service are 0.1
probability. Similarly, 3 years is maybe 0.3 and so on. But as the number of years increases, let's say if it was six or seven years, there is almost a certainty that your car is going to break down.
That is what this graph shows.
So this is an example of a application of the classification algorithm.
And we will see in little details how exactly logistic regression is applied here.
One more thing needs to be added here is that the dependent variables outcome is discrete.
So if we are talking about whether the car is going to break down or not, so that is a discrete value, the y that we are talking about, the dependent variable that we are talking about.
What we are looking at is whether the car is going to break down or not, yes or no.
That is what we are talking about.
So here the outcome is discrete and not a continuous value. So this is how the logistic regression curve looks.
Let me explain a little bit what exactly and how exactly we are going to determine the class the outcome rather.
So for a logistic regression curve, a threshold has to be set saying that because this is a probability calculation.
Remember, this is a probability calculation, and the probability itself will not be zero or one.
But based on the probability, we need to decide what the outcome should be.
So there has to be a threshold. Like for example, 0.5 can be the threshold, let's say in this case.
So any value of the probability below 0.5 is considered to be 0, and any value above 0.5 is considered to be 1.
So an output of let's say 0.8 will mean that the car will break down. So that is considered as an output of 1.
And let's say an output of 0.29 is considered as 0, which means that the car will not break down.
So that's the way logistic regression works.
Now let's do a quick comparison between logistic regression and linear regression because they both have the term regression in them, so
it can cause confusion.
So let's try to remove that confusion.
So what is linear regression? Linear regression is a process, is once again an algorithm for supervised learning.
However, here you're going to find a continuous value, you're going to determine a continuous value.
It could be the price of a real estate property, it could be your hike, how much hike you're going to get, or it could be a stock price.
These are all continuous values, these are not discrete compared to a yes or a no kind of a response that we are looking for in logistic regression. So this is one example of a linear regression.
Let's say the HR team of a company tries to find out what should be the salary hike of an employee.
So they collect all the details of their existing employees, their ratings, and their salary hikes, what has been given, and that is the labeled information that is available,
and the system learns from this.
It is trained and it learns from this labeled information so that when a new employee's information is fed based on the rating, it will determine what should be the high.
So this is a linear regression problem and a linear regression example. Now, salary is a continuous value.
You can get 5000, 5500, 5600.
It is not discrete like a cat or a dog.
Or an apple or a banana, these are discrete, or a yes or a no, these are discrete values, right?
So this where you are trying to find continuous values is where we use linear regression.
So let's say just to extend on this scenario, we now want to find out whether this employee is going to get a promotion or not.
So we want to find out that is a discrete problem, right?
A yes or no kind of a problem.
In this case, we actually cannot use linear regression, even though we may have labeled data. So this is the label data.
So based on the employee rating, these are the ratings, and then some people got the promotion, and this is the ratings for which people did not get promotion.
That is a no, and this is the rating for which people got promotion.
We just plotted the data about whether a person has got an employee has got promotion or not, yes, no, right?
So there is nothing in between, and what is the employee's rating?
Okay, and ratings can be continuous, that is not an issue. But the output is discrete in this case, whether employee got promotion, yes, no.
Okay, so if we try to plot that and we try to find a straight line, this is how it would look, and as you can see, it doesn't look very right
because looks like there will be a lot of errors.
Thus, root mean square error, if you remember for linear regression, would be very, very high, and also the the values cannot go beyond zero or beyond one.
So the graph should probably look somewhat like this, clicked at zero and one, but still the straight line doesn't look
right.
Therefore, instead of using a linear equation, we need to come up with something different, and therefore, the logistic regression model
looks somewhat like this.
So we calculate the probability, and if we plot that probability not in the form of a straight line, but we need to use some other equation,
we will see very soon what that equation is, then it is a gradual process, right?
So you see here people with some of these ratings are not getting any promotions, and then slowly uh at certain rating they get promotion, so that is a gradual process,
and uh this is how the math behind logistic regression looks.
So we are trying to find the odds for a particular event happening, and this is the formula for finding the odds.
So the probability of an event happening divided by the probability of the event not happening, so p if it is the probability of the event happening,
probability of the person getting a promotion and divided by the probability of the person not getting a promotion, that is one minus p.
So this is how you measure the odds.
Now the values of the odds range from 0 to infinity. So when this probability is 0, then the odds will the value of the odds is equal to 0.
And when the probability becomes 1, then the value of the odds is 1 by 0, that will be infinity. But the probability itself remains between 0 and 1.
Now, this is how an equation of a straight line looks.
So y is equal to beta 0 plus beta 1x where beta 0 is the y intercept and beta 1 is the slope of the line.
If we take the odds equation and take a log of both sides, then this would look somewhat like this.
And the term logistic is actually derived from the fact that we are doing this. We take a log of px by 1 minus px.
This is an extension of the calculation of odds that we have seen, right?
And that is equal to beta 0 plus beta 1x, which is the equation of the straight line. And now from here, if you want to find out the value of px, we will see we can take the exponential on both sides.
and then if we solve that equation, we will get the equation of px, like this.
px is equal to 1 by 1 plus e to the power of minus beta 0. plus beta 1x.
And recall this is nothing but the equation of the line which is equal to y. Y is equal to beta 0 plus beta 1x.
So that this is the equation also known as the sigmoid function, and this is the equation of the logistic regression algorithm.
Alright, and if this is plotted, this is how the sigmoid curve is obtained.
So let's compare linear and logistic regression, how they are different from each other. Let's go back.
So linear regression is solved or used to solve regression problems, and logistic regression is used to solve classification problems.
So both are called regression, but linear regression is used for solving regression problems where we predict continuous values,
whereas logistic regression is used for solving classification problems where we have have to predict discrete values.
The response variables in case of linear regression are continuous in nature, whereas here they are categorical or discrete in nature.
And the linear regression helps to estimate the dependent variable when there is a change in the independent variable.
Whereas here, in case of logistic regression, it helps to calculate the probability or the possibility of a particular event happening.
And linear regression, as the name suggests, is a straight line, that's why it's called linear regression.
Whereas logistic regression is a sigmoid function and the curve is the shape of the curve is S.
It's an S-shaped curve. This is another example of application of logistic regression in weather prediction, whether it's going to rain or not rain.
Now keep in mind both are used in weather prediction.
If we want to find the discrete values like whether it's going to rain or not rain, that is a classification problem. We use logistic regression.
But if we want to determine what is going to be the temperature tomorrow, then we use linear regression.
So just keep in mind that in weather prediction we actually use both. But these are some examples of logistic regression.
So we want to find out whether it's going to be rain or not, whether it's going to be sunny or not, whether it's going to snow or not. These are all logistic regression examples.
A few more examples.
Classification of objects.
This is a again another example of logistic regression. Now, here of course, one distinction is that these are multi-class classification.
So logistic regression is not used in its original form, but it is used in a slightly different form.
So we say whether it is a dog or not a dog. I hope you understand.
So instead of saying is it a dog or a cat or elephant, we convert this into saying so because we need to keep it to binary classification.
So we say is it a dog or not a dog?
Is it a cat or not a cat? So that's the way logistic regression can be used for classifying objects. Otherwise, there are other techniques which can be used for performing multiclass classification.
In healthcare, logistic regression is used to find the survival rate of a patient.
So they take multiple parameters like trauma score and age and so on and so forth, and they try to predict the rate of survival.
Alright, now finally, let's take an example and see how we can apply logistic regression to predict the number that is shown in the image.
So this is actually a live demo.
I will take you into Jupyter Notebook and show the code. But before that, let me take you through a couple of slides to explain what we are trying to do.
So let's say you have an 8x8 image and there the image has a number 1, 2, 3, 4, and you need to train your model to predict what this number is. So how do we do this?
So the first thing is obviously in any machine learning process you train your model.
So in this case, we are using logistic regression, so and then we provide a training set to train the model and then we test.
How accurate our model is with the test data, which means that like any machine learning process, we split our initial data into two parts
training set and test set. With the training set, we train our model, and then with the test set, we we test the model till we get good accuracy and then we use it for
inference, right?
So that is typical methodology of uh training, testing, and then deploying of machine learning models.
So let's uh take a look at the code and uh see what we are doing. So I'll not go line by line but just take you through some of the blocks.
So, first thing we do is import all the libraries, and then we basically take a look at the images and see what is the total number of images
we can display using matplotlib.
Some of the images or a sample of these images, and then we split the data into training and test as I mentioned earlier, and we can do some exploratory analysis,
and then we build our model.
We train our model with the training set, and then we test it with our test set and find out how accurate our model is using the confusion matrix, the heat map, and use heat map for visualizing this.
And I will show you in the code what exactly is the confusion matrix and how it can be used for finding the accuracy.
In our example, we got we get an accuracy of about 0.94, which is pretty good, or 94%, which is pretty good. Alright, so what is the Confucian matrix?
This is an example of a Confucian matrix, and this is used for identifying the accuracy of a classification model
or like a logistic regression model.
So the most important part in a Confucian matrix is that first of all, this as you can see, this is a matrix, and the size of the matrix depends on how many outputs we are expecting,
right?
So, to the most important part here is that the model will be most accurate when we have the maximum numbers in its diagonal.
Like in this case, that's why it has almost 93-94 %, because the diagonals should have the maximum numbers, and the others
other than diagonals, the cells other than the diagonal should have very few numbers.
So here that's what is happening. So there is a 2 here, there are there's a one here, but most of them are along the diagonal. This what does this mean?
This means that the number that has been fed is zero and the number that has been detected is also zero. So the predicted value and the actual value are the same.
So along the diagonals, that is true, which means that let's let's take this diagonal, right?
If if the maximum number is here, that means that uh like here in this case it is 34, which means that 34 of the images that have been fed,
or rather, actually, there are two misclassifications in there. So 36 images have been fed, which have number 4, and out of which 34 have been predicted correctly as number 4,
and one has been predicted as number 8, and another one has been predicted as number 9. So these are two misclassifications, okay.
So that is the meaning of saying that the maximum number should be in the diagonal.
So if you have all of them, so for an ideal model which has let's say 100% accuracy, everything will be only in the diagonal. There will be no numbers other than zero in all other cells.
So that is like a hundred percent accurate model, okay.
So that's uh just of how to use this matrix, uh, how to use this uh confusion matrix.
I know the name uh is is a little funny sounding confusion matrix, but actually it is not very confusing, it's very straightforward.
So you're just plotting what has been predicted and what is the labeled information or what is the actual data that's also known as the ground truth sometimes.
Okay, these are some fancy terms that are used.
So predicted label and the actual label, that's all it is.
Okay, yeah, so we are showing a little bit more information here. So 38 have been predicted, and here you will see that all of them have been predicted correctly.
There have been 38 zeros, and the the predicted value and the actual value is is exactly the same. Whereas in this case, for right, it has uh there are I think 37 plus 5.
Yeah, 42 have been fed the images, 42 images are of digit 3, and uh the accuracy is
only 37 of them have been accurately predicted.
Three of them have been predicted as number seven, and two of them have been predicted as number eight, and so on and so forth. Okay, all right.
So, with that let's go into Jupyter notebook and see how the code looks.
So this is the code.
In in Jupyter notebook for logistic regression.
In this particular demo, what we are going to do is train our model to recognize digits, which are the images
which have digits from, let's say, 0 to 5 or 0 to 9, and um. and then we will see how well it is trained and whether it is able to predict these numbers correctly or not.
So let's get started. So the first part is as usual, we are importing some libraries that are required, and uh then the last line in this block is to load the digits.
So let's go ahead and run this code.
Then here we will visualize the shape of these uh digits. So we can see here if we take a look, this is how the shape is 1797 by 64.
These are like 8 by 8 images, so that's that's what is reflected in this uh shape.
Now from here onwards, we are basically once again importing some of the libraries that are required, like numpy and mapplot, and we will take a look at uh some of the sample images that we have
loaded. So the this one, for example, creates a figure, uh, and then we go ahead and take a few sample images to see how they look. So let me run this code and so that it becomes easy to understand.
So these are about five images, sample images that we are looking at 0, 1, 2, 3, 4. So this is how the images, this is how the data is okay.
And uh based on this, we will actually train our logistic regression model and then we will test it and see how well it is able to recognize. So the way it works is the pixel information.
So as you can see here, this is an 8 by 8 pixel kind of uh image, and uh the each pixel whether it is activated or not activated, that is the information available for each pixel.
Now, based on the pattern of this activation and non-activation of the various pixels, this will be identified as a zero, for example, right?
Similarly, as you can see, so overall each of these numbers actually has a different pattern of the pixel activation, and that's pretty much that our model
needs to learn. Uh, for which number, what is the pattern of the activation of the pixels, right? So that is what we are going to train our model.
Okay, so the first thing we need to do is to split our data into training and test data set, right?
So whenever we perform any training, we split the data into training and test so that the training data set is used to train the system.
So we pass this probably multiple times and then we test it with the test data set.
And the split is usually in the form of there, and there are various ways in which you can split this data, it is up to the individual preferences.
In our case, here we are splitting in the form of 23 and 77. So when we say test size as 20.23, that means 23% of the entire data is
used for testing, and the remaining 77% is used for training. So there is a readily available function which is uh called train test split.
So we don't have to write any special code for the splitting, it will automatically split the data based on the proportion that we give here, which is test size.
So we just give the test size automatically training size will be determined, and uh we pass the data that we want to split.
And the the results will be stored in X underscore train and y underscore train for the training data set. And what is X underscore train? These are these are the features, right?
Which is like the independent variable and y underscore train is the label, right?
So in this case, what happens is we have the input value, which is or the features value, which is in x underscore train, and since this is the labeled data
for each of them, each of the observations, we already have the label information saying whether this digit is a zero or a one
or a two. So that, that's this is what will be used for comparison to find out whether the the system is able to recognize it correctly or there is an error.
For each observation, it will compare with this.
Right, so this is the label.
So the same way x underscore train, y underscore train is for the training data set, x underscore test, y underscore test is for the test data set.
Okay, so let me go ahead and execute this code as well, and then we can go and check quickly what is the how many entries are there and in each of their.
So x underscore train the shape is 1383 by 64 and y underscore train has 1383 because there is uh nothing like the second part is not uh required here,
and then x underscore test shape we see is 414. So actually there are 414 observations in test and 1383 observations in train.
So that's basically what these four lines of code are saying. Okay.
Then we import the uh logistic regression library and uh, which is a part of scikit -learn, so we we don't have to implement the logistic regression process itself;
we just call these uh the function and uh, let me go ahead and execute that so that uh we have the logistic regression library imported. Now we create an instance of logistic regression, right?
So logistic REGR is uh is an instance of logistic regression, and then we use that for training our model. So let me first execute this code. So these two lines.
So the first line basically creates an instance of logistic regression model, and then the second line where is where we are passing our data,
the training data set, right? This is our the the predictors and uh this is our target. We are passing this data set to train our model, all right.
So once we do this, in this case the data is not large, but by and large, uh the training is what takes usually a lot of time.
So we spend in machine learning activities in machine learning projects, we spend a lot of time for the training part of it.
Okay, so here the data set is relatively small, so it was pretty quick. So, alright, so now our model has been trained using the training data set, and uh we want to see how accurate this is.
So, what we'll do is we will test it out in probably faces. So, let me first try out how well this is uh working for uh one image.
Okay, I will just try it out with one image, my the first entry in my test data set and see whether it is uh correctly predicting or not.
So I and in order to test it, so for training purpose, we use the fit method. There is a method called fit which is for training the model.
And once the training is done, if you want to test for uh a particular value new input, you use the predict method.
Okay, so let's run the predict method and we pass this particular image and uh we see that the
shape is uh the prediction is four. So let's try a few more.
Let me see for the next 10.
Uh seems to be fine. So let me just go ahead and test the entire data set. Okay, that's basically what we will do.
So now we want to find out how accurately this has performed. So we use the score method to find what is the percentage of accuracy, and we see here that it has performed up to 94%
accurate. Okay, so that's uh on this part. Now, what we can also do is we can um also see this accuracy using what is known as a confusion matrix.
So let us go ahead and try that as well so that we can also visualize how well uh this model has uh done.
So let me execute this piece of code which will basically import some of the libraries that are required, and um we we basically create a confusion matrix,
an instance of confusion matrix by running a confusion matrix and passing these uh values.
So we have so this confusion underscore matrix method takes two parameters one is the y underscore test
and the other is uh the prediction. So, what is the y underscore test?
These are the labeled values which we already know for the test data set, and predictions are what the system has predicted for the test data set.
Okay, so this is known to us.
And this is what the system has the model has generated. So we kind of create the confusion matrix and we will print it. And this is how the Confucian matrix looks.
As the name suggests, it is a matrix. And the key point out here is that the accuracy of the model is determined by how many numbers are there in the diagonal.
The more the numbers in the diagonal, the better the accuracy is.
Okay. And first of all, the total sum of all the numbers in this whole matrix is equal to the number of observations in the test data set. That is the first thing, right?
So if you add up all these numbers, that will be equal to the number of uh observations in the test data set. And then out of that, the maximum number of them should be in the diagonal.
That means the accuracy is predicted. If the the numbers in the diagonal are less and in all other places there are a lot of numbers, uh which means the accuracy is very low.
The diagonal indicates a correct prediction. This means that the actual value is the same as the predicted value. Here again, actual value is same as the predicted value and so on, right?
So the moment you see a number here, that means the actual value is something and the predicted value is something else, right?
Similarly, here the actual value is something and the predicted value is something else.
So that is basically how we read the Confucian matrix. Now, how do we find the accuracy?
You can actually add up the total values in the diagonal, so it's like 38 plus 44 plus 43 and so on, and
divide that by the total number of test observations that will give you the percentage accuracy using a Confucian matrix.
Now let us visualize this Confucian matrix in a slightly more sophisticated way using a heat map.
So we will create a heat map with some we'll add some colors as well. It's uh it's like a more visually uh visually more appealing. So that's the whole idea.
So if we let me run this piece of code and this is how the heat map uh looks, uh, and as you can see here, the diagonals again uh are
all the values are here, most of the values, so which means reasonably this seems to be reasonably accurate, and yeah, basically the accuracy score is 94%.
This is calculated as I mentioned by adding all these numbers divided by the total test values or the total number of observations in
test data set.
Okay, so this is the Confucian matrix for logistic regression.
Alright, so now that we have seen the Confucian matrix, let's take a quick sample and see how well uh the system has
classified, and we will take a few examples of the data.
So if we see here we we picked up randomly a few of them, so this is uh number four, which is the actual value, and also the predicted value, both are four.
This is an image of zero, so the predicted value is also zero, actual value is of course zero, then this is the image of nine,
so this has also been predicted correctly. Nine and actual value is nine, and this is an image of one, and again this has been predicted correctly as like the actual value.
Okay, so this was a quick demo of logistic regression, how to use logistic regression to identify images.
What is a decision tree?
Let's go through a very simple example before we dig in deep.
Decision tree is a tree-shaped diagram used to determine a course of action.
Each branch of the tree represents a possible decision or currents or reaction. Let's start with a simple question. How do identify a random vegetable from a shopping bag?
So we have this group of vegetables in here, and we can start off by asking a simple question is it red? And if it's not, then it's gonna be the purple fruit to the left, probably an eggplant.
If it's true, it's gonna be one of the red fruits. Is a diameter greater than two? If false, it's gonna be a what looks to be a red chili.
And if it's true, it's gonna be a bell pepper from the capsicum family. So it's a capsicum.
Problems that decision tree can solve.
So let's look at the two different categories the decision tree can be used on.
It can be used on the classification, the true false, yes, no, and it can be used on regression, where we figure out what the next value is in a series of numbers or a group of data.
In classification, the classification tree will determine a set of logical if-then conditions to classify problems.
For example, discriminating between three types of flowers based on certain features.
In regression, a regression tree is used when the target variable is numerical or continuous in nature. We fit the regression model to the target variable using each of the independent variables.
Each split is made based on the sum of squared error.
Before we dig deeper into the mechanics of the decision tree, let's take a look at the advantages of using a decision tree. And we'll also take a glimpse at the disadvantages.
The first thing you'll notice is that it's simple to understand, interpret, and visualize. It really shines here because you can see exactly what's going on in a decision tree.
Little effort is required for data preparation, so you don't have to do special scaling. There's a lot of things you don't have to worry about when using a decision tree.
It can handle both numerical and categorical data, as we discovered earlier, and nonlinear parameters don't affect its performance.
So even if the data doesn't fit an easy curved graph, you can still use it to create an effective decision or prediction.
If we're going to look at the advantages of a decision tree, we also need to understand the disadvantages of a decision tree.
The first disadvantage is overfitting. Overfitting occurs when the algorithm captures noise in the data.
That means you're solving for one specific instance instead of a general solution for all the data. High variance. The model can get unstable due to small variation in data. Low bias tree.
A highly complicated decision tree tends to have a low bias, which makes it difficult for the model to work with new data.
Decision tree important terms. Before we dive in further, we need to look at some basic terms.
We need to have some definitions to go with our decision tree and the different parts we're going to be using. We'll start with entropy.
Entropy is a measure of randomness or unpredictability in the data set.
For example, we have a group of animals in this picture. There's four different kinds of animals, and this data set is considered to have a high entropy.
You really can't pick out what kind of animal it is based on looking at just the four animals as a big clump of entities.
So as we start splitting it into subgroups, we come up with our second definition, which is information gain. Information gain. It is a measure of decrease in entropy after the data set is split.
So in this case, based on the color yellow, we've split one group of animals on one side as true and those who aren't yellow as false.
As we continue down the yellow side, we split based on the height, true or false equals 10. And on the other side, height is less than 10, true or false.
And as you see, as we split it, the entropy continues to be less and less and less. And so our information gain is simply the entropy, E1 from the top, and how it's changed to E2 in the bottom.
And we'll look at the deeper math, although you really don't need to know a huge amount of math when you actually do the programming in Python, because it'll do it for you.
But we'll look on the actual math at how they compute entropy. Finally, we went into the different parts of our tree, and they call the leaf node.
Leaf node carries the classification or the decision, so it's the final end at the bottom.
The decision node has two or more branches. This is where we're breaking the group up into different parts. And finally, you have the root node. The topmost decision node is known as the root node.
How does a decision tree work? Wonder what kind of animals I'll get in the jungle today. Maybe you're the hunter with a gun, or if you're more into photography, you're a photographer with a camera.
So let's look at this group of animals and let's try to classify different types of animals based on their features using a decision tree.
So the problem statement is to classify the different types of animals based on their features using a decision tree. The data set is looking quite messy and the entropy is high in this case.
So let's look at a training set or a training data set.
And we're looking at color, we're looking at height, and then we have our different animals. We have our elephants, our giraffes, our monkeys, and our tigers.
And they're of different colors and shapes. Let's see what that looks like. And how do we split the data?
We have to frame the conditions that split the data in such a way that the information gain is the highest. Note gain is the measure of decrease in entropy after splitting.
So the formula for entropy is the sum, that's what this symbol looks like, that looks like kind of like a uh E funky E of K, where I equals 1 to K.
K would represent the number of animals, the different animals in there, where value or P value of I would be the percentage of that animal
times the log base 2 of the same, the percentage of that animal. Let's try to calculate the entropy for the current data set and take a look at what that looks like.
And don't be afraid of the math. You don't really have to memorize this math. Just be aware that it's there and this is what's going on in the background.
And so we have three giraffes, two tigers, one monkey, two elephants, a total of eight animals gathered. And if we plug that into the formula, we get an entropy that equals three over eight.
So we have three giraffes, a total of eight, times the log. Usually they use base two on the log.
So log base two of three over eight, plus, in this case let's say it's the elephants, two over eight, two elephants over total of eight, times log base two,
two over eight, plus one monkey over total of eight, log base two, one over eight, and plus two over eight of the tigers, log base
two over eight.
And if we plug that into our computer or calculator, I obviously can't do logs in my head, we get an entropy equal to 0.571.
The program will actually calculate the entropy of the data set similarly after every split to calculate the gain.
Now we're not going to go through each set one at a time to see what those numbers are. We just want you to be aware that this is a formula or the mathematics behind it.
Gain can be calculated by finding the difference of the subsequent entropy values after a split. Now we will try to choose a condition that gives us the highest gain.
We will do that by splitting the data using each condition and checking that the gain we get out of them. The condition that gives us the highest gain will be used to make the first split.
Can you guess what that first split will be just by looking at this image? As a human, it's probably pretty easy to split it.
Let's see if you're right. If you guessed the color yellow, you're correct. Let's say the condition that gives us the maximum gain is yellow. So we will split the data based on the color yellow.
If it's true, that group of animals goes to the left. If it's false, it goes to the right. The entropy after the splitting has decreased considerably.
However, we still need some splitting at both the branches to attain an entropy value equal to zero. So we decide to split both the nodes using height as a condition.
Since every branch now contains single label type, we can say that entropy in this case has reached the least value.
And here you see we have the giraffes, the tigers, the monkey, and the elephants all separated into their own groups.
This tree can now predict all the classes of animals present in the dataset with 100% accuracy. That was easy.
Use case loan repayment prediction. Let's get into my favorite part and open up some Python and see what the programming code and the scripting looks like.
In here, we're going to want to do a prediction.
And we start with this individual here who's requesting to find out how good his customers are going to be, whether they're going to repay their loan or not for his bank.
And from that, we want to generate a problem statement to predict if a customer will repay loan amount or not. And then we're going to be using the decision tree algorithm in Python.
Let's see what that looks like and let's dive into the code. In our first few steps of implementation, we're going to start by importing the necessary packages that we need from Python.
And we're going to load up our data and take a look at what the data looks like. So the first thing I need is I need something to edit my Python and run it in. So let's flip on over.
And here I'm using the Anaconda Jupyter Notebook.
Now you can use any Python IDE you like to run it in, but I find the Jupyter Notebooks really nice for doing things on the fly. And let's go ahead and just paste that code in the beginning.
And before we start, let's talk a little bit about what we're bringing in. And then we're going to do a couple things in here.
We have to make a couple changes as we go through this first part of the import. The first thing we bring in is NumPy as NP.
That's very standard. When we're dealing with mathematics, especially with uh very complicated machine learning tools, you almost always see the NUMPy come in for your number your numbers.
It's called number Python, it has your mathematics in there. In this case, we actually could take it out, but generally you'll need it for most of your different things you work with.
And then we're going to use pandas as PD.
That's also a standard. The pandas is a data frame setup, and you can liken this to taking your basic data and storing it in a way that looks like an Excel spreadsheet.
So as we come back to this, when you see NP or PD, those are very standard uses, you'll know that that's the pandas. And I'll show you a little bit more when we explore the data in just a minute.
Then we're going to need to split the data. So I'm going to bring in our train test and split. And this is coming from the SK Learn package cross-validation.
In just a minute, we're going to change that and we'll go over that too. And then there's also the SK.tree import decision tree classifier. That's the actual tool we're using.
Remember, I told you don't be afraid of the mathematics, it's going to be done for you.
Well, the decision tree classifier has all that mathematics in there for you, so you don't have to figure it back out again. And then we have sklearn.metrics for accuracy score.
We need to score our setup. That's the whole reason we're splitting it between the training and testing data. And finally, we still need the sklearn import tree.
And that's just the basic tree function it's needed for the decision tree classifier. And finally, we're going to load our data down here.
And I'm going to run this and we're going to get two things on here. One, we're going to get an error, and two, we're going to get a warning. Let's see what that looks like.
So the first thing we had is we have an error.
Why is this error here? Well, it's looking at this and says I need to read a file.
And when this was written, the person who wrote it, this is their path where they stored the file.
So let's go ahead and fix that.
And I'm going to put in here my file path. I'm just going to call it full file name.
And you'll see it's on my C drive and there's this very lengthy setup on here where I stored the data2.csv file.
Don't worry too much about the full path because on your computer it'll be different.
The data.2.csv file was generated by Simply Learn.
If you want a copy of that, you can comment down below and request it here in the YouTube.
And then if I'm gonna give it a name, full file name,
I'm gonna go ahead and change it here
to full
file name.
So let's go ahead and run it now and see what happens.
And we get a warning.
When you're coding, understanding these different warnings and these different errors that come up is probably the hardest lesson to learn.
So let's just go ahead and take a look at this and use this as a uh opportunity to understand what's going on here.
If you read the warning, it says the cross-validation is depreciated. So it's a warning on it's being removed.
And it's going to be moved in favor of the model selection.
So if we go up here, we have sklearn.crossvalidation. And if you research this and go to the sklearn site, you'll find out that you can actually just swap it right in there with model selection.
And so when I come in here and I run it again,
that removes a warning.
What they've done is they've had two different developers develop it in two different branches.
And then they decided to keep one of those and eventually get rid of the other one.
That's all that is.
And very easy and quick to fix.
Before we go any further, I went ahead and opened up the data from this file. Remember the data file we just loaded on here, the data underscore two.csv.
Let's talk a little bit more about that and see what that looks like both as a text file, because it's a comma-separated variable file, and in a spreadsheet.
This is what it looks like as a basic text file. You can see at the top they've created a header and it's got one, two, three, four, five columns, and each column has data in it.
And let me flip this over because we're also going to look at this uh in an actual spreadsheet so you can see what that looks like.
And here I've opened it up in the OpenOffice Calc, which is pretty much the same as Excel, and zoomed in, and you can see we've got our columns and our rows of data. A little easier to read in here.
We have a result, yes, yes, no. We have initial payment, last payment, credit score, house number.
If we scroll way down,
we'll see that this occupies a thousand and one lines of code or lines of data,
with uh the first one being a column and then one thousand lines of data.
Now, as a programmer,
if you're looking at a small amount of data, I usually start by pulling it up in different sources so I can see what I'm working with.
But in larger data, you won't have that option.
It'll just be um too too large. So you need to either bring in a small amount that you can look at it like we're doing right now, or we can start looking at it through the Python code.
So let's go ahead and move on and take the next couple steps to explore the data using Python. Let's go ahead and see what it looks like in Python to print the length and the shape of the data.
So let's start by printing the length of the database. We can use a simple line function from Python.
And when I run this, you'll see that it's a thousand long. And that's what we expected. There's a thousand lines of data in there if you subtract the uh column head.
And this is one of the nice things when we did the uh balance data from the panda read CSV, you'll see that the header is row zero,
so it automatically removes the row
and then shows the data separate.
It does a good job sorting that data out for us.
And then we can use a different function, and let's take a look at that.
And again, we're going to utilize the tools in panda,
and since the balance underscore data was loaded as a panda data frame,
we can do a shape on it.
And let's go ahead and run the shape and see what that looks like.
What's nice about the shape is not only does it give me the length of the data, we have a thousand lines, it also tells me there's five columns.
So when we were looking at the data, we had five columns of data. And then let's take one more step to explore the data using Python.
And now that we've taken a look at the length and the shape, let's go ahead and use the pandas module for head. Another beautiful thing in the dataset that we can utilize.
So let's put that on our sheet here, and we have print dataset and balance data.head.
And this is a pandas print statement of its own. So it has its own print feature in there.
And then we went ahead and gave a label for our print job here of data set, just a simple print statement.
And when we run that, and let's just take a closer look at that. Let me zoom in here.
There we go.
Pandas does such a wonderful job of making this a very clean, readable data set.
So you can look at the data, you can look at the column headers, you can have it uh when you put it as the head, it prints the first five lines of the data.
And we always start with zero. So when we have five lines, we have zero, one, two, three, four instead of one, two, three, four, five.
That's a standard scripting and programming set, as you want to start with the zero position.
And that is what the data head does. It pulls the first five rows of data, puts it in a nice format that you can look at and view. Very powerful tool to view the data.
So instead of having to flip and open up an Excel spreadsheet or open office calc or trying to look at a Word doc where it's all scrunched together and hard to read,
you can now get a nice open view of what you're working with.
We're working with a shape of a thousand long, five wide, so we have five columns, and we do the full data head, you can actually see what this data looks like.
The initial payment, last payment, credit scores, house number.
So let's take this now that we've explored the data and let's start digging into the decision tree. So in our next step, we're going to train and build our data tree.
And to do that, we need to first separate the data out.
We're going to separate it into two groups so that we have something to actually train the data with, and then we have some data on the side to test it, to see how good our model is.
Remember, with any of the machine learning, you always want to have some kind of test set to weigh it against so you know how good your model is when you distribute it.
Let's go ahead and break this code down and look at it in pieces.
So first we have our X and Y.
Where do X and Y come from?
Well, X is going to be our data, and Y is going to be the answer or the target. You can look at it source and target.
In this case, we're using X and Y to denote the data in and the data that we're actually trying to guess what the answer is going to be.
And so to separate it, we can simply put in X equals the balance of the data dot values. The first brackets means that we're going to select all the lines in the database. So it's all the data.
And the second one says we're only going to look at columns one through five. Remember we always start with zero?
Zero is a yes or no, and that's whether the loan went default or not. So we want to start with one. If we go back up here, that's the initial payment, and it goes all the way through the house number.
Well, if we want to look at uh one through five, we can do the same thing for y, which is the answers, and we're going to set that just equal to the zero row.
So it's just the zero row, and then it's all rows going in there. So now we've divided this into two different data sets, one of them with the
data going in, and one with the answers.
Next, we need to split the data.
And here you'll see that we have it split into four different parts.
The first one is your X training, your X test, your Y train, your Y test.
Simply put, we have X going in where we're going to train it, and we have to know the answer to train it with.
And then we have X test where we're going to test that data.
And we have to know in the end what the Y was supposed to be.
And that's where this train test split comes in that we loaded earlier in the modules.
This does it all for us. And you can see they set the test size equal to 0.3, so that's roughly 30% will be used in the test.
And then we use a random state, so it's completely random which rows it takes out of there.
And then finally we get to actually build our decision tree.
And they've called it here CLF underscore entropy.
That's the actual decision tree or decision tree classifier.
And in here they've added a couple variables, which we'll explore in just a minute.
And then finally, we need to fit the data to that.
So we take our CLF entropy that we created and we fit the X train. And since we know the answers for X trade or the Y train, we go ahead and put those in.
And let's go ahead and run this.
And what most of these SKLearn modules do is when you set up the variable, in this case, when we set the CLF entropy equal decision tree classifier,
it automatically prints out what's in that decision tree.
There's a lot of variables you can play with in here, and it's quite beyond the scope of this tutorial to go through all of these and how they work.
But we're working on entropy, that's one of the options.
We've added that it's completely a random state of 100, so 100%. And we have a max depth of three.
Now the max depth, if you remember above when we were doing the different graphs of animals, means it's only going to go down three layers before it stops.
And then we have minimal samples of leaves is five. So it's going to have at least five leaves at the end. So I'll have at least three splits.
We'll have no more than three layers and at least five end leaves with the final result at the bottom.
Now that we've created our decision tree classifier, not only created it but trained it.
Let's go ahead and apply it and see what that looks like.
So let's go ahead and make a prediction and see what that looks like.
We're going to paste our predict code in here.
And before we run it, let's just take a quick look at what it's doing here.
We have a variable yPredict that we're going to do.
And we're going to use our variable CLF entropy that we created.
And then you'll see dot predict.
And it's very common in the SKLearn modules that their different tools have the predict when you're actually running a prediction.
In this case, we're going to put our X test data in here.
Now, if you delivered this for use and actual commercial use and distributed it, this would be the new loans you're putting in here to guess
whether the person's going to be uh pay them back or not.
In this case, though, we need to test out the data and just see how good our sample is, how good of our tree does at predicting the loan payments.
And finally, since Anaconda Jupyter Notebook is it works as a command line for Python, we can simply put the Y predictE in to print it.
I could just as easily have put the print
and put brackets around Y predict E in to print it out.
We'll go ahead and do that. It doesn't matter which way you do it.
And you'll see right here that it runs a prediction.
This is roughly 300 in here. Remember it's 30% of a thousand, so you should have about 300 answers in here.
And this tells you which each one of those lines of our test went in there, and this is what our why predict came out.
So let's move on to the next step. We're going to take this data and try to figure out just how good a model we have.
So here we go, since sklearn does all the heavy lifting for you and all the math, we have a simple line of code to let us know what the accuracy is.
And let's go ahead and go through that and see what that means and what that looks like.
Let's go ahead and paste this in and let me zoom in a little bit.
There we go.
So you have a nice full picture.
And we'll see here we're just gonna do a print accuracy is.
And then we do the accuracy score.
And this was something we imported um earlier, if you remember at the very beginning. Let me just scroll up there real quick so you can see where that's coming from.
That's coming from here down here from sklearn.metrics import accuracy score.
And you could probably run a script, make your own script to do this very easily.
How accurate is it? How many out of 300 do we get right?
And so we put in our y test, that's the one we ran the predict on, and then we put in our y predict en that's the answers we got,
and we're just going to multiply that by a hundred, because this is just going to give us an answer as a decimal, and we want to see it as a percentage. And let's run that and see what it looks like.
And
if you see here, we got an accuracy of 93.66667.
So when we look at the number of loans and we look at how good our model fit, we can tell people it has about a 93.6 fitting to it.
So just a quick recap on that.
We now have accuracy setup on here.
And so we have created a model that uses a decision tree algorithm to predict whether a customer will repay the loan or not.
The accuracy of the model is about 94.6%.
The bank can now use this model to decide whether it should approve the loan request from a particular customer or not.
And so this information is really powerful. We may not be able to, as individuals, understand all these numbers because they have thousands of numbers that come in.
But you can see that this is a smart decision for the bank to use a tool like this to help them to predict how good their
profits are going to be off of the loan balances and how many are going to default or not. We're going to be looking at random forest, one of the many powerful tools in the machine learning library.
Before we dive into the topic, let's start by looking at a few of the uses for random forest.
Currently, today it's used in remote sensing.
For example, they're used in the ETM devices. If you're a space buff, that's the enhanced thermatic mapper they use on satellites, which see far outside the human spectrum for looking at land masses.
And they acquire images of the Earth's surface.
The accuracy is higher, and training time is less than many other machine learning tools out there.
Also, object detection, multi-class object detection is done using random forest algorithms.
A good example is a traffic where you're trying to sort out the different cars, buses, and things.
And it provides a better detection in complicated environments. It's very complicated up there.
And then we have another example, Connect.
And let's take a little closer look at Connect. Connect, they use a random forest as part of the game console.
And what it does is it tracks the body movements and it recreates it in the game.
And let's see what that looks like.
We have a user who performs a step. In this case, it looks like uh Elvis Presley going there.
That is then recorded so that Connect registers the movement and then it marks the user based on accuracy. And it looks like we have uh prints going on this one from uh Elvis Presley to Prince.
It's great.
Uh so it marks the user based on the accuracy. If we look at that a little closer, we have a training set to identify body parts.
Where are the hands, where are the feet, uh, what's going on with the body.
That then goes into a random forest classifier that learns from it.
Once we've trained the classifier, it then identifies the body parts while the person's dancing, and it's able to represent that in a computer format, and then based on that
it scores the game and how accurate you are as being Elvis Presley or Prince in your dancing.
So why random forest? It's always important to understand why we use this tool over the other ones.
What are the benefits here? And so with the random forest, the first one is there's no overfitting.
If you use of multiple trees, reduce the risk of overfitting.
Training time is less. Overfitting means that we have fit the data so close to what we have as our sample that we pick up on all the weird parts.
And instead of predicting the overall data, you're predicting the weird stuff, which you don't want.
High accuracy runs efficiently in large database.
For large data, it produces highly accurate predictions. In today's world of big data, this is really important.
And this is probably where it really shines. This is where why random forest really comes in.
It estimates missing data.
Data in today's world is very messy. So when you have a random forest, it can maintain the accuracy when a large proportion of the data is missing.
What that means is: if you have data that comes in from five or six different areas, and maybe they took one set of statistics in one area,
and they took a slightly different set of statistics in the other. so they have some of the same shared data. but one is missing like the number of children in the house.
if you're doing something over demographics, and the other one is missing the size of the house.
It will look at both of those separately and build two different trees, and then it can do a very good job of guessing which one fits better, even though it's missing that data.
Let us dig deep into the theory of exactly how it works.
And let's look at what is random forests.
Random forests or random decision forest is a method that operates by constructing multiple decision trees.
The decision of the majority of the trees is chosen by the random forest as the final decision.
And let's uh we have some nice graphics here. We have a decision tree, and they actually use a real tree to denote the decision tree, which I love.
And given a random some kind of picture of a fruit, this decision tree decides that the output is it's an apple.
And we have a decision tree two where we have that picture of the fruit goes in, and this one decides that it's a lemon.
And the decision three tree gets another image and it decides it's an apple, and then this all comes together in what they call the random forest.
And this random forest then looks at it and says, okay, I got two votes for apple, one vote for lemon. The majority is apples, so the final decision is apples.
To understand how the random forest works, we first need to dig a little deeper and take a look at the random forest and the actual decision tree and how it builds that decision tree.
In looking closer at how the individual decision trees work, we'll go ahead and continue to use the fruit example, since we're talking about trees and forests.
A decision tree is a tree-shaped diagram used to determine a course of action.
Each branch of the tree represents a possible decision, occurrence, or reaction.
So in here we have a bowl of fruit, and if you look at that, it looks like they switch from lemons to oranges. We have oranges, cherries, and apples.
And the first decision of the decision tree might be is a diameter greater than or equal to three? And if it says false, it knows that they're cherries because everything else is bigger than that.
So all the cherries fall into that decision. So we have all that data we're training.
We can look at that, we know that that's what's going to come up.
Is the color orange?
Well goes, hmm, orange or red. Well, if it's true, then it comes out as the orange, and if it's false, that leaves apples.
So in this example, it sorts out the fruit in the bowl or the images of the fruit.
A decision tree, these are very important terms to know, because these are very central to understanding the decision tree and when working with them. The first is entropy.
Everything on the decision tree and how it makes those decisions is based on entropy. Entropy is a measure of randomness or unpredictability in the data set.
Then they also have information gain, the leaf node, the decision node, and the root node.
We'll cover these other four terms as we go down the tree, but let's start with entropy.
So starting with entropy, we have here a high amount of randomness.
What that means is that whatever's coming out of this decision, if it was going to guess based on this data, it wouldn't be able to tell you whether it's a lemon or an apple.
It would just say it's a fruit.
So the first thing we want to do is we want to split this apart.
And we take the initial data set, we're going to sit create a data set one and a data set two. We just split it in two.
And if you look at these new data sets, after splitting them, the entropy of each of those sets is much less.
So for the first one, whatever comes in there, it's going to sort that data and it's going to say, okay, if this data goes this direction, it's probably an apple.
And if it goes into the other direction, it's probably a lemon.
So that brings us up to information gain.
It is the measure of decrease in the entropy after the data set is split.
What that means in here is that we've gone from one set, which has a very high entropy, to two lower sets of entropy.
And we've added in the values of E1 for the first one and E2 for the second two, which are much lower.
And so that information gain is increased greatly in this example.
And so you can find that the information grain simply equals decision E1 minus E2.
As we're going down our list of uh definitions, we'll look at the leaf node.
And the leaf node carries the classification or the decision.
So we look down here to the leaf node, we finally get to our set one or our set two.
When it comes down there and it says, okay, this object's gone into set one.
If it's gone into set one, it's going to be split by some means and we'll either end up with apples on the leaf node or a lemon on the leaf node, and on the right it'll either be an apple or lemons.
Those leaf nodes are those final decisions or classifications. That's the definition of leaf node in here.
If we're going to have a final leaf where we make the decision, we should have a name for the nodes above it, and they call those decision nodes.
A decision node, decision node has two or more branches.
And you can see here where we have the five apples and one lemon, and in the other case the five lemons and one apple, they have to make a choice of which tree it goes down
based on some kind of measurement or information given to the tree.
And that brings us to our last definition.
The root node, the topmost decision node, is known as the root node. And this is where you have all of your data and you have your first decision it has to make or the first split in information.
So far, we've looked at a very general image with the fruit being split. Let's look and see exactly what that means to split the data and how do we make those decisions on there.
Let's go in there and find out how a decision tree works.
So let's try to understand this and let's use a simple example, and we'll stay with the fruit.
We have a bowl of fruit.
And so let's create a problem statement. And the problem is we want to classify the different types of fruits in the bowl based on different features.
The data set in the bowl is looking quite messy and the entropy is high in this case.
So if this bowl was our decision maker, it wouldn't know what choice to make. It has so many choices.
Which one do you pick? Apple, grapes, or lemons? And so we look in here, we're going to start with the training set.
So this is our data that we're training our data with. And we have a number of options here. We have the color, and under the color we have red, yellow, purple.
We have a diameter, uh 331, 331, and we have a label, apple, lemon, grapes, apple, lemon grapes.
And how do we split the data?
We have to frame the conditions to split the data in such a way that the information gain is the highest.
It's very key to note that we're looking for the best gain.
We don't want to just start sorting out the smallest piece in there.
We want to split it the biggest way we can. And so we measure this decrease in entropy, that's what they call it entropy, there's our entropy, after splitting.
And now we'll try to choose a condition that gives us the highest gain. We will do that by splitting the data using each condition and checking the gain that we get out of them.
The conditions that give us the highest gain will be used to make the first split.
So let's take a look at these different conditions. We have color, we have diameter, and if we look underneath that, we have a couple different values.
We have diameter equals three, color equals yellow, red, diameter equals one.
And when we look at that, you'll see over here we have one, two, three, four threes. That's a pretty hardy selection.
So let's say the condition gives us a maximum gain of three.
So we have the most pieces fall into that range.
So our first split from our decision node is we split the data based on the diameter. Is it greater than or equal to three?
If it's not, that's false, it goes into the grape bowl.
And if it's true, it goes into a bowl fold of lemon and apples.
The entropy after splitting has decreased considerably.
So now we can make two decisions. If you look at they're very uh much less chaos going on there.
This node has already attained an entropy value of zero as you can see. There's only one kind of label left for this branch.
So no further splitting is required for this node.
However, this node on the right is still requires a split to decrease the entropy further.
So we split the right node further based on color.
If you look at this, if I split it on color, that pretty much cuts it right down the middle, and it's the only thing we have left in our choices of color and diameter, too.
And if the color is yellow, it's going to go to the right bowl, and if it's false, it's going to go to the left bowl.
So the entropy in this case is now zero. So now we have three bowls with zero entropy. There's only one type of data in each one of those bowls.
So we can predict a lemon with a hundred percent accuracy.
And we can predict the apple also with a hundred percent accuracy, along with our grapes up there.
So we've looked at kind of a basic tree in our forest.
But what we really want to know is how does a random forest work as a whole?
So to begin our um random forest classifier, let's say we already have built three trees. And we're going to start with the first tree that looks like this.
Just like we did in the example, this tree looks at the diameter. If it's greater than or equal to three, it's true, otherwise it's false.
So one side goes to the smaller diameter, one side goes to larger diameter. And if the color is orange, it's going to go to the right, true. We're using oranges now instead of lemons.
And if it's red, it's going to go to the left, false.
And we build a second tree, very similar, but it's split differently.
Instead of the first one being split by a diameter, uh this one, when they created it, if you look at that first bowl, it has a lot of red objects. So it says, is the color red?
Because that's going to bring our entropy down the fastest.
And so of course if it's true, it goes to the left. If it's false, it goes to the right.
And then it looks at the shape, false or true, and so on and so on.
And tree three, is the diameter equal to one?
And it came up with this because there's a lot of cherries in this bowl.
So that would be the biggest split on there is is the diameter equal to one? That's going to drop the entropy the quickest.
And as you can see, it splits it into true. If it goes false, and they've added another category, does it grow in the summer?
And if it's false, it goes off to the left. If it's true, it goes off to the right.
Let's go ahead and bring these three trees. So you can see them all in one image. So this would be three completely different trees categorizing a fruit.
And let's take a fruit.
Now let's try this.
And this fruit, if you look at it, we've blackened it out.
You can't see the color on it, so it's missing data. Remember one of the things we talked about earlier is that a random forest works really good if you're missing data, if you're missing pieces.
So this fruit has an image, but maybe the person had a black and white com camera when they took the picture.
And we're going to take a look at this, and it's going to have um, they put the color in there. So ignore the color down there. But the diameter equals three.
We find out it grows in the summer, equals yes, and the shape is a circle.
And if you go to the right, you can look at what one of the decision trees did. This is the third one.
Is the diameter greater than or equal to three? Is the color orange? Well, it doesn't really know on this one, but it if you look at the value, it'd say true and it go to the right.
Tree two classifies it as cherries. Is the color equal red?
Is the shape a circle?
True, it is a circle.
So this would look at it and say, oh, that's a cherry.
And then we go to the other classifier and it says, is the diameter equal one?
Well that's false. Does it grow in the summer?
True.
So it goes down and looks at as oranges.
So how does this random forest work? The first one says it's an orange.
The second one said it was a cherry. And the third one says, hmm, it's an orange.
And you can guess that if you have two oranges and one says it's a cherry, uh, when you add that all together, the majority of the vote says orange.
So the answer is it's classified as an orange, even though we didn't know the color and we're missing data on it. I don't know about you, but I'm getting tired of fruit.
So let's switch, and I did promise you we'd start looking at a case example and get into some Python coding.
Today we're going to use the case, the iris flower analysis.
Ooh, this is the exciting part as we roll up our sleeves and actually look at some Python coding.
Before we start the Python coding, we need to go ahead and create a problem statement.
Wonder what species of iris do these flowers belong to? Let's try to predict the species of the flowers using machine learning in Python. Let's see how it can be done.
So here we begin to go ahead and implement our Python code. And you'll find that the first half of our implementation is all about organizing and exploring the data coming in.
Let's go ahead and take this first step, which is loading the different modules into Python. And let's go ahead and put that in our favorite editor, whatever your favorite editor is.
In this case, I'm going to be using the Anaconda Jupyter Notebook, which is one of my favorites. Certainly there's Notepad
and Eclipse and dozens of others, or just even using the Python terminal window. Any of those will work just fine to go ahead and explore this Python coding. So here we go.
Let's go ahead and flip over to our Jupyter Notebook. And I've already opened up a new page for Python 3 code. And I'm just going to paste this right in there.
And let's take a look and see what we're bringing into our Python. The first thing we're going to do is from the sklearn.datasets, import load iris.
Now this isn't the actual data, this is just the module that allows us to bring in the data, the load iris.
And the iris is so popular, it's been around since 1936 when Ronald Fisher published a paper on it. And they're measuring the different parts of the flower.
And based on those measurements, predicting what kind of flower it is.
And then if we're going to do a random forest classifier, we need to go ahead and import a random forest classifier from the sklearn module. So sklearn.ensemble, import random forest classifier.
And then we want to bring in two more modules. Um, and these are probably the most commonly used modules in Python and data science with any of the um other modules that we bring in.
And one is going to be pandas. We're going to import pandas as pd. PD is the common term used for pandas.
And pandas is basically creates a data format for us where when you create a pandas data frame, it looks like an Xscale spreadsheet.
And you'll see that in a minute when we start digging deeper into the code. Pandas just wonderful because it plays nice with all the other modules in there.
And then we have NumPy, which is our numbers python. And the numbers python allows us to do different mathematical sets on here.
We'll see right off the bat, we're going to take our np and we're going to go ahead and seed the randomness with it with zero. So np.random.seed is seeding that is zero.
This code doesn't actually show anything. We're going to go ahead and run it because I need to make sure I have all those loaded. And then let's take a look at the next module on here.
The next six slides, including this one, are all about exploring the data. Remember, I told you half of this is about looking at the data and getting it all set.
So let's go ahead and take this code right here, the script, and let's get that over into our Jupyter notebook. And here we go. We've gone ahead and uh run the imports.
And I'm going to paste the code down here.
And let's take a look and see what's going on. The first thing we're doing is we're actually loading the iris data.
And if you remember up here, we loaded the module that tells it how to get the iris data. Now we're actually assigning that data to the variable iris.
And then we're going to go ahead and use the DF to define data frame.
And that's going to equal PD. And if you remember that's pandas as pd, so that's our pandas.
And panda data frame. And then we're looking at iris data and columns equals iris feature names.
And we're going to do the DF head. And let's run this so you can understand what's going on here.
The first thing you want to notice is that our DF has created uh what looks like an Excel spreadsheet.
And in this Excel spreadsheet, we have set the columns.
So up on the top you can see the four different columns, and then we have the data, iris.data down below. It's a little confusing without knowing where this data is coming from.
So let's look at the bigger picture, and I'm going to go print. I'm just going to change this for a moment.
And we're going to print Oliviris and see what that looks like.
So when I print Oliviris, I get this long list of information.
And you can scroll through here and see all the different titles on there.
What's important to notice is that first off there's a brackets at the beginning. So this is a Python dictionary.
And in a Python dictionary, you'll have a key or a label, and this label pulls up whatever information comes after it.
So feature names, which we actually used over here under columns, is equal to an array of sepal length, sepal width, pedal length,
pedal width. These are the different names they have for the four different columns. And if you scroll down far enough, you'll also see data down here. Oh goodness, it came up right towards the top.
And uh data is equal to the different data we are looking at.
Now there's a lot of other things in here like target, we're gonna be pulling that up in a minute, and there's also the names, uh the target names, which is further down,
and we'll show you that also in a minute.
Let's go ahead and set that back
to the head.
And this is one of the neat features of pandas and panda data frames.
Is when you do df.head or the pandadata frame.head, it'll print the first five lines of the data set in there,
along with the headers if you have it. In this case, we have the column headers set to iris features.
And in here you'll see that we have 01234. In Python, most arrays always start at zero. So when you look at the first five, it's going to be zero one two three four, not one, two, three, four, five.
So now we've got our iris data imported into a data frame. Let's take a look at the next piece of code in here.
And so in this section here of the code, we're going to take a look at the target.
And let's go ahead and get this into our notebook, this piece of code, so we can discuss it a little bit more in detail.
So here we are in our Jupyter notebook. I'm going to put the code in here.
And before I run it, I want to look at a couple things going on. So we have uh df species, and this is interesting because right here you'll see where I have df species in brackets,
which is uh the key code for creating another column. And here we have iris.target. Now these are both in the pandas setup on here. So in pandas we can do either one.
I could have just as easily done iris and then in brackets target, depending on what I'm working on. Both are acceptable.
Let's go ahead and run this code and see how this changes. And what we've done is we've added the target from the iris data set as another column on the end.
Now, what species is, this is what we're trying to predict.
So we have our data, which tells us the answer for all these different pieces, and then we've added a column with the answer.
That way, when we do our final setup, we'll have the ability to program our neural network to look for these different data and know what a Setosa
is, or a Vera color, which we'll see in just a minute, or Virginica. Those are the three that are in there. And now we're going to add one more column.
I know we're organizing all this data over and over again. It's kind of fun. There's a lot of ways to organize it.
What's nice about putting everything onto one data frame is I can then do a printout and it shows me exactly what I'm looking at.
And I'll show you where you can where that's different, where you can alter that and do it slightly differently. But let's go ahead and put this into our script up to debt now.
And here we go, we're gonna put that down here.
And we're gonna run that.
And let's talk a little bit about what we're doing. Now we're exploring data, and one of the challenges is knowing how good your model is. Did your model work?
And to do this, we need to split the data. And we split it into two different parts. They usually call it the training and the testing.
And so in here, we're gonna go ahead and put that in our database so you can see it clearly.
And we've set it df, and remember you can put brackets, this is creating another column, is train, so we're gonna use part of it for training, and this equals np,
remember that stands for numpy, dot random dot uniform. So we're generating a random number between zero and one, and we're gonna do it for each of the rows. That's where the length df comes from.
So each row gets a generated number, and if it's less than 0.75, it's true, and if it's greater than 0.75, it's false.
This means we're gonna take 75% of the data, roughly, because there's a randomness involved, and we're gonna use that to train it, and then the other 25%
we're gonna hold off to the side and use that to test it later on. So let's flip back on over and see what the next step is.
So now that we've labeled our database for which is training and which is testing, let's go ahead and sort that into two different variables,
train and test. And let's take this code and let's bring it into our project. And here we go, let's paste it on down here. And before I run this, let's just take a quick look at what's going on here.
Is we have up above, we created, remember there's our def.head, which prints the first five rows, and we've added a column is train at the end.
And so we're gonna take that, we're gonna create two variables.
We're gonna create two new data frames. One's called train, one's called test, 75% in train, 25% in test,
and then to sort that out.
We're going to do that by doing DF, our main original data frame with the iris data in it. And if DF is train equals true, it's going to go in the train.
And if df is train equals false, it goes in the test.
And so when I run this, we're going to print out the number in each one. Let's see what that looks like.
And you'll see that it puts 118 in the training module and it puts 32 in the testing module, which lets us know that there was 150 lines of data in here.
So if you went and looked at the original data, you could see that there's 150 lines. And that's roughly 75% in one and 25% for us to test our model on afterward.
So let's jump back to our code and see where this goes. In the next two steps, we want to do one more thing with our data, and that's make it readable to humans.
I don't know about you, but I hate looking at zeros and ones. So let's start with the features, and let's go ahead and take those and make those readable to humans, and let's put that in our code.
Let's see, here we go, paste it in. And you'll see here we've done a couple very basic things. We know that the columns in our data frame, again, this is a panda thing, the DF columns.
And we know the first four of them, 0, 1, 2, 3, that'd be the first four, are going to be the features or the titles of those columns. And so when I run this,
you'll see down here that it creates an index, CPA length, sepa width, pedal length, and pedal width.
And this should be familiar, because if you look up here, here's our column titles going across, and here's the first four.
One thing I want you to notice here is that when you're in a command line, whether it's Jupyter Notebook or you're running command line in the terminal window,
if you just put the name of it, it'll print it out. This is the same as doing print
features.
And uh the shorthand is you just put features in here.
If you're actually writing a code and saving the script and running it by remote, you really need to put the print in there.
But for this, and when I run it, you'll see it gives me the same thing.
But for this, we want to go ahead and we'll just leave it as features, because it doesn't really matter.
And this is one of the fun thing about Jupyter Notebooks is I'm just building the code as we go. And then we need to go ahead and create the labels for the other part.
So let's take a look and see what that.
For our final step in prepping our data, before we actually start running the training and the testing, is we're gonna go ahead and convert the species
on here into something the computer understands. So let's put this code into our script and see where that takes us.
Alright, here we go. We've set y equal to pd.factorize, train species of zero. So let's break this down just a little bit. We have our pandas right here, pd, factorize.
What is factorize doing? I'm gonna come back to that in just a second.
Let's look at what train species is and why we're looking at the group zero on there.
And let's go up here and here is our species.
Remember this? We created this whole column here for species.
And then it has satosa, satosa, satosa, satosa, and if you scroll down enough, you'd also see Virginica and Vera color.
We need to convert that into something the computer understands, zeros and ones.
So the train species of zero, because this is in the format of a of an array of arrays, so you have to have the zero on the end. And then species is just that column.
Factorize goes in there and looks at the fact that there's only three of them.
So when I run this, you'll see that y generates an array that's equal to, in this case, it's the training set, and it's zeros,
ones, and twos representing the three different kinds of flowers we have.
So now we have something the computer understands and we have a nice table that we can read and understand. And now finally we get to actually start doing the predicting. So here we go.
We have two lines of code. Oh my goodness, that was a lot of work to get to two lines of code. But there is a lot in these two lines of code.
So let's take a look and see what's going on here and put this into our full script that we're running.
And let's paste this in here. And let's take a look and see what this is. We have we're creating a variable CLF and we're going to set this equal to the random forest classifier.
And we're passing two variables in here, and there's a lot of variables you can play with. As far as these two are concerned, they're very standard.
N jobs, all that does is to prioritize it. Not something to really worry about. Usually when you're doing this on your own computer, you do n jobs equals two.
If you're working in a larger or big data and you need to prioritize it differently, this is what that number does is it changes your priorities and how it's going to run across the system
and things like that. And then the random state is just how it starts.
Zeros fine for here.
But uh let's go ahead and run this.
We also have clf.fit train features, comma y. And before we run it, let's talk about this a little bit more. CLF.fit. So we're fitting, we're training it.
We are actually creating our random forest classifier right here. This is the code that does everything. Now we're going to take our training set. Remember, we kept our test off to the side.
And we're going to take our training set with the features, and then we're going to go ahead and put that in, and here's our target, the Y.
So the Y is 0, 1, and 2 that we just created, and the features is the actual data going in that we put into the training set. And let's go ahead and run that.
And this is kind of an interesting thing because it printed out the random forest classifier
and everything around it.
And so when you're running this in your terminal window or in a script like this, this automatically treats this like just like when we were up here
and I typed in Y and it printed out Y instead of print y.
This does the same thing.
It treats this as a variable and prints it out. But if you were actually running your code, that wouldn't be the case. And what is printed out is it shows us all the different variables we can change.
And if we go down here, you can actually see n jobs equals two.
You can see the random state equals zero. Those are the two that we sent in there. You would really have to dig deep to find out all these different meanings of all these different settings on here.
Some of them are self-explanatory if you kind of think about it a little bit, like max features is auto.
So all the features that we're putting in there is just going to automatically take all four of them. Whatever we send it, it'll take.
Some of them might have so many features because you're processing words.
There might be like 1.4 million features in there because you're doing legal documents and that's how many different words are in there.
At that point, you probably want to limit the maximum features that you're going to process.
And leaf nodes, that's the end nodes. Remember, we had the fruit and we're talking about the leaf nodes. Like I said, there's a lot in this. We're looking at a lot of stuff here.
So you might have uh in this case, there's probably only think three leaf nodes, maybe four.
You might have thousands of leaf nodes, at which point you do need to put a cap on that and say, okay, you can only go so far, and then we're gonna use all of our resources on processing this.
And that really is what most of these are about is limiting the process and making sure we don't uh overwhelm a system. And there's some other settings in here.
Again, we're not gonna go over all of them. Warm start equals false. Warm start is if you're programming it one piece at a time externally.
Since we're not, we're not gonna have like we're not gonna continually train this particular learning tree.
And again, like I said, there's a lot of things in here that you'll want to look up more detail from the SK Learn. And if you're digging in deep and running a major project on here.
For today, though, all we need to do is fit or train our features and our target why. So now we have our training model.
What's next? If we're going to create a model,
we now need to test it. Remember, we set aside the test feature, test group, 25% of the data. So let's go ahead and take this code and let's put it into our script and see what that looks like.
Okay, here we go.
And we're gonna run this.
And it's going to come out with a bunch of zeros, ones, and twos, which represents the three type of flowers the Setosa, the Virginica, and the Versa color.
And what we're putting into our predict is the test features.
And I always kind of like to know what it is I am looking at. So, real quick, we're going to do test
features.
And remember, features is an array
of sepal length, sepal width, pedal length, pedal width. So when we put it in this way, it actually loads all these different columns that we loaded into features.
So if we did just features, let me just do features in here so you can see what features looks like. This is just playing with the with pandas data frames. You'll see that it's an index.
So when you put an index in like this
into test features, into test, it then takes those columns and creates a panda data frames from those columns. And in this case,
we're going to go ahead and put those into our predict.
So we're going to put each one of these lines of data, the 5.0, 3.4, 1.5, 0.2, and we're going to put those in and we're going to predict what
our new forest classifier is going to come up with. And this is what it predicts. It predicts 0001211222. And
again, this is the flower type, Satosha, Virginica, and VersaColor. So now that we've taken our test features, let's explore that. Let's see exactly what that data means to us.
So the first thing we can do with our predicts is we can actually generate a different prediction model.
When I say different, we're going to view it differently.
It's not that the data itself is different. So let's take this next piece of code and put it into our script.
So we're pasting it in here, and you'll see that we're doing uh predict and we've added underscore proba for probability.
So there's our clf.predict probability. So we're running it just like we ran it up here, but this time with this, we're going to get a slightly different result.
And we're only going to look at the first ten.
So you'll see down here, instead of looking at all of them, uh, which was uh what 27, you'll see right down here that this generates a much larger field on the probability.
And let's take a look and see what that looks like and what that means.
So when we do the predict underscore probaba for probability, it generates three numbers. So we had three leaf nodes at the end. And if you remember from all the theory we did, this is the predictors.
The first one is predicting a one for Setosa, it predicts a zero for Virginica, and it predicts a zero for Versicolor,
and so on and so on and so on. And let's um, you know what, I'm gonna change this just a little bit.
Let's look at ten
to twenty, just because we can.
And we start to get in a little different of data, and you'll see right down here, it gets to this one, this line right here.
And this line has 0, 0.5, 0.5.
And so if we're gonna vote, and we have two equal votes, it's gonna go with the first one.
So it says uh Setosa gets zero votes, Virginica gets 0.5 votes, VersaColor gets 0.5 votes, but let's just go with the Virginica since these two are equal,
and so on and so on down the list. You can see how they vary on here.
So now we've looked at both how to do a basic predict of the features, and we've looked at the predict probability. Let's see what's next on here.
So now we want to go ahead and start mapping names for the plants.
We want to attach names so that it makes a little more sense for us. And that's what we're gonna do in these next two steps.
We're gonna start by setting up our predictions and mapping them to the names. So let's see what that looks like.
And let's go ahead and paste that code in here and run it.
And this goes along with the next piece of code. So we'll skip through this quickly and then come back to it a little bit. So here's iris.target names.
And uh if you remember correctly, this was the the names that we've been talking about this whole time the Setosa, Virginica, VersaColor. And then we're gonna go ahead and do the prediction again.
We've run it, we could have just set a variable equal to this instead of rerunning it each time. But we're going ahead and run it again, clf.predict test features.
Remember that returns the zeros, the ones, and the twos.
And then we're gonna set that equal to predictions. So this time we're actually putting it in a variable, and when I run this,
it distributes and it it comes out as an array, and the array is satosa, satosa, satosa, satosa, satosa. We're only looking at the first five.
We could actually do, let's do the first 25 just so we can see a little bit more on there.
And you'll see that it starts uh mapping it to all the different flower types, the Versicolor and the Virginica in there. And let's see how this goes with the next one.
So let's take a look at the top part of our species in here, and we'll take this code and put it in our script.
And let's put that down here and paste it. There we go, and we'll go ahead and run it.
And let's talk about both these sections of code here and how they go together. The first one is our predictions. And I went ahead and did uh predictions through 25, but let's just do five.
And so we have satosa, satosa, satosa, satosa. That's what we're predicting from our test model.
And then we come down here and we look at test species. I remember I could have just done test.species dot head, and you'll see it says satosa, satosa, setosa, setosa, and they match.
So the first one is what our forest is doing, and the second one is what the actual data is. Now, is we need to combine these so that we can understand what that means.
We need to know how good our forest is, how good it is at predicting the features. So that's where we come up to the next step, which is lots of fun.
We're gonna use a single line of code to combine our predictions and our actuals so we have a nice chart to look at. And let's go ahead and put that in our script in our Jupyter notebook here.
Let's see, let's go ahead and paste that in. And then I'm gonna because I'm on the Jupyter Notebook, I can do a control minus so you can see the whole line there.
There we go, resize it.
And let's take a look and see what's going on here.
We're gonna create in pandas, remember PD stands for pandas, and we're doing a cross tab. This function takes two sets of data and creates a chart out of them.
So when I run it, you'll get a nice chart down here, and we have the predicted species.
So across the top you'll see the Setosa versicolor Virginica and the actual species, Satosinica. And so the way to read this chart, and let's go ahead and take a look on how to read this chart here.
When you read this chart, you have Satosha where they meet, you have Versicolor where they meet, and you have Virginica where they meet. And they're meeting where the actual and the predicted agree.
So this is the number of accurate predictions. So in this case it equals 30. If you add 13 plus 5 plus 12, you get 30.
And then we notice here where it says Virginica, but it was supposed to be versicolor. This is inaccurate.
So now we have two, two inaccurate predictions and 30 accurate predictions.
So we'll say that the model accuracy is 93.
That's just 30 divided by 32. And if we multiply it by 100, we can say that it is 93% accurate. So we have a 93% accuracy with our model.
I did want to add one more quick thing in here on our scripting before we wrap it up. So let's flip back on over to my script.
In here, we're gonna take this uh line of code from up above.
I don't know if you remember it, but predicts equals the iris.target underscore names.
So we're gonna map it to the names, and we're gonna run the prediction, and we ran it on test features.
But you know, we're not just testing it, we want to actually deploy it. So at this point, I would go ahead and change this, and this is an array of arrays.
This is really important when you're running these to know that.
So you need the double brackets, and I could actually create data, maybe let's let's just do two flowers. So maybe I'm processing more data coming in, and we'll put two flowers in here.
And then uh I actually want to see what the answer are is.
So let's go ahead and type in preds and print that out. And when I run this, you'll see that I've now predicted two flowers that maybe I measured in my front yard as versicolor and versicolor.
Not surprising since they put the same data in for each one.
This would be the actual uh end product going out to be used on data that you don't know the answer for.
So that's going to conclude our scripting part of this. Introducing Naive Bayes Classifier.
Have you ever wondered how your mail provider implements spam filtering, or how online news channels perform news text classification,
or how companies perform sentimental analysis of their audience on social media. All of this and more is done through a machine learning algorithm called Naive Bayes Classifier.
Welcome to Naive Bayes Tutorial. My name is Richard Kirshner.
I'm with the Simply Learn team. That's www.simplylearn.com. Get certified, get ahead.
What's in it for you? We'll start with what is Naive Bayes, a basic overview of how it works.
We'll get into Naive Bayes and machine learning, where it fits in with our other machine learning tools, why do we need naive Bayes?
And understanding Naive Bayes classifier, a much more in-depth of how the math works in the background.
Finally, we'll get into the advantages of the naive Bayes classifier in the machine learning setup.
And then we'll roll up our sleeves and do my favorite part.
We'll actually do some Python coding and do some text classification using the Naive Bayes.
What is Naive Bayes?
Let's start with a basic introduction to the Bayes theorem, named after Thomas Bayes from the 1700s, who first coined this in the Western literature.
Naive Bayes classifier works on the principle of conditional probability as given by the Bayes theorem.
Before we move ahead, let us go through some of the simple concepts in the probability that we will be using.
Let us consider the following example of tossing two coins.
Here we have two quarters, and if we look at all the different possibilities of what they can come up as, we get that they can come up as head heads, they can come up as head tell,
tell head, and tell tell. When doing the math on probability, we usually denote probability as a P, a capital P.
So the probability of getting two heads equals one fourth. You can see on our data set we have two heads, and this occurs once out of the four possibilities.
And then the probability of at least one tell occurs three-quarters of the time.
You'll see on three of the coin tosses we have tells in them.
And out of four, that's three fourths. And then the probability of the second coin being a head given the first coin is tail is one half.
And the probability of getting two heads given the first coin is a head is one half. We'll demonstrate that in just a minute and show you how that math works.
Now when we're doing it with two coins, it's easy to see. But when you have something more complex, you can see where these pro these formulas really come in and work.
So the Bayes theorem gives us the conditional probability of an event A given another event B has occurred.
In this case, the first coin toss will be B and the second coin toss A.
This can be confusing because we've actually reversed the order of them and go from B to A instead of A to B. You'll see this a lot when you work in probabilities.
The reason is we're looking for event A. We want to know what that is, so we're going to label that A since that's our focus. And then given another event B has occurred.
In the Bayes theorem, as you can see on the left, the probability of A occurring given B has occurred equals the probability of B occurring given A has occurred
times the probability of A over the probability of B. This simple formula can be moved around just like any algebra formula.
And we could do the probability of A after a given B times probability of B equals the probability of B given A times probability of A.
You can easily move that around and multiply it and divide it out.
Let us apply Bayes' theorem to our example.
Here we have our two quarters, and we'll notice that the first two probabilities of getting two heads and at least one tail, we compute directly off the data.
So you can easily see that we have one example, HH, out of four, one fourth, and we have three with tells in them, giving us three quarters or three fourths,
seventy-five percent.
The second condition, the second uh set, three and four, we're gonna explore a little bit more in detail.
Now we stick to a simple example with two coins because you can easily understand the math. The probability of throwing a tell doesn't matter what comes before it, and the same with the heads.
So it's still gonna be 50% or one half. But when that comes when that probability gets more complicated, let's say you have a D6 dice or some other instance, then this formula really comes in handy.
But let's stick to the simple example for now. In this sample space, let A be the event that the second coin is head and b be the event that the first coin is tells.
Again, we reversed it because we want to know what the second event's gonna be. So we're gonna be focusing on A. And we write that out as the probability of A given B.
And we know this from our formula that that equals the probability of B given A times the probability of A over the probability of B.
And when we plug that in, we plug in the probability of the first coin being tells given the second coin is heads,
and the probability of the second coin being heads given the first coin being over the probability of the first coin being tells.
When we plug that data in, and we have the probability of the first coin being tells given the second coin is heads, times the probability of the second coin being heads
over the probability of the first coin being tells. You can see it's a simple formula to calculate.
We have one half times one half over one half, or one half equals 0.5, or one fourth.
So the Bayes theorem basically calculates the conditional probability of the occurrence of an event based on prior knowledge of conditions that might be related to the event.
We will explore this in detail when we take up an example of online shopping further in this tutorial. Understanding naive Bayes and machine learning.
Like with any of our other machine learning tools, it's important to understand where the naive Bayes fits in the hierarchy.
So under the machine learning, we have supervised learning, and there is other things like unsupervised learning. There's also a reward system.
This falls under the supervised learning.
And then under the supervised learning, there's classification, there's also regression, but we're going to be in the classification side.
And then under classification is your naive Bayes.
Let's go ahead and glance into where is Naive Bayes used. Let's look at some of the use scenarios for it.
As a classifier, we use it in face recognition.
Is this Cindy or is it not Cindy or whoever? Or it might be used to identify parts of the face that they then feed into another part of the face recognition program.
This is the eye, this is the nose, this is the mouth.
Weather prediction, is it going to be rainy or sunny? Medical recognition.
News prediction.
It's also used in medical diagnosis. We might diagnose somebody as either as high risk or not as high risk for cancer or heart disease or other ailments.
And news classification.
You look at the Google News and it says, well, is this political or is this world news? Or a lot of that's all done with a naive Bayes.
Understanding naive Bayes classifier.
Now we already went through a basic understanding with the coins and the two heads and two tells and head tail, tailheads, etc.
We're going to do just a quick review on that and remind you that the naive Bayes classifier is based on the Bayes theorem, which gives a conditional probability of
event A given event B.
And that's where the probability of A given B equals the probability of B given A times probability of A over probability of B.
Remember this is an algebraic function, so we can move these different entities around.
We can multiply by the probability of B, so it goes to the left hand side, and then we could divide by the probability of A given B.
And just as easily come up with a new formula for the probability of B.
To me, staring at these algebraic functions kind of gives me a slight headache. It's a lot better to see if we can actually understand how this data fits together in a table.
And let's go ahead and start applying it to some actual data so you can see what that looks like.
So we're gonna start with the shopping demo problem statement.
And remember we're gonna solve this first in uh table form so you can see what the math looks like, and then we're gonna solve it in Python.
And in here we want to predict whether the person will purchase a product. Are they gonna buy or don't buy?
Very important if you're running a business, you want to know how to maximize your profits or at least maximize the purchase of the people coming into your store.
And we're gonna look at a specific combination of different variables. In this case, we're gonna look at the day, the discount, and the free delivery.
And you can see here under the day we want to know whether it's uh on the weekday.
You know, somebody's working, they come in after work, or maybe they don't work.
Weekend, you can see the bright colors coming down there, celebrating not being in work or holiday.
And did we offer a discount that day? Yes or no. Did we offer free delivery that day? Yes or no.
And from this, we want to know whether the person is going to buy based on these traits so we can maximize them and find out the best system for getting somebody to come in and purchase
our goods and products from our store.
Now, having a nice visual is great, but we do need to dig into the data.
So let's go ahead and take a look at the data set. We have a small sample data set of 30 rows. We're showing you the first 15 of those rows for this demo.
Now, the actual data file you can request, just type in below under the comments on the YouTube video, and we'll send you some more information and send you that file.
As you can see here, the file is very simple: columns and rows. We have the day, the discount, the free delivery, and did the person purchase or not.
And then we have under the day whether it was a weekday, a holiday, was it the weekend.
This is a pretty simple set of data, and long before computers, people used to look at this data and calculate this all by hand.
So let's go ahead and walk through this and see what that looks like when we put that into tables.
Also note in today's world, we're not usually looking at three different variables in 30 rows.
Nowadays, because we're able to collect data so much, we're usually looking at 27, 30 variables across hundreds of rows.
The first thing we want to do is we're gonna take this data and uh based on the data set containing our three inputs,
day, discount, and free delivery, we're gonna go ahead and populate that to frequency tables for each attribute.
So we want to know if they had a discount, how many people buy and did not buy.
Did they have a discount, yes or no?
Do we have a free delivery? Yes or no. On those days, how many people made a purchase and how many people didn't? And the same with the three days of the week. Was it a weekday, a weekend, a holiday?
And did they buy, yes or no?
As we dig in deeper to this table for our Bayes theorem, let the event buy be A. Now remember when we looked at the coins, I said we really want to know what the outcome is.
Did the person buy or not?
And that's usually event A is what you're looking for. And the independent variables discount free delivery and day B B.
So we'll call that probability of B.
Now let us calculate the likelihood table for one of the variables.
Let's start with day, which includes weekday, weekend, and holiday. And let us start by summing all of our rows.
So we have the uh weekday row, and out of the weekdays, there's nine plus two, so it's eleven weekdays, there's eight weekend days, and eleven
Well, it's a lot of holidays. And then we want to sum up the total number of days. So we're looking at a total of 30 days.
Let's start pulling some information from our chart and see where that takes us.
And when we fill in the chart on the right, you can see that nine out of twenty four purchases are made on the weekday, seven out of twenty four purchases on the weekend.
And 8 out of 24 purchases on a holiday.
And out of all the people who come in, 24 out of 30 purchase. You can also see how many people do not purchase.
On the weekday, it's two out of six didn't purchase, and so on and so on.
We can also look at the totals, and you'll see on the right we put together some of the formulas. The probability of making a purchase on the weekend comes out 11 out of 30.
So out of the 30 people who came into the store throughout the weekend, weekday, and holiday, 11 of those purchases were made on the weekday.
And then you can also see the probability of them not making a purchase.
And this is done for doesn't matter which day of the week.
So we call that probability of no buy would be six over thirty or point two. So there's a 20% chance that they're not going to make a purchase no matter what day of the week it is.
And finally we look at the probability of BFA.
In this case, we're going to look at the probability of the weekday and not buying.
Two of the no buys were done out of the weekend out of the six people who did not make purchases.
So when we look at that, the probability of the weekday without a purchase is going to be 0.33 or 33%.
Let's take a look at this at different probabilities.
And based on this likelihood table, let's go ahead and calculate conditional probabilities as below.
The first three we just did, the probability of making a purchase on the weekday is 11 out of 30, or roughly 36 or 37%, 0.367.
The probability of not making a purchase at all, doesn't matter what day of the week, is roughly 0.2 or 20%.
And the probability of a weekday no purchase is roughly 2 out of 6. So 2 out of 6 of our no purchases were made on the weekday.
And then finally we take our P of A B.
If you lucked, we've kept the symbols up there. We got P of probability of B, probability of A, probability of B if A.
We should remember that the probability of A if B is equal to the first one times the probability of no per
buys over the probability of the weekday.
So we could calculate it both off the table we created. We can also calculate this by the formula and we get the 0.367, which equals or 0.33 times 0.2 over 0.367,
which equals 0.179, or roughly uh 17 to 18%.
And that'd be the probability of no purchase done on the weekday.
And this is important because we can look at this and say, as the probability of buying on the weekday is more than the probability of not buying on the weekday,
we can conclude that customers will most likely buy the product on a weekday.
Now we've kept our chart simple and we're only looking at one aspect. So you should be able to look at the table and come up with the same information or the same conclusion.
That should be kind of intuitive at this point.
Next, we can take the same setup.
We have the frequency tables of all three independent variables. Now we can construct the likelihood tables for all three of the variables we're working with.
We can take our day like we did before, and we have weekday, weekend, and holiday, and we filled in this table. And then we can come in and also do that for the discount, yes or no.
Did they buy, yes or no?
And we fill in that fold table. So now we have our probabilities for a discount and whether the discount leads to a purchase or not, and the probability for free delivery.
Does that lead to a purchase or not?
And this is where it starts getting really exciting.
Let us use these three likelihood tables to calculate whether a customer will purchase a product on a specific combination of day, discount, and free delivery
or not purchase.
Here, let us take a combination of these factors.
Day equals holiday, discount equals yes, free delivery equals yes.
Let's dig deeper into the math and actually see what this looks like.
And we're going to start with looking for the probability of them not purchasing on the following combinations of days. We're actually looking for the probability of A equal no buy, no purchase.
And our probability of B we're going to set equal to is it a holiday? Did they get a discount? Yes.
And was it a free delivery? Yes.
Before we go further, let's look at the original equation.
The probability of A if B equals the probability of B given the condition A and the probability times probability of A over the probability of B occurring.
Now this is basic algebra, so we can multiply this information together.
So when you see the probability of A given B, in this case the condition is B, C, and D, or the three different variables we're looking at.
And when you see the probability of B, that would be the conditions. We're actually going to multiply those three separate conditions out.
Probability of, you'll see that in a second in the formula, times the full probability of A over the full probability of B.
So here we are back to this, and we're going to have let a equal no purchase. And we're looking for the probability of B on the condition A, where A sets for three different things.
Remember that equals the probability of A given the condition B.
And in this case, we just multiply those three different variables together.
So we have the probability of the discount times the probability of free delivery times the probability is the day equal a holiday.
Those are our three variables of the probability of A if B.
And then that is going to be multiplied by the probability of them not making a purchase.
And then we want to divide that by the total probabilities, and they're multiplied together.
So we have the probability of a discount, the probability of a free delivery, and the probability of it being on a holiday.
When we plug those numbers in, we see that one out of six were no purchase on a discounted day, two out of six were a no purchase on a free delivery day,
and three out of six were a no purchase on a holiday.
Those are our three probabilities of A of B multiplied out. And then that has to be multiplied by the probability of a no purchase.
And remember the proper probability of a no buy is across all the data.
So that's where we get the six out of thirty.
We divide that out by the probability of each category over the total number. So we get the 20 out of 30 had a discount, 23 out of 30 had a yes for free delivery, and 11 out of 30 were on a holiday.
We plug all those numbers in, we get 0.178.
So in our probability math, we have a 0.178 if it's a no-buy for a holiday, a discount, and a free delivery.
Let's turn that around and see what that looks like if we have a purchase.
I promise this is the last page of math before we dig into the Python script.
So here we're calculating the probability of the purchase using the same math we did to find out if they didn't buy.
Now we want to know if they did buy. And again, we're going to go by the day equals a holiday, discount equals yes, free delivery equals yes, and let a equal buy.
Now, right about now you might be asking, why are we doing both calculations?
Why would we want to know the no buys and buys for the same data going in?
Well, we're going to show you that in just a moment, but we have to have both of those pieces of information so that we can figure it out as a percentage as opposed to a probability equation.
And we'll get to that normalization here in just a moment.
Let's go ahead and walk through this calculation.
And as you can see here, the probability of A on the condition of B, B being all three categories, did we have a discount with a purchase? Did we have a free delivery with a purchase?
And did we is the day equal to holiday?
And when we plug this all into that formula and multiply it all out, we get our probability of a discount, probability of a free delivery, probability of the day being a holiday,
times the overall probability of it being a purchase divided by, again, multiplying the three variables, out, the full probability of there being a discount,
the full probability of being a free delivery, and the full probability of there being a day equal holiday.
And that's where we get this 19 over 24 times 21 over 24 times 8 over 24 times the P of A, 24 over 30,
divided by the probability of the discount, the free delivery times the day, or 20 over 30, 23 over 30, times 11 over 30, and that gives us our.
So, what are we going to do with these two pieces of data we just generated?
Well, let's go ahead and go over them. We have a probability of purchase equals 0.986.
We have a probability of no purchase equals 0.178.
So finally we have a conditional probabilities of purchase on this day.
Let us take that, we're going to normalize it, and we're going to take these probabilities and turn them into percentages.
This is simply done by taking the sum of probabilities, which equals 0.98686 plus 0.178, and that equals the 1.164. If we divide each probability by the sum, we get the percentage.
And so the likelihood of a purchase is 84.71%, and the likelihood of no purchase is 15.29%
given these three different variables.
So it's if it's on a holiday, if it's uh with a discount and has free delivery, then there's an 84.71% chance that the customer's going to come in and make a purchase. Hooray!
They purchased our stuff. We're making money. If you're owning a shop, that's like is the bottom line is you want to make some money so that you can keep your shop open and have a living.
Now, I promised you that we were going to be finishing up the math here with a few pages. So we're going to move on and we're going to do two steps.
The first step is I want you to understand why you want to under why you want to use the naive Bayes. What are the advantages of naive Bayes?
And then once we understand those advantages, we'll just look at that briefly, then we're going to dive in and do some Python coding.
Advantages of Naive Bayes classifier.
So let's take a look at the six advantages of the naive Bayes classifier. And we're going to walk around this lovely wheel. It looks like an origami folded paper.
The first one is very simple and easy to implement.
Certainly, you could walk through the tables and do this by hand. You've got to be a little careful because the notations can get confusing.
You have all these different probabilities, and I certainly mess those up as I put them on, you know, is it on the top or the bottom? You've got to really pay close attention to that.
When you put it into Python, it's really nice because you don't have to worry about any of that. You let the Python handle that, the Python module.
But understanding it, you can put it on a table and you can easily see how it works, and it's a simple algebraic function.
It needs less training data.
So if you have smaller amounts of data, this is a great, powerful tool for that.
Handles both continuous and discrete data.
It's highly scalable with number of predictors and data points.
So as you can see, you can just keep multiplying different probabilities in there, and you can cover not just three different variables or sets. You can now expand this to even more categories.
Number five, it's fast. It can be used in real-time predictions. This is so important.
This is why it's used in a lot of our predictions on online shopping carts, referrals, spam filters, is because there's no time delay as it has to go through and figure out a neural network
or one of the other mini setups where you're doing classification.
And certainly there's a lot of other tools out there in the machine learning that can handle these, but most of them are not as fast as the naive Bayes.
And then finally, it's not sensitive to irrelevant features.
So it picks up on your different probabilities, and if you're short on data on one probability, you can kind of it automatically adjust for that.
Those formulas are very automatic, and so you can still get a very solid predictability, even if you're missing data or you have overlapping data for two completely different areas.
We see that a lot in doing census and studying of people and habits, where they might have one study that covers one aspect, another one that overlaps, and because the two overlap,
they can then predict the unknowns for the group that they haven't done the second study on, or vice versa.
So it's very powerful in that it.
Is not sensitive to the irrelevant features, and in fact, you can use it to help predict features that aren't even in there.
So now we're down to my favorite part. We're gonna roll up our sleeves and do some actual programming. We're gonna do the use case text classification.
Now I would challenge you to go back and send us a note on the notes below underneath the video and request the data for the shopping cart.
So you can plug that into Python code and do that on your own time so you can walk through it since we walked through all the information on it.
But we're gonna do a Python code doing text classification, very popular for doing the naive bays.
So we're gonna use our new tool to perform a text classification of news headlines and classify news into different topics for a news website.
As you can see here, we have a nice image of the Google News and then related on the right, subgroups. I'm not sure where they actually pulled the actual data we're gonna use from.
It's one of the standard sets. But certainly this can be used on any of our news headlines in classification.
So let's see how it can be done using the naive Bayes classifier. Now we're at my favorite part. We're actually gonna write some Python script. Roll up our sleeves.
And we're gonna start by doing our imports. These are very basic imports, including our news group, and we'll take a quick glance at the target names.
Then we're gonna go ahead and start training our data set and putting it together. We'll put together a nice graph because it's always good to have a graph to show what's going on.
And once we've trained it and we've shown you a graph of what's going on, then we're gonna explore how to use it and see what that looks like.
Now I'm gonna open up my favorite editor or inline editor for Python.
You don't have to use this, you can use whatever your editor that you like, whatever uh interface, IDE you want. This just happens to be the Anaconda Jupyter Notebook.
And I'm gonna paste that first piece of code in here so we can walk through it. And let's make it a little bigger on the screen so you have a nice view of what's going on.
Uh and we're using Python 3, in this case 3.5.
So this would work in any of your 3x.
If you have it set up correctly, it should also work in a lot of the 2x. You just have to make sure all of the versions of the modules match your Python version.
And in here, you'll notice the first line is your percentage matplot library inline.
Now, three of these lines of code are all about plotting the graph. This one lets the notebook notes and this is the inline setup, that we want the graphs to show up on this page.
Without it, in a notebook like this, which is an uh explorer interface, it won't show up.
Now, a lot of IDEs don't require that.
A lot of them, like on if I'm working on one of my other setups, it just has a pop-up and the graph pops up on there.
So you have a that setup also. But for this, we want the mapplot library inline.
And then we're going to import numpy as np.
That's number python, which has a lot of different formulas in it that we use for both of our sklearn module.
And we also use it for any of the upper math functions in Python. And it's very common to see that as np, numpy as np.
The next two lines are all about our graphing.
Remember I said three of these were about graphing? Well, we need our mapplot library.pyplot as plt, and you'll see that plt is a very common setup, as is the SNS and just like the NP.
And we're going to import Cborne as SNS, and we're going to do the SNS.set.
Now, Cborne sits on top of Pyplot, and it just makes a really nice heat map. It's really good for heat maps. And if you're not familiar with heat maps, that just means we give it a color scale.
The term comes from the brighter red it is, the hotter it is in some form of data, and you can set it to whatever you want. And we'll see that later on.
So those you'll see that those three lines of code here are just importing the graph function so we can graph it.
And as a data scientist, you always want to graph your data and have some kind of visual.
It's really hard just to shove numbers in front of people and they look at it and it doesn't mean anything.
And then from the sklearn.data sets, we're going to import the fetch20 newsgroups.
Very common one for analyzing, tokenizing words and setting them up and exploring how the words work and how do you categorize different things when you're dealing with documents.
And then we set our data equal to fetch 20 newsgroups. So our data variable will have the data in it.
And we're going to go ahead and just print the target names, data.target names. And let's see what that looks like.
And you'll see here we have alt atheism, comp graphics, comp OSMS windows.misscellaneous. And it goes all the way down to talkpolitics.miscellaneous, talkreligion.miscellaneous.
These are the categories they've already assigned to this news group.
And it's called fetch 20 because you'll see there's, I believe, there's 20 different topics in here or 20 different categories as we scroll down.
Now we've gone through the 20 different categories and we're going to go ahead and start defining all the categories and set up our data.
So we're actually getting here going to go ahead and get it, get the data all set up and take a look at our data.
And let's move this over to our Jupyter notebook and let's see what this code does.
First, we're going to set our categories. Now, if you noticed up here, I could have just as easily set this equal to data dot target underscore names because it's the same thing.
But we want to kind of spell it out for you so you can see the different categories.
It kind of makes it more visual so you can see what your data is looking like in the background.
Once we've created the categories, we're going to open up a train set.
So this training set of data is going to go into fetch 20 newsgroups, and it's a subset in there called train and categories equals categories. So we're pulling out those categories that match.
And then if you have a train set, you should also have the testing set. We have test equals fetch 20 newsgroups, subset equals test, and categories equals categories.
Let's go down one side so it all fits on my screen.
There we go.
And just so we can really see what's going on, let's see what happens when we print out one part of that data.
So it creates train and under train it creates train.data and we're just going to look at data piece number five.
And let's go ahead and run that and see what that looks like.
And you can see when I print train.data number five, under train, it prints out one of the articles. This is article number five. You can go through and read it on there.
And we can also go in here and change this to test, which should look identical because it's splitting the data up into different groups, train and test.
And we'll see test number five is a different article, but it's another article in here.
And maybe you're curious and you want to see just how many articles are in here. We could do length of train.data.
And if we run that, you'll see that the training data has 11,314 articles.
So we're not going to go through all those articles. That's a lot of articles.
But we can look at one of them just so you can see what kind of information is coming out of it and what we're looking at. And we'll just look at number five for today.
And here we have it. Rewording the Second Amendment IDs, VTT line 58, lines 58 in article, uh, etc. And you can scroll all the way down and see all the different parts to there.
Now we've looked at it, and that's pretty complicated when you look at one of these articles to try to figure out how do you weight this.
If you look down here, we have different words, and maybe the word from.
Well, from is probably in all the articles, so it's not gonna have a lot of meaning as far as trying to figure out whether this article fits one of the categories or not.
So trying to figure out which category it fits in based on these words is where the challenge comes in.
Now that we've viewed our data, we're gonna dive in and do the actual predictions. This is the actual naive base.
And we're gonna throw another model at you or another module at you here in just a second.
We can't go into too much detail, but it deals specifically working with words and text and what they call tokenizing those words.
So let's take this code and let's uh skip on over to our Jupyter notebook and walk through it.
And here we are in our Jupyter Notebook. Let's paste that in there, and I can run this code right off the bat. It's not actually gonna display anything yet, but it has a lot going on in here.
So at the top, we had the print module from the earlier one.
I didn't know why that was in there. So we're gonna start by importing our necessary packages.
And from the SK LearnFeatures extraction.txt, we're gonna import TFIDF Vectorizer.
I told you we're gonna throw a module at you.
We can't go too much into the math behind this or how it works. You can look it up. The notation for the math is usually tf.idf.
And that's just a way of weighing the words. And it weighs the words based on how many times are used in a document, how many times or how many documents they're used in.
And it's a well-used formula. It's been around for a while.
It's a little confusing to put this in here. But let's let it know that it just goes in there and weights the different words in the document for us. That way we don't have to wait.
And if you put a weight on it, if you remember I was talking about that up here earlier, if these are all emails, they probably all have the word from in them.
From probably has a very low weight. It has very little value in telling you what this document's about.
Same with words like in, in article, in articles, in, cost of, un, maybe cost might, or where words like criminal,
weapons, destruction, these might have a heavier weight because they describe a little bit more what the article's doing. Well, how do you figure out all those weights in the different articles?
That's what this module does. That's what the TFIDF vectorizer is going to do for us.
And then we're going to import our sklearn.naibase, and that's our multinomial NB.
Multinomial Naive Bayes. Pretty easy to understand that, where that comes from. And then finally we have the Sky Learn pipeline import make pipeline.
Now the make pipeline is just a cool piece of code because we're going to take the information we get from the TFIDF vectorizer and we're going to pump that into
the multinomial NB. So a pipeline is just a way of organizing how things flow.
It's used commonly, you probably already guessed what it is if you've done any businesses. They talk about the sales pipeline.
If you're on a work crew or project manager, you have your pipeline of information that's going through or your projects and what has to be done in what order.
That's all this pipeline is. We're going to take the TFID vectorizer and then we're going to push that into the multinomial NB.
Now we've designated that as the variable model.
We have our pipeline model.
And we're going to take that model, and this is just so elegant, this is done in just a couple lines of code.
Model.fit and we're going to fit the data and first the train data and then the train target.
Now the train data has the different articles in it.
You can see the one we were just looking at.
And the train dot target is what category they already categorize that that particular article as.
And what's happening here is the train data is going into the TFID vectorizer.
So when you have one of these articles, it goes in there, it weights all the words in there. So there's thousands of words with different weights on them.
I remember once running a model on this, and I literally had 2.4 million tokens go into this. So when you're dealing like large document bases, you can have a huge number of different words.
It then takes those words, gives them a weight, and then based on that weight, based on the words and the weights, and then puts that into the multinomial
NB.
And once we go into our naive base, we want to put the train target in there.
So the train data that's been mapped to the TFID vectorizer is now going through the multinomial NB, and then we're telling it, well, these are the answers.
These are the answers to the different documents. So this document that has all these words with these different weights from the first part is going to be whatever category it comes out of.
Maybe it's the talk show or the article on religion miscellaneous.
Once we fit that model, we can then take labels and we're going to set that equal to model dot predict.
Most of the SK Learn use the term dot predict to let us know that we've now trained the model and now we want to get some answers.
And we're going to put our test data in there because our test data is the stuff we held off to the side.
We didn't train it on there and we don't know what's going to come up out of it. And we just want to find out how good our labels are. Do they match what they should be?
Now I've already run this through.
There's no actual output to it to show. This is just setting it all up.
This is just training our model, creating the labels so we can see how good it is, and then we move on to the next step to find out what happened.
To do this, we're going to go ahead and create a confusion matrix and a heat map.
So The confusion matrix, which is confusing just by its very name, is basically gonna ask how confused is our answer?
Did it get it correct?
Or did it miss some things in there or have some missed labels?
And then we're gonna put that on a heat map so we'll have some nice colors to look at to see how that plots out.
Let's go ahead and take this code and see how that uh take a walk through it and see what that looks like.
So back to our Jupyter notebook.
I'm gonna put the code in there.
And let's go ahead and run that code.
Take it just a moment.
And remember we had the inline, that way my graph uh shows up on the inline here.
And let's walk through the code and then we'll look at this and see what that means.
So make it a little bit bigger.
There we go.
No reason not to use the whole screen.
Too big.
So we have here from sklearn matrix import confusion matrix.
And that's just gonna generate a set of data that says I the prediction was such the actual truth was either agreed with it or was something different.
And it's gonna add up those numbers so we can take a look and just see how well it worked. And we're gonna set a variable mat equal to confusion matrix.
We have our test target, our test data that was not part of the training.
Very important in data science, we always keep our test data separate. Otherwise, it's not a valid model if we can't properly test it with new data.
And this is the labels we created from that test data. These are the ones that we predict it's going to be.
So we go in and we create our SN heat map.
The SNS is our C born, which sits on top of the Piplot.
So when we create a SNS.heat map, we take our confusion matrix, and it's gonna be uh mat.t.
And then we have other variables that go into the sns.heat map.
We're not gonna go into detail what all the variables mean.
The annotation equals true, that's what tells it to put the numbers here. So you have the 166, the one, the 0001, format D and C bar equals false have to do with the uh format.
If you take those out, you'll see that some things disappear. And then the x tick labels and the y tick labels, those are our target names.
And you can see right here that's the alt atheism comp graphics, comp OSMS windows.miscellaneous.
And then finally, we have our plt.x label. Remember the SNS or the C born sits on top of our mapplot library, our PLT. And so we want to just tell it X label equals a true is is true.
The labels are true, and then the Y label is prediction label.
So when we say a true, this is what it actually is, and the prediction is what we predicted.
And let's look at this graph because that's probably a little confusing the way we rattled through it.
And what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna go ahead and flip back to the slides, because they have a black background they put in there that helps it shine a little bit better
so you can see the graph a little bit easier.
So in reading this graph, what we want to look at is how the color scheme has come out.
And you'll see a line right down the middle diagonally from upper left to bottom right.
What that is, is if you look at the labels, we have our predicted label on the left and our true label on the right. Those are the numbers where the prediction and the true come together.
And this is what we want to see is we want to see those lit up. That's what that heat map does. Is you can see that it did a good job of finding those data.
And you'll notice that there's a couple of red spots on there where it missed.
You know, it's a little confused when we talk about talk religion miscellaneous versus talk politics miscellaneous, social religion Christian versus alt
atheism.
It mislabeled some of those. And those are very similar topics, so you could understand why it might mislabel them.
But overall, it did a pretty good job.
If we're gonna create these models, we want to go ahead and be able to use them.
So let's see what that looks like.
To do this, let's go ahead and create a definition, a function to run.
And we're gonna call this function, let me just expand that just a notch here. There we go.
I like mine in big letters.
Predict categories. We want to predict the category.
We're gonna send it s, a string, and then we're sending it train equals train. We have our training model, and then we had our pipeline, model equals model.
This way we don't have to resend these variables each time.
The definition knows that because I said train equals train and I put the equal for model.
And then we're gonna set the prediction equal to the model.predict s.
So it's gonna send whatever string we send to it. It's gonna push that string through the pipeline, the model pipeline.
It's gonna go through and uh tokenize it and put it through the TFIDF, convert that into numbers and weights for all the different documents and words,
and then it'll put that through our naive base.
And from it, we'll go ahead and get our prediction. We're gonna predict what value it is.
And so we're gonna return train.target names predict of zero.
And remember that the train.target names, that's just categories. I could have just as easily put uh categories in there dot predict of zero.
So we're taking the prediction, which is a number, and we're converting it to an actual category.
We're converting it from um, I don't know what the actual numbers are, but let's say zero equals alt atheism. So we're gonna convert that zero to the word. Or uh one maybe it equals comp graphics.
So we're gonna convert number one into comp graphics. That's all that is.
And then we gotta go ahead and and then we need to go ahead and run this.
So I load that up, and then once I run that, we can start doing some predictions.
I'm gonna go ahead and type in predict category, and let's just do predict category Jesus Christ.
And it comes back and says it's social, religion, Christian.
That's pretty good. Now note I didn't put print on this.
One of the nice things about the Jupyter Notebook editor and a lot of inline editors is if you just put the name of the variable out, as returning the variable train.target underscore names,
it'll automatically print that for you.
In your own IDE, you might have to put in print. Let's see where else we can take this. And maybe you're a space science buff. So how about sending load to international
space station?
And if we run that, we get science space.
Or maybe you're a uh automobile buff.
And let's do um, oh they were gonna tell me Audi is better than BMW, but I'm gonna do BMW is better than an Audi. So maybe you're a car buff.
And we run that, and you'll see it says recreational. I'm assuming that's what REC stands for.
Autos.
So I did a pretty good job labeling that one.
How about uh if we have something like a caption running through there? President of India.
And if we run that, it comes up and says talk politics miscellaneous.
So when we take our definition or our function and we run all these things through, kudos! We made it!
We were able to correctly classify texts into different groups based on which category they belong to using the naive Bayes classifier.
Now we did throw in the pipeline, the TF IDF vectorizer, we threw in the graphs.
Those are all things that you don't necessarily have to know to understand the naive Bayes setup or classifier, but they're important to know.
One of the main uses for the Naive Bayes is with the TF IDF tokenizer or vectorizer, where it tokenizes a word and adds labels.
And we use the pipeline because you need to push all that data through and it makes it really easy and fast.
You don't have to know those to understand naive Bayes, but they certainly help for understanding the industry and data science.
And we can see our categorizer, our naive Bayes classifier.
We were able to predict the category religion, space, motorcycles, autos, politics, and properly classify all these different things we pushed into our prediction and our trained model.
Before we dive into the SVM, let's take a look at applications of the support vector machine.
At least some general ones that are commonly used with it.
Face detection, text, and hypertext categorization, classification of images, and bioinformatics.
These are only but a few of those that are used with this SVM.
As we go through this lesson, see if you can figure out what other ones you could apply it to, and also what you would want to use some other tools for.
So in this example, last week, my son and I visited a fruit shop. Dad, is that an apple or a strawberry?
So the question comes up: what fruit did I just pick up from the fruit stand? After a couple of seconds, you could figure out that it was a strawberry.
So let's take this model a step further and let's uh why not build a model which can predict an unknown data?
And in this, we're going to be looking at some sweet strawberries or crispy apples. We wanted to be able to label those two and decide what the fruit is. And we do that by having data already put in.
So we already have a bunch of strawberries, we know our strawberries, and they're already labeled as such.
We already have a bunch of apples, we know our apples and are labeled as such. Then once we train our model, that model then can be given the new data. And the new data is this image.
In this case, you can see a question mark on it, and it comes through and goes, it's a strawberry. In this case, we're using the support vector machine model.
SVM is a supervised learning method that looks at data and sorts it into one of two categories.
And in this case, we're sorting the strawberry into the strawberry side. At this point, you should be asking the question, how does the prediction work?
Before we dig into an example with numbers, let's apply this to our fruit scenario.
We have our support vector machine.
We've taken it and we've taken labeled sample of data, strawberries and apples, and we draw on a line down the middle between the two groups.
This split now allows us to take new data, in this case an apple and a strawberry, and place them in the appropriate group based on which side of the line they fall in.
And that way we can predict the unknown.
As colorful and tasty as the fruit example is, let's take a look at another example with some numbers involved, and we can take a closer look at how the math works.
In this example, we're going to be classifying men and women. And we're going to start with a set of people with a different height and a different weight.
And to make this work, we'll have to have a sample data set of female, where you have their height and weight, 174, 65, 174, 88,
and so on. And we'll need a sample data set of the male. They have a height 179, 90, 180 to 80, and so on. Let's go ahead and put this on a graph so we have a nice visual.
So you can see here we have two groups based on the height versus the weight.
And on the left side, we're going to have the women, on the right side, we're going to have the men.
Now, if we're going to create a classifier, let's add a new data point and figure out if it's male or female. So before we can do that, we need to split our data first.
We can split our data by choosing any of these lines. In this case, we've drawn two lines through the data in the middle that separates the men from the women.
But to predict the gender of a new data point, we should split the data in the best possible way. And we say the best possible way because this line has a maximum space that separates the two classes.
Here you can see there's a clear split between the two different classes. And in this one there's not so much a clear split. This doesn't have the maximum space that separates the two.
That is why this line best splits the data. We don't want to just do this by eyeballing it.
And before we go further, we need to add some technical terms to this.
We can also say that the distance between the points and the line should be as far as possible.
In technical terms, we can say the distance between the support vector and the hyperplane should be as far as possible.
And this is where the support vectors are the extreme points in the data set.
And if you look at this data set, they have circled two points, which seem to be right on the outskirts of the women and one on the outskirts of the men.
And hyperplane has a maximum distance to the support vectors of any class.
Now you'll see the line down the middle, and we call this the hyperplane because when you're dealing with multiple dimensions, it's really not just a line but a plane of intersections.
And you can see here where the support vectors have been drawn in dashed lines.
The math behind this is very simple.
We take D plus, the shortest distance to the closest positive point, which would be on the men's side, and D minus is the shortest distance to the closest negative point, which is on the women's side.
The sum of D plus and D minus is called the distance margin, or the distance between the two support vectors that are shown in the dashed lines.
And then by finding the largest distance margin, we can get the optimal hyperplane. Once we've created an optimal hyperplane, we can easily see which side the new data fits in.
And based on the hyperplane, we can say the new data point belongs to the male gender. Hopefully that's clear how that works on a visual level.
As a data scientist, you should also be asking what happens if the hyperplane is not optimal?
If we select a hyperplane having low margin, then there is a high chance of misclassification.
This particular SVM model, the one we discussed so far, is also called or referred to as the LSVM.
So far so clear, but a question should be coming up.
We have our sample data set.
But instead of looking like this, what if it looked like this, where we have two sets of data, but one of them occurs in the middle of another set?
You can see here where we have the blue and the yellow, and then blue again on the other side of our data line. In this data set, we can't use a hyperplane.
So when you see data like this, it's necessary to move away from a 1D view of the data to a two-dimensional view of the data. And for the transformation, we use what's called a kernel function.
The kernel function will take the 1D input and transfer it to a two dimensional output.
As you can see in this picture here, the 1D, when transferred to a two dimensional, makes it very easy to draw a line between the two data sets.
What if we make it even more complicated?
How do we perform an SVM for this type of data set?
Here you can see we have a two-dimensional data set where the data is in the middle surrounded by the green data on the outside.
In this case, we're going to segregate the two classes. We have our sample data set, and if you draw a line through, it's obviously not an optimal hyperplane in there.
So to do that, we need to transfer the 2D to a 3D array.
And when you translate it into a three-dimensional array using the kernel, you can see where you can place a hyperplane right through it and easily split the data.
Before we start looking at a programming example and dive into the script, let's look at the advantage of the support vector machine.
We'll start with high dimensional input space, or sometimes referred to as the curse of dimensionality.
We looked at earlier one dimension, two dimension, three dimension.
When you get to a thousand dimensions, a lot of problems start occurring with most algorithms that have to be adjusted for. The SVM automatically does that in high dimensional space.
One of the high dimensional space, one high dimensional space that we work on is sparse document vectors.
This is where we tokenize the words in documents so we can run our machine learning algorithms over them. I've seen ones get as high as 2.4 million different tokens.
That's a lot of vectors to look at. And finally we have regularization parameter.
The regularization parameter or lambda is a parameter that helps figure out whether we're going to have a bias or overfitting of the data.
Whether it's going to be overfitted to a very specific instance or it's going to be biased to a high or low value.
With the SVM, it naturally avoids the overfitting and bias problems that we see in many other algorithms.
These three advantages of the support vector machine make it a very powerful tool to add to your repertoire of machine learning tools.
Now, we did promise you a use case study where we're actually going to dive into some Python programming. And so we're going to go into a problem statement and start off with the zoo.
So in the zoo example, we have family members going to the zoo and we have the young child going, Dad, is that a group of crocodiles or alligators? Well, that's hard to differentiate.
And zoos are a great place to start looking at science and understanding how things work, especially as a young child.
And so we can see the parents sitting here thinking, well, what is the difference between a crocodile and an alligator?
Well, one, crocodiles are larger in size, alligators are smaller in size, snout width, the crocodiles have a narrow snout, and alligators have a wider snout.
And of course, in the modern day and age, the father's sitting here thinking, how can I turn this into a lesson for my son? And he goes, let a support vector machine segregate the two groups.
I don't know if my dad ever told me that, but that would be funny. Now in this example, we're not going to use actual measurements and data.
We're just using that for imagery. And that's very common in a lot of machine learning algorithms and setting them up.
But let's roll up our sleeves and we'll talk about that more in just a moment as we break into our Python script.
So here we arrive in our actual coding.
And I'm going to move this into a Python editor in just a moment.
But let's talk a little bit about what we're going to cover.
First, we're going to cover in the code the setup, how to actually create our SVM.
And you're going to find that there's only two lines of code that actually create it, and the rest of it is done so quick and fast that it's all here in the first page.
And we'll show you what that looks like as far as our data, because we're going to create some data. I talked about creating data just a minute ago.
And so we'll get into the creating data here, and you'll see this nice correction of our two blobs, and we'll go through that in just a second.
And then the second part is we're going to take this and we're going to bump it up a notch. We're going to show you what it looks like behind the scenes.
But let's start with actually creating our setup.
I like to use the Anaconda Jupyter Notebook because it's very easy to use, but you can use any of your favorite Python editors or setups and go in there.
But let's go ahead and switch over there and see what that looks like.
So here we are in the Anaconda Python notebook or Anaconda Jupyter Notebook with Python. We're using Python 3. I believe this is 3.5, but it should be work in any of your 3x versions.
And uh you'd have to look at the SK Learn and make sure if you're using a 2x version or an earlier version. And let's go ahead and put our code in there.
And one of the things I like about the Jupyter Notebook is I can go up to View, and I'm going to go ahead and toggle the line numbers on to make it a little bit easier to talk about.
And we can even increase the size because this is edited in in this case I'm using Google Chrome Explorer and that's how it opens up for the editor.
Although anyone, any like I said, any editor will work. Now the first step is going to be our imports.
And we're going to import four different parts. The first two I want you to look at are line one and line two are NUPy as np and mapplotlibrary.pyplot as plt.
Now these are very standardized imports when you're doing work. The first one is the numbers Python.
We need that because part of the platform we're using uses that for the numpy array.
And I'll talk about that in a minute so you can understand why we want to use a numpy array versus the standard Python array.
And normally it's pretty standard setup to use np for numpy. The map plot library is how we're going to view our data.
So this has uh you do need the np for the sklearn module, but the map plot library is purely for our use for visualization.
And so you really don't need that for the SVM, but we're gonna put it there so you have a nice visual aid and we can show you what it looks like.
That's really important at the end when you finish everything, so you have a nice display for everybody to look at.
And then finally, we're gonna I'm gonna jump one ahead to line number four. That's the sklearn.datasets.samples generator import make blobs.
And I told you that we were gonna make up data.
And this is a tool that's in the sklearn to make up data.
I personally don't want to go to the zoo, get in trouble for jumping over the fence, and probably get eaten by the crocodiles or alligators as I work on measuring their snouts and width and length.
Instead, we're just gonna make up some data.
And that's what that make blobs is. It's a wonderful tool if you're ready to test your your uh setup and you're not sure about what data you're gonna put in there.
You can create this blob and it makes it real easy to use. And finally, we have our actual SVM, the SKLearn Import SVM on line three.
So that covers all our imports. We're gonna create, remember I used the make blobs to create data, and we're gonna create a capital X and a lowercase y equals make blobs in samples equals 40.
So we're gonna make 40 lines of data.
It's gonna have two centers with a random state equals 20. So each each each group's gonna have 20 different pieces of data in it.
And the way that looks is that we'll have under X um an XY plane.
So I'll have two numbers under X, and Y will be zero or one.
That's the two different centers. So we have uh yes or no, in this case alligator or crocodile, that's what that represents.
And then I told you that the actual SK learner, the SVM, is in two lines of code, and we see it right here with CLF equals SVM
dot svc kernel equals linear, and I set SQL to one. Although in this example, since we are not uh regularizing the data, since we want it to be very clear and easy to see, I went ahead,
you can set it to a thousand a lot of times when you're not doing that.
But for this thing, linear, because it's a very simple linear example, we only have the two dimensions, and it'll be a nice linear hyperplane, it'll be a nice linear line instead of a full plane.
So we're not dealing with a huge amount of data.
And then all we have to do is do CLF.fit X comma y. And that's it.
CLF has been created, and then we're gonna go ahead and display it.
And I'm gonna talk about this display here in just a second, but let me go ahead and run this code.
And this is what we've done is we've created two blobs. You'll see the blue on the side and then kind of an orange-ish uh on the other side. That's our two sets of data.
They represent one represents crocodiles and one represents alligators, and then we have our measurements. In this case, we have like the uh width and length of the snout.
And I did say I was gonna come up here and talk just a little bit about our plot, and you'll see PLT, that's what we imported. We're gonna do a scatter plot.
That means we're just putting dots on there.
And then look at this notation. I have the capital X, and then in brackets I have a colon, comma zero.
That's from NumPy.
If you did that in a regular array, you'll get an error in a Python array. You have to have that in a NumPy array. It turns out that our make blobs returns a numpy array.
And this notation is great because what it means is the first part is the colon, means we're gonna do all the rows. That's all the data in our blob we created under capital X.
And then the second part has a comma zero.
We're only gonna take the first value.
And then if you notice we do the same thing, but we're going to take the second value. Remember, we always start with 0 and then 1.
So we have column 0 and column 1. And you can look at this as our xy plots.
The first one is the x plot, and the second one is the y plot.
So the first one is on the bottom, 0, 2, 4, 6, 8, and 10. And then the second one, x of the 1, is the 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10 going up the left hand side.
S equals 30 is just the size of the dots. We can see them. It's said real tiny dots. And then C map equals plt.cm.paired.
And you'll also see the C equals Y. That's the color.
We're using two colors, 0, 1, and that's why we get the nice blue and the two different colors for the alligator and the crocodile.
Now you can see here that we did this, the actual fit was done in two lines of code. A lot of times there'll be a third line where we regularize the data.
We set it between like minus 1 and 1 and we reshape it. But for this it's not necessary, and it's also kind of nice because you can actually see what's going on.
And then if we wanted to, we wanted to actually run a prediction, let's take a look and see what that looks like.
And to predict some new data, and we'll show this again as we get towards the end of digging in deep, you can simply assign your new data.
In this case, I am giving it a width and length 3.4 and a width and length 5.6.
And note that I put the data as a set of brackets, and then I have the brackets inside.
And the reason I do that is because when we're looking at data, it's designed to process a large amount of data coming in. We don't want to just process one line at a time.
And so in this case, I'm processing two lines, and then I'm just going to print and you'll see CLF dot predict new data.
So the CLF and the dot predict part is going to give us an answer, and let's see what that looks like.
And you'll see 0 1. So predicted the first one, the 3.4 is going to be on the one side, and the 5.6 is going to be on the other side. So one came out as an alligator and one came out as a crocodile.
Now that's pretty short explanation for the setup, but really we want to dug in and see what it's going on behind the scenes. And let's see what that looks like.
So the next step is to dig in deep and find out what's going on behind the scenes.
And also put that in a nice pretty graph.
We're going to spend more work on this than we did actually generating the original model.
And you'll see here that we go through a few steps, and I'll move this over to our editor in just a second. We come in, we create our original data.
It's exactly identical to the first part, and I'll explain why we redid that and show you how not to redo that.
And then we're going to go in there and add in those lines.
We're going to see what those lines look like and how to set those up.
And finally, we're going to plot all that on here and show it, and you'll get a nice graph with the what we saw earlier when we were going through the theory behind this,
where it shows the support vectors and the hyperplane.
And those are done where you can see the support vectors as the dashed lines and the solid line, which is the hyperplane.
Let's get that into our Jupyter notebook.
Before I scroll down to a new line, I want you to notice line 13. It has plot show. And we're going to talk about that here in just a second, but let's scroll down to a new line down here.
And I'm going to paste that code in.
And you'll see that the plot show has moved down below. Let's scroll up a little bit.
And if you look at the top here of our new section, one, two, three, and four is the same code we had before.
And let's go back up here and take a look at that.
We're going to fit the values on our SVM and then we're going to plot scatter it, and then we're going to do a plot show.
So you should be asking why are we redoing the same code?
Well, when you do the plot show, that blanks out what's in the plot. So once I've done this plot show, I have to reload that data.
Now we could do this simply by removing it up here, rerunning it, and then coming down here, and then we wouldn't have to rerun these first four lines of code.
Now in this, it doesn't matter too much, and you'll see the plot show is down here and then removed right there on line five. I'll go ahead and just delete that out of there.
Because we don't want to blank out our screen. We want to move on to the next setup.
So we can go ahead and just skip the first four lines because we did that before.
And let's take a look at the ax equals plt.gca.
Now right now we're actually spending a lot of time just graphing. That's all we're doing here.
Okay, so this is how we just display a nice graph with our results and our data.
AX is very standard note used variable when you talk about PLT, and it's just setting it to that axis, the last axes in the PLT.
It can get very confusing if you're working with many different layers of data on the same graph, and this makes it very easy to reference the AX.
So this reference is looking at the PLT that we created and we already mapped out our two blobs on.
And then we want to know the limits.
So we want to know how big the graph is, and we can find out the x limit and the y limit simply with the get x limit and get y limit commands, which is part of our MetPlot library.
And then we're going to create a grid, and you'll see down here we have we've set the variable xx equal to np.line space x limit 0 x limit 1,
30, and we've done the same thing for the y space.
And then we're going to go in here and we create a mesh grid. And this is a numpy command.
So we're back to our numbers Python.
Let's go through what these numpy commands mean with the line space and the mesh grid.
We've taken xx, small x xx equals mp line space, and we have our x limit zero and our x limit one, and we're going to create 30 points on it. And we're going to do the same thing for the y axis.
Now this has nothing to do with our evaluation. It's uh all we're doing is we're creating a grid of data.
And so we're creating a set of points between 0 and the x limit.
We're creating 30 points, and the same thing with the y. And then the mesh grid loops those all together so it forms a nice grid.
So if we were going to do this, say between the limit 0 and 10 and do 10 points, we would have a 0, 0, 1, 1, 0, 1, 0,
2, 0, 3, 0, 4 to 10, and so on. You can just imagine a point at each corner of one of those boxes. And the mesh grid combines them all.
So we take the yy and the xx we created and creates the full grid. And we've set that grid into the y coordinates and the xx coordinates.
Now remember when working with numbi and python, we like to separate those.
We like to have instead of it being x comma one, you know, x comma y and then x2, comma, y2, and the next set of data, it would be uh a column of x's and a column of y's.
And that's what we have here is we have a column of y's and we put it as a capital YY and a column of X's, capital XX, with all those different points being listed.
And finally we get down to the numpy V stack.
Just as we created those in the mesh grid, we're now gonna put them all into one array, xy array.
Now that we've created the stack of data points, we're gonna do something interesting here. We're gonna create a value z and the z equals the CLF.
That's our uh that's our support vector machine we created, and we've already trained.
And we have a dot decision function, and we're gonna put the xy in there.
So here we have all this data. We're gonna put that xy in there, that data, and we're gonna reshape it. And you'll see that we have the xx dot shape in here.
This literally takes the xx, resets it up, connected to the y and the z value.
Let's us know whether it is the left hand side. It's going to generate three different values, the z value does.
And it'll tell us whether that data is a support vector to the left, the hyperplane in the middle, or the support vector to the right. So it generates three different values for each of those points.
And those points have been reshaped so that they're right on a line on those three different lines. So we've set all of our data up, we've labeled it to three different areas, and we've reshaped it.
And we've just taken 30 points in each direction.
If you do the math, you have 30 times 30, so that's 900 points of data. And we separate it between the three lines and reshaped it to fit those three lines.
We can then go back to our map plot library where we've created the AX, and we're going to create a contour. And you'll see here we have contour capital XX capital Y.
These have been reshaped to fit those lines. Z is the labels. So now we have the three different points with the labels in there, and we can set the colors equals K.
And I told you we had three different labels, but we have uh three levels of data. The alphas just makes it kind of see-through. So it's only uh 0.5 of the value in there.
So when we graph it, the data will show up from behind it, wherever the lines go. And finally, the line styles.
This is where we set the two support vectors to be dash dash lines, and then a single one is just a straight line. That's what all that setup does. And then finally, we take our ax.scatter.
We're gonna go ahead and plot the support vectors, but we've programmed it in there so that they look nice, like the dash dash line and the dashed line on that grid.
And you can see here when we do the CLF dot support vectors, we are looking at column zero and column one, and then again we have the s
equals 100, so we're gonna make them larger, and the line width equals one, face colors equals none.
Let's take a look and see what that looks like when we show it.
And you can see we get down to our end result, it creates a really nice graph.
We have our two support vectors and dashed lines, and they have the near data, so you can see those two points, or in this case the four points where those lines nicely cleave the data,
and then you have your hyperplane down the middle, which is as far from the two different points as possible, creating the maximum distance.
So you can see that we have our nice output for the size of the body and the width of the snout, and we've easily separated the two groups of crocodile and alligator. Congratulations, you've done it.
We've made it. Of course, these are pretend data for our crocodiles and alligators, but this hands-on example will help you to encounter any support vector machine projects in the future,
and you can see how easy they are to set up and look at in depth. Okay, we're going to cover the K nearest neighbors, a lot referred to as KNN.
And KNN is really a fundamental place to start in the machine learning.
It's a basis of a lot of other things, and just the logic behind it is easy to understand and incorporated in other forms of machine learning.
So today, what's in it for you?
Why do we need KNN?
What is KNN?
How do we choose the factor K?
When do we use KNN?
How does KNN algorithm work?
And then we'll dive into my favorite part, the use case.
Predict whether your person will have diabetes or not. That is a very common and popular used data set as far as testing out models and learning how to use the different models in machine learning.
By now, we all know machine learning models make predictions by learning from the past data available.
So we have our input values, our machine learning model builds on those inputs of what we already know, and then we use that to create a predicted output.
Is that a dog?
No, dear, you can differentiate between a cat and a dog based on their characteristics.
Cats.
Cats have sharp claws, uses to climb, smaller length of ears, meows and purrs, doesn't love to play around.
Dogs have dull claws, bigger length of ears, barks, loves to run around.
You usually don't see a cat running around people, although I do have a cat that does that. Where dogs do.
And we can look at these, we can say we can evaluate the sharpness of the claws, how sharp are their claws, and we can evaluate the length of the ears,
and we can usually sort out cats from dogs based on even those two characteristics.
Now tell me if it is a cat or a dog. Not question, usually little kids know cats and dogs by now. Unless you live in a place where there's not many cats or dogs.
So if we look at the sharpness of the claws, the length of the ears, and we can see that the cat has smaller ears and sharper claws than the other animals.
Its features are more like cats, it must be a cat.
Sharp claws, length of ears, and it goes in the cat group.
Because KNN is based on feature similarity, we can do classification using KNN classifier.
So we have our input value, the picture of the black cat.
It goes into our trained model and it predicts that this is a cat coming out.
So what is KNN?
What is the KNN algorithm?
K nearest neighbors is what that stands for.
It's one of the simplest supervised machine learning algorithms mostly used for classification.
So we want to know is this a dog or it's not a dog? Is it a cat or not a cat?
It classifies a data point based on how its neighbors are classified.
KNN stores all available cases and classifies new cases based on a similarity measure.
And here we've gone from cats and dogs right into wine, another favorite of mine.
And here you see we have a measurement of sulfur dioxide versus the chloride level, and then the different wines they've tested and where they fall on that graph
based on how much sulfur dioxide and how much chloride. K and KNN is a perimeter that refers to the number of nearest neighbors to include in the majority of the voting process.
And so if we add a new glass of wine there, red or white, we want to know what the neighbors are. In this case we're gonna put uh k equals five.
We'll talk about k in just a minute. A data point is classified by the majority of votes from its five nearest neighbors.
Here the unknown point would be classified as red since four out of five neighbors are red.
So how do we choose k?
How do we know k equals five? I mean that's what is the value we put in there, so we're gonna talk about it.
How do we choose the factor k? K and N algorithm is based on feature similarity.
Choosing the right value of k is a process called parameter tuning and is important for better accuracy.
So at k equals three we can classify we have a question mark in the middle as either a as a square or not. Is it a square or is it in this case a triangle?
And so if we set k equals to three, we're gonna look at the three nearest neighbors. We're gonna say this is a square.
And if we put k equals to seven, we classify as a triangle, depending on what the other data is around it.
And you can see as the k changes, depending on where that point is, that drastically changes your answer.
And uh we jump here or we go, how do we choose the factor of k? You'll find this in all machine learning. Choosing these factors, that's the face you get.
It's like, oh my gosh, did I choose the right k? Did I set it right, my values in whatever machine learning tool you're looking at so that you don't have a huge bias in one direction or the other.
And in terms of KNN, the number of k, if you choose it too low, the bias is based on it's just too noisy.
It's it's right next to a couple things, and it's gonna pick those things, and you might get a skewed answer.
And if your k is too big, then it's gonna take forever to process. So you're gonna run into processing issues and resource issues.
So what we do, the most common use, and there's other options for choosing k, is to use the square root of n.
So n is a total number of values you have, and you take the square root of it.
In most cases you also, if it's an even number, so if you're using uh like in this case squares and triangles, if it's even you want to make your k value odd.
That helps it select better.
So in other words, you're not going to have a balance between two different factors that are equal.
So usually you take the square root of n, and if it's even you add one to it or subtract one from it, and that's where you get the k value from. That is the most common use and it's pretty solid.
It works very well.
When do we use KNN?
We can use KNN when data is labeled.
So you need a label on it. We know we have a group of pictures with dogs, dogs, cats, cats.
Data is noise free.
And so you can see here when we have a class and we have like underweight, 140, 23, hello kitty, normal, that's pretty confusing. We have a high variety of data coming in, so it's very noisy.
And that would cause an issue. Data set is small, so we're usually working with smaller data sets where you might get into gig of data if it's really clean, it doesn't have a lot of noise.
Because KNN is a lazy learner, i.e., it doesn't learn a discriminative function from the training set. So it's very lazy.
So if you have very complicated data and you have a large amount of it, you're not going to use the KNN.
But it's really great to get a place to start. Even with large data, you can sort out a small sample and get an idea of what that looks like using the KNN.
And also just using for smaller data sets, KNN works really good.
How does the KNN algorithm work?
Consider a data set having two variables, height in centimeters and weight in kilograms, and each point is classified as normal or underweight.
So we can see right here we have two variables, you know, true false, or either normal or they're not, they're underweight.
On the basis of the given data, we have to classify the below set as normal or underweight using Kn.
So if we have new data coming in that says fifty-seven kilograms and 177 centimeters, is that going to be normal or underweight?
To find the nearest neighbors, we'll calculate the Euclidean distance.
According to the Euclidean distance formula, the distance between two points in the plane with the coordinates xy and ab is given by distance d
equals the square root of x minus a squared plus y minus b squared.
And you can remember that from the two edges of a triangle. We're computing the third edge since we know the x side and the y side.
Let's calculate it to understand clearly.
So we have our unknown point, and we placed it there in red, and we have our other points where the data is scattered around.
The distance d1 is the square root of 170 minus 167 squared plus 57 minus 51 squared, which is about 6.7.
And distance 2 is about 13.
And distance 3 is about 13.4. Similarly, we will calculate the Euclidean distance of unknown data point from all the points in the data set.
And because we're dealing with small amount of data, that's not that hard to do, and it's actually pretty quick for a computer,
and it's not a really complicated math. You can just see how close is the data based on the Euclidean distance.
Hence, we have calculated the Euclidean distance of unknown data point from all the points as shown, where x1 and y1 equal fifty-seven and 170,
whose class we have to classify. So now we're looking at that, we're saying, well, here's the Euclidean distance, who's gonna be their closest neighbors?
Now let's calculate the nearest neighbor at k equals three.
And we can see the three closest neighbors puts them at normal.
And that's pretty self-evident. When you look at this graph, it's pretty easy to say, okay, what you know, we're just voting. Normal, normal, normal, three votes for normal.
This is gonna be a normal weight.
So majority of neighbors are pointing towards normal, hence, as per Kn algorithm, the class of 57170 should be normal.
So a recap of KNN. Positive integer K is specified along with a new sample.
We select the K entries in our database which are closest to the new sample.
We find the most common classification of these entries. This is the classification we give to the new sample.
So as you can see, it's pretty straightforward.
We're just looking for the closest things that match what we got. So let's take a look and see what that looks like in a use case in Python. So let's dive into the predict diabetes use case.
So, use case, predict diabetes.
The objective predict whether a person will be diagnosed with diabetes or not.
We have a data set of 768 people who were or were not diagnosed with diabetes.
And let's go ahead and open that file and just take a look at that data.
And this is in a simple spreadsheet format. The data itself is comma separated, very common set of data, and it's also a very common way to get the data.
And you can see here we have columns A through I. That's what one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight.
Um, eight columns with a particular attribute, and then the ninth column, which is the outcome, is whether they have diabetes. As a data scientist, the first thing you should be looking at is insulin.
Well, you know, if someone has insulin, they have diabetes because that's why they're taking it.
And that could cause issue in some of the machine learning packages, but for a very basic setup, this works fine for doing the KNN.
And the next thing you notice is it it didn't take very much to open it up. Um I can scroll down to the bottom of the data, there's 768. It's pretty much a small data set.
You know, at 769, I can easily fit this into my RAM on my computer. I can look at it, I can manipulate it, and it's not going to really tax just a regular desktop computer.
You don't even need an enterprise version to run a lot of this. So let's start with importing all the tools we need.
And before that, of course, we need to discuss what IDE I'm using.
Certainly you can use any uh particular editor for Python, but I like to use for doing uh very basic visual stuff the Anaconda, which is great for doing demos,
with the Jupyter Notebook.
And just a quick view of the Anaconda Navigator, which is the new release out there, which is really nice. You can see under Home I can choose my application. We're gonna be using Python 3.6.
I have a couple different uh versions on this particular machine.
If I go under environments, I can create a unique environment for each one, which is nice. And there's even a little button there where I can install different packages.
So if I click on that button and open the terminal, I can then use a simple pip install to install different packages I'm working with.
Let's go ahead and go back under home and we're gonna launch our notebook.
And I've already, you know, kind of like uh the old cooking shows, I've already prepared a lot of my stuff,
so we don't have to wait for it to launch because it takes a few minutes for it to open up a browser window. In this case, I'm gonna it's gonna open up Chrome because that's my default that I use.
And since the script is pre-done, you'll see I have a number of windows open up at the top, the one we're working in.
And uh since we're working on the KNN predict whether a person will have diabetes or not, let's go ahead and put that title in there. And I'm also gonna go up here and click on cell.
Actually, we want to go ahead and first insert a cell below, and then I'm gonna go back up to the top cell, and I'm gonna change the cell type to markdown.
That means this is not gonna run as Python, it's a markdown language. So if I run this first one, it comes up in nice big letters, which is kind of nice. Remind us what we're working on.
And by now, you should be familiar with doing all of our imports. We're gonna import the pandas as pd, import numpy as np, pandas is the uh pandas data frame, and numpy is a number array.
Very powerful tools to use in here.
So we have our imports.
So we've brought in our pandas, our numpy, our two general Python tools.
And then you can see over here we have our train test split.
By now you should be familiar with splitting the data.
We want to split part of it for training our thing and then training our particular model, and then we want to go ahead and test the remaining data just see how good it is.
Preprocessing, a standard scalar preprocessor, so we don't have a bias of really large numbers.
Remember in the data we had like number pregnancies isn't gonna get very large, where the amount of insulin they take can get up to 256. So 256 versus six, that will skew results.
So we want to go ahead and change that so that they're all uniform between uh minus one and one.
And then the actual tool.
This is the K neighbors classifier we're gonna use.
And finally the last three are three tools to test, all about testing our model. How good is it? Let me just put down test on there. And we have our confusion matrix, our F1 score, and our accuracy.
So we have our two general Python modules we're importing, and then we have our six modules specific from the SKLearn setup.
And then we do need to go ahead and run this so that these are actually imported.
There we go.
And then move on to the next step.
And so in this set we're going to go ahead and load the database. We're going to use pandas. Remember pandas is pd.
And we'll take a look at the data in Python. We looked at it in a simple spreadsheet. But usually I like to also pull it up so that we can see what we're doing.
So here's our dataset equals pd.readcsv.
That's a pandas command.
And the diabetes folder I just put in the same folder where my iPython script is.
If you put it in a different folder, you'd need the full length on there. We can also do a quick length of uh the dataset.
That is a simple Python command, L-EN for length.
We might even let's go ahead and print that. We'll go print. And if you do it on its own line, length.dataset in the Jupyter Notebook, it'll automatically print it.
But when you're in most of your different setups, you want to do the print in front of there.
And then we want to take a look at the actual dataset. And since we're in pandas, we can simply do dataset head. And again, let's go ahead and add the print in there.
If you put a bunch of these in a row, you know, the dataset one head, dataset two head, it only prints out the last one.
So I usually always like to keep the print statement in there.
But because most projects only use one data frame, pandas data frame, doing it this way doesn't really matter. The other way works just fine.
And you can see when we hit the run button, we have the 768 lines, which we knew. And we have our pregnancies. It's automatically given a label on the left.
Remember the head only shows the first five lines. So we have zero through four.
And just a quick look at the data, you can see it matches what we looked at before. We have pregnancy, glucose, blood pressure all the way to age, and then the outcome on the end.
And we're gonna do a couple things in this next step.
We're going to create a list of columns where we can't have zero.
There's no such thing as zero skin thickness or zero blood pressure, zero glucose. Uh any of those you'd be dead.
So not a really good factor if they don't if they have a zero in there because they didn't have the data.
And we'll take a look at that because we're gonna start replacing that information with a couple of different things. And let's see what that looks like.
So first we create a nice list, as you can see. We have the values talk about glucose, blood pressure, skin thickness.
Uh and this is a nice way when you're working with columns is to list the columns you need to do some kind of transformation on.
Uh very common thing to do. And then for this particular setup, we certainly could use the there's some panda tools that will do a lot of this where we can replace the NA.
But we're gonna go ahead and do it as a dataset column equals dataset column.replace. This is this is still pandas. You can do it direct. There's also one that's that you look for your N-A-N.
A lot of different options in here.
But the N-A-N, NumPyNA N is what that stands for, is non doesn't exist. So the first thing we're doing here is we're replacing the zero with a numpy none. There's no data there. That's what that says.
That's what this is saying right here.
So put the zero in and we're gonna replace zeros with no data.
So if it's a zero, that means the person's well, hopefully not dead. Hopefully they just didn't get the data.
The next thing we want to do is we're gonna create the mean, which is the n integer from the dataset from the column.mean where we skip NA's. We can do that.
That is uh panda's command there, the skip NA. So we're gonna figure out the mean of that data set.
And then we're gonna take that data set column and we're gonna replace all the NPNAN with the means. Why did we do that?
And we could have actually just uh taken this step and gone right down here and just replaced zero and skip anything we're
except you could actually there's a way to skip zeros and then just replace all the zeros.
But in this case we want to go ahead and do it this way, so you could see that we're switching this to a non-existent value. And we're gonna create the mean. Well, this is the average person.
So if we don't know what it is, if they did not get the data and the data's missing, one of the tricks is you replace it with the average. What is the most common data for that?
This way you can still use the rest of those values to do your computation, and it kind of just brings that particular value, those missing values, out of the equation.
Let's go ahead and take this and we'll go ahead and run it. It doesn't actually do anything, so we're still preparing our data.
If you want to see what that looks like, it we don't have anything in the first few lines, so it's not going to show up. But we certainly could look at a row. Let's do that.
Let's go into our data set with printed data set.
And let's pick in this case let's just do glucose.
And if I run this, this is gonna print all the different glucose levels going down. And we thankfully don't see anything in here that looks like missing data, at least on the ones it shows.
You can see it skipped a bunch in the middle. Because that's what it does. If you have too many lines in Jupyter Notebook, it'll skip a few and and go on to the next in a dataset.
Let me go and remove this. And we'll just zero out that. And of course, before we do any processing, before proceeding any further, we need to split the dataset into our train and testing data.
That way we have something to train it with and something to test it on.
And you're gonna notice we did a little something here with the uh pandas database code.
There we go, my drawing tool. We've added in this right here off the data set.
And what this says is that the first one in pandas, this is from the PD pandas, it's gonna say within the data set, we want to look at the eye location
and it is all rows. That's what that says. So we're gonna keep all the rows, but we're only looking at zero, column zero to eight.
Remember column nine, here it is right up here, we printed it in here, is outcome.
Well, that's not part of the training data, that's part of the answer. Yes, column nine, but it's listed as eight, number eight.
So zero to eight is nine columns. So uh eight is the value.
And when you see it in here, zero, this is actually zero to seven. It doesn't include the last one.
And then we go down here to y, which is our answer, and we want just the last one, just column eight.
And you can do it this way with this particular notation.
And then if you remember we imported the train test split, that's part of the SK learn right there.
And we simply put in our X and our Y. We're gonna do random state equals zero. You don't have to necessarily seed it, that's a seed number.
I think the default is one when you seed it, I'd have to look that up. And then the test size. Test size is 0.2.
That simply means we're gonna take 20% of the data and put it aside so that we can test it later.
That's all that is.
And again, we're gonna run it.
Not very exciting. So far we haven't had any printout other than to look at the data. But that is a lot of this is prepping this data. Once you prep it, the actual lines of code are quick and easy.
And we're almost there, but the actual running of our KNN, we need to go ahead and do a scale the data.
If you remember correctly, we're fitting the data in a standard scalar, which means instead of the data being from you know five to three hundred and three in one column
and the next column is one to six, we're gonna set that all so that all the data is between minus one and one. That's what that standard scalar does. Keeps it standardized.
And we only want to fit the scalar with the training set, but we want to make sure the testing set is the x test going in
is also transformed. So it's processing it the same.
So here we go with our standard scalar. We're gonna call it sc underscore x for the scalar, and we're gonna import the standard scalar into this variable, and then our x train equals sc
underscore x dot fit transform. So we're creating the scalar on the x train variable, and then our x test we're also gonna transform it.
So we've trained and transformed the x train, and then the x test isn't part of that training. It isn't part of the of training the transformer, it just gets transformed, that's all it does.
And again, we're gonna go ahead and run this.
If you look at this, we've now gone through these steps, all three of them.
We've taken care of replacing our zeros for key columns that shouldn't be zero, and we replace that with the means of those columns,
that way that they fit right in with our data models.
We've come down here and we split the data. So now we have our test data and our training data, and then we've taken and we've scaled the data.
So all of our data going in. Now no, we don't tra we don't train the Y part, the Y train and Y test.
That never has to be trained. It's only the data going in.
That's what we want to train in there. Then define the model using K neighbors classifier and fit the train data in the model.
So we do all that data prep, and you can see down here we're only going to have a couple lines of code where we're actually building our model and training it.
That's one of the cool things about Python and how far we've come. It's such an exciting time to be in machine learning because there's so many automated tools.
Let's see, before we do this, let's do a quick length of and let's do y. We want let's just do length of y.
And we get 768. And if we import math, we do math.square root, let's do y train. There we go.
It's actually supposed to be X train.
Before we do this, let's go ahead and do import math and do math square root length of y test.
And when I run that, we get twelve point four oh nine. I want to see show you where this number comes from we're about to use. Twelve is an even number.
So if you know if you're ever voting on things, remember the neighbors all vote. Don't want to have an even number of neighbors voting. So we want to do something odd.
And let's just take one away and we'll make it eleven.
Let me delete this out of here. That's one of the reasons I love Jupyter Notebook because you can flip around and do all kinds of things on the fly.
So we'll go ahead and put in our classifier. We're creating our classifier now, and it's going to be the K neighbors classifier. N neighbors equal eleven.
Remember we did 12 minus 1 for 11, so we have an odd number of neighbors.
P equals 2, because we're looking for is it are they diabetic or not? And we're using the Euclidean metric.
There are other means of measuring the distance. You could do like square square means value. There's all kinds of ways to measure this.
But the Euclidean is the most common one and it works quite well.
It's important to evaluate the model.
Let's use the confusion matrix to do that.
And we're going to use the confusion matrix, wonderful tool, and then we'll jump into the F1 score.
And finally accuracy score, which is probably the most commonly used quoted number when you go into a meeting or something like that.
So let's go ahead and paste that in there, and we'll set the CM equal to confusion matrix.
Y test, y predict.
So those are the two values we're going to put in there. And let me go ahead and run that and print it out.
And the way you interpret this is that you have the y predicted, which would be your title up here.
We could do uh let's just do P-R-E-D.
Predicted across the top and actual going down.
It's always hard to to write in here. Actual.
That means that this column here down the middle, that's the important column.
And it means that our prediction said 94 and prediction and the actual agreed on 94 and 32.
This number here, the 13 and the 15, those are what was wrong.
So you could have like three different if you're looking at this across three different variables instead of just two, you'd end up with the third row down here and that column going down the middle.
So in the first case we have the the and I believe the zero is the ninety-four people who don't have diabetes. The prediction said that 13 of those people did have diabetes and were at high risk.
And the 32 that had diabetes it had correct, but our prediction said another 15 out of that 15 it classified as incorrect.
So you can see where that classification comes in and how that works on the confusion matrix.
Then we're going to go ahead and print the F1 score.
Let me just run that. And you see we get a 0.69 in our F1 score.
The F1 takes into account both sides of the balance of false positives.
Where if we go ahead and just do the accuracy account, and that's what most people think of, is it looks at just how many we got right out of how many we got wrong.
So a lot of people, when you're a data scientist and you're talking to other data scientists, they're going to ask you what the F1 score, the F score is.
If you're talking to the general public or the uh decision makers in the business, they're going to ask what the accuracy is. And the accuracy is always better than the F1 score.
But the F1 score is more telling. It lets us know that there's more false positives than we would like on here.
But 82%, not too bad for a quick flash look at people's different statistics and running an SK Learn and running the KNN,
the K nearest neighbor on it.
So we have created a model using KNN, which can predict whether a person will have diabetes or not, or at the very least,
whether they should go get a checkup and have their glucose checked regularly or not.
The print accuracy score, we got the point eight one eight, was pretty close to what we got, and we can pretty much round that off and just say we have an accuracy of eighty percent.
Tells us it is a pretty fair fit in the model.
So what is K-means clustering?
K-means clustering is an unsupervised learning algorithm.
In this case, you don't have labeled data unlike in supervised learning.
So you have a set of data and you want to group them.
And as the name suggests, you want to put them into clusters, which means objects that are similar in nature, similar in characteristics,
need to be put together.
So that's what k means clustering is all about.
The term k is basically a number.
So we need to tell the system how many clusters we need to perform.
So if k is equal to 2, there will be two clusters, if k is equal to 3, 3 clusters, and so on and so forth. That's what the k stands for.
And of course, there is a way of finding out what is the best or optimum value of k for a given data. We will look at that.
So that is k means clustering.
So let's take an example. K means clustering is used in many many scenarios, but let's take an example of cricket, the game of cricket.
Let's say you received data of a lot of players from maybe all over the country or all over the world, and this data has
information about the runs scored by the people or by the player and the wickets taken by the player.
And based on this information, we need to cluster this data into two clusters, batsmen and bowlers.
So this is an interesting example.
Let's see how we can perform this.
So we have the data which consists of primarily two characteristics, which is the runs and the wickets.
So the bowlers basically take wickets and the batsmen score runs.
There will be, of course, a few bowlers who can score some runs, and similarly, there will be some batsmen who will who would have taken a few wickets.
But with this information, we want to cluster those players into batsmen and bowlers.
So how does this work?
Let's say this is how the data is.
So there are information, there is information on the y-axis about the run scored and on the x-axis about the wickets taken by the players.
So if we do a quick plot, this is how it would look.
And
when we do the clustering, we need to have the clusters like shown in the third diagram out here.
So we need to have a cluster which consists of people who have scored high runs, which is basically the batsmen, and then we need a cluster with people who have taken a lot of wickets,
which is typically the bowlers.
There may be a certain amount of overlap, but we will not talk about it right now.
So with k-means clustering, we will have here that means k is equal to two, and we will have two clusters, which is batsmen and bowlers.
So how does this work?
The way it works is the first step in k-means clustering is the allocation of two centroids randomly.
So two points are assigned as so-called centroids. So in this case we want two clusters, which means k is equal to two.
So two points have been randomly assigned as centroids. Keep in mind these points can be anywhere, they are random points. They are not initially, they are not really the centroids.
Centroid means it's a central point of a given data set, but in this case, when it starts off, it's not really the centroid.
Okay, so these points, though in our presentation here we have shown them one point closer to these data points and another closer to these data points, they can be assigned randomly anywhere.
Okay, so that's the first step.
The next step is to determine the distance of each of the data points from each of the randomly assigned centroids.
So for example, we take this point and find the distance from this centroid and the distance from this centroid.
This point is taken and the distance is found from this centroid and this centroid, and so on and so forth.
For every point, the distance is measured from both the centroids, and then whichever distance is less,
that point is assigned to that centroid. So, for example, in this case, visually it is very obvious that all these data points are assigned to this centroid,
and all these data points are assigned to this centroid, and that's what is represented here in blue color and in this yellow color.
The next step is to actually determine the central point or the actual centroid for these two clusters.
So we have this one initial cluster, this one initial cluster, but as you can see, these points are not really the centroid.
Centroid means it should be the central position of this data set, central position of this data set.
So that is what needs to be determined as the next step.
So the central point or the actual centroid is determined, and the original randomly allocated centroid is repositioned to the actual centroid of this new clusters.
And this process is actually repeated. Now what might happen is some of these points may get reallocated.
In our example, that is not happening probably, but it may so happen that the distance is found between each of these data points once again with these centroids.
And if there is if it is required, some points may be reallocated. We will see that in a later example, but for now we will keep it simple.
So this process is continued till the centroid repositioning stops, and that is our final cluster.
So this is our so after iteration, we come to this position, this situation where the centroid doesn't need any more repositioning,
and that means our algorithm has converged.
Convergence has occurred, and we have the cluster, two clusters, we have the clusters with a centroid.
So this process is repeated.
The process of calculating the distance and repositioning the centroid is repeated till the repositioning stops,
which means that the algorithm has converged and we have the final cluster with the data points and the centroids.
So this is what you're going to learn from this session.
We will talk about the types of clustering, what is K-means clustering, application of K-means clustering.
K-means clustering is done using distance measure.
So we will talk about the common distance measures, and then we will talk about how K-means clustering works and go into the details of K-means clustering algorithm.
And then we will end with a demo and a use case for K-means clustering.
So let's begin.
First of all, what are the types of clustering?
There are primarily two categories of clustering hierarchical clustering and then partitional clustering.
And each of these categories are further subdivided into agglomerative and divisive clustering and k-means and fuzzy C means clustering.
Let's take a quick look at what each of these types of clustering are.
In hierarchical clustering, the clusters have a tree like structure, and hierarchical clustering is further divided into agglomerative
and divisive.
Agglomerative clustering is a bottom-up approach. We begin with each element as a separate cluster and merge them into successively larger clusters. So for example, we have A, B, C, D, E, F.
We start by combining B and C form one cluster, D E and E form one more, then we combine D, E, and F one more bigger cluster, and then add B C
to that, and then finally A to it.
Compare to that, divisive clustering or divisive clustering is a top down approach.
We begin with the whole set and proceed to divide it into successively smaller clusters. So we have A, B, C, D, E, F.
We first take that as a single cluster and then break it down.
Into A, B, C, D, E, and F.
Then we have partitional clustering split into two subtypes, k-means clustering and fuzzy c means.
In k-means clustering, the objects are divided into the number of clusters mentioned by the number k. That's where the k comes from.
So if we say k is equal to 2, the objects are divided into two clusters, c1 and c2.
And the way it is done is the features or characteristics are compared and all objects having similar characteristics are clubbed together.
So that's how k-means clustering is done. We will see it in more detail as we move forward.
And fuzzy c -means is very similar to k-means in the sense that it clubs objects that have similar characteristics together.
but while in k-means clustering, two objects cannot belong to or any object. a single object cannot belong to two different clusters.
in c -means objects can belong to more than one cluster.
So that is the primary difference between k-means and fuzzy c means.
So what are some of the applications of k-means clustering?
K-means clustering is used in a variety of examples or variety of business cases in real life, starting from academic performance,
diagnostic systems, search engines, and wireless sensor networks and many more.
So let us take a little deeper look at each of these examples. Academic performance. So based on the scores of the students, students are categorized into A, B, C, and so on.
Clustering forms a backbone of search engines.
When a search is performed, the search results need to be grouped together.
The search engines very often use clustering to do this.
And similarly, in case of wireless sensor networks, the clustering algorithm plays the role of finding the cluster heads
which collects all the data in its respective cluster.
So clustering, especially k-means clustering, uses distance measure.
So let's take a look at what is distance measure.
So while these are the different types of clustering, in this video we will focus on k-means clustering.
So distance measure tells how similar some objects are.
So the similarity is measured using what is known as distance measure.
And what are the various types of distance measures?
There is Euclidean distance, there is Manhattan distance, then we have squared Euclidean distance measure and cosine distance measure.
These are some of the distance measures supported by k-means clustering.
Let's take a look at each of these.
What is Euclidean distance measure? This is nothing but the distance between two points.
So we have learnt in high school how to find the distance between two points.
This is a little sophisticated formula for that, but we know a simpler one is square root of y2 minus y1 whole square plus x2
minus x1 whole square.
So this is an extension of that formula. So that is the Euclidean distance between two points.
What is the squared Euclidean distance measure?
It's nothing but the square of the Euclidean distance as the name suggests.
So instead of taking the square root, we leave the square as it is.
And then we have Manhattan distance measure. In case of Manhattan distance, it is the sum of the distances across the x-axis and the y axis.
And note that we are taking the absolute value so that the negative values don't come into play.
So that is the Manhattan distance measure. Then we have cosine distance measure.
In this case, we take the angle between the two vectors formed by joining the points from the origin.
So that is the cosine distance measure.
Okay, so that was a quick overview about the various distance measures that are supported by k means.
Now let's go and check how exactly k means clustering works.
Okay, so this is how k-means
clustering works. This is like a flowchart of the whole process.
There is a starting point, and then we specify the number of clusters that we want. Now there are a couple of ways of doing this.
We can do by trial and error.
So we specify a certain number. maybe k is equal to 3 or 4 or 5 to start with. and then as we progress, we keep changing until we get the best clusters.
or there is a technique called elbow technique whereby we can determine the value of k.
what should be the best value of k?
how many clusters should be formed?
So once we have the value of k, we specify that, and then the system will assign that many centroids.
So it picks randomly that to start with randomly that many points that are considered to be the centroids of these clusters.
And then it measures the distance of each of the data points from these centroids and assigns those points to the corresponding centroid from which the distance is minimum.
So each data point will be assigned to the centroid which is closest to it.
And thereby we have k number of initial clusters.
However, this is not the final clusters.
The next step it does is for the new groups, for the clusters that have been formed, it calculates the mean position,
thereby calculates the new centroid position.
The position of the centroid moves compared to the randomly allocated one.
So it's an iterative process. Once again, the distance of each point is measured from this new centroid point.
And if required, the data points are reallocated to the new centroids, and the mean position or the new centroid is calculated once again.
If the centroid moves, then the iteration continues, which means the convergence has not happened, the clustering has not converged.
So as long as there is a movement of the centroid, this iteration keeps happening.
But once the centroid stops moving, which means that the cluster has converged or the clustering process has converged,
that will be the end result.
So now we have the final position of the centroid and the data points are allocated accordingly to the closest centroid.
I know it's a little difficult to understand from this simple flowchart, so let's do a little bit of visualization and see if we can explain it better.
Let's take an example.
If we have a data set for a grocery shop, so let's say we have a data set for a grocery shop and now we want to find out how many clusters this has to be spread across.
So how do we find the optimum number of clusters?
There is a technique called the elbow method.
So when these clusters are formed, there is a parameter called within sum of squares.
And the lower this value is, the better the cluster is. That means all these points are very close to each other.
So we use this within sum of squares as a measure to find the optimum number of clusters that can be formed for a given data set.
So we create clusters or we let the system create clusters of a variety of numbers, maybe of ten.
10 clusters and for each value of k the within SS is measured and the value of k which has the least amount of within SS or WSS that's
taken as the optimum value of k.
So this is the diagrammatic representation.
So we have on the y axis the within sum of squares or w ss and on the x axis we have the number of clusters.
So as you can imagine, if you have k is equal to one, which means all the data points are in a single cluster, the within SS value will be very high
because they are probably scattered all over.
The moment you split it into two, there will be a drastic fall in the within SS value.
that's what is represented here.
But then as the value of k increases, the decrease, the rate of decrease will not be so high.
It will continue to decrease, but probably the rate of decrease will not be high.
So that gives us an idea. So from here we get an idea, for example, the optimum value of K should be either 2 or 3 or at the most 4.
But beyond that, increasing the number of clusters is not dramatically changing the value in WSS because that pretty much gets stabilized.
Okay, now that we have got the value of K and let's assume that these are our delivery points, the next step is basically to
assign two centroids randomly.
So let's say C1 and C2 are the centroids assigned randomly.
Now the distance of each location from the centroid is measured and each point is assigned to the centroid which is closest to it.
So for example, these points are very obvious that these are closest to C1, whereas this point is far away from C2.
So these points will be assigned which are close to C1 will be assigned to C1, and these points or locations which are close to C2 will be assigned to C2.
And then so this is the how the initial grouping is done.
This is part of C1 and this is part of C2.
Then the next step is to calculate the actual centroid of this data because remember C1 and C2 are not the centroids, they've been randomly assigned points,
and only thing that has been done was the data points which are closest to them have been assigned.
But now in this step, the actual centroid will be calculated, which may be for each of these data sets somewhere in the middle.
So that's like the mean point that will be calculated, and the centroid will actually be positioned or repositioned there.
Same with C2.
So the new centroid for this group is C2 in this new position and C1 is in this new position.
Once again, the distance of each of the data points is calculated from these centroids.
Now remember, it's not necessary that the distance still remains the or each of these data points still remain in the same group.
By recalculating the distance, it may be possible that some points get reallocated.
Like so. You see this?
So this point earlier was closer to C2 because C2 was here, but after recalculating
repositioning, it is observed that this is closer to C1 than C2.
So this is the new grouping. So some points will be reassigned.
And again, the centroid will be calculated. And if the centroid doesn't change, so that is a repetitive process, iterative process.
and if the centroid doesn't change —once, the centroid stops changing.
that means the algorithm has converged.
and this is our final cluster.
with this as the centroid, C1 and C2 as the centroids.
these data points as a part of each cluster.
So I hope this helps in understanding the whole process, iterative process of K means clustering.
So let's take a look at The k means clustering algorithm.
Let's say we have x1, x2, x3, n number of points as our inputs, and we want to split this into
k clusters or we want to create k clusters.
So the first step is to randomly pick k points and call them centroids. They are not real centroids because centroid is supposed to be a center point, but they are just called centroids.
And we calculate the distance of each and every input point from each of the centroids.
So the distance of X1 from C1, from C2, C3, each of the distances we calculate.
And then find out which distance is the lowest and assign x1 to that particular random centroid.
Repeat that process for x2.
Calculate its distance from each of the centroids C1, C2, C3 up to CK and find which is the lowest distance and assign x2 to that particular centroid. Same with X3 and so on.
So that is the first round of assignment that is done.
Now we have K groups because there are we have assigned the value of K.
So there are K centroids and so there are K groups.
All these inputs have been split into K groups.
However, remember we picked the centroids randomly, so they are not real centroids.
So now what we have to do?
We have to calculate the actual centroids for each of these groups, which is like the mean position.
Which means that the position of the randomly selected centroids will now change and they will be the mean positions of this
newly formed K groups.
And once that is done, we once again repeat this process of calculating the distance, right?
So this is what we are doing as a part of step 4.
We repeat step 2 and 3. So we again calculate the distance of x1 from the centroid C1, C2, C3, and then C which is the lowest value and assign X1
to that.
Calculate the distance of X2 from C1, C2, C3 or whatever up to CK and find whichever is the lowest distance and
assign x2 to that centroid and so on.
In this process, there may be some reassignment.
X1 was probably assigned to cluster C2, and after doing this calculation, maybe now X1 is assigned to C1.
So that kind of reallocation may happen.
So we repeat the steps 2 and 3 till the position of the centroids don't change or stop changing.
And that's when we have convergence.
So let's take a detailed look at each of these steps.
So we randomly pick k cluster centers, we call them centroids because they are not initially they are not really the centroids.
So we let us name them C1, C2 up to CK.
And then step two, we assign each data point to the closest center.
So what we do? We calculate the distance of each x value from each c value.
So the distance between x1, c1, distance between x1, c2, x1, c3, and then we find which is the lowest value, and?
That's the minimum value we find.
And assign X1 to that particular centroid.
Then we go next to X2.
Find the distance of X2 from C1, X2 from C2, X2 from C3, and so on up to CK, and then assign it to the point
or to the centroid which has the lowest value and so on.
So that is step number two.
In step number three, we now find the actual centroid for each group. So what has happened as a part of step number two?
We now have all the points, all the data points grouped into K groups because we wanted to create K clusters,
right?
So we have K groups, each one may be having a certain number of input values, and they need not be equally distributed, by the way.
Based on the distance, we will have K groups.
But remember the initial values of the C1, C2 were not really the centroids of these groups, right? We assign them randomly.
So now in step three we actually calculate the centroid of each group, which means the original point which we thought was the centroid
will shift to the new position, which is the actual centroid for each of these groups.
Okay?
And we again calculate the distance. So we go back to step two, which is what?
We calculate again the distance of each of these points from the newly positioned centroids, and if required,
we reassign these points to the new centroids.
So as I said earlier, there may be a reallocation.
So we now have a new set or a new group. We still have K groups, but the number of items and the actual assignment may be different from what was in
step two here.
Okay, so that might change.
Then we perform step three once again to find the new centroid of this new group.
So we have again a new set of clusters, new centroids and new assignments.
We repeat this step two again, once again, we find, and then it is possible that after iterating through three or four or five times,
the centroid will stop moving in the sense that when you calculate the new value of the centroid, that will be same as the original value, or there will be very marginal change.
So that is when we say convergence has occurred, and that is our final cluster.
That's the formation of the final cluster.
Alright, so let's see a couple of demos of K-means clustering.
We will actually see some live demos and Python Notebook using Python Notebook.
But before that, let's find out what's the problem that we are trying to solve.
The problem statement is let's say Walmart wants to open a chain of stores across the state of Florida and
it wants to find the optimal store locations.
Now the issue here is if they open too many stores close to each other, obviously they will not make profit, but
if they if the stores are too far apart, then they will not have enough sales.
So how do they optimize this?
Now for an organization like Walmart, which is an e-commerce giant, they already have the addresses of their customers in their database.
So they can actually use this information or this data and use K means clustering to find the optimal location.
Now, before we go into the Python notebook and show you the live code.
I wanted to take you through very quickly a summary of the code in the slides and then we will go into the Python notebook.
So in this block we are basically importing all the required libraries like NumPy, Matplotlib, and so on.
And we are loading the data that is available in the form of let's say the addresses.
For simplicity's sake, we will just take them as some data points.
Then the next thing we do is quickly do a scatter plot to see how they are related to each other with respect to each other.
So in the scatter plot we see that there are a few distinct groups already being formed.
So you can actually get an idea about how the cluster would look and how many clusters, what is the optimal number of clusters.
And then starts the actual k-means clustering process.
So we will assign each of these points to the centroids, and then check whether they are the optimal distance,
which is the shortest distance, and assign each of the points, data points, to the centroids, and then go through this iterative
process till the whole process converges.
And finally, we get an output like this.
So we have four distinct clusters, and
which is, if we can say that this is how the population is probably distributed across Florida state, and these centroids
are like the location where the store should be, the optimum location where the store should be.
So that's the way we determine the best locations for the store, and that's how we can help Walmart find the best locations for their stores in Florida.
So now let's take this into Python notebook. Let's see how this looks when we are learning running the code live.
Alright, so this is the code for k-means clustering in Jupyter Notebook.
We have a few examples here which we will demonstrate how k-means clustering is used, and even there is a small implementation of k-means clustering as well.
Okay, so let's get started. Okay, so this block is basically importing the various libraries that are required, like Matplotlib and NumPy and so on and so forth,
which would be used as a part of the code. Then we are going and creating blobs which are similar to clusters. Now, this is a very neat feature which is available in ScikitLearn.
Make blobs is a nice feature which creates clusters of data sets. So that's a wonderful functionality that is readily available for us to create some test data kind of thing.
Okay, so that's exactly what we are doing here. We are using make blobs and we can specify how many clusters we want. So centers we are mentioning here.
So it will go ahead and so we just mentioned four, so it will go ahead and create some test data for us, and this is how it looks, as you can see.
Visually, also we can figure out that there are four distinct classes or clusters in this data set, and that is what make
blobs actually provides.
Now, from here onwards, we will basically run the standard k-means functionality that is readily available. So we really don't have to implement k-means itself.
The k-means functionality or the function is readily available. You just need to feed the data and we'll create the clusters. So this is the code for that.
We import k-means and then we create an instance of k-means and we specify the value of k. This n underscore clusters is the value of k.
Remember, k means in k means k is basically the number of clusters that you want to create, and it is a integer value.
So this is where we are specifying that. So we have k is equal to 4.
And so that instance is created.
We take that instance, and as with any other machine learning functionality, fit is what we use the function or the method, rather,
fit is what we use to train the model. Here there is no real training kind of thing, but that's the call. Okay, so we are calling fit, and what we are doing here, we are just passing the data.
So X has these values, the data that has been created, right?
So that is what we are passing here, and this will go ahead and create the clusters, and
then we are using.
After doing fit, we run the predict which basically assigns for each of these observations which cluster
it belongs to.
Alright, so it will name the clusters. Maybe this is cluster one, this is two, three, and so on, or I will actually start from zero, cluster zero, one, two, and three, maybe,
and then for each of the observations, it will assign based on which cluster it belongs to, it will assign a value. So that is stored in y underscore k means.
When we call predict, that is what it does, and we can take a quick look at these y underscore k means or with the cluster numbers that have been assigned for each observation.
So this is the cluster number assigned for observation one, maybe this is for observation two, observation three, and so on. So they we have how many about I think 300 samples, right?
So all the 300 samples, there are 300 values here, each of them the cluster number is given, and the cluster number goes from 0 to 3.
So there are four clusters, so the numbers go from 0, 1, 2, 3.
So that's what is seen here. Okay, now so this was a quick example of generating some dummy data and then clustering that.
Okay, and this can be applied if you have proper data, you can just load it up into x, for example, here, and then run the k-means.
So this is the central part of the k-means clustering program example.
So you basically create an instance and you mention how many clusters you want by specifying this parameter and underscore clusters, and that is also the value of k,
and then pass the data to get the values.
Now, the next section of this code is implementation of a k-means. Now, this is kind of a rough implementation of the k-means algorithm. So we will just walk you through.
I will walk you through the code at each step what it is doing, and then we will see a couple of more examples of how k-means clustering
can be used in maybe some real life examples, real life use cases.
All right. So in this case, here what we are doing is basically implementing k-means
clustering, and there is a function or a library calculates for a given two pairs of points, it will calculate the the distance between them and see which one is the closest and so on.
So this is like this is pretty much like what k-means does, right? So it calculates the distance of each point or each data set from predefined centroid, and then based on whichever is the lowest,
this particular data point is assigned to that centroid. So that is basically available as a standard function, and we will be using that here.
So, as explained in the slides, the first step that is done in case of k-means clustering is to randomly assign
some centroids.
So, as a first step, we randomly allocate a couple of centroids which we call here, we are calling as centers.
And then we put this in a loop and we take it through an iterative process.
For each of the data points, we first find out using this function pairwise distance argument;
for each of the points, we find out which one, which center or which randomly selected centroid is the closest, and accordingly,
we assign that data or the data point to that particular centroid or cluster.
And once that is done for all the data points, we calculate the new centroid by finding out the mean position
with the the center position, right? So we calculate the new centroid, and then we check if the new centroid is the coordinates or the position is the same as the previous centroid,
the positions we will compare. And if it is the same, that means the process has converged. So remember, we do this process till the centroids or the centroid doesn't move anymore, right?
So the centroid gets relocated each time this reallocation is done. So the moment it doesn't change anymore, the position of the centroid doesn't change anymore, we know that convergence has occurred.
So till then, so you see here this is like an infinite loop. While true is an infinite loop, it only breaks when the centers are the same, the new center and old center positions are the same.
And once that is done, we return the centers and the labels.
Now, of course, as explained, this is not a very sophisticated and advanced implementation, very basic implementation, because one of the flaws in this is that sometimes what happens is the centroid,
the position will keep moving, but in the change will be very minor. So, in that case, also with that is actually convergence. right so for example, the change is 0.0001.
We can consider that as convergence. Otherwise, what will happen is this will either take forever or it will be never ending. So that's a small flaw here.
So that is something additional checks may have to be added here. But again, as mentioned, this is not the most sophisticated implementation.
This is like a kind of a rough implementation of the k-means clustering.
Okay, so if we execute this code, this is what we get as the output. So this is the definition of this particular function, and then we call that find underscore clusters and we pass our data
x and the number of clusters, which is four.
And if we run that and plot it, this is the output that we get. So this is of course each cluster is represented by a different color.
So we have a cluster in green color, yellow color, and so on and so forth. And these big points here, these are the centroids, this is the final position of the centroids.
And as you can see visually, also this appears like a kind of a center of all these points here, right? Similarly, this is like the center of all these points here and so on.
So this is the example, or this is an example of an implementation of k-means clustering, and next we will move on to see a couple of examples of how k-means
clustering is used in maybe some real life scenarios or use cases. In the next example or demo, we are going to see how we can use k-means clustering to perform color compression.
We will take a couple of images, so there will be two examples, and we will try to use k-means clustering to compress the colors.
This is a common situation in image processing when you have an image with millions of colors, but then you cannot render it on some devices which may not have enough memory.
so that is the scenario where where something like this can be used.
So
before again we go into the Python notebook, let's take a look at quickly the the code.
As usual, we import the libraries and then we import the image and then we will flatten it.
So the reshaping is basically we have the image information is stored in the form of pixels, and if the images
like for example 427 by 640 and it has three colors, so that's the overall dimension of the of the initial image.
We just reshape it and then feed this to our algorithm, and this will then create clusters of
only 16 clusters. So this this colors, there are millions of colors, and now we need to bring it down to 16 colors. So we use k is equal to 16, and this is how when we visualize this is how it looks.
There are these are all about 16 million possible colors.
The input color space has 16 million possible colors, and we just some compress it to 16 colors.
So this is how it would look when we compress it to 16 colors, and this is how the original image looks, and after compression to 16 colors,
this is how the new image looks. As you can see, there is not a lot of information that has been lost, though the image quality is definitely
reduced a little bit.
So this is an example which we are going to now see in Python notebook. Let's go into the Python, and once again, as always, we will import some libraries and load this image called flower.jpg.
Okay, so let we load that and this is how it looks. This is the original image, which has I think 16 million colors, and this is the shape of this image, which is basically what is the
shape is nothing but the overall size, right? So this is 427 pixel by 640 pixel, and then there are three layers, which is this three basically is for RGB, which is red, green,
blue.
So color image will have that, right? So that is the shape of this. Now, what we need to do is data. Let's take a look at how data is looking.
So let me just create a new cell and show you what is in data. Basically, we have captured this information.
So, data is what let me just show you here. All right,
so let's take a look at China. What are the values in China? And if we see here, this is how the data is stored. This is nothing but the pixel values.
Okay, so this is like a matrix, and each one has about four for this 427 by 640 pixels. All right. so this is how it looks.
Now the issue here is these values are large, the numbers are large, so we need to normalize them to between 0 and 1,
right? So that's why we will basically create one more variable which is data, which will contain the values between 0 and 1. And the way to do that is divide by 255.
So we divide China by 255, and we get the new values in data.
So let's just run this piece of code, and this is the shape. So we now have also. yeah. what we have done is we changed using reshape. we converted into the three dimensional
into a two dimensional
data set. and let us also take a look at how.
let me just insert
probably a cell here and take a look at how data is looking. Alright, so this is how data is looking, and now you see this is the values are between zero and one, right?
So if you earlier noticed in case of China the values were large numbers, now everything is between zero and one. This is one of the things we need to do. All right,
so after that, the next thing that we need to do is to visualize this, and we can take random set of maybe 10,000 points
and plot it and check and see how this looks. So let us just plot this. And so this is how the original the color the pixel distribution is.
These are two plots: one is red against green, and another is red against blue, and this is the original distribution of the color.
So then what we will do is we will use k-means clustering to create just 16 clusters for the various colors
and then apply that to the image. Now, what will happen is since the data is large because there are millions of colors, using regular k-means may be a little time consuming.
So there is another version of k-means which is called mini batch k-means.
So we will use that which is which processes in the overall concept remains the same, but this basically processes it in smaller batches, that's the only thing.
Okay, so the results will pretty much be the same. So let's go ahead and execute this piece of code and also visualize this so that we can see that there are these.
This is how the 16 colors uh would look. So this is red against green, and this is red against blue. There is uh quite a bit of similarity between this original color schema and the new one, right?
So it doesn't look very, very completely different or anything like that. Now we apply this the newly created colors to the image, and we can take a look how this is looking now.
We can compare both the images. So this is our original image, and this is our new image. So as you can see, there is not a lot of information that has been lost.
it pretty much looks like the original image. Yes, we can see that, for example, here there is a little bit, it appears a little dullish compared to this one, right?
Because we kind of took off some of the finer details of the color, but overall the high-level information has been maintained.
At the same time, the main advantage is that now this can be this is an image which can be rendered on a device which may not be that very sophisticated.
Now let's take one more example with a different image.
In the second example, we will take an image of the summer palace in China and we repeat the same process.
This is a high definition color image with millions of colors and also three dimensional.
Now we will reduce that to 16 colors using k-means clustering. and we do the same process.
like before: we reshape it, and then we cluster the colors to 16, and then we render the image once again.
and we will see that the color, the quality of the image slightly deteriorates, as you can see here.
This has much finer details in this.
Which are probably missing here, but then that's the compromise because there are some devices which may not be able to handle this kind of uh high density images.
So let's run this code in Python notebook. Okay.
Alright, so let's apply the same technique for another picture which is even more intricate and has probably
much complicated color schema. So this is the image now. Once again, we can take a look at the shape, which is 427 by 640 by 3.
And this is the new data would look somewhat like this compared to the flower image.
So we have some new values here
and we will also bring this as you can see the numbers are much big, so we will uh much bigger, so we will now have to
scale them down to values between 0 and 1, and that is done by dividing by 255.
So let's go ahead and do that
and reshape it, okay?
So we get a two-dimensional
matrix, and we will then, as a next step. we will go ahead and visualize this: how it looks, the the 16 colors.
and this is basically how it would look —16 million colors —and. now, we can
create the clusters out of this. The 16k means clusters we will create.
So, this is how the distribution of the pixels would look with 16 colors, and then we go ahead and apply this
and visualize how it is looking for
with the new just the 16 colors. So, once again, as you can see, this looks much richer in color, but at the same time, and this probably doesn't have —as we can see,
it doesn't look as rich as this one, but nevertheless, the information is not lost: the shape and all that stuff.
And this can be also rendered on a slightly, uh, device which is probably not that sophisticated. Okay, so that's pretty much it.
So we have seen two examples of how color compression can be done using k-means clustering.
and we have also seen in the previous examples of how to implement k-means, the code to roughly how to implement k-means
clustering. and we use some sample data using blob to just execute the k-means clustering. Ever wondered how hands-on projects can land you your dream job in machine learning?
Whether your IA internships or full-time positions, recruiters are always on the lookout for one real thing, real experience. And the best way to showcase that? Machine learning projects.
In today's video, we'll dive into five amazing machine learning project ideas that will not only sharpen your skills, but will also make your portfolio shine.
Each project brings a unique challenge and mastering them will set you apart in the competitive machine learning job market.
So let's get started and explore how these projects can transform your career. And remember, for each project, you can find all the resources and start a code in the description below.
Let's kick things off with something really practical and highly relevant. Real time face mask detection. Now you must be thinking, why focus on this?
Well, imagine a world where AI helps us ensure safety in public spaces, especially during health crises like pandemics. With the guise of computer vision, we can make that happen.
In this project, you will work with tools like OpenCV and TensorFlow to create a model that detects whether people are wearing face masks in real time or using live camera feeds.
You'll learn how to process images on the fly and handle real time data, which is crucial in many industries like security, healthcare, and public safety.
This project will also give you a solid foundation in computer vision, something every machine learning enthusiast will be comfortable with.
Check the description below for all the resources and start a code to build the project.
Now that you've got a hang on the computer vision part, you're probably curious on how to build something that feels more personal.
That's where our second project comes in: Movie Recommendation System. You've probably used Netflix or YouTube's recommendation engine, right?
It's a great example of machine learning in action, giving you a personalized suggestion based on your tastes.
In this project, you will build your own recommendation system using Python, Pandas, and ScikitLearn.
You'll explore two powerful techniques, that is content-based filtering and collaborative filtering.
Where content-based filtering uses movie details and collaborative filtering leverages user behavior.
This is the perfect way to practice working with large data sets, learning about recommendation algorithms and fine-tuning models to deliver the best results.
Find the resources and start a code for the project in the description below. Next, let's tackle something that could really level up your skills for the job market itself.
How about an AI resume matcher? Have you ever wondered how companies sit through hundreds of resumes to find the perfect candidate? Well, now you'll learn how to build that system.
You'll use powerful natural language processing tools like Spacey and BERT to match job descriptions with the best-fitting resumes.
By deploying the system with Streamlit, you'll also get the hands-on experience with web deployment.
This project is great for practicing NLP, learning about the intricacies of text processing, and giving you a tool that HR systems could actually use in their hiring process.
Plus, it's a fantastic addition to your portfolio. Check out the description for all the resources and starter code for this project. Now let's move on to something that's both timely and impactful.
Fake news detection. In a world flooded with information distinguishing fact from fiction has never been more important.
With this project, you will dive into text classification, training a model that detects fake news articles based on patterns in language.
By using NLP pipelines and tools like logistic regression and BERT, you'll learn how to clean and process datasets, a vital skill when working with unstructured text.
Not only will you gain expertise in handling text data, but you will also understand how to evaluate models using metrics like accuracy,
precision, and recall, which are critical skills for any machine learning practitioner. You'll find all the relevant resources and start a code for this project in the description below.
Finally, let's get into something that's a bit more advanced but super exciting. Stock price prediction using LSTM.
You've probably heard about financial models predicting stock prices, but what does it really take to build one?
In this project, you will use LSTM, which is long short-term memory networks, a type of deep learning model specifically designed for time series forecasting.
Using TensorFlow and financial APIs, you'll build a model that predicts future stock prices based on historical data.
You will also know how to handle both real-time and historical data, perform scaling, and evaluate the model's performance.
This project will give you an in-depth knowledge of deep learning as well as how it applies to financial forecasting, a field that's booming with opportunities.
All the resources and starter code for the project are linked in the description below. Here are some bonus tips and project deployment.
Now that you have built your project, you're probably wondering how do I show them off? Don't worry, we've got you covered. It's time to talk about the deployment and presentation.
Once your projects are polished, hosting them onto GitHub is a great way to showcase your work to potential employers.
You can also deploy your models with platforms like Streamlit, Flask, or even Heroku, turning them into interactive web applications so that others can try them out.
And don't forget to highlight these projects on your resume and LinkedIn profile.
This is your opportunity to show off your practical skills, and when interviewers ask you about your experience, you'll be able to talk about real life projects that you have worked on.
For all the deployment tools and resources, make sure to check out the links in the description. And that's a lab.
We have explored five amazing machine learning projects that not only sharpen your skills but also boost your employability.
Whether you're interested in computer vision, natural language processing, or time series forecasting, there's a project for you. Now it's time to get your building.
Which project are you excited to tackle first? Let us know in the comments below.
Today, we will learn about some of the machine learning and deep learning interview questions.
So let's begin with our first question.
The first question is how to detect outliers in data.
So, in data analytics and machine learning,
you often find data points that lie at an abnormal distance from other points in a random sample from a population.
Those are called outliers.
Now, outliers in data can significantly impact any prediction analysis.
There are majorly three different methods to treat outliers.
First, we have the univariate method.
It is one of the simplest methods for detecting outliers.
The univariate method uses box plots.
A box plot is a graphical display for describing the distributions of the data.
Box plots use the median and the lower and upper quartiles.
This method looks for data points with extreme values on one variable.
Next, we have the multivariate method.
So the multivariate outliers can be found in an n-dimensional space having n features.
We look for unusual combinations of all the variables in this method.
Finally, we have Minkowski error.
This method reduces the contribution of potential outliers in the training process.
The Minkowski error is a loss index that is more insensitive to outliers than the standard mean squared error.
Now moving on to the second question: What is a confusion matrix?
So a confusion matrix is a table that is used to describe the performance of a classification model and a set of test data for which the true values are already known.
The target variable has two values, positive or negative.
The columns represent the actual values of the target variable, which you can see here. The rows represent the predicted values of the target variable, which you can see here.
Now there are four important terms that are related to confusion matrix.
First, we have true positive, which is this one.
So in true positive, the predicted value matches the actual value.
So the actual value was positive and the model also predicted a positive value.
Then we have true negative,
which is also represented as Tn.
The true negative depicts the predicted value matches the actual value.
Now the actual value was negative and the model predicted a negative value.
Next we have false positive.
Now false positive is also known as type 1 error.
In false positive, the predicted value was falsely predicted.
The actual value was negative, but the model predicted a positive value.
Finally we have false negative, a false negative is also known as type 2 error.
So in false negative, the predicted value was falsely predicted.
The actual value was positive, but the model predicted a negative value.
Now moving to a third question,
which is explain the ROC curve.
Now the ROC curve is one of the most important evaluation matrix for checking the performance of any classification model.
ROC stands for receiver operating characteristic.
Receiver operating characteristic or ROC curve is a method to compare the diagnostic tests.
The ROC curve is created by plotting the true positive rate against the false positive rate at various threshold settings.
So here on the y-axis you have the true positive rate, on the x-axis we have the false positive rate.
The true positive rate indicates the proportion of observations that were correctly predicted to be positive out of all positive observations.
Similarly, the false positive rate is the proportion of observations that are incorrectly predicted to be positive out of all negative observations.
You can take an example, suppose in medical testing, the true positive rate is the rate in which people are correctly identified to test positive for the disease in question,
let's say the coronavirus testing.
ROC does not depend on any class distribution.
This makes it useful for evaluating classifiers predicting rare events such as diseases or disasters.
Now moving to the fourth question, we have
what are the assumptions for linear regression?
So linear regression analysis is used for modeling the relationship between a single dependent variable y and one or more feature or predictor variables.
Some of the important assumptions for linear regression are so first
they should have linearity.
So linear regression needs the relationship between the independent and the dependent variables to be linear.
It is also crucial to check for outliers since linear regression is sensitive to outlier effects.
Next, we have homoscedasticity.
Homoscedasticity illustrates a situation in which the error term, that is, the noise or random disturbance in the relationship between the features and the target variable
is the same across all levels of the dependent variables.
Third, we have independence, so observations should be independent of each other.
Finally, we have no multi collinearity, so there should be little or no multi collinearity.
Independent variables should not be too highly correlated.
Now moving to our fifth question in our list of interview questions.
The question is What is regularization in machine learning?
Explain the L2 regularization.
So regularization is a machine learning technique that is used to reduce the errors by fitting the function appropriately on the training set in order to avoid overfitting of data.
So overfitting happens when a model learns the detail and noise in the training data to the extent that it negatively impacts the performance of the model on new data.
So here you can see we have
a nice plot which shows how overfitting of data can be visualized.
And here
we have a good fit line over the same data points.
So this is also known as the regression line.
Now L2 regularization is also known as ridge regression.
So ridge regression modifies the overfit and model by adding the squared magnitude of coefficient as a penalty term to the loss function.
So on the right you can see a set of data points plotted and we have our linear regression line,
and here we are calculating the cost function for the ridge regression
line. So our cost function is actually loss plus lambda into summation of W squared where loss is actually the sum of squared errors or squared residuals.
Lambda stands for penalty for the errors, W is called the slope of the curve or line.
Okay.
Now consider a case
where there are two points passing through the linear regression line.
Now if you calculate the cost function,
we get the value as 1.69.
So here we have assumed that loss is 0 since the two points lie directly on the line.
We have taken lambda to be 1 and w is 1.3.
So if you use this function or this formula,
you get the cost function as 1.69.
Now moving ahead, let's consider another situation where we will calculate the same cost function for the ridge regression line.
There is some loss for both the points as they are not on the same line.
So here you can see the sum of squared residuals is 0.05, which actually is the sum of 0.2 square, I am assuming this as 0.2
and 0.1 for this one.
So if you square both and add it, the value is 0.05, a lambda is again 1, and w we have assumed to be 0.6.
Now if you find the cost function, the value is 0.41.
Let's draw the linear regression line and the ridge regression line with all the points.
We find that the ridge regression line as the best fit since its cost function is less.
So
there are three methods to split a decision tree.
First, we have variance.
So reduction in variance is an algorithm that is used for continuous target variables.
This algorithm uses the standard formula of variance to choose the best split.
So here you can see the standard formula of variance, which is summation of x that is all the individual points, minus x bar, which is the mean
squared divided by the total number of observations.
Now the split with lower variance is selected as the criteria to split the population.
Now the steps to calculate variance is you need to calculate variance for each node and then you need to calculate for each split as the weighted average of each node variance.
Moving ahead, the second method we have is information gain.
So information gain is used for splitting the nodes when the target variable is categorical.
It works on the concept of entropy.
Now the degree of disorganization in a system is known as entropy.
So here you can see the formula for information gain which is one minus entropy.
Finally, we have Gini impurity.
So Gini impurity is the probability of incorrectly classifying a randomly chosen element in the dataset if it were randomly labeled according to the class distribution in the dataset.
So below you can see the formula for Gini impurity.
So we have 1 minus summation of pi whole square, where n represents the number of classes and P of I represents the probability of randomly picking an element of class I.
Now moving to the seventh question.
So the question is how do we find the optimum cluster value in k means clustering algorithm?
Now there are two methods to find the optimum cluster value.
So first we have the elbow method, which is one of the most well known for finding the optimum number of clusters.
So in this method, you need to calculate the within cluster sum of squared errors for different values of k and choose the k for which within cluster
sum of squared errors first starts to diminish.
So in the below plot of squared errors versus the number of clusters k, you can see at k is equal to 4 the squared error
starts to diminish.
So hence our optimum k value is 4.
Next we have the silhouette method.
So the silloid method measures how similar a point is to its own cluster compared to other clusters.
The average silloid method computes the average siloid of observations for different values of k.
The optimum number of clusters k is the one that maximizes the average siloid over a range of possible values for k.
The silloid score reaches its global maximum at the optimal k.
So in our case, the average silloid reaches maximum at k is equal to 2, which you can see here. So our optimum cluster value will be 2 here.
Moving ahead,
the eighth question in our list is how does the pooling layer work in a convolutional neural network?
So the pooling layer performs a downsampling operation in order to reduce the dimensionality of the feature map.
So in the pooling operation, you slide a two-dimensional filter over each channel of feature map and summarize the features lying within the region covered by the filter.
It is a common practice to periodically insert a pooling layer in between successive convolutional layers in a convolutional neural network architecture.
So the pooling layer operates independently on every depth slice in the input and resizes it spatially using the max operation.
So in the diagram shown here, you can see we have a rectified feature map.
We are using a 2x2 filter and performing a max pooling operation.
So consider this as the filter if you perform the max operation over the values,
let's say 0, 5, 3, and 1. So considering this one, our pooled feature map maximum value will be 5.
Similarly, for this chunk of data, it is going to be 7.
Next, if you slide the filter over this square frame, you get 8, and similarly, here you get 6.
So this is also known as a pooled feature map.
Moving ahead,
the ninth question in our list is how does LSTM network work?
So long short-term memory networks are a type of recurrent neural networks that are capable of learning order dependence and sequence prediction problems.
So remembering information for long periods of time is practically their default behavior.
Now LSTMs also have this chain-like structure which you can see here,
but the repeating module has a different structure.
So instead of having a single neural network layer, there are four interacting in a very special way.
Now you can see these are called as gates.
These gates contain sigmoid activations.
A sigmoid activation is similar to the tan H activation.
Instead of squishing values between minus 1 and plus 1, it squishes values between 0 and 1.
An LSTM has four gates.
Now these are called forget, remember, learn and use or output.
So if you see this, in the first step, we use the forget gate that decides what information should be thrown away or kept.
The information from the previous hidden state and the information from the current input is passed through the sigmoid function.
Values come out between 0 and 1.
So if the value is closer to 0, it means you need to forget that information.
And if the value is closer to 1, it means you need to keep that information.
Next, we have the input gate.
So the input gate is used to update the cell state.
First, we pass the previous hidden state and the current input into a sigmoid function.
That decides which values will be updated by transforming the values to be between 0 and 1.
0 means not important and 1 means important.
You also pass the hidden state and current input into the tanage function to flatten the values between minus 1 and plus 1.
This helps to regulate the network.
Then you multiply the tanage output with the sigmoid output.
The sigmoid output will decide which information is important to keep from the tanage output.
And finally, in step 3, we have the output gate.
This output gate is used to decide
what the next hidden state should be.
First, we pass the previous hidden state and the current input into a sigmoid function.
Then we pass the newly modified cell state into the tanage function.
We then multiply the tanage output with the sigmoid output to decide what information the hidden state should carry.
The output is the hidden state.
The new cell state and the new hidden state is then carried over to the next time step.
Finally, talking about the last question in our list of interview questions, we have
explained the concept of gradient descent in deep learning.
Now gradient descent is an optimization algorithm which is mainly used to find the minimum of a function.
In machine learning, gradient descent is used to update the parameters in a model.
Parameters can vary according to the algorithm such as coefficients in linear regression and weights in neural networks.
You can see
we have these maps and on the y-axis we have the loss,
on the x-axis we have the weight,
and here we are trying to find the local minimum or the global minimum.
Now this gradient descent method is used to minimize the cost function and update the parameters of the learning model.
The gradient always points in the direction of the steepest increase in the loss function.
The gradient descent algorithm takes a step in the direction of the negative gradient in order to reduce the loss as quickly as possible.
To determine the next point along the loss function curve, the gradient descent algorithm adds some fraction of the gradient's magnitude to the starting point.
Now this process is repeated to find the global minimum.
Convolution Neural Network Tutorial My name is Richard Kirschner with the Simply Learn team. That's www.simplylearn.com. Get it certified, get ahead.
Today we're going to be covering the convolutional neural network tutorial.
Do you know how deep learning recognizes the objects in an image?
And really, this particular neural network is how image recognition works. It's very central, one of the biggest building blocks for image recognition.
It does it using convolution neural network.
And we over here we have the basic picture of a hummingbird. Pixels of an image fed as input. You have your input layer coming in. So it takes that graphic and puts it into the input layer.
You have all your hidden layers, and then you have your output layer and your output layer. One of those is going to light up and say, oh, it's a bird.
We're going to go into depth. We're going to actually go back and forth on this a number of times today.
So if you're not catching all the image, don't worry, we're going to get into the details.
So we have our input layer, accepts the pixels of the image as input in the form of arrays.
And you can see up here where they've actually labeled each block of the bird in different arrays.
So we'll dive into deep as to how that looks like and how those matrices are set up.
Your hidden layer carry out feature extraction by performing certain calculations and manipulations.
So this is the part that kind of reorganizes that picture multiple ways until we get some data that's easy to read for the neural network.
This layer uses a matrix filter and performs convolution operation to detect patterns in the image.
And if you remember that convolution means to coil or to twist. So we're going to twist the data around and alter it and use that operation to detect a new pattern.
There are multiple hidden layers, like convolution layer rel U is how that is pronounced, when that's the rectified linear unit.
That has to do with the activation function that's used.
Pooling layer also uses multiple filters to detect edges, corners, eyes, feathers, beak, etc.
And just like the term says, pooling is pooling information together.
And we'll look into that a lot closer here.
So if you're if it's a little confusing now, we'll dig in deep and try to get you squared away with that. And then finally there is a fully connected layer that identifies the object in the image.
So we have these different layers coming through in the hidden layers and they come into the final area, and that's where we have, let's say,
one node or one neural network entity that lights up that says it's a bird.
What's in it for you?
We're gonna cover an introduction to the CNN.
What is convolution neural network, how CNN recognizes images. We're gonna dig deeper into that and really look at the individual layers in the convolutional neural network.
And finally we do a use case implementation using the CNN. We'll begin our introduction to the CNN by introducing the pioneer of convolutional neural network, Jan Lekun.
He was the director of Facebook AI Research Group, built the first convolutional neural network called LeNet in 1988.
So these have been around for a while and have had a chance to mature over the years.
It was used for character recognition tasks like reading zip code digits.
Imagine processing mail and automating that process.
CNN is a feed forward neural network that is generally used to analyze visual images by producing data with a grid-like topology.
A CNN is also known as a convenet.
And very key to this is we are looking at images. That was what this was designed for.
And you'll see the different layers as we dig in, mirror some of the other, some of them are actually now used since we're using uh TensorFlow and Karas in our code later on.
You'll see that some of those layers appear in a lot of your other neural network frameworks.
but in this case, this is very central to processing images and doing so in a variety that captures multiple images and really drills down into their different features.
In this example here, you see flowers of two varieties, orchid and a rose.
I think the orchid is much more dainty and beautiful, and the rose smells quite beautiful. I have a couple of rose bushes in my yard.
they go into the input layer, that data is sent to all the different nodes in the next layer, one of the hidden layers, based on its different weights and its setup.
It then comes out and gives those a new value. Those values then are multiplied by their weights and go to the next hidden layer, and so on, and then you have the output layer,
and one of those nodes comes out and says it's an orchid, and the other one comes out and says it's a rose, depending on how well it was trained.
What separates the CNN or the convolutional neural network from other neural networks is a convolutional operation, forms the basis of any convolutional neural network.
In a CNN, every image is represented in the form of arrays of pixel values.
So here we have a real image of the digit eight, that then gets put onto its pixel values, represented in the form of an array.
In this case you have a two-dimensional array. And then you can see in the final in form we transform the digit eight into its representational form of pixels of zeros and one,
where the ones represent in this case the black part of the eight, and the zeros represent the white background.
To understand the convolution neural network or how that convolutional operation works, we're gonna take a sidestep and look at matrices.
In this case, we're gonna simplify it and we're gonna take two matrices, A and B, of one dimension.
Now, kind of separate this from your thinking as we learn that you want to focus just on the matrix aspect of this.
And then we'll bring that back together and see what that looks like when we put the pieces for the convolutional operation.
Here we've set up two arrays. We have in this case a single dimension matrix. And we have A equals five, three, seven, five, nine, seven, and we have b equals one, two, three.
So in the convolution, as it comes in there, it's going to look at these two, and we're going to start by doing multiplying them. A times b.
And so we multiply the arrays element wise, and we get five six six.
Where five is the five times one, six is three times two, and then the other six is two times three.
And since the two arrays aren't the same size, they're not the same setup, we're gonna just truncate the first one and we're gonna look at the second array multiplied
just by the first three elements of the first array.
Now that's gonna be a little confusing. Remember a computer gets to repeat these processes hundreds of times. So we're not gonna just forget those other numbers later on.
We'll see, we'll bring those back in.
And then we have the sum of the product. In this case, five plus six plus six equals 17. So in our a times b, our very first digit in that matrix of a times b is 17.
And if you remember I said we're not going to forget the other digits. So we now have three, two, five.
We move one set over, and we take three, two, five, and we multiply that times b, and you'll see that three times one is three, two times two is four, and so on and so on.
We sum it up, so now we have the second digit of our a times b product in the matrix.
And we continue on with that same thing, so on and so on. So then we would go from 375 to seven five nine to five nine seven.
This short matrix that we have for A, we've now covered all the different entities in A that match three different levels of B.
Now in a little bit we're gonna cover where we use this math at, this multiplying of matrices and how that works.
but it's important to understand that we're going through the matrix and multiplying the different parts to it to match the smaller matrix with the larger matrix.
I know a lot of people get lost at is you know what's going on here with these matrixes? Uh ooh, scary math. Not really that scary when you break it down.
We're looking at a section of A and we're comparing it to B.
So when you break that down in your mind like that, you realize, okay, so I'm I'm just taking these two matrixes and comparing them, and I'm bringing the value down into one matrix,
A times B.
We're deuc that information in a way that will help the computer see different aspects.
Let's go ahead and flip over again back to our images.
Here we are back to our images.
Talking about going to the most basic two-dimensional image you can get to. Consider the following two images. The image for the symbol backslash.
When you press the backslash, the above image is processed.
you can see there for the image for the forward slash is the opposite.
So we click the forward slash button, that flips.
very basic. We have four pixels going in. Can't get any more basic than that. Here we have a little bit more complicated picture.
We take a real image of a smiley face, then we represent that in the form of black and white pixels. So if this was an image in the computer, it's black and white.
And like we saw before, we convert this into the zeros and ones.
So where the other one would have just been a matrix of just four dots, now we have a significantly larger image coming in.
So don't worry, we're going to bring this all together here in just a little bit. Layers in convolutional neural network.
When we're looking at this, we have our convolution layer, and that really is the central aspect of processing images in the convolutional neural network.
That's why we have it. And then that's going to be feeding in.
And you have your rel U layer, which is, you know, as we talked about the rectified linear unit. We'll talk about that a little bit later. The ReLU
is how that layer is activated, is the math behind it, what makes the neurons fire. You'll see that in a lot of other neural networks.
When you're using it just by itself, it's for processing smaller amounts of data, where you use the atom activation feature for large data coming in.
Now, because we're processing small amounts of data in each image, the rel U layer works great.
You have your pooling layer, that's where you're pooling the data together. Pooling is a neural network term, it's very commonly used. I like to use the term reduce.
So if you're coming from the map and reduce side, you'll see that we're mapping all this data through all these networks, and then we're going to reduce it. We're going to pool it together.
And then finally we have the fully connected layer. That's where our output is going to come out.
So we have started to look at matrixes. We've started to look at the convolutional layer and where it fits in and everything. We've taken a look at images.
So we're going to focus more on the convolution layer since this is a convolutional neural network.
A convolution layer has a number of filters and perform convolution operation.
Every image is considered as a matrix of pixel values. Consider the following five by five image whose pixel values are only zero and one.
Now, obviously, when we're dealing with color, there's all kinds of things that come in on color processing, but we want to keep it simple and just keep it black and white.
And so we have our image pixels.
So we're sliding the filter matrix over the image and computing the dot product to detect the patterns.
And right here, you're going to ask, where does this filter come from?
This is a bit confusing because the filter is going to be derived later on. We build the filters when we program or train our model. So you don't need to worry what the filter actually is.
What you do need to understand how a convolution layer works is what is the filter doing.
Filter, and you'll have many filters. You don't have just one filter.
You'll have lots of filters that are going to look for different aspects. And so the filter might be looking for just edges, it might be looking for different parts.
We'll cover that a little bit more detail in a minute. Right now we're just focusing on how the filter works as a matrix. Remember earlier we talked about multiplying matrices together?
And here we have our two-dimensional matrix.
And you can see we take the filter and we multiply it in the upper left image. And you can see right here one times one, one times zero, one times one.
We multiply those all together, then sum them, and we end up with a convolved feature of four.
We're going to take that and sliding the filter matrix over the image and computing the dot product to detect patterns. So we're just going to slide this over.
We're going to predict the first one and slide it over one notch, predict the second one, and so on and so on all the way through until we have a new matrix.
And this matrix, which is the same size as the filter, has reduced the image, and whatever filter, whatever that's filtering out, is going to be looking at just those features
reduced down to a smaller matrix.
So once the feature maps are extracted, the next step is to move them to the ReLU layer.
So the rel U layer, the next step, first is going to perform an element-wise operation.
So each of those maps coming in, if there's negative pixels, so it sets all the negative pixels to zero.
And you can see this nice graph where it just zeros out the negatives, and then you have a value that goes from zero up to whatever value is coming out of the matrix.
This introduces nonlinearity to the network. So up until now, we have a when we say linearity, we're talking about the fact that the feature has a value. So it's a linear feature.
This feature came up and has, let's say the feature is the edge of the beak.
or the backslash that we saw. Um it'll look at that and say, okay, this feature has a value from negative 10 to 10 in this case. if it was one, it'd say, yeah, this might be a beak, it might not.
might be an edge right there. A minus five means, no, we're not even going to look at it, to zero.
And so we end up with an output, and the output takes all these features, all these filtered features.
Remember, we're not just running one filter on this, we're running a number of filters on this image.
And so we end up with a rectified feature map that is looking at just the features coming through and how they weigh in from our filters. So here we have an input of a looks like a toucan bird.
Very exotic looking.
Real image is scanned in multiple convolution and the ReLU layers for locating features.
And you can see up here is turn it into a black and white image.
And in this case we're looking in the upper right hand corner for a feature, and that box scans over. A lot of times it doesn't scan one pixel at a time.
A lot of times it will skip by two or three or four pixels to speed up the process. That's one of the ways you can compensate if you don't have enough resources on your computation for large images.
And it's not just one filter slowly goes across the image. You have multiple filters have been programmed in there.
So you're looking at a lot of different filters going over the different aspects of the image and just sliding across there and forming a new matrix.
One more aspect to note about the RELU layer is we're not just having one RELU coming in.
So not only do we have multiple features going through, but we're generating multiple RELU layers for locating the features. That's very important to note. So we have quite a bundle.
We have multiple filters, multiple RELU, which brings us to the next step, forward propagation.
Now we're going to look at the pooling layer. The rectified feature map now goes through a pooling layer. Pooling is a downsampling operation that reduces the dimensionality of the feature map.
That's all we're trying to do. We're trying to take a huge amount of information and reduce it down to a single answer. This is a specific kind of bird. This is an iris. This is a rose.
So you have a rectified feature map.
you see here we have a rectified feature map coming in. We set the max pooling with a two by two filters and a stride of two.
And if you remember correctly, I talked about not going one pixel at a time. Well that's where the stride comes in.
We end up with a two by two pooled feature map, but instead of moving one over each time and looking at every possible combination, we skip a
few there. We go by two, we skip every other pixel, and we just do every other one. And this reduces our rectified feature map, which as you can see over here, 16 by 16 to a four by four.
So we're continually trying to filter and reduce our data so that we can get to something we can manage.
And over here you see that we have the max 3, 4, 1, and 2. And in the max pooling, we're looking for the max value, a little bit different than what we were looking at before.
So coming from the rectified feature, we're now finding the max value, and then we're pooling those features together.
So instead of thinking this as image of the map, think of this as how valuable is a feature in that area. How much of a feature value do we have?
we just want to find the best or the maximum feature for that area.
They might have that one piece of the filter of the beak said, Oh, I see a one in this beak in this image, and then it skips over and says,
I see a three in this image, and says, Oh, this one is rated as a four.
We don't want to sum it together because then you know you might have like five ones and it'll say, ah, five, but you might have four zeros and one
ten, and that ten says, well, this is definitely a beak, where the ones will say, probably not a beak.
A little strange analogy since we're looking at a bird, but you can see how that pooled feature map comes down, and we're just looking for the max value in each one of those matrixes.
Pooling layer uses different filters to identify different parts of the image, like edges, corners, body, feathers, eyes, beak,
etc. I know I focus mainly on the beak, but obviously each feature could be a different part of the bird coming in.
So let's take a look at what that looks like.
Structure of a convolution neural network so far. This is where we're at right now.
We have our input image coming in, and then we use our filters, and there's multiple filters on there that are being developed, to kind of twist and change that data, and so we multiply the
matrices. We take that little filter, maybe it's a two by two, we multiply it by each piece of the image. And if we step two, then it's every other piece of the image.
That generates multiple convolution layers. So we have a number of convolution layers we have set up in there just looking at that data.
We then take those convolution layers, we run them through the relu setup, and then once we've done through the ReLU setup, and we have multiple RELU's going on,
multiple layers that are relU, then we're going to take those multiple layers and we're gonna be pooling them. So now we have the pooling layers or multiple poolings going on.
Up until this point we're dealing with sometimes it's multiple dimensions. You can have three dimensions, some strange data setups that aren't doing images but looking at other things.
They can have four, five, six, seven dimensions. so right now we're looking at 2D image dimensions coming in into the pooling layer.
So the next step is we want to reduce those dimensions or flatten them. So flattening.
Flattening is a process of converting all of the resultant two-dimensional arrays from pooled feature map into a single long continuous linear vector.
So over here you see where we have a pooled feature map, maybe that's the bird wing, and it has values 6847. And we want to just flatten this out and turn it into 6847 or a single linear vector.
And we find out that not only do we do each of the pooled feature maps, we do all of them into one long linear vector.
So now we've gone through our convolutional neural network part, and we have the input layer into the next setup.
All we've done is taken all those different pooling layers and we've flattened them out and combine them into a single linear vector going in.
So after we've done the flattening, we have just a quick recap because we've covered so much, so it's important to go back and take a look at each of the steps we've gone through.
The structure of the network so far is we have our convolution where we twist it and we filter it and multiply the matrices.
We end up with our convolutional layer, which uses the rel U to figure out the values going out into the pooling.
And so you have numerous convolution layers that then create numerous pooling layers pooling that data together, which is the max value,
which one we want to send forward, we want to send the best value. And then we're gonna take all of that from each of the pooling layers and we're gonna flatten it.
And we're gonna combine them into a single input going into the final layer.
Once you get to that step, you might be looking at that going, boy, that looks like the normal input to most neural network. And you're correct, it is.
So once we have the flattened matrix from the pooling layer, that becomes our input. So the pooling layer is fed as an input to the fully connected layer to classify the image.
And so you can see as our flattened matrix comes in, in this case we have the pixels from the flattened matrix fed as an input back to our toucan or whatever that kind of bird that is.
I need one of these to identify what kind of bird that is. It comes into our forward propagation network.
and that will then have the different weights coming down across, and then finally it selects that that's a bird and that it's not a dog or a cat in this case.
Even though it's not labeled, the final layer there in red is our output layer, our final output layer that says bird, cat, or dog.
So, quick recap of everything we've covered so far.
We have our input image, which is twisted and multiplied, the filters are multiplied times the uh matrix, the two matrixes multiplied all the filters to create our convolution layer.
Our convolution layers, there's multiple layers in there, because it's all building multiple layers off the different filters,
then goes through the relue as this activation, and that creates our pooling.
And so once we get into the pooling layer, we then and the pooling look for who's the best, what's the max value coming in from our convolution.
And then we take that layer and we flatten it, and then it goes into a fully connected layer, our fully connected neural network, and then to the output.
And here we can see the entire process, how the CNN recognizes a bird. This is kind of nice because it's showing the little pixels and where they're going.
You can see the filter is generating this convolution network, and that filter shows up in the bottom part of the convolution network. And then based on that, it uses the reload for the pooling.
The pooling then find out which one's the best, and so on, all the way to the fully connected layer at the end, or the classification in the output layer.
So that'd be a classification neural network at the end.
So we covered a lot of theory up till now. And you can imagine each one of these steps has to be broken down in code. So putting that together can be a little complicated.
Not that each step of the process is overly complicated, but because we have so many steps. We have one, two, three, four, five different steps going on here with substeps in there.
We're going to break that down and walk through that in code.
So in our use case implementation using the CNN, we'll be using the CFAR 10 dataset from Canadian Institute for Advanced Research for classifying images across 10 categories.
Unfortunately, they don't let me know whether it's going to be a toucan or some other kind of bird.
But we do get to find out whether it can categorize between a ship, a frog, deer, bird, airplane, automobile, cat, dog, horse, truck. So that's a lot of fun.
And if you're looking anything in the news at all of our automated cars and everything else, you can see where this kind of processing is so important in today's world and very cutting
edge. As far as what's coming out in the commercial deployment, I mean this is really cool stuff. We're starting to see this just about everywhere in industry.
So a great time to be playing with this and figuring it all out. Let's go ahead and dive into the code and see what that looks like when we're actually writing our script.
Before we go on, let's do one more quick look at what we have here.
Let's just take a look at data batch one keys. And remember in Jupyter Notebook, I can get by with not doing the print statement. If I put a variable down there, it'll just display the variable.
And you can see in our data batch one for the keys, since this is a dictionary, we have the batch one label, data, and file names.
so you can actually see how it's broken up in our dataset.
So for the next step, or step four as we're calling it, we want to display the image using matplotlibrary.
There's many ways to display the images. You could even well there's other ways to drill into it, but mapplot library is really good for this.
And we'll also look at our first reshape setup or shaping the data so you can have a little glimpse into what that means.
so we're going to start by importing our mapplot, and of course, since I am doing Jupyter Notebook, I need to do the mapplot inline command so it shows up on my page.
So here we go, we're going to import matplot library.pyplot as plt.
And if you remember mapplot library, the pyplot is like a canvas that we paint stuff onto. And there's my percentage sign mapplot library inline. So it's going to show up in my notebook.
And then of course we're going to import Numpy as NP for our numbers python array setup.
And let's go ahead and set X equals to data batch one. So this will pull in all the data going into the X value.
And then because this is just a long stream of binary data, we need to go a little bit of reshaping.
So in here we have to go ahead and reshape the data.
We have 10,000 images. Okay, that looks correct. And this is kind of an interesting thing. It took me a little bit to I had to go research this myself to figure out what's going on with this data.
And what it is, is it's a 32 by 32 picture.
And let me do this.
Let me go ahead and do a drawing pad on here.
so we have 32 bits by 32 bits, and it's in color. So there's three bits of color.
Now, I don't know why the data is particularly like this. It probably has to do with how they originally encoded it. But most pictures put the three afterward.
So what we're doing here is we're gonna take the shape, we're gonna take the data, which is just a long stream of information,
and we're gonna break it up into 10,000 pieces, and those 10,000 pieces then are broken into three pieces each, and those three pieces then are 32 by 32.
You can look at this like an old-fashioned projector where they have the red screen or the red projector, the blue projector, and the green projector, and they add them all together.
And each one of those is a 32 by 32 bit.
So that's probably how this was originally formatted, was in that kind of ideal. Things have changed.
So we're going to transpose it and we're going to take the three, which was here, and we're going to put it at the end.
So the first part is reshaping the data from a single line of bit data or whatever format it is into.
10,000 by 3 by 32 by 32. And then we're going to transpose the color factor to the last place. So it's the image, then the 32 by 32 in the middle.
That's this part right here. And then finally we're going to take this which is three bits of data and put it at the end. So it's more like we do we process images now.
And then as type, this is really important that we're going to use an integer 8.
You can come in here and you'll see a lot of these, they'll try to do this with a float or a float 64.
What you gotta remember though is a float uses a lot of memory. So once you switch this into something that's not integer 8, which is goes up to 128, you are just gonna the the amount of RAM,
let's just put that in here, is gonna go way up. The amount of RAM that it loads.
so you want to go ahead and use this. You can try the other ones and see what happens if you have a lot of RAM on your computer.
But for this exercise, this will work just fine.
And let's go ahead and take that and run this.
So now our x variable is all loaded and it has all the images in it from the batch one, data batch one.
And just to show what we are talking about with the as type on there, if we go ahead and take x0 and just look for its max value, let me go ahead and run that.
you'll see it doesn't oops, I said 128, it's 255.
you'll see it doesn't go over 255, because it's basically an ASCII character is what we're keeping that down to. We're keeping those values down.
So they're only 255 0 to 255 versus uh float value, which would bring this up exponentially in size.
And since we're using the mapplot library, we can do um whoops, that's not what I wanted.
Since we're using the mapplot library, we can take our canvas and just do a plt.im for image show, and let's just take a look at what x0
looks like.
And it comes in, I'm not sure what that is, but you can see it's a very low grade image broken down to the minimal pixels on there.
And if we did the same thing, oh let's do let's see what one looks like. Hopefully it's a little easier to see.
Run on there, not enter.
Let's hit the run on that.
Uh and we can see this is probably a semi-truck. That's a good guess on there.
And I can just go back up here instead of typing the same line in over and over. And we'll look at three.
that looks like a dump truck unloading, uh, and so on. You can do any of the 10,000 images. We can just jump to 55. looks like some kind of animal looking at us there, probably a dog.
And just for fun, let's do just one more run on there, and we can see a nice car for our image number four.
so you can see we paste through all the different images, it's very easy to look at them, and they've been reshaped to fit our view and what the uh mapplot
library uses for its format.
So the next step is we're gonna start creating some helper functions.
We'll start by a one-hot encoder to help us when we're processing the data. Remember that your labels they can't just be words, they have to switch it, and we use the one hot encoder to do that.
And then we'll also create a class CIFAR helper, so it's going to have an init and a setup for the images.
And then finally we'll go ahead and run that code so you can see what that looks like, and then we get into the fun part where we're actually going to start creating our model,
our actual neural network model.
So let's start by creating our one hot encoder.
We're going to create our own here, and it's going to return an out, and we'll have our vector coming in and our values equal ten.
What this means is that we have the ten values, the ten possible labels. And remember we don't look at the labels as a number, because a car isn't one more than a horse.
That'd be just kind of bizarre to have horse equals zero, car equals one, plane equals two, cat equals three. So a cat plus a car equals what?
so instead we create a numpy array of zeros.
And there's going to be ten values, so we have ten different values in there. So you have zero or one. One means it's a cat, zero means it's not a cat.
in the next line it might be that one means it's a car, zero means it's not a car.
So instead of having one output with a value of zero to ten, you have ten outputs with the values of zero to one. That's what the one hot encoder is doing here.
And we're going to utilize this in code in just a minute. So let's go ahead and take a look at the next helpers. We have a few of these helper functions we're going to build.
And when you're working with a very complicated Python project, dividing it up into separate definitions and classes is very important.
Otherwise, it just becomes really ungainly to work with.
So let's go ahead and put in our next helper which is a class.
And this is a lot in this class. So we'll break it down here. And let's just start uh whoops we can put a space right in there.
There we go. Now this is a little bit more readable.
I had a second space. So we're going to create our class, the cipher helper.
And we'll start by initializing it. Now there's a lot going on in here.
So let's start with the init part. self.i equals zero. That'll come in in a little bit. We'll come back to that in the lower part. We want to initialize our training batches.
So when we went through this, there was like a meta batch. We don't need the meta batch, but we do need the data batch one, two, three, four, five. And we do not want the testing batch in here.
This is just the self all train batches.
So we're going to come make an array of all those different images.
And then of course we left the test batch out, so we have our self.test batch.
Uh we're going to initialize the training images and the training labels, and also the test images and the test labels.
So these are just this is just to initialize these variables in here.
Then we create another definition down here, and this is going to set up the images. let's just take a look and see what's going on in there.
Now we could have all just put this as part of the init part, since this is all just helper stuff. But breaking it up again makes it easier to read.
It also makes it easier when we start executing the different pieces to see what's going on.
So that way we have a nice print statement to say, hey, we're now running this and this is what's going on in here.
We're gonna set up these self-training images at this point, and that's gonna go to a numpy array v stack.
And in there we're gonna load up in this case, the data for D and self, all train batches.
Again, that points right up to here. So we're gonna go through each one of these files or each one of these data sets, because they're not a file anymore. We've brought them in.
Data batch one points to the actual data.
And so our self-training images is gonna stack them all into our into a numpy array.
And then it's always nice to get the training length, and that's just a total number of self-training images in there.
And then we're going to take the self-training images.
let me switch marker colors because I am getting a little too much on the markers up here.
Oops, there we go.
Bring down our marker change so we can see it a little better.
And at this point, this should look familiar. Where did we see this? Well, when we wanted to look at this above and we wanted to look at the images in the Mapplot library, we had to reshape it.
So we're doing the same thing here.
We're taking our self-training images and based on the training length, total number of images, because we stacked them all together, so now it's just one large file of images.
We're going to take and uh look at it as our three video cameras that are each displaying 32 by 32;
we're going to switch that around so that now we have each of our images that stays the same place, and then we have our 32 by 32, and then by our
three, our last our three different values for the color.
And of course we want to go ahead and they run this where we say divide by 255. That was from earlier. It just brings all the data into zero to one.
That's what this is doing. So we're turning this into a zero to one array, which is all the pictures 32 by 32 by 3.
And then we're going to take the self-training labels and we're gonna pump those through our one hot encoder we just made, and we're gonna stack them together.
And again, we're converting this into an array that goes from instead of having horse equals one, dog equals two, and then horse plus dog would equal three, which would be cat.
now it's gonna be you know an array of ten where each one is zero to one.
Then we want to go ahead and set up our test images and labels.
And when we're doing this, you're gonna say it's the same thing we just did with the rest of them. We just change colors right here.
This is no different than what we were doing up here with our training set.
we're gonna stack the different images, we're gonna get the length of them so we know how many images are in there.
you certainly could add them by hand, but it's nice to let the computer do it, especially if it ever changes on the other end and you're using other data.
And again, we reshape them and transpose them, and we also do the one hot encoder. Same thing we just did on our training images. So now our test images are in the same format.
So now we have a definition which sets up all our images in there. And then the next step is to go ahead and batch them or next batch.
And let's do another breakout here for batches because this is really important to understand.
Tiz to throw me for a little loop when I'm working with TensorFlow or Karas or a lot of these.
We have our data coming in. If you remember we had like 10,000 photos. Let me just put 10,000 down here. We don't want to run all 10,000 at once.
So we want to break this up into batch sizes.
And you also remember that we had the number of photos, in this case length of test or whatever number is in there. we also have 32 by 32 by 3.
So when we're looking at the batch size, we want to change this from 10,000 to a batch of, in this case, I think we're gonna do batches of a hundred.
So we want to look at just 100, the first hundred of the photos.
And if you remember we set self i equal to zero.
so what we're looking at here is we're gonna create x.
We're gonna get the next batch from the very initialized. We've already initialized it for zero. So we're gonna look at x from zero to batch size, which we've set to 100.
so just the first hundred images. And then we're gonna reshape that into and this is important to let the data know that we're looking at 100 by 32 by 32
Now we've already formatted it to the 32 by 32 by three. This just sets everything up correctly so that x has the data in there in the correct order and the correct shape.
And then the y, just like the x, is our labels. So our training labels, again, they go from zero to batch size.
In this case, they do self I plus batch size because the self-i is going to keep changing.
And then finally we increment the self i because we have zero, so we so the next time we call it, we're gonna get the next batch size. And so basically we have x and y.
X being the photograph data coming in and y being the label.
And that of course is labeled through one hot encoder.
So if you remember correctly, if it was say horse is equal to zero, it would be one for the zero position, since this is the horse, and then everything else would be zero in here.
Let me just put lines through there. There we go, there's our array. Hard to see that array.
So let's go ahead and take that and we're going to finish loading it since this is our class.
And now we're armed with all this our setup over here. Let's go ahead and load that up. And so we're gonna create a variable ch with the CFAR helper in it. And then we're going to do ch.setupimages.
now we could have just put all of the setup images under the init, but by breaking this up into two parts, it makes it much more readable.
And also if you're doing other work, there's reasons to do that as far as the setup.
Let's go ahead and run that.
And you can see where it says setting up training images and labels, setting up test images.
And that's one of the reasons we broke it up, is so that if you're testing this out, you can actually have print statements in there telling you what's going on, which is really nice.
they did a good job with this setup. I like the way that it was broken up in the back.
And then one quick note, you want to remember that batch to set up the next batch, says we have to run batch equals ch next batch of 100, because we're going to use the 100 size.
but we'll come back to that. We're gonna use that. Just remember that that's part of our code we're gonna be using in a minute from the definition we just made. So now we're ready to create our model.
First thing we want to do is we want to import our TensorFlow as TF.
I'll just go ahead and run that so it's loaded up. And you can see we got a warning here.
that's because they're making some changes, it's always growing, and they're gonna be depreciating one of the values from float64 to float type, or is treated as an NP float sixty-four.
Uh nothing to really worry about because this doesn't even affect what we're working on, because we've set all of our stuff to a 255 value or 0 to 1.
And do keep in mind that 0 to 1 value that we converted to 255 is still a float value, But it'll easily work with either the numpy float 64
or the numpy d type float. It doesn't matter which one it goes through, so the depreciation would not affect our code as we have it.
And in our tensorflow we'll go ahead, let me just increase the size in there just a moment so you can get a better view of what we're typing in. we're gonna set a couple placeholders here.
And so we have we're going to set x equals tf placeholder tf float32. We just talked about the float 64 versus the numpy float. We're actually just going to keep this at float 32.
More than a significant number of decimals for what we're working with.
And since it's a placeholder, we're going to set the shape equal to, and we've set it equal to none, because at this point we're just holding the place on there.
We'll be setting up as we run the batches, that's what that first value is. And then 32 by 32 by 3, that's what we've reshaped our data to fit in.
And then we have our y true equals placeholder tf float32, and the shape equals none, comma ten. Ten is the ten different labels we have, so it's an array of ten.
And then let's create one more placeholder.
We'll call this hold prob or hold probability.
And we're gonna use this. We don't have to have a shape or anything for this. This placeholder is for what we call dropout.
If you remember from our theory before, we drop out so many nodes is looking at or the different values going through, which helps decrease bias.
So we need to go ahead and put a placeholder for that also.
And we'll run this, so it's all loaded up in there. So we have our three different placeholders. And since we're in TensorFlow, when you use Carras, it does some of this automatically.
But we're in TensorFlow direct. Caras sits on TensorFlow. We're gonna go ahead and create some more helper functions.
We're gonna create something to help us initialize the weights, initialize our bias.
If you remember that each layer has to have a bias going in, we're going to go ahead and work on our conversional 2D, our max pool.
So we have our pooling layer, our convolutional layer, and then our normal full layer. So we're going to go ahead and put those all into definitions, and let's see what that looks like in code.
And you can also grab some of these helper functions from the MNIST, the NIST setup.
Let me just put that in there if you're under the TensorFlow. So a lot of these are already in there, but we're going to go ahead and do our own, and we're gonna create our init weights.
And one of the reasons we're doing this is so that you can actually start thinking about what's going on in the back end.
So even though there's ways to do this with an automation, sometimes these have to be tweaked and you have to put in your own setup in here.
now we're not gonna be doing that, we're just gonna recreate them for our code.
And let's take a look at this. We have our weights, and so what comes in is going to be the shape, and what comes out is going to be random numbers.
So we're gonna go ahead and just init some random numbers based on the shape with a standard deviation of 0.1.
Kind of a fun way to do that. And then the TF variable uh init random distribution. So we're just creating a random distribution on there. That's all that is for the weights.
Now you might change that. You might have a higher standard deviation. In some cases, you actually load preset weights.
That's pretty rare.
Usually you're testing that against another model or something like that, and you want to see how those weights configure with each other.
now remember we have our bias, so we need to go ahead and initialize the bias with a constant in this case we're using 0.1.
A lot of times the bias is just put in as one, and then you have your weights add on to that. but we're gonna set this as 0 one.
so we want to return a convolutional 2D, in this case a neural network. This is would be a layer on here.
What's going on with the con 2D is we're taking our data coming in, we're going to filter it.
Strides, if you remember correctly, strides came from here's our image, and then we only look at this picture here, and then maybe we have a stride of one.
So we look at this picture here, and we continue to look at the different filters going on there. The other thing this does is that we have our data coming in as 32 by
32 by 3.
And we want to change this so that it's just this is three dimensions, and it's going to reformat this as just two dimensions.
So it's going to take this number here and combine it with the 32 by 32. So this is a very important layer here because it's reducing our data down using different means. And it connects down.
I'm just going to jump down one here.
it goes with the convolutional layer.
So you have your kind of your pre-formatting and the setup, and then you have your actual convolution layer that goes through on there.
And you can see here we have init weights by the shape, init bias, shape of three, because we have the three different here's our three again.
And then we return the TFNN relu with the convention 2D. So this convolutional has this feeding into it right there. It's using that as part of it. And of course the input is the XY plus B the bias.
So that's quite a mouthful, but these two are the are the keys here to creating the convolutional layers there.
The convolutional 2D coming in, and then the convolutional layer, which then steps through and creates all those filters we saw.
Then of course we have our pooling. so after each time we run it through the convectional layer, we want to pool the data.
if you remember correctly on the on the pool side, and let me just get rid of all my marks, it's getting a little crazy there.
And in fact, let's go ahead and jump back to that slide. Let's just take a look at that slide over here.
so we have our image coming in, we create our convolutional layer with all the filters.
Remember the filters go you know, the filters coming in here and it looks at these four boxes, and then if it's a step, let's say step two,
it then goes to these four boxes, and then the next step, and so on.
so we have our convolutional layer that we generate, or convolutional layers. They use the relu function. there's other functions out there.
For this though, the relu is the uh most the the one that works the best, at least so far, I'm sure that will change. Then we have our pooling. Now, if you remember correctly, the pooling was max.
so if we had the filter coming in and they did the multiplication on there, and we have a one and maybe a two here, and another one here, and a three here,
three is the max. And so out of all of these, you then create an array that would be three, and if the max is over here, two or whatever it is.
That's what goes into the pooling of what's going on in our pooling.
so again we're reducing that data down, reducing it down as small as we can, and then finally we're going to flatten it out into a single array,
and that goes into our fully connected layer.
And you can see that here in the code. Right here, we're going to create our normal full layer.
so at some point we're going to take from our pooling layer, this will go into some kind of flattening process, and then that will be fed into the
different layers going in down here.
and so we have our input size, you'll see our input layer get shape, which is just going to get the shape for whatever is coming in.
and then input size, initial weights is also based on the input layer coming in. And the input size down here is based on the input layer shape.
So we're just gonna already use the shape and already have our size coming in.
And of course, you have to make sure you init the bias. Always put your bias on there, and we'll do that based on the size.
So this will return tf.matmole input layer w plus b. This is just a normal full layer. That's what this means right down here. That's what we're gonna return.
So that was a lot of steps we went through. Let's go ahead and run that. So those are all loaded in there.
And let's go ahead and create the layers. Let's see what that looks like.
Now that we've done all the heavy lifting and everything, we get to do all the easy part.
Let's go ahead and create our layers.
We'll create a convolution layer one and two, two different convolutional layers, and then we'll take that and we'll flatten that out and create a reshape
pooling in there for our reshape, and then we'll have our full layer at the end.
So let's start by creating our first convolutional layer. Then we come in here and let me just run that real quick. And I want you to notice on here the three and the 32.
This is important because coming into this convolutional layer, we have three different channels and 32 pixels each.
so that has to be in there.
The four and four you can play with.
This is your filter size. So if you remember, you have a filter and you have your image, and the filter slowly steps over and filters out this image depending on what your step is.
For this particular setup, 4.4 is just fine. That should work pretty good for what we're doing and for the size of the image.
And then of course at the end, once you have your convolutional layer set up, you also need to pool it,
and you'll see that the pooling is automatically set up so that it would see the different shape based on what's coming in.
So here we have max 2x2 and we put in the convolutional one that we just created. The convolutional layer we just created goes right back into it.
And that right up here, as you can see, is the X it's coming in from here. So it knows to look at The first model and set the the data accordingly. Set that up so it matches.
And we went ahead and ran this already. I think I ran it. Let me go and run it again. And if we're gonna do one layer, let's go ahead and do a second layer down here.
And it's uh we'll call it convo two.
It's also a convolutional layer on this, and you'll see that we're feeding convolutional one in, the pooling.
So it goes from convolutional one into convolutional one pooling, from convolutional one pooling into convolutional two, and then from convolutional two
into convolutional two pooling.
And we'll go ahead and take this and run this. So these variables are all loaded into memory.
And for our flattened layer, let's go ahead and we'll do since we have 64 coming out of here and we have uh four by four going in,
let's do eight by eight by sixty-four. So let's do four thousand and ninety-six. This is gonna be the flat layer, so that's how many bits are coming through on the flat layer. And we'll reshape this.
So we'll reshape our uh uh convo 2 pooling, and that will feed into here, the convo 2 pooling, and then we're gonna set it up as a single layer that's 4,096
in size. That's what that means there. We'll go ahead and run this. So we've now created this variable, the convo 2 flat, and then we have our first full layer.
This is the final neural network where we have the flat layer going in. And we're going to again use the ReLU for our setup on there on a neural network for evaluation.
And you'll notice that we're going to create our first full layer. Our normal full layer, that's our definition.
So we created that, that's creating the normal full layer, and our input for the data comes right here from the this goes right into it, the convo two
flat. So this tells it how big the data is. And we're going to have it come out, it's going to have 1024, that's how big the layer is coming out.
We'll go ahead and run this. So now we have our full layer one, and with the full layer one, we want to also define the full one dropout to go with that.
So our full layer one comes in, keep probability equals whole probability. Remember we created that earlier, and the full layer one is what's coming into it.
And this is going backwards and training the data. We're not training every weight, we're only training a percentage of them each time, which helps get rid of the bias.
So let me go ahead and run that. And finally we'll go ahead and create a y predict, which is going to equal the normal full one dropout and ten, because we have ten labels in there.
Now, in this neural network, we could have added additional layers. That would be another option to play with.
You can also play with instead of 1024, you can use other numbers for the way that sets up and what's coming out going into the next one.
We're only going to do just the one layer and the one layer dropout.
And you can see if we did another layer, it'd be real easy just to feed in the full one dropout into full layer two.
And then full layer two dropout would have full layer two feed into it, and then you'd switch that here for the y prediction. For right now, this is great.
This particular data set is tried and true, and we know that this will work on it.
And if we just type in y predict and we run that, we'll see that this is a tensor object shape question mark 10 d type
32. a quick way to double check what we're working on.
So now we've got all of our we've done a setup all the way to the y predict, which we just did, we want to go ahead and apply the loss function and make sure that's set up in there.
create the optimizer, and then uh trainer optimizer and create a variable to initialize all the global TF variables.
So before we dive in to the loss function, let me point out one quick thing or just kind of a rehab over a couple things.
And that is when we're playing with this these setups, we pointed out up here we can change the 4.4 and use different numbers there. They change your outcome.
So depending on what numbers you use here will have a huge impact on how well your model fits.
And that's the same here of the 1024 also. This is also another number that if you continue to raise that number, you'll get possibly a better fit, you might overfit.
And if you lower that number, you'll use less resources.
And generally, you want to use this in the exponential growth.
An exponential being two, four, eight, 16, And in this case, the next one down would be five twelve. You can use any number there, but those would be the ideal numbers when you look at this data.
So the next step in all this is we need to also create a way of tracking how good our model is. And we're going to call this a loss function.
And so we're going to create a cross-entropy loss function. And so before we discuss exactly what that is, let's take a look and see what we're feeding it.
we're going to feed it our labels, and we have our true labels and our prediction labels.
so coming in here is where the two different variables we're sending in or the two different probability distributions is one that we know is true and what we think it's going to be.
Now this function right here, when they talk about cross entropy, in information theory, the cross entropy between two probability distributions
over the same underlying set of events measures the average number of bits needed to identify an event drawn from the set. That's a mouthful. really we're just looking at the amount of error in here.
How many of these are correct and how many of these are incorrect. So how much of it matches? And we're going to look at that, we're just going to look at the average.
That's what the mean the reduced to the mean means here. So we're looking at the average error on this.
And so the next step is we're gonna take the error. We want to know our cross entropy or our loss function, how much loss we have. That's gonna be part of how we train the model.
So when you know what the loss is and we're training it, you feed that back into the back propagation setup. And so we want to go ahead and optimize that. Here's our optimizer.
We're gonna create the optimizer using an atom optimizer.
Remember there's a lot of different ways of optimizing the data. Atom's the most popular used.
so our optimizer is going to equal the TF train atom optimizer. If you don't remember what the learning rate is, we just pop this back into here. Here's our learning rate.
When you have your weights, you have all your weights and your different nodes that are coming out. Here's our node coming out, um, and it has all its weights.
And then the error is being prop sent back through in reverse on our neural network.
So we take this error and we adjust these weights based on the different formulas, in this case the atom formula is what we're using. We don't want to just adjust them completely.
We don't want to change this weight so it exactly fits the data coming through. Because if we made that kind of adjustment, it's going to be biased to whatever the last data we sent through is.
Instead, we're gonna multiply that by 0.001 and make a very small shift in this weight. So our delta W is only 0.001 of the actual delta W of the full change we're going to compute from the atom.
And then we want to go ahead and train it, so our training or set up a training variable or function, and this is going to equal our optimizer minimize
cross entropy.
And we make sure we go ahead and run this, so it's loaded in there, and then we're almost ready to train our model. But before we do that, we need to create one more variable in here.
And we're going to create a variable to initialize all the global TF variables.
And when we look at this, the TF global variable initializer, this is a TensorFlow object.
It goes through there and it looks at all our different setup that we have going under our TensorFlow and then initializes those variables.
so it's kind of like a magic wand because it's all hidden in the back end of TensorFlow.
All you need to know about this is that you have to have the initialization on there, which is an operation, and you have to run that once you have your setup going.
So we'll go ahead and run this piece of code, and then we're gonna go ahead and train our data. So let me run this, so it's loaded up there.
And so now we're gonna go ahead and run the model by creating a graph session. Graph session is a TensorFlow term.
So you'll see that coming up. It's one of the things that throws me because I always think of graph X and Spark and Graph as just general graphing. but they talk about a graph session.
So we're gonna go ahead and run the model and let's go ahead and walk through this what's going on here.
And let's paste this data in here, and here we go. So we're going to start off with a with a TF session as sess. So that's our actual TF session we've created. so we're right here with the TF session.
Our session we're creating, we're gonna run TF Global Variable Initializer. So right off the bat, we're initializing our variables here.
and then we have for I and range 500. So what's going on here, remember 500? We're gonna break the data up and we're gonna batch it in at 500 points each.
We've created our session run. So we're gonna do with TF session as session.
Right here. We've created our variable session and then we're going to run and we're going to go ahead and initialize it. So we have our TF Global Variables Initializer that we created.
That initializes our session in here.
The next thing we're going to do is we're going to go for I in range of 500 batch equals ch.next batch. So if you remember correctly, this is loading up 100 pictures at a time.
And this is going to loop through that 500 times. So we are literally doing what is that? 500 times 100 is 50,000.
So that's 50,000 pictures we're gonna process right there.
And the first process is we're gonna do a session run. We're gonna take our train, we created our train variable or optimizer in there. We're gonna feed it the dictionary.
we had our feed dictionary that we created, and we have x equals batch zero coming in, y true, batch one, hold the probability, 0
five. And then just so that we can keep track of what's going on, we're gonna every 100 steps we're gonna run a print.
So currently on step format accuracy is and we're gonna look at matches equals tf dot equal tf argument
y prediction one tf.arg max y true, comma one.
So we're gonna look at this as how many matches it has. And here our ACC, all we're doing here is we're going to take the matches, how many matches they have, it creates it, it generates a chart.
We're going to convert that to float, that's what the TFCast does, and then we just want to know the average. We just want to know the average of the accuracy.
And then we'll go ahead and print that out, print session run accuracy feed dictionary. So it takes all this and it prints out our accuracy on there.
So let's go ahead and take this. Oops, flip screens there.
Let's go ahead and take this and let's run it. And this is going to take a little bit to run. so let's see what happens on my old laptop.
And we'll see here that we have our current we're currently on step zero. It takes a little bit to get through the accuracy, and this will take just a moment to run.
We can see that on our step zero it has an accuracy of 0.1 or 0.1028.
and as it's running, we'll go ahead, you don't need to watch it run all the way, but this accuracy is going to change a little bit up and down,
so we've actually lost some accuracy during our step two.
but we'll see how that comes out. Let's come back after we run it all the way through and see how the different steps come out. I was actually reading that backwards.
the way this works is the closer we get to one, the more accuracy we have. so you can see here we've gone from a 0.1 to a 0.39.
Um and we'll go ahead and pause this and come back and see what happens when we're done with the full run.
Alright, now that we've prepared the meal, got it in the oven, and pulled out my finished dish here, if you've ever watched any of the old cooking shows.
Let's discuss a little bit about this accuracy going on here and how do you interpret that.
We've done a couple things.
First, we've defined accuracy. the reason I got it backwards before is you have loss or accuracy.
And with loss, you'll get a graph that looks like this. It goes, oops that's an S by the way. There we go.
You get a graph that curves down like this, and with accuracy, you get a graph that curves up. This is how good it's doing. Now in this case, one is supposed to be really good accuracy.
That means it gets close to one, but it never crosses one. So if you have an accuracy of one, that is phenomenal.
In fact that's pretty much unheard of. And the same thing with loss. If you have a loss of zero, that's also unheard of. The zero is actually on this this axis right here as we go in there.
So how do we interpret that? Because you know, if I was looking at this and I go, oh, 0.51, that's 51%. You're doing 50-50. No, this is not percentage.
Let me just put that in there. It is not percentage. This is logarithmic.
What that means is that 0.2 is twice as good as 0.1. And when we see 0.4, that's twice as good as 0.2. Real way to convert this into a percentage.
You really can't say this is a direct percentage conversion. What you can do though is in your head, if we were to give this a percentage, we might look at this as 50%, we're just guessing,
equals 0.1. And if 50% roughly equals 0.1, that's where we started up here at the top. Remember at the top here, here's our 0.1028.
The accuracy of 50%, then 75% is about 0.2.
And so on and so on. Don't quote those numbers because that doesn't work that way.
They say that if you have 0.95, that's pretty much saying 100%.
And if you have anywhere between, you'd have to go look this up. Let me go ahead and remove all my drawings there. so the magic number is 0.5. We really want to be over a 0.5 in this whole thing.
And we have both 0.5004, remember this is accuracy.
If we were looking at loss, then we'd be looking the other way. But 0.05, you know, instead of how high it is, we want how low it is. but with accuracy being over a 0.5 is pretty valid.
That means this is pretty solid. And if you get to a 0.95, then it's a direct correlation.
That's what we're looking for here in these numbers.
You can see we finished with this model at 0.5135, so still good. and if we look at when they ran this in the other end, remember there's a lot of randomness that goes into it when we see the weights.
they got 0.5251, so a little better than ours. But that's fine. You'll find your own comes up a little bit better or worse depending on just that randomness.
And so we've gone through the whole model. We've created, we trained the model, and we've also gone through on every uh hundredth run to test the model to see how accurate it is.
And now that we have a solid running model and accuracy, let's go ahead and take a look at what we covered today.
We did cover a lot, because this is a very complicated subject, and it's not so much complicated in
any individual step, it just has a lot of steps involved. so today we covered what is a convolutional neural network.
And you can see we have the pictures coming in to the input layer, to the hidden layers, to the output layer, and then orchid or rows. We talked about the very basics at the beginning.
And we discussed how a CNN recognizes images, and the very basics is we converted the image into a pixel map of zeros and ones.
Then we dived into layers in a convolutional neural network.
And we had our convolutional layer, our fully convected layer, our ReLU layer, and our pooling layer. And we looked at pooling layer.
It reduces the data down to a smaller amount by finding the first it finds the matches and then it finds the maximum value in that match.
and we discussed all the different layers in there.
We went into the fully connected layer, which is your normal the neural networks you're probably used to dealing with, where we're just building a forward propagation neural network.
And we connected them all together. And you can see here:
we took the bird. we did
our feature extraction in multiple hidden layers, where we had our convolution, which then generated those little individual filters. and we had our RELU. and then we took the RELU.
we max pooled those. and then we took all of those pooled values at the end. so they've been reduced to smaller mappings.
we've reduced that. and then we fed that into the fully connected layer. And then finally, we went into the use case implementation using CNN, and we walked through a full demo on the coding on there.
Now over to our training experts.
And with that, we have reached the end of this session on AI machine learning and deep learning full course training 26.
If you have any doubts or queries, let us know in the comments below, and our team of experts will be happy to help you as soon as possible.
Until next time, thank you and keep learning.
Stay tuned for more from Simply Learn.